<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Life of Caligula Cæfar (Fragment)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Encoded document</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Transcription from provided manuscript page.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <pb n="243" />
      <fw type="header">The Life of Caligula Cæfar. </fw>
      
      <p>
        to be brought back to have his tongue cut out, and then return'd him again to the place of Execution. 
      </p>
      
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28"><p>
        Having called home a perfon who had been baniſhed a long time, he demanded of him how he had ſpent his time in his banishment, who replying in flattery, <q rend="italic">I pray'd to the Gods continually, that Tiberius might die and you succeed him in his Empire, as is hapned fince.</q>  He imagined the reſt which remained in exile prayed as heartily for his death, and upon that bare imagination, fent officers on purpoſe about the Iſlands, to put them all to the ſword.  A fancy coming into his head to fee ſuch a Senator mangled and flash'd, he fuborn'd certain perſons, ſome to fall upon him as he entred the Court, to call him <q rend="italic">Enemy to the State</q>, and ſtabbing him with their Styletto's to deliver him over to the rest of their companions to be cut in pieces, nor could his cruelty be fatiated till his Members and Bowels, after they had been drawn about the Streets, were brought before him, and piled up into a heap. </p>
      </div>
      
      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
        <p>
        And if he was barbarous in his actions, he was little better in his words;  He was wont to ſay There was nothing in this nature he commended fo muchas (in his own words) his <foreign>adiatrepfian</foreign>, or unrelenting at the fight of Executions.  His Grandmother Antonia admoniſhing one day; as if his diſobedience had been nothing at all, <q rend="italic">Remember</q> (fays he) <q rend="italic">I may do what I please, with whom I please.</q>  Having a deſign to poiſon his own brother, and fufpecting he used Antidotes, <q rend="italic">How</q> (fays he) <q rend="italic">is there any Antidote against Cafar?</q>  Having baniſh'd his Siſters, he threatned them, <q rend="italic">That he had Swords as well as Islands.</q>  A Prætorian Citizen, who by reaſon of an indiſpoſition, had got leave to retire into the Iſle of <placeName rend="italic">Anticyra</placeName> defiring 
      </p>
    </div>
      
      <fw type="signature">R </fw>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>