<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>
            <pb n="417"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      THE NINTH BOOK, Being the LIFE OF <persName rend="italic">AULUS VITELLIUS</persName>, THE NINTH Emperour of <placeName rend="italic">ROME</placeName>.
    </p>
    <p>
      HIſtorians do not a little differ about the Extraction of <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName>; ſome will having him Noble and Antient, others Modern, Mean and Contemptible, which I ſhould have thought had proceeded from the flattery or obloquie of thoſe who lived under the Empire of <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName>, if I had not found that before
      <pb n="418"/>
      his time they were in Controverſie about the Condition of his Family.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      There is extant a little book of <persName rend="italic">Q. Enloquius</persName>, to <persName rend="italic">Q. Vitellius</persName> Quæſtor in the days of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> of happy Memory, by which it appears that the <persName rend="italic">Vitellii</persName> are deſcended from <persName rend="italic">Faunus</persName> King of the <foreign rend="italic">Aborigines</foreign>, and <persName rend="italic">Vitellia</persName> who was adored as a Goddeſs in many places, and that they had the ſoveraign Command in all the Territories of the <placeName rend="italic">Latins</placeName>. That the remainder of this race was tranſplanted from the <placeName rend="italic">Sabins</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, where they were received amongſt the <foreign rend="italic">Patricii</foreign>,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      and that the <placeName rend="italic">Vitellian</placeName> Cauſey from the <placeName rend="italic">Janiculum</placeName> to the Sea, is a token of their greatneſs, as well as a Colony of the ſame name; which they antiently deſired to take into their protection, and to defend againſt the <placeName rend="italic">Equiculi</placeName> with the forces of their own houſe only, and at their own proper expence.
    </p>
    <p>
      That afterwards in the time of the <placeName rend="italic">Samnites</placeName> war, ſupplies being ſent into <placeName rend="italic">Apulia</placeName>, ſome of the <persName rend="italic">Vitellii</persName> remained and ſettled at <placeName rend="italic">Nuceria</placeName>, and that a long while after ſome of their progeny returned to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and were received into the Senators Order.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. On the contrary, ſeveral have writ that the Founder of this Family was a Libertine. <persName rend="italic">Caſſius Severus</persName> and others affirm it was a Cobler, whoſe Son growing rich by purchaſing confiſcated goods, married the Daughter of one <persName rend="italic">Antiochus</persName> a Baker, a common Harlot, and had a Son by her who became afterwards a Gentleman of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. But I leave this deſcrepancy undetermin'd:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      As to the buſineſs; <persName rend="italic">Publius Vitellius</persName> of <placeName rend="italic">Nucerian</placeName> extraction, (let the quality and Original of his Anceſtors be what they will) was moſt certainly a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight, Procurator to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and left behind him four Sons, who (retaining their Fathers Surname) were diſtinguiſh'd
      <pb n="419"/>
      by their Prænomina onely; there were <persName rend="italic">Aulus</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Quintus</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Publius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName>: <persName rend="italic">Aulus</persName> died in his Conſulſhip, which dignity he entred upon with <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName> the Father of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, a Man who lived very ſplendidly, and was famous for the Magnificence of his feaſts.
    </p>
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Quintus</persName> was turn'd out of the Senate and degraded, upon an Order of the Houſe, at the motion of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, that ſuch perſons of the Senate as were unfit for that honour, might be ſecluded.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Publius</persName> accus'd <persName rend="italic">Piſo</persName> his profeſt Enemy, and proſecuted him ſo ſtrictly for murdering <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> (whoſe companion he was) that he caus'd him to be condemn'd. After he had exercis'd the Prætorſhip, being apprehended amongſt the reſt of the Conſpirators with <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>, and committed to the cuſtody of his Brother, he open'd his own veins with a Pen-knife; after which not ſo much to lengthen his life, as to gratifie the importunity of his friends, he ſuffer'd them to bind up his wounds, and was cured, but died in the ſame priſon afterwards of another diſtemper.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> when his Conſulſhip expired, was made Governour of <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, during which Government he not only drill'd and inveigled <persName rend="italic">Artabanus</persName> King of the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName> into a Conference, but with great artifice prevail'd with him to render worſhip and veneration to the Enſigns of the Legions. Not long after this, with <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> the Emperour he bare two ordinary Conſulſhips, and the Office of Cenſor, and when <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> was abſent upon his expedition into Great <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName>, <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> was left Regent in his place.
    </p>
    <p>
      He was a man of great innocence, and induſtry, but he lay under a ſcandal for an immoderate love he had for a Libertine woman, with whom he was ſo fondly inamour'd, he caus'd her ſpittle to be mingled with honey, and us'd it as a fomentation for the chafing
      <pb n="420"/>
      of his throat and arteries, and that not ſeldom, or in private, but daily, and in publick.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      His nature was marvellouſly inclin'd to flattery, and he was the man which gave the firſt example of adoring <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> as a God: for after his return from <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, he never came into his Preſence but with his head cover'd with a vail, turning himſelf about, and then falling down proſtrate before him.
    </p>
    <p>
      He left no ſtone unturn'd to work himſelf into favour with <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, and obſerving him infinitely addicted to his wives and his freed-men, he beg'd of <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName> as the greateſt kindneſs ſhe could do him, that ſhe would give him leave but to pull off her ſhooes, and having taken one off from her right foot, he carried it away with him and wore it conſtantly betwixt his robe and his tunick, kiſſing it greatly at ſome times. The golden Images of <persName rend="italic">Narciſſus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Pallas</persName>, he worſhipt as his Houſhold Gods: and when <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> exhibited his ſecular ſhows to the people, his congratulation was this, <q rend="italic">Sæpe facias</q>, <q rend="italic">May you do the ſame many times.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He died of a Palſie the next day after it took him, leaving two children which he had by <persName rend="italic">Sextilia</persName>, a virtuous Lady and of an honorable family; he had the happineſs to ſee them both Conſuls in one year, the youngeſt ſucceeding his Brother for ſix months together. Being dead, the Senate honour'd him with a publick Funeral, and a Statue before the <placeName rend="italic">Roſtra</placeName> with this inſcription, <q rend="italic">Pietatis immobilis erga Principem</q>; <q rend="italic">Of unmovable Loyalty towards his Prince.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      3. <persName rend="italic">Aulus Vitellius</persName> the Emperour, was the Son of <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> and born the 24th day of September, or as ſome will have it the 7th, when <persName rend="italic">Druſus Cæſar</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Norbanus Flaccus</persName> were Conſuls: The Aſtrologers calculated his Nativity, and made ſuch predictions of his fortune, that his parents were in great apprehenſion
      <pb n="421"/>
      of him; and his Father us'd all the power he had to hinder him from taking any imployment of importance upon him during his life. When he was ſent to the Legions, and proclaim'd Emperour, his Mother wept and lamented it, as his unhappineſs, and misfortune. His infancy and youth, he paſt at <placeName rend="italic">Caprea</placeName>, amongſt lewd and infamous perſons, ſubſervient to the pleaſures of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>; inſomuch as he gain'd an ill name amongſt them, was call'd by the Surname of <foreign rend="italic">Spintria</foreign> perpetually; and it was thought the comlineſs of the Son was the occaſion of the advancement of his Father.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. His vices increaſing with his years, and being overwhelm'd with all kind of debauchery, it was no hard matter for him to attain the principal places at Court. With <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> he inſinuated by his dexterity in managing his Chariot, with <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> for his inclination to Dice: But more eſpecially with <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, for the cauſes aforeſaid, as alſo upon a peculiar piece of ſervice when he was Preſident at the ſolemnity call'd <foreign rend="italic">Neroneum</foreign>, for underſtanding his deſire of being ingaged for the prize amongſt the reſt of the Harpers, and that he was aſhamed to declare it, though he was invited and importun'd to it by all; when he went out of the Theatre he followed him, and pretending that the people perſiſted in their requeſt, and had ſent him to ſolicit his return, he prevail'd with him to come back again and put in among the reſt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. In this manner by the favour of theſe three Emperours, he was advanc'd to the moſt conſiderable offices, both of the Church and State. He exercis'd the Proconſulſhip of <placeName rend="italic">Africa</placeName>, and had the overſight of the publick works, which he executed with great inequality. In his Province he comported himſelf honourably
      <pb n="422"/>
      two years together, during which time he continued there as Lieutenant to his Brother; But he took not the ſame methods in his City adminiſtrations; for it is reported he took away the Offerings and Ornaments belonging to the Temples, changing ſome of them, and inſtead of Gold and Silver, (which were there before) putting Tin and Copper in their places.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. He married <persName rend="italic">Petronia</persName>, the daughter of one who had been Conſul, by whom he had a Son named <persName rend="italic">Petronianus</persName>, who was blind of one eye. His Mother having made him her Heir, upon condition he ſhould be freed out of the power of his Father, <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> infranchis'd him, and (as is believ'd) not long after made him away, accuſing him to have deſign'd the death of his Parents, and pretending that touch'd with remorſe of Conſcience, he had taken the poiſon himſelf which he had provided for his Father. A while after he married <persName rend="italic">Galeria Fundana</persName>, whoſe Father had been Prætor, and by her he had Children of both ſexes; amongſt the reſt, one Son who had ſo great a ſtammering and impediment in his ſpeech, he was no more to be underſtood than if he had been dumb.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. He was ſent by <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> into the Low-Countries, contrary to the opinion of all the world, by the favour (as was ſuppos'd) of <persName rend="italic">T. Vinnius</persName>, who was very powerful at that time, and whoſe friendſhip he had gain'd long ſince, by ſiding with him in the ſame Faction. But <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> profeſs'd openly, he did not advance him out of any extraordinary eſteem he had of him, but becauſe he believ'd thoſe people leaſt to be fear'd, which were ſo much addicted to their belly, and that the greedineſs of his appetite, might be ſatiated by the plenty of that
      <pb n="423"/>
      Province; ſo that 'tis clear, his imployment in that Charge was an effect rather of the Contempt, than Favour of the Emperour.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      It is certain alſo, that when he was to ſet out, he had not wherewithal to bear his charges on the way; and that he was ſo bare of money and neceſſitous, that being to leave his Wife and Children at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he mued them up in a Garret which he hired for them, let his own houſe for the remainder of the year, and pawn'd a Pearl out of his Mothers ear, to defray the expence of his journey. When he had furniſh'd himſelf in this manner, he had no ſmall trouble to free himſelf from his Creditors, which throng'd to him in great numbers, endeavouring to retard and detain him: Amongſt the reſt there were <placeName rend="italic">Sinueſſians</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Formians</placeName>, whoſe publick Taxes and Impoſitions being to paſs through his hands, he had miſapply'd, and converted part of them to his own uſe. To diſingage himſelf from them, he frighted them with an Action of Slander, having not long before brought an Action of Battery againſt a Libertine, which ſolicited the payment of a ſum of money he ow'd him, with too much eagerneſs, pretending that he had kick'd and abus'd him; nor could he be perſwaded to withdraw his Action, till he had extorted from him fifty thouſand Seſterces.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      At his arrival in his Province, the Army not being over-well affected to the Emperour, and prone to new troubles, he was receiv'd with all expreſſion of joy imaginable, declaring it could be nothing but the Gods which had ſent them the Son of a perſon had been Conſul three times, in the flower and vigour of his age, and of an affable and generous nature. <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> omitted not any thing that might increaſe the good opinion they had conceiv'd of him of old; For as he was in his journey,
      <pb n="424"/>
      he would kiſs and ſalute any Common Souldier he met upon the way, go into the Inns, and Victualling-houſes, and enquire of the Mulettiers and Travellers with great courteſie, whether they had had their Breakfaſts, and belch upon them ſometimes, to aſſure them that he had had his.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. Being got to the Camp, he denied no bodies requeſt; of his own grace and motion he took off all notes of ignominy, diſpenc'd with thoſe which were guilty, and pardon'd all ſuch as ſtood condemn'd at that time: Whereupon he had ſcarce paſs'd one whole month amongſt them, but without regard either to the day, or the time, they came one night into his Chamber on a ſudden, and taking him away in the very poſture they found him, they ſaluted him Emperour; and putting the Sword of <persName rend="italic">Divus Julius</persName> into his hand, (which was taken out of the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, and given him by one of the Souldiers in their firſt acclamations) they led him with great triumph through the principal and moſt frequented Streets of the Town.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      When he return'd to the <foreign rend="italic">Prætorium</foreign>, which was his own Quarters, he found the Chimney of the room where he dined on fire; and obſerving a general conſternation in his friends, who looked upon it as a dangerous Omen, he recollected them with theſe words, <q rend="italic">Courage, be of good chear, this flame is for nothing but to light us:</q> Nor did he make any other ſpeech to the Souldiers.
    </p>
    <p>
      After this, the Army in the Upper <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName> (which was then in Rebellion againſt <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, in favour of the Senate) having declar'd for him, by common conſent they tender'd him the Surname of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>; which he accepted very readily, deferring the Title of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>,
      <pb n="425"/>
      and refuſing abſolutely that of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> for ever.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. As ſoon as he had the news that <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> was dead, having put the affairs of the Province in order, he divided his Forces, ſent one party before againſt <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName>, and march'd himſelf with the reſt as a Reſerve: To the Troops in the Van there arrived an accident of very good Omen; for on a ſudden, from the right ſide of the Squadron, an Eagle appear'd, which flying round about their Standards and Enſigns, hover'd ſoftly before them, as it were to ſhew them the way. On the contrary, as he moved, and the party with him, all the Statues on Horſeback which were erected for him in many places, their legs failing them, on a ſudden fell down and were broken to pieces; and the Garland of Laurel which he wore moſt religiouſly about his head, fell off into a River. A while after, as he was in his Tribunal, adminiſtring Juſtice in <placeName rend="italic">Vienna</placeName>, a Cock came and ſate upon his ſhoulder, and afterwards upon his head: And the Events were ſuitable to the Preſages; for his Lieutenants had the good fortune to ſettle him in the Empire, but he was not ſo happy as to hold it.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. While he was yet in <placeName rend="italic">Gaule</placeName>, he had the News of his Victory at <placeName rend="italic">Bebriacum</placeName>, and the death of <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName>; whereupon without more ado, by one ſingle Edict he disbanded his Prætorian Cohorts, as ſeditious, and of ill example, commanding them to deliver in their Arms to the Tribunes. Thoſe hundred and twenty, whoſe Petitions to <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> he had found, deſiring recompence for their aſſiſtance in killing of <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, he caus'd to be ſearched out, and puniſhed ſeverely. Theſe beginnings were honourable, and made them hope from him, whatever was to be deſired
      <pb n="426"/>
      in ſo great a Prince; but he behaved himſelf afterwards according to his ill inclinations, and former way of living, rather than to the Majeſty and Grandeur of an Emperour:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For no ſooner had he begun his journey, but he rode through the Cities in a Triumphal manner. He ſtirr'd not upon the Rivers, but in his painted Pleaſure-boats, trim'd and adorn'd with Garlands of Flowers, and victuall'd with the moſt exquiſite delicates could be got, without any order or diſcipline either amongſt his Souldiers or Servants, ſporting himſelf and laughing at their rapines and inſolencies, how inſupportable ſoever: For not being contented with Free-quarter wherever they came, they enfranchis'd what Slaves they thought good, and where any reſiſted, they made no ſcruple to beat, wound, and kill them as they pleas'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      When he came into the Fields where the Battle was fought, there were ſome of his Train who nauſeated and deteſted the ſmell of the dead bodies; but he had the impudence to confirm them, with this moſt abominable ſpeech, <q rend="italic">A dead Enemy ſmells well, but a dead Citizen better:</q> Yet immediately to qualifie and correct the uglineſs of the ſavour, he call'd for good ſtore of Wine, drunk it publickly, and according to his accuſtomed vanity diſtributed the reſt amongſt his Souldiers. Beholding the Stone under which <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> was buried, with an inſcription engraven upon it to his memory, he ſaid, <q rend="italic">He was worthy of that Monument</q>; and having gotten the Poniard with which he kill'd himſelf, he ſent it to <placeName rend="italic">Colonia Agrippina</placeName> to be dedicated to <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, and paſs'd one whole night in his revellings upon the <placeName rend="italic">Apennine</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. At length he entred the City, with his Trumpets before him, in his Imperial Mantle, his Sword
      <pb n="427"/>
      by his ſide, in the midſt of his Military Enſigns, his Attendants in their Caſſocks of War, and his Souldiers with their Arms preſented:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After which (in defiance of all Law both Divine and Humane) he grew worſe and worſe, and took upon himſelf the dignity of High Prieſt, upon the very ſame day on which the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName> were defeated by the <placeName rend="italic">Gauls</placeName> near the River <placeName rend="italic">Allia</placeName>, which was eſteem'd unfortunate for ever after. He ordain'd, the Comitia or Aſſemblies for the Election of Magiſtrates, ſhould be held from ten years to ten years, and himſelf be made perpetual Conſul: And that it might appear to all the World, what example he propos'd to follow in the Government of the Commonwealth, he Sacrificed publickly to the Ghoſt of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, in the midſt of the Field of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, in a General Aſſembly of the Prieſts: And at a ſolemn Feaſt, being much pleas'd with one which play'd upon the Harp, he commanded him to ſing ſomething in commendation of <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName>; whereupon the Harper beginning one of <persName rend="italic">Nero's</persName> Songs, he was the firſt which clapt his hands, and gave moſt evident tokens of his applauſe.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. In this manner he began his Empire, wherein the moſt part of his affairs were managed by the Counſel or Capricio of Players, Charioteers, or ſuch kind of inconſiderable fellows, amongſt which <persName rend="italic">Aſiaticus</persName> his Freed-man, had a principal place. This <persName rend="italic">Aſiaticus</persName> was a perſon with whom he had had the infamous commerce of a mutual proſtitution, when he was a youth; but growing weary of that trade, he ran away from him: afterwards by accident he found him ſelling a certain Drink called <foreign rend="italic">Poſca</foreign> at <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName>, caus'd him to be ſeized upon; and clapt into Irons; but upon ſecond thoughts, he releas'd him,
      <pb n="428"/>
      and receiv'd him into the ſame favour as before. Not long after, being again offended at his Contumacy, and ill humour, he ſold him to an ambulatory Fencing-maſter, and ſtole him away again when he was ready to have been produc'd upon the Stage, to have play'd his Prize amongſt the reſt of the Combatants; as ſoon as he accepted his Province, he infranchis'd him quite; and the firſt day of his Empire, he preſented him at Supper with a Gold Ring; though that very morning, being earneſtly requeſted by all people to conferr that honour upon him, he rejected their prayers, and ſeem'd to abominate ſo great a blot and diſparagement to the Equeſtrian Order.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="428"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. He was addicted to all ſorts of vices, but eſpecially to Luxury and Cruelty, he eat conſtantly three meals a day, and ſometimes four, not contenting himſelf with his breakfaſt, dinner and ſupper, unleſs he had his Collation afterwards, with all which he comported well enough having brought his body to a habit of Vomiting when he pleas'd: But theſe Feaſts were not alwaies at his own charge; he frequently invited himſelf to his friends, to breakfaſt in one place, to dinner in another, to ſupper in a third, all in the ſame day, and they entertain'd him generally with ſo much magnificence, ſeldom any of their Treats coſt them leſs than 40000 Seſterces apiece.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But the moſt memorable ſupper that was made for him, was by his Brother at his firſt coming to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, in which, by report, two thouſand ſeveral diſhes of fiſh, and ſeven thouſand of fowl (the choiceſt of both ſorts that could be got) were ſerved up to his Table; and yet his own profuſion exceeded all this, at the dedication of that platter, which by reaſon of its vaſtneſs and capacity<pb n="429"/>, he call'd the Buckler of <persName rend="italic">Minerva</persName>. In this diſh he had an Oglia brought up, made of the Sounds of the fiſh called <foreign rend="italic">Scarri</foreign>, the brains of Pheaſants and Peacocks, the tongues of the bird call'd <foreign rend="italic">Phœnicopterus</foreign>, the ſmall guts of Sea Lampreys fetcht on purpoſe by his Galleys from the <placeName rend="italic">Carpathian</placeName> Sea, and the coaſts of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Nor was he more inſatiable, than unſeaſonable in his Gluttony, not being able to contain during the time he was at ſacrifice, from plucking the entrails, corn, and meal (half roaſt and parch'd as they were) out of the fire, to devour them: and in the Inns upon the road as he travell'd, he fell aboard what ever he met with, not only meat ſo hot as no other body could touch, but cold meat left the day before, and ſuch fragments as were half eaten already.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. He was ſo unnaturally inclin'd to cruelty, he puniſh'd all ſorts of people with death, upon the leaſt occaſion whatever. There was no fraud or hypocriſie which he left unpractis'd, to deſtroy ſuch perſons of Quality as had been formerly his Schoolfellows, and his Aſſociates; careſſing them ſo far ſometimes, as to give them even a ſhare in the Government of the State. To one of them, amongſt the reſt, who being in a violent fit of a Feaver, deſired to drink, he mingled poiſon with cold water, and gave it him with his own hand.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Such Uſurers, Scriveners, and Publicans, as demanded either payment of what he ow'd them in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, or Toll and Duty upon the Road, he ſeldom or never excus'd: Of which number one coming to ſalute him, he commanded him to be put to death; but his mind turning of a ſudden, he ſent for him back again. This action of his being applauded by all people, as a ſignal piece of Clemency, he caus'd him to be executed<pb n="430"/> before his face, declaring, <q rend="italic">That he meant only to feed his own eyes with the ſpectacle.</q> Having condemn'd another to death, he executed his two Sons for company, for no other reaſon, but that they had preſum'd to intercede for their Father.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      A <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight being haled away likewiſe to his puniſhment, crying out to him as he went along, <q rend="italic">You are my Heir, you are my Heir</q>; he caus'd him to ſhew his Teſtament, and finding himſelf only Co-heir with a Freed-man of the Teſtators, to make his inheritance ſecure, he order'd them both to be hang'd. Some of the meaner ſort he put to death likewiſe, and for no other cauſe, but that they had laugh'd at the blew faction of the Charioteers, upon a fancy that they did it in contempt of him, and that they durſt not have been ſo audacious, but that they had hopes of ſome new revolution.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      But againſt no ſort of people was his anger more viſible, than againſt Aſtrologers and Fortune-tellers; no ſooner was any of them accus'd, but without troubling himſelf to enquire into the truth, he commanded them to be ſlain. That which had given him ſo great a Picque againſt that Profeſſion, was this: Having publiſh'd an Edict, requiring all Mathematicians to depart the City of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> by the Calends of October; there was a Libel ſet up in the ſame form, <q rend="italic">Requiring (in the name of the Chaldeans) <persName rend="italic">Vitellius Germanicus</persName> to depart the World by the ſame day.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      He was ſuſpected alſo to have had a hand in the death of his Mother, having commanded that no meat ſhould be given her, under pretence that ſhe was ſick, and it would do her harm; induc'd thereto by the Predictions of an Old woman, whom he believ'd as an Oracle, and who had told him, <q rend="italic">That if he outliv'd his Mother, he ſhould Reign a long time<pb n="431"/> in health and ſecurity.</q> Others will have it, that being weary of her preſent condition, and apprehending to be worſe, ſhe beg'd poiſon of her Son, and he was ſo dutiful as to grant her deſire.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. The eighth month after he was Emperor, the Armies in <placeName rend="italic">Mœſia</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Pannonia</placeName> revolted from him, and of the Tranſmarine forces, thoſe in <placeName rend="italic">Judæa</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName> did the ſame; part of them declaring for <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>, who was amongſt them, and part of them taking an Oath to him in his abſence. To retain therefore the affections of the reſt of his Troops he cared not what largeſſes he gave either in publick or private; and in his Levies in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he promis'd all voluntiers not only immediate diſmiſſion after the victory was obtain'd, but the ſame rewards as if they had been Veterans, and ran through the whole courſe of the wars.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      At length the Enemy advancing upon him both by Land and by Sea, He ſent his Brother with a Fleet of new rais'd men and Fencers, on the one ſide, and on the other ſide, ſuch Officers and Souldiers as had gain'd the Battle at <placeName rend="italic">Bebriacum</placeName>. Being beaten, or betray'd in all places, he capitulated with <persName rend="italic">Flavius Sabinus</persName> the Brother of <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> to deliver up all, upon condition his life might be ſpared, and 100 millions of Seſterces allowed him for his ſubſiſtence; a while after he preſented himſelf before the Stairs of the Palace, and in the midſt of the Souldiers declar'd, <q rend="italic">That he did reſign the Empire, and that when he accepted it firſt, it was againſt his Will.</q> The Souldiers unanimouſly oppoſing, he deferr'd it for the preſent, but the next morning by break of day he appear'd at the <placeName rend="italic">Roſtra</placeName> in mourning, and with many tears made the ſame declaration in writing.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The Soldiers and People interrupted him the ſecond time, exhorting him not to deſpond, and promiſing him their<pb n="432"/> utmoſt aſſiſtance; he recollected his Spirits, and unexpectedly falling upon <persName rend="italic">Sabinus</persName> and the reſt of the Flavians when they thought themſelves ſecure; he forc'd them into the Capitol, and ſetting fire to the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> conſum'd them all in it; during which combat and conflagration he was feaſting in the Palace of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, and with great pleaſure beheld all the paſſages in that lamentable Spectacle. A while after repenting of what he had done, and laying the fault upon other people, he called a publick aſſembly, before whom he took a ſolemn Oath, and compelled the reſt to take the ſame, <q rend="italic">That nothing was more dear to him than the peace &amp; tranquillity of the Common-wealth.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      After which pulling off his ſword, he preſented it firſt to the Conſul, he refuſing it, to the Magiſtrates, and Senators one by one, but no body receiving it, he departed with reſolution to depoſit it in the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Concord</persName>; and when ſome of them cryed out, <q rend="italic">That he himſelf was Concord,</q> he return'd and not only proteſted that he retain'd the Sword, but that he accepted alſo the Surname of <persName rend="italic">Concord</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. The condition of his affairs being thus, he intreated the Senate to depute certain of the <persName rend="italic">Veſtal</persName> Virgins and other perſons to repair to the Enemy, and to deſire peace, or at leaſt a preciſe time for a Conference. The next morning as he was attending their anſwer, the Scouts brought in word the Enemy was at hand; being ſurpriz'd with the news, he ſhut himſelf up cloſe in a kind of a Litter, and accompanied only with two perſons, his Baker and Cook, he took his way to his Fathers houſe upon the <placeName rend="italic">Aventin</placeName> Mount, deſigning from thence to make his eſcape into <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>. A while after upon an idle and uncertain report, that peace was concluded, he ſuffer'd<pb n="433"/> himſelf to be reconvey'd to his Palace, where finding all things ſolitary and abandon'd, and thoſe perſons which came with him, to deſert him privately, he put a girdle with certain pieces of Gold ſtitcht into it, about him, and fled into the Porters lodge, tyed a Dog at the door without, and barricado'd it on the inſide with the bed and bedding.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. By this time a party of <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſians</persName> had entred the Palace, and no body appearing, they ſearcht all places (as is uſual) till at laſt having diſcover'd him, they pull'd him out of his Kennel, and not knowing him, inquired only who he was, and if he could tell them where they might find <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName>; at firſt he deceiv'd them by a lye, but afterwards being known, he pretended he had matters of great importance to diſcover to <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>, and beg'd very hard that they would keep him, though it were in Priſon, till he could ſpeak with him. But all was in vain, for tying his hands behind him, putting a halter about his neck, and tearing his very clothes from off his back, they dragged him half naked into the Market place, through the whole ſtreet called the <placeName rend="italic">Via Sacra</placeName>, upbraiding him with a thouſand injurious words, and uſing him with inexpreſſible indignity, tying his head backward with his hair (as is uſual to the moſt execrable Malefactors) and holding the point of a ſword under his chin, leſt by bending down his head he might prevent the ſhewing of his Face:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      ſome pelted him with dung, and dirt, others revil'd him by his great diſh, others call'd him Incendiary, others reproacht him by the imperfections of his body, (for he was of an enormous tallneſs, his face red for the moſt part with drinking of Wine, his belly very fat, and not well ſupported by one of his thighs, which was bruiſed long before, by the bruſh of a Chariot, whilſt<pb n="434"/> he was waiting upon <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> in one of his Careers) at laſt having brought him to the <placeName rend="italic">Gemonian</placeName> ſtairs, they kill'd him with little ſtrokes, and from thence dragged him with a hook and threw him into <placeName rend="italic">Tyber</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      18. In this manner he died, with his Son and his Brother, in the 57th year of his age. His end correſponding exactly with the predictions of thoſe who interpreted the Omen which befell him (as we have mentioned) at <placeName rend="italic">Vienna</placeName>, which was no other than that he ſhould fall into the hands of a Frenchman, for he was killed by <persName rend="italic">Antonius Primus</persName>, who commanded the adverſe party; was born in <placeName rend="italic">Toloſe</placeName>, and in his minority was call'd <persName rend="italic">Becco</persName>, which in the French language is as much as the beak of a Cock.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
