<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>
<pb n="319"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      IN the <persName rend="italic">Domitian</persName> race, there were two illuſtrious Families, the <persName rend="italic">Calvini</persName>, and the <persName rend="italic">Ænobarbi</persName>; the <persName rend="italic">Ænobarbi</persName> derived both their Original, and Surname, from <persName rend="italic">Lucius Domitius</persName>, and upon this occaſion: As he was returning out of the Countrey upon a time, there appear'd to him two young men of extraordinary beauty <pb n="320"/> and ſtature, commanding him to acquaint the Senate and People of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, with a Victory they had obtain'd, of which as yet they had no certainty; and as an evidence of their divinity, ſtroaking him gently on the cheeks, they chang'd the colour of his hair, from black into a kind of reddiſh or Copper colour: which miraculous mark continued to his poſterity, and ſince that time the greateſt part of them have had red beards.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having been honoured with ſeven Conſulſhips, two Triumphs, and two Cenſorſhips, and having been receiv'd into the number of the <foreign rend="italic">Patritii</foreign>, they remain'd all of them with the ſame Surname, without aſſuming any other before it, beſides <persName rend="italic">Cneius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName>, which they varied and diverſifyed very conſiderably, uſing either of them ſometimes for three perſons together, and then again changing them alternatively one after another. The three firſt <persName rend="italic">Ænobarbi</persName>, were called <persName rend="italic">Lucii</persName>, the three ſubſequent, <persName rend="italic">Cnei</persName>; the reſt called themſelves <persName rend="italic">Lucii</persName>, or <persName rend="italic">Cnei</persName>, by turns one after another. And here I think it will not be amiſs, to give ſome ſhort repreſentation of the manners and qualifications of ſeveral of his Predeceſſors, to evince and clear it out to the World, that <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> had degenerated ſo far from the Virtue of his Anceſtors, that he ſeem'd to have retain'd nothing but their Vice.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. I ſhall begin therefore with <persName rend="italic">Cneius Domitius</persName>, his Great-Great-Grandfather: Whilſt he was Tribune of the people, being diſguſted by the High Prieſts, becauſe they had elected another perſon into his Fathers place, and paſt him by, he transferred the right of Subrogating Prieſts (which belong'd formerly to their Colledges) to the People. In his Conſulſhip, having Conquer'd the <placeName rend="italic">Allobroges</placeName>, <pb n="321"/> and <placeName rend="italic">Arverni</placeName>, he rode through his Province mounted in great ſtate upon an Elephant, attended by a multitude of Souldiers, as in a ſolemn Triumph.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Upon this <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName> it was, that <persName rend="italic">Licinius Craſſus</persName> the Orator had this expreſſion, <q rend="italic">No wonder if he had a beard of Braſs, whoſe face was of Iron, and his heart of Lead.</q> His Son being Prætor afterwards, accus'd <persName rend="italic">Caius Cæſar</persName> (as ſoon as he was out of his Conſulſhip) before the Senate, it being the common opinion he had exercis'd that Office contrary to the Laws, and auſpicia; afterwards being made Conſul himſelf, he uſed his utmoſt endeavours to fetch back <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> from the <placeName rend="italic">Gaules</placeName>, where he had the Command of the Army, and having prevail'd to be named his Succeſſor, by thoſe of his own faction, he began the Civil War, and was taken priſoner at <placeName rend="italic">Corfinium</placeName>;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      being ſet at liberty, he came to <placeName rend="italic">Marſeilles</placeName>, which at that time was cloſely beſieg'd, and confirm'd the Garriſon very much by his arrival; but he deſerted it afterwards on a ſudden, and was kill'd at length at the Battle of <placeName rend="italic">Pharſalia</placeName>. He was a man fierce and rigid in his nature, but not over-conſtant in his reſolutions. The extremity of his affairs having reduc'd him into a deſpair of their growing better, he was ſo fearful of that death which ſo often he deſired, that having taken poiſon to diſpatch himſelf, he repented of what he had done, took an Antidote to bring it up again, and infranchis'd his Phyſician, for having prepar'd and temper'd the poiſon ſo on purpoſe, that it could do him no great harm. <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> the Great conſulting with his friends, in what manner he ſhould comport himſelf with ſuch as ſtood Neuter, and ſided not at all, he was the only man which advis'd him to treat them as Enemies.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="322"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. This <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName> left a Son, worthy without doubt to be preferr'd before all the reſt of his race; who being condemn'd by the Law <foreign rend="italic">Pedia</foreign>, as privy to the murder of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>, (though he was really innocent) betook himſelf to <persName rend="italic">Caſſius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName>, who were his Kinſmen, and continued with them till their deaths; after which he retain'd the Command of the Fleet, which they had given him long before, and augmented it in ſpight of all his diſaſters; till at laſt of his own accord, when his whole party was irrecoverably ruin'd, he ſurrendred it to <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName>, who receiv'd it as an extraordinary obligation.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In fine, he was the only perſon condemn'd by that Law, who was re-admitted into his Native Countrey, and advanc'd to the moſt conſiderable honours. A while after, the fire of Civil diſſention breaking out again, he was made Lieutenant to the ſaid <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>; who having rendred himſelf unacceptable to ſome conſiderable perſons, by his infamous amours and dalliances with <persName rend="italic">Cleopatra</persName>, they offer'd to ſupplant <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>, and give the Command to <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName> in his ſtead; but not daring either to refuſe or accept it confidently, by reaſon of an unexpected fit of ſickneſs, he retired to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and died within few dayes; <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> aſperſing him, that he had deſerted his party for nothing, but that he was not able to endure the abſence of his Miſtris <persName rend="italic">Servilia Nais</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. This <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName> was the Father of him, who was known afterwards to be the buyer of the Goods and Chattels which <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> left by his Will; and was eminent for his dexterity in managing of Chariots, as well as for his Triumphal Ornaments, which he acquired by his magnanimity and conduct in the <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> Wars. <pb n="323"/> But his vices and paſſions gave no ſmall diminution to his Glory, for he was moſt notoriouſly arrogant, prodigal, and cruel. When he was but Ædilis, he forc'd <persName rend="italic">Lucius Plancus</persName> (though he was Cenſor) to give him the place. In his Conſulſhip and Prætorſhip he produc'd ſeveral Knights of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and Ladies of honour, to act Farces, and obſcure enterludes publickly upon the Stage. He exhibited baiting of wild Beaſts, not only in the Cirque, but in every quarter of the City; and Sword-plays with ſuch cruelty, that <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> having admoniſh'd him privately in vain, he was neceſſitated to reſtrain him by an Edict on purpoſe.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. Being married to <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> the Elder, he had a Son by her, worthy indeed to be the Father of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, as one that was deteſtable in every part of his life: in his youth he accompanied <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſar</persName> in a journey he made into the <placeName rend="italic">Levant</placeName>, in which he ſlew one of his freedmen; for no other cauſe, but for refuſing to drink as much as he commanded; being diſcharged therefore from the Company of his friends, he led his life with no leſs exorbitance than before; for in the <placeName rend="italic">Via Appia</placeName> he drove his Chariot over a boy on purpoſe, and trode him to death; and in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, in the middle of the Forum, he pull'd out a Gentlemans eye for reprehending him with more than ordinary liberty.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His perfidiouſneſs was ſo great, that he not only defeated the Goldſmiths of the prices of ſuch Commodities as they had bought; but in his Prætorſhip he defrauded the victors in the Chariot Courſes, of the rewards of their Victory; for which tricks his Siſter having merrily rebuk'd him, and the Maſters of the Factions made their ſolemn complaints, he ordain'd, That for the future the ſaid prices and rewards ſhould be paid them forthwith. <pb n="324"/> About the latter end of the Reign of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> he was accus'd of Treaſon, Adulteries and inceſt with his Siſter <persName rend="italic">Lepida</persName>, but he eſcap'd his puniſhment by the alteration of the times, and died at <placeName rend="italic">Pyrgi</placeName> of a Dropſie, leaving <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> his Son by <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> was born at <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName> on the fifteenth of <foreign rend="italic">December</foreign>, about Nine Months after the death of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, he came into the World ſo exactly at ſun-riſing, that his beams may be ſaid to have touch'd him before they fell upon the earth. Amongſt the many ill preſages which happen'd upon his Birth (of which ſeveral were very dreadful) his Father <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName> his Expreſſion was look'd upon as one; who being congratulated by his Friends upon the birth of his Son, made anſwer, <q rend="italic">That there could nothing proceed from <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> and him, but what was deteſtable, and pernitious to the Commonwealth.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Of the ſame future infelicity, there was an evident ſign alſo on the day he was named; for <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> being deſired by his Siſter to give the Child what name he thought good; the Emperour fixing his Eyes upon <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> (his Unkle by whom when he was Emperour afterwards, <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> was adopted) declared he gave him his name, which he did more in merriment than earneſt; and yet <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> took it exceedingly ill, <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> at that time being the only laughing-ſtock of the Court.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      When he was three years old he loſt his Father, who left him his heir but in a third part, and it had been well if he could have received all that: but his Coheir <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> having ſeized upon the Goods, and his Mother being baniſh'd, he was reduc'd to that condition, he was forc'd to be brought up in the houſe of <persName rend="italic">Lepida</persName> his Aunt, under the Pædagogy of a Dancing-Maſter, and a Barber. But <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> arriving at the Empire, he not only recovered his Fathers Eſtate, but was <pb n="325"/> very much enrich'd by the inheritance of <persName rend="italic">Criſpus Paſſienus</persName> his Father-in-law;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      His Mother likewiſe being recall'd, and having wrought her ſelf into the favour of the Emperour, he became ſo conſiderable, that he gave occaſion of Jealouſie to <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName> the Wife of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>: inſomuch that it was generally reported ſhe imployed ſeveral perſons to ſtrangle him as he was aſleep after dinner; ſuppoſing him to have deſigned himſelf a Competitor with <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName>; and it was added to the ſtory that they were diverted from their Enterprize by a Dragon, which coming ſuddenly from under his Pillow, frighted them away. That which gave foundation to this Fable, was, That there was found about his Bolſter the reliques of a Serpent, which by his Mothers command were inclos'd in a Bracelet of Gold, and wore a long time afterwards upon his right arm; at length abhorring any Monument or Memorial of his Mother he threw them away, but would gladly have had them again in his ſubſequent extremities, but could not recover them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. Before he was yet arriv'd at the fourteenth year of his age, he made himſelf eminent in the Circenſian Games, and eſpecially in a Combat a la Troyenne. At eleven years old he was adopted by <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>; and <persName rend="italic">Annæus Seneca</persName> (who was a Senator at that time) had the care of his inſtitution; it is reported that <persName rend="italic">Seneca</persName> dreamt the next night, he was teaching <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName>, which <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> made good in a ſhort time, diſcovering the ſame marks of inhumanity and ill nature, in the firſt experiments he could give; for taking it with great indignation that after his adoption, his Brother <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> ſaluted him by the name of <persName rend="italic">Ænobarbus</persName> as he was wont to do before; he endeavour'd to perſwade his Father, he was ſuppoſititious <pb n="326"/> and a Changling. His Aunt <persName rend="italic">Lepida</persName> being in affliction, he bare teſtimony againſt her in open Court, to gratifie his Mother, who was the perſon which proſecuted her ſeverely.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being call'd to the Bar, at the firſt pleading he made, he promiſed the people a Congiary, or Dole, and a Donative to the Souldier. Having proclaim'd a Tournament, he rid himſelf to the Liſts at the head of the Prætorian Cohorts, with a Shield in his hand; afterwards he gave his Father thanks ſolemnly in the Senate, and being Conſul, made a <foreign rend="italic">Latine</foreign> Oration in behalf of the <placeName rend="italic">Bononians</placeName>, and another in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> for the <placeName rend="italic">Rhodians</placeName>, and the Inhabitants of <placeName rend="italic">Ilium</placeName>. He began to exerciſe a Juriſdiction, as Governour of the City, upon the Holy-dayes of the <placeName rend="italic">Latines</placeName>; in which he ſate publickly to hear Cauſes, receiving and diſcuſſing ſeveral Pleas and Declarations with great patience, which were brought into the Court by the moſt conſiderable Advocates of the City; not formal and ſhort ones, as is cuſtomary, but moſt important, and many which were earneſtly moved; which was contrary to an expreſs Edict of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>. A while after he married <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, and exhibited the divertiſement of wilde Beaſts, and Circenſian Games, for the proſperity of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. On the ſeventeenth year of his age, the death of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> being publickly known, (having choſen the moſt propitious hour of the day to make his entrance upon the Empire, all the reſt of that day having been dire and portentous) he went forth amongſt his Guards: and being ſaluted Emperour by them before the ſtairs of his Palace, he was carried in a Litter into the Camp, and from thence having made a ſhort Speech to the Souldiers, he hurried away in great haſte to the Senate, where <pb n="327"/> he continued till Evening, and refus'd none of the immenſe honours accumulated upon him, but the Title of <foreign rend="italic">Pater Patriæ</foreign>, Father of his Countrey, and that in conſideration of his youth.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. Beginning his Empire in this manner, with a pretended oſtentation of Piety, he made a moſt magnificent Funeral for <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, prais'd him in a ſolemn Oration, and Conſecrated him when he had done. He perform'd great honours likewiſe to the memory of his Father <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName>: He gave his Mother an abſolute Juriſdiction in all things, both publick and private: The firſt day of his Government, to the Officer that attended him for the word, he gave only this, <foreign rend="italic">Optima Mater</foreign>, <q rend="italic">my beſt Mother</q>; and was many times afterwards ſeen publickly with her in the ſame Litter: He eſtabliſh'd a Colony at <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName>, in which he plac'd ſeveral of his Veteran Souldiers, drawn out of his Prætorian Cohorts, under the Command of the moſt wealthy of his Officers, after he had forc'd them to remove their habitations, where he made a Harbour alſo at an incredible expence.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. To give yet a more certain and acceptable teſtimony of his good Nature, he declar'd he would manage his affairs, and govern his people, according to the Model of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and omit no occaſion of ſhewing his liberality, clemency, and courteſie. Great Impoſitions he either took away quite, or reduc'd them to a competent moderation. The rewards due to Informers againſt ſuch as tranſgreſs'd againſt the Law <foreign rend="italic">Papian</foreign>, he retrench'd to a fourth. He diſtributed 400 Seſterces apiece to each of the people: To ſuch of the Senators as were poor, and illuſtriouſly deſcended, he allow'd annual Salaries, to the value ſometimes of 500000 Seſterces, <pb n="328"/> beſides a gratuity of Corn, which he allow'd monthly to his Prætorian Bands.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being deſired one day to ſet his hand to a Warrant, for the Execution of a condemn'd perſon, <q rend="italic">What would I give</q> (ſaid he) <q rend="italic">that I knew not how to write or read?</q> He was of ſo happy a memory, he ſaluted all the Orders of the City particularly by their names: The Senate giving him thanks for the juſtneſs of his Adminiſtration, he reply'd with ſingular modeſty, <q rend="italic">Let that alone till I deſerve it.</q> He was ſo much inclining to Popularity, that he admitted the common fort of people to his Exerciſes in the Field of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>. He declaimed in publick many times; He recited Verſes of his own making, and that not only privately in his own Houſe, but publickly upon the Theatre, and with ſo general an applauſe, a ſolemn Service and Proceſſion was appointed in honour of them, and ſome of them decreed to be writ in Letters of Gold, and dedicated to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. He gave them the diverſion of ſundry ſorts of Shows, as the Juvenal, and Circenſian Games, Stage-plays, and Sword-fights, and others: in the Juvenal paſtimes, he admitted old Conſularies, and Matrons; in the Circenſian Games, he appropriated a place for the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knights, in which they were private, and apart from the reſt of the people; and exhibited Courſes, with Chariots drawn by four Camels.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Such Plays as were inſtituted for the Eternity of the Empire, were by his order call'd <foreign rend="italic">Maximi</foreign>, in which perſons of both Orders and Sexes acted their parts: A Knight of moſt eminent quality in the City, pranc'd down a ſteep deſcent upon an Elephant. <pb n="329"/> There was acted alſo a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Comedy, compos'd by <persName rend="italic">Afranius</persName>, and intituled <foreign rend="italic">Incendium</foreign>, in which permiſſion was granted to the Actors, to rifle the Houſe as it was burning, and to take to themſelves what of the Houſhold-ſtuff they could catch. During theſe paſtimes, there was not a day but he ſcatter'd a thouſand Tickets, for all ſorts of things amongſt the people, as for Birds of ſeveral kinds, Corn, Cloths, Gold, Silver, Gems, Pearl, Pictures, Slaves, Horſes, and tamed Beaſts; and at laſt he gave them Ships, Houſes, Iſlands, and Eſtates, according to the Billets they produc'd, in which the names of all thoſe things were written.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. He beheld theſe Plays from the moſt eminent part of the Theatre: He built a Theatre of Wood in a years time, not far from the Field of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, in which he preſented them with Sword-fights, but without ſuffering any body to be kill'd, nay though he were a Malefactor. He brought into the Liſt 400 Senators, and 600 <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Gentlemen, (of good quality and Eſtates) to fight at ſharp, beſides others (not inferiour to them) to bait the wild Beaſts, and proſtitute themſelves to the moſt abject Offices of the Stage. He exhibited in like manner a Naval Fight upon Salt-water, with great Beaſts ſwimming in it; and infranchis'd ſeveral young Gentlemen which were Strangers, for having perform'd their parts handſomely in the Pyrrhick Dances.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In one of theſe Balls, by moſt admirable deſign, it was contriv'd that a Bull ſhould leap <persName rend="italic">Paſiphae</persName>, who was hidden in a Machine of Wood in the ſhape of a Cow; and it was acted ſo well, that many of the Spectators believ'd it was really ſo indeed. In the repreſentation of <persName rend="italic">Icarus</persName>, he which perſonated him, at the very firſt attempt of his flying, fell down ſo near the Emperours Box, that he was beſprinkled with his blood. <pb n="330"/> He ſate as Preſident very ſeldom at theſe Plays; his manner was moſt uſually to peep thorow a kind of a Lettice, but at laſt the whole Gallery was open'd, and he beheld them there.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He was the firſt which ever inſtituted Quinquennial Conteſts, or Prizes in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, after the Cuſtom of the <foreign rend="italic">Greeks</foreign>, and they were of three ſorts, Muſick, Wraſtling, and Horſemanſhip, which were called <foreign rend="italic">Neronia</foreign>. Having dedicated his Baths, and a place peculiar for all ſorts of Exerciſes, he allow'd Oyl for the Senators and Gentlemen gratis, ordaining perſons for Judges which had been Conſuls, to be elected by Lot, and ſit in the place of the Prætors. After this he came down into the Orcheſtra amongſt the Senators; and the Crown which was prepar'd for the prize and reward of him that ſhould tranſcend in <foreign rend="italic">Latine</foreign> Proſe, and Verſe, (for which the moſt eminent perſons of the City contended) being by their conſent adjudg'd to him, he accepted very willingly. The flattery of the Judges having preſented him with a Harp, he adored it, and commanded it to be carried to the Statue of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      On the day in which the Gymnick Games were celebrated in the <placeName rend="italic">Septa</placeName>, he was ſhaved the firſt time, (againſt the great Sacrifice call'd <foreign rend="italic">Buthyſia</foreign>) and having caus'd his Beard to be inclos'd in a Golden Box, ſet richly about with pretious Stones, he conſecrated it to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>; and becauſe the Prieſts of <persName rend="italic">Ceres</persName> at <placeName rend="italic">Olympia</placeName>, were allow'd to ſee the ſpectacles of Wraſtling, he invited the Veſtal Virgins to ſee his Champions.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. Amongſt the number of his Shows, we may put (and not improperly) the entrance of <persName rend="italic">Tiridates</persName> King of <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName> into the City. The day deſigned for his reception, by publick Edict was put <pb n="331"/> off by reaſon of ill weather for ſome time; but at length it proving fair, his Guards were plac'd about the Temples in the Forum, in their Arms, and he appear'd ſitting upon a Throne of Ivory before the <placeName rend="italic">Roſtra</placeName>, in his Triumphal habit, in the midſt of his Military Enſigns and Banners.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In this pomp and formality he receiv'd <persName rend="italic">Tiridates</persName>, who threw himſelf immediately at his feet, but he took him up again with his right hand, and kiſs'd him: after which having taken off his Tiara, he put the Diadem upon his head, and a perſon which had been Prætor being appointed to interpret, he pronounc'd aloud to the people whatever <persName rend="italic">Tiridates</persName> ſaid. After which the Emperour brought him into the Theatre, where <persName rend="italic">Tiridates</persName> having made new Complements of ſubmiſſion and humility, he took him and plac'd him on his right ſide next to himſelf: Whereupon he was ſaluted Emperour; and having caus'd a Crown of Laurel to be carried into the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, he ſhut up the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Janus</persName>, as a token of univerſal peace and tranquillity.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. He exercis'd the Office of Conſul four times; the firſt, for two months; the ſecond and the laſt, for ſix; and the third, for four: The ſecond and the third were ſucceſſive, but the other two with ſome years of intermiſſion between.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. In his ordinary Juriſdiction, he ſeldom gave anſwer to any motion or Petition, till the next day, and then alwayes in writing, to avoid miſtake: In ſuch Cauſes as were diſcuſs'd before him, his method was, to diſpatch them by turns, in the ſame order they were preſented. Having receiv'd the Opinions of the Judges diſtinctly in writing, he read them privately by himſelf, but gave Judgment according to his own fancy.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <pb n="332"/> It was a long time before he could be perſwaded to admit the Sons of Libertines into the Senate, and to ſuch of them as had been preferr'd by his Predeceſſors, he deny'd all honourable imployment. To ſweeten and ſupport ſuch Candidates as were ſupernumerary, and loſt their Elections, and to make them the more patient of their delay, he gave them the Command of his Legions. He conferr'd the Conſulſhip moſt commonly but for three months; and if either of the Conſuls died before the Calends of <foreign rend="italic">January</foreign>, he never ſubſtituted any in his place; abominating the preſident of <persName rend="italic">Caninius Rebilus</persName>, who was Conſul but for one day. He vouchſafed the Triumphal Ornaments, and thoſe which belong'd to the Quæſtorian Dignity, to ſome of the Equeſtrian Order, and that without reſpect of any ſervice perform'd by them in the Wars, to deſerve them. The accounts which were ſent to the Senate in ſome ſort of affairs he communicated to them by the Conſuls, paſſing by and waiving the Office of the Quæſtor, to whom it properly belong'd.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>



<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. He invented a new model for Houſes, contriving a kind of Gallery or Gatehouſe before every one of them, from the Battlements of which they might be able to beat off or avert any accident by fire, and thoſe he promis'd to build at his own charges. He had a reſolution likewiſe to extend the Walls of the City as far as <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>, from whence he deſign'd, by the help of a Canal, to bring the Sea into the Old Town.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Many things he reformed in his time, and many things inſtituted anew: He moderated their luxury in Entertainments, reducing their ſet and ſolemn Feaſts, to diſtributions and private Collations. He forbad by Proclamation the ſelling of any thing boyl'd in Taverns, beſides <pb n="333"/> Pulſe and Herbs, whereas before that they were allow'd to ſell all ſorts of meat: He perſecuted the <foreign rend="italic">Chriſtians</foreign> very ſeverely, by reaſon of the novelty of their Superſtition. The ſports of the Charioteers (who by long practice had got a liberty of cheating and pilfering (as it were in jeſt) whatever came in their way) he forbad alſo and ſuppreſs'd; as likewiſe the factions of the Mimicks and Buffons, whom he baniſh'd, with the Actors themſelves.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. To prevent Forgeries, it was contrived at that time, that no Tables or Books ſhould be ſigned or ſealed, before they were ſtruck through, and a thread drawn three times through the holes: That in all Wills, the two firſt Tables ſhould have nothing written in them, but the Names of the Teſtators, and that they ſhould be ſhew'd as blanks to the perſons which were to ſeal; that the perſon which drew the Will, ſhould not be capable of a Legacy, to prevent foiſting in his own name amongſt the reſt of the Legacies: Beſides theſe regulations, he ordain'd alſo, that ſuch Clients as had Suits depending, ſhould pay certain and reaſonable Fees to their Advocates, and no more; but for the Seats or Benches of Court, they ſhould pay nothing at all, there being allowance for that out of the Exchequer: That the Actions before the Commiſſioners of the Treaſury, ſhould be removed into the Common Pleas, before the Judges and Delegates, and that from the ſaid Judges no Appeal ſhould lye, but to the Senate themſelves.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      18. Having neither hopes nor deſign of propagating his Empire, he had once thoughts of withdrawing his Army out of <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName>, and had certainly done it, had it not been for ſhame, and fear of <pb n="334"/> eclipſing the Glory his Father had gain'd in thoſe parts. All that he did which was memorable, was only this, he reduc'd <placeName rend="italic">Pontus</placeName> into a Province, and that too by the conſent of <persName rend="italic">Polemon</persName> their King; and (when <persName rend="italic">Cottius</persName> was dead) he did as much for a Kingdom upon the <placeName rend="italic">Alpes</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      19. He never undertook but two Expeditions into Foreign parts, one into <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, and the other into <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName>; That into <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, he gave over the very day he took his reſolution, diſcourag'd partly by a Religious ſcruple, and partly by the danger of the Enterprize: For having gone in ſolemn Proceſſion about all the Temples in the City, and having ſate himſelf down at laſt in the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Veſta</persName>, when he aroſe again, his Gown was hung to the ſeat, and immediately there was ſuch a miſt before his eyes, as took away his ſight.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being arriv'd in <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName>, he propoſed to make a cut thorow the <placeName rend="italic">Iſthmus</placeName>, in order to a communication of the two Seas; and having aſſembled his Prætorian Cohorts, he made a Speech to them to begin the work chearfully; and for their greater encouragement, he commanded the ſignal to be given with a Trumpet; and having digg'd the firſt Scuttle full himſelf, he carried it away upon his own ſhoulders.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He made preparation likewiſe for an Expedition to the <placeName rend="italic">Caſpian</placeName> Gates, having liſted a new Legion of <placeName rend="italic">Italian</placeName> young men, each of them of ſix foot high, which he called the Squadron of <persName rend="italic">Alexander the Great</persName>. Thus far I have mentioned ſuch of his Actions as were either praiſe-worthy, or innocent; and I have put them together, to ſeparate and diſtinguiſh them from the wicked and deteſtable Actions, which I ſhall ſpeak <pb n="335"/> of hereafter.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      20. Among the reſt of the Sciences which he had learn'd in his minority, he had a particular eſteem for Muſick; inſomuch that as ſoon as he had poſſeſs'd himſelf of his Empire, he ſent immediately for <persName rend="italic">Trepnus</persName>, who was the moſt famous perſon for his skill upon the Harp in thoſe times; being arriv'd he lik'd his hand ſo well, that he paſs'd away the time every night in hearing him play, and ſing, ſometimes till it was very late; at length by his aſſiduous attention, he became capable of doing ſomething himſelf; and was ſo much delighted with that kind of Inſtrument, that he obſerv'd the ſame rules which the Maſters in thoſe profeſſions were accuſtomed to practice; either for the conſervation, or ſtrengthning of their Voices. He us'd to lie down upon his back, and lay a thin plate of lead upon his ſtomach, purged, and vomited often; abſtain'd from Apples and all meats reputed prejudicial to his Voice; till at laſt being conceited of his proficiency, he would needs appear upon the Stage, and ſing publickly before the People, though his Voice was neither ſtrong, nor clear; alledging a <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> Proverb ordinarily to his friends, <q rend="italic">That conceal'd Muſick was not valued at all.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The firſt place he ſhew'd his abilities in that kind, was in <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>; where though the Theatre was ſhaken with a ſudden Earth-quake, and in no ſmall danger of falling; yet he would not give over till he had finiſh'd the Song he had began. In the ſame place he ſang for ſeveral days together, without any intermiſſion, more than for the refreſhment of his Voice; and being grown impatient of living privately at home, he could not forbear ſhowing himſelf upon the Theatre as ſoon as he came out of his Baths; and having feaſted publickly in the Orcheſtra, in the preſence of the people, he promiſed them <pb n="336"/> in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>, <q rend="italic">That when he had waſh'd his throat, he would give them a Leſſon upon a Baſe note.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Being much delighted with the praiſes of ſome <placeName rend="italic">Alexandrians</placeName> which were but lately arrived at <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>, he ſent for more of them over in great haſte: beſides theſe he ſelected a certain number of young Gentlemen of the Equeſtrian Order, and above 5000 of the luſtieſt young men amongſt the Commons, which being divided into Squadrons, were to learn the three ſeveral ſorts of applauſes; one of them reſembling the humming of Bees, the other the falling of rain upon the Tiles, and the laſt, the clattering of earthen Veſſels one againſt another. Whilſt he was ſinging, he was attended by ſome of theſe Youths, the handſomeſt could be found, who were alwaies richly habited, their hair powder'd and perfum'd with all poſſible advantage, and a ring of great value upon their left hand; for whoſe particular Education and Conduct he appointed Governours, and allow'd them 400000 Seſterces for their penſions.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      21. He was ſo ſtrangely tranſported with Muſick, and Singing, that he renewed the <foreign rend="italic">Neronean</foreign> Priſes in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, before the time appointed at their firſt inſtitution. The people which were about him, deſiring one day in flattery to hear his Heavenly Voice, he told them, <q rend="italic">That being ſo importunate, they ſhould have it if they pleas'd, but it muſt be (publickly) in the Gardens;</q> But the Souldiers then upon the Guard, joyning their prayers to the reſt, he promis'd to ſatisfie them immediately, and without more ado, he entred his name in the liſt of Profeſſors of Muſick, and having put in his lot into the Urne amongſt the reſt of the Harpers, he entred upon the Theatre according to his lot, the Captain of his Guard carrying his Harp after him; the Tribunes of the Army attending <pb n="337"/> him with the moſt intimate of his friends.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having ſpoken his Prologue, he ſate down, and by the Mouth of <persName rend="italic">Cluvius Rufus</persName> a Conſulary man, he acquainted the people, that he would repreſent the ſtory of <persName rend="italic">Niobe</persName>, which he perform'd accordingly, and held it out till it was near the tenth hour of the day; and that he might have more frequent occaſion of ſinging, he put off and deferred the reſt of the conteſt, and the diſtribution of the prizes till the next year: But fancying that alſo ſomething too long, he forbore not to preſent himſelf uſually at all publick ſhews: In private plays likewiſe, he was not aſhamed to play his part amongſt the reſt of the Actors, and to accept of a Million of Seſterces which were offered him by one of the Prætors:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He ſang Tragedies in diſguiſes, perſonating the Heroes and Gods, the Goddeſſes and great Ladies of antient times, with Vizards and Masks adapted to his face, and the womans, according as he loved her: amongſt other things, he ſung and acted <persName rend="italic">Canace</persName> in travail; <persName rend="italic">Oreſtes</persName> murdering his Mother; <persName rend="italic">Oedipus</persName> pulling out his own eyes, and <persName rend="italic">Hercules</persName> in a Frenzy. In which laſt repreſentation, it is reported that a young Souldier at that time upon the Guard in the Theatre, ſeeing the Emperour dreſt, and bound in chains, as the argument required, ſuppoſing it real violence, he ran into his relief in good earneſt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      22. From his infancy, he was a great lover of Horſes, and would talk often of the Circenſian Games, though he was forbidden; Being rebuked by his Maſter upon a time, for lamenting a diſaſter which had befallen a Manager of the Chariots of the green faction, who falling from his Chariot, was dragg'd up and down the Courſe, he put it off with an excuſe, <pb n="338"/> and proteſted, <q rend="italic">He ſpake of no body but <persName rend="italic">Hector</persName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In the beginning of his Reign he entertain'd himſelf daily at a Game with Chariots of Ivory on a board, and there was nothing to be ſeen in the Circus, how flight and inconſiderable ſoever, but he would leave his retirements to be there, incognito at firſt, but afterwards publickly, ſo as every one knew what day he would be preſent. Having intimated that he would augment the number of prizes, the courſes were multiplied, and protracted till it grew late in the Evening, and the Maſters of the Factions became ſo malepert, they would not vouchſafe to bring out their Squadrons, unleſs they might be aſſured to run all day long.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      By degrees he took a fancy of driving a Chariot himſelf, and delighted to be frequently ſeen. Having taken his rudiments, and firſt practice in the Gardens amongſt the Slaves and inferiour ſort of people, he expos'd himſelf at length in the Grand Circus, to the eyes of all: one of his Freed-men giving the ſignal with a Napkin from the ſame place where the Magiſtrates were wont to do it. Nor was he contented to have given experiments of his skill and dexterity in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, but he muſt need go into <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName> (as I ſaid before) to perform as much there. All the Cities in which there were any prizes for Muſick having taken a reſolution to ſend the Crowns deſigned for the Players upon the Harp unto him; he took it ſo kindly, he not only preferr'd their Embaſſadours, and gave them audience before any of the reſt, but he admitted them to an entertainment he made for his moſt particular friends: and being deſired by one of them as they were ſitting at ſupper to give them a Song, he granted his requeſt, and (tranſported with their extravagant applauſe) cry'd out, <q rend="italic">The <foreign rend="italic">Greeks</foreign> were the only <pb n="339"/> perſons had a good ear, that none but they were worthy of him, and his endeavours.</q> Neither did he put off his Voyage any longer, for as ſoon as he had croſs'd over the Sea to <placeName rend="italic">Caſſiope</placeName>, he began to ſing immediately before the Altar of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Caſſius</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      23. After this, he was one at all prizes whatever: Thoſe Games which formerly celebrated at more remote times, he reduc'd into the compaſs of a year, reiterating ſome of them upon occaſion, and adding a Muſick prize to the Olympick exerciſes, contrary to the precedent cuſtom of the place. He was ſo much addicted to theſe ſorts of diverſions, that he made them his whole buſineſs and ſtudy; and being ſolicited earneſtly upon a time, by <persName rend="italic">Helius</persName> one of his Free-men, that he would return and be preſent at the adminiſtration of the City affairs, he writ him word back again in theſe terms, <q rend="italic">Though it be your deſire and advice I ſhould return with all diligence, yet you ought rather to wiſh, that <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> may return worthy of himſelf.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Whilſt he was ſinging, it was not permitted to any man to depart the Theatre, upon any occaſion though never ſo neceſſary; inſomuch that it is reported women were delivered there, and ſeveral perſons ſo tyred, with the tediouſneſs and flattery of the applauses, (the Gates of the place being ſhut up) that they either leap'd privately over the wall, or elſe fell down, and diſſembled themſelves dead, that they might be carried out as to their burials.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      It is ſcarce to be believed with what fear and anxiety, with what emulation of his adverſaries, with what apprehenſion of his Judges, he contended in theſe prizes. He was ſo mean and poor ſpirited, that he obſerv'd and pryed into every thing relating to his Competitors; if they were of the ſame condition and quality, he carry'd things fair with them outwardly, <pb n="340"/> but traduc'd them under hand, and took all wayes poſſible to diſparage them behind their backs; if they were indiſputably better skill'd, his way was then to bribe and corrupt them with preſents: And for the Judges he accoſted them with great reverence, and told them, <q rend="italic">That he had done what was poſſible to be done, but that the event was in the hands of Fortune, that being wiſe and learned men as they were, it belong'd to them to exclude things of fortune and chance.</q> The Judges animating and incouraging him by their fair words, he withdrew better ſatisfied a little, yet it was ſeldom without jealouſie; for if any of them had ſaid nothing, he took not their ſilence for an effect of their modeſty, but on the contrary imputed it to the doggedneſs and malignity of their nature, and could not forbear declaring that he had them in ſuſpicion.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      24. In all his contentions he was ſo ſtrict and punctual an obſerver of the Laws, that he never durſt venture to ſpit, nor to wipe the ſweat off of his forehead, with any thing but his arm: In a Tragedy in which he acted one day, his Baton falling out of his hand, he took it up again immediately, but it was in ſuch diſorder, and fear of being rejected for that miſcarriage, that he could not recollect himſelf till one of the Actors in flattery aſſured him with an oath, that the ſhouts and acclamations of the people being ſo great, ſo ſmall a thing as that could not be obſerved. When he was Victor in any prize, his cuſtom was, to pronounce his own Victory himſelf, for which cauſe he was in perpetual contention with the Cryer. And to the end that there might remain no Monument or Footſtep of any other Victors, he commanded their ſtatues to be pull'd down in all places, to be dragged along the ſtreets, <pb n="341"/> and thrown into the Common-ſhores.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He diverted himſelf many times with managing the Chariot; in the Olympick Games, he drove one with ten Horſes; though in one of his Poems he reproach'd a King <persName rend="italic">Mithridates</persName> for doing the ſame: His Courſe was ſo furious, he was thrown out of his Box, where being remounted again, and not able to continue, he gave over before he had finiſh'd his Carier; yet he carried the prize nevertheleſs: At his departure from thence, he enfranchiſed the whole Province, made the Judges free of the City, beſides conſiderable preſents which he gave them in ready money, which bountiful actions he proclaim'd publickly with his own Mouth, from the middle of the courſe on the day they celebrated the <foreign rend="italic">Iſthmian</foreign> Games.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      25. Being returned from <placeName rend="italic">Greece</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>, he entred into the Town through a breach in the Wall (according to the Cuſtom of Victors) in a Chariot drawn with white Horſes, that being the place in which he had firſt improv'd himſelf in thoſe Arts. The ſame Courſe he obſerv'd in his entries at <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Albanum</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; where he entred in the ſame Chair in which <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> made his Triumph, habited in a Purple Robe, his Mantle ſtudded with ſtars of Gold, with an Olympick Crown upon his head, a Pythick Crown in his right hand, and others carried before him in great Pomp, with inſcriptions not only where and whom he conquer'd, but the very Subject and argument of each fable and ſong. Immediately after his Chariot, followed a throng of people, with their acclamations and applauſes according to the manner of an Ovation, crying out with a loud voice, they were <foreign rend="italic">Auguſtians</foreign>, and the Souldiers of his Triumph. From thence, (having caus'd an Arch of the Grand Cirque to be beaten down) he march'd <pb n="342"/> through the <placeName rend="italic">Velabrum</placeName> and Forum, ſtraight up to the <placeName rend="italic">Palatium</placeName>, and from thence to the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName>: In his paſſage ſacrifices were offer'd all along, ſaffron ſtrewed about the ſtreets, Birds were let fly, and Ribands and Junckets thrown amongſt the people.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being arrived at his Palace, they hung the Crowns which he had won at thoſe ſacred conteſts, round about his bed, upon ſeveral of his Statues in the habit of a Harper, with which impreſſion he caus'd his Money to be ſtamp'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      After this he was ſo far from remitting any thing of his ſtudies in this kind, that for the preſervation of his Voice, he never made ſpeech to his Souldiers more, but ſignified his pleaſure to them either in writing, or by the mouth of another Man. Nor would he do any thing either ſeriouſly or in merriment unleſs his Phonaſcus (who had the care of his voice) was by, to admoniſh him to take heed he did not ſtrain himſelf too much, and to thruſt his handkerchief to his Mouth if he perſiſted: In ſhort, he was ſo jealous and ſo ambitious of the glory of ſinging and playing well, that he profeſt himſelf a friend or an Enemy according as every man commended him more or leſs.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      26. At firſt he endeavoured to conceal his petulancy, luſt, luxury, avarice and cruelty, as if he had deſigned to have them thought only the extravagancies of his youth: but it was clear enough to every body, they were the effects of his Nature. As ſoon as the Evening was ſhut in, he put on a diſguiſe, and away amongſt the Taverns and Victualing-houſes, wandring and playing about the ſtreets, beating ſuch as he found late abroad, wounding ſuch as reſiſted, drenching them in the houſes of Office; breaking up ſhops and plundering them <pb n="343"/> when he had done; having firſt eſtabliſh'd a Fair, or Market in his houſe, where all that he ſtole or pillaged were expoſed to ſale.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      However in theſe frolicks he ran a hazard many times, not only of loſing his Eyes, but his life; Once he was battered almoſt to death, by a Senator, to whoſe Wife he had offer'd ſome incivility; and thereupon he never went abroad ſo late afterwards, but he had ſome of the Officers of his Guards following him privately at a diſtance. In the day time being convey'd in a Chair into the Theatre, he not only beheld the quarrels and mutinies of the Players from the upper part of the Proſcenium, but he ſet them together by the Ears, and when they were engaged, he took great delight in throwing Stones, and pieces of Wood amongſt people, with which he once brake the head of a Prætor.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      27. But by degrees his Vices increas'd ſo, that he laid aſide all pretence of jeſting or ſhame, and without all care of concealing or excuſing what he did, he flew out into greater and more publick exorbitancies.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He ſpun out his Meals from noon to midnight, refreſhing himſelf often with hot or cold Baths, according to the ſeaſon of the year, or the variety of the weather. He feaſted many times alſo in publick, ſometimes in the <placeName rend="italic">Naumachia</placeName>, or place deſigned for the Naval Combats, ſometimes in the Field of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, and ſometimes in the Grand Circus, attended by the moſt debauch'd and moſt infamous women of the whole City.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      As often as he went down the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>, or paſs'd by the <placeName rend="italic">Baian</placeName> Gulf, Booths were ſet up along the banks, and women diſpoſed at their ſeveral doors, to invite and allure him on either ſhore. He invited himſelf to Supper likewiſe to his more particular Friends, and <pb n="344"/> they treated him uſually with ſo much magnificence, that one of them ſpent 400 millions of Seſterces on a Sweet-bag, at one Entertainment; and another ſomething more, in Roſes, odoriferous Diſtillations, and Perfumes.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      28. Beſides his unnatural converſation with Boys, and his adulteries with married Women, he deflowered a Veſtal Virgin call'd <persName rend="italic">Rubria</persName>: He was very near marrying of <persName rend="italic">Acte</persName>, who was no more than a Freed-woman; though he brib'd and ſuborn'd certain perſons who had been Conſuls, to ſwear and aſſert that ſhe was of Royal Extraction. Having caus'd a youth named <persName rend="italic">Sporus</persName> to be gelt, his folly was ſo great, that he endeavour'd to transform him quite into a Woman; after which he married him, with the uſual formalities of a Dowry, and Veyle, and kept him afterwards in his houſe in the quality of his Wife: upon which occaſion it was wittily ſaid, <q rend="italic">That the World had been happy, if <persName rend="italic">Nero's</persName> Father <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName> had had no better a Spouſe.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He caus'd this <persName rend="italic">Sporus</persName> to be dreſs'd up in the habit of an Empreſs, and carrying him in a Litter, he accompanied him publickly in the Aſſizes and Market Towns of <placeName rend="italic">Greece</placeName>, and afterwards in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> about the Street <placeName rend="italic">Sigillaria</placeName>, kiſſing him frequently as they paſs'd along. It is not doubted at all, but he had a paſſionate deſire to lye with his own Mother; but he was diverted from that, by certain of her back friends, who apprehended leſt ſo great a favour ſhould make her (who was proud and high enough already) much more inſolent and miſchievous: And as a mark of his inceſtuous deſires, having underſtood there was a Lady at that time extremely like his Mother <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, he ſent for her, and receiv'd her amongſt his Concubines. It is reported likewiſe, <pb n="345"/> that whenever he rode alone in the Litter with his Mother, he had his inceſtuous dalliances with her, which were diſcover'd by the ſpotting and pollution of his Clothes.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      29. He proſtituted himſelf in ſuch manner to all ſorts of uncleanneſs, that there was ſcarce a part in his body undefiled. At laſt he invented a new kind of paſtime, altogether abominable: Having cover'd himſelf over with the skin of a wild Beaſt, he was ſlipt (as it were) ſuddenly out of a Cave, and fell violently upon the ſecrets of men and women, which he had order'd to be faſten'd ſtark naked to a ſtake hard by; and when he had ſatisfied his brutality, he was to be killed (in jeſt) by his Freed-man <persName rend="italic">Doriphorus</persName>, to whom he was married, (as <persName rend="italic">Sporus</persName> was to him) and counterfeited the cryes and complaints of a new married Virgin: I have been told by divers, that he was abſolutely perſwaded, all people were as wicked and unchaſt as himſelf, but that they had generally the diſcretion to conceal it: Whereupon whoever profeſs'd his own obſcenity freely, he as freely forgave him all the reſt of his Crimes, of what nature ſoever they were.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      30. He was of opinion, that all the pleaſure and advantage of Riches, conſiſted in laviſhneſs and profuſion; eſteeming them moſt penuriouſly ſordid, who kept any accompt of their Expences, and them as ſplendidly magnificent, who ſquander'd and conſum'd all. He never mention'd his Unkle <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, but with an Elogie, becauſe in ſo ſhort a time he had diſſipated the vaſt ſums which <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> had left him: for which reaſons he obſerv'd no meaſure in his Gifts or Expences.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Tis almoſt incredible, and yet 'tis true, he allow'd <persName rend="italic">Tiridates</persName> 20000 Crowns a <pb n="346"/> day, whilſt he continued in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and at his departure he made him a Preſent of above a hundred millions of Seſterces more. He gave to <persName rend="italic">Menecrates</persName> a Harper, and to <persName rend="italic">Spicillus</persName> a Sword-player, the Patrimonies and Houſes of Noble perſons, and ſuch as had had the honour of a Triumph. He made a moſt princely Funeral for his Monkey, on whom he had beſtow'd the Eſtate of <persName rend="italic">Paneros</persName> the Uſurer, both in the City and Countrey.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He never put on one Garment, above once. At Dice he ventured ordinarily 400 Seſterces upon every point: When he fiſh'd, his Net was of Gold, and the Cords of Purple, or Scarlet died in Grain. He never travell'd with leſs than a thouſand Chariots in his Train; his Mules ſhod with Silver, and his Mulitiers in fine Crimſon Liveries of Cloth of <placeName rend="italic">Canuſium</placeName>; beſides an Horſe-Guard of <placeName rend="italic">Africans</placeName>, with Bracelets and other accoutrements, very glorious and rich, and Foot-men.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


<pb n="348"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Caves under ground in <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName>; and might be got out again with very little pains.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      32. But his hopes being fruſtrate in that, and his treaſures ſo exhausted that he was not able to pay his Souldiers or gratifie his Veterans as he had formerly done, without running in their ſcore; and putting them off, he betook himſelf to all manner of circumvention and rapine.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The firſt thing he decreed was, that inſtead of the Moiety, three fourths ſhould be required and collected out of the Eſtates of ſuch enfranchiſed perſons, as without juſt cauſe had aſſumed the name of any of the Families, to which he was allied; that their Wills ſhould be void, and their Poſſeſſions confiſcate, who had ſhown themselves ungrateful to their Prince in leaving him nothing, and that ſuch Lawyers as had drawn or dictated the ſaid Wills, ſhould be finable and puniſh'd. That all words and actions ſhould be brought within the Compass of Treaſon, if there was but any one informer to juſtifie the accuſation.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He redemanded all the Crowns and rewards which ſeveral Cities had offer'd him at any time, and he refus'd. Having forbid the use of the Violet and Purple colours, he ſent one privately to ſell ſome few ounces upon a Fair, and then pretending diſobedience of his Orders, he clapt up all the Merchants which had bought them. Another time as he was ſinging, he obſerv'd a Lady in the Theatre habited in Purple, and having made ſigns to his Officers to apprehend her, he not only caus'd her to be pull'd down, and her Robe to be taken away, but he took away her estate alſo.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He never gave any man an office, but he had theſe words into the bargain; <q rend="italic">You know what I need, and let us make it our business that no man may have any thing to call his own.</q> Finally he ſpared not the very <pb n="349"/> Temples themselves, from whence he took away all their Gifts and Oblations of any conſiderable value; melting down their Images of Gold and Silver, not excuſing ſo much as the Images of the Tutelar Gods, which <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> restored within a while afterwards.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      33. His Parricides and Murders he began with <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, of whoſe death though he was not principally the Author, yet he was an accomplice, and acceſſary thereunto: Neither did he at all diſſemble the matter, alleadging many times a <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> Proverb in commendation of Muſhromes, and crying them up, as Meat for the Gods, becauſe <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> was poiſoned with one of them: This is moſt certain, when he was dead he abus'd his memory with the moſt opprobrious Calumnies he could invent, accuſing him ſometimes of cruelty, ſometimes of folly, never ſpeaking of him but with ſcorn, and to expreſs, <q rend="italic">He had ceas'd to live</q>, he would say, <q rend="italic">He had ceas'd to play the fool amongst men;</q> perverting the meaning of the word <foreign rend="italic">Morari</foreign>, by making the firſt Syllable long, which ought to have been ſhort. He reſcinded many of his Acts and Conſtitutions, as the decrees of an idle and diſtracted man; and without ſhowing any reſpect to his memory or aſhes, he caus'd them to be buried in a very mean Tomb, railed in with ſome ſlight and inconſiderable matter:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The envy he bore to <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> (as well by reason of his voice (which was better than his) as becauſe he was jealous leſt the Memory of his Father might gain him the affection of the people, to his diſadvantage and prejudice) put him upon a reſolution of giving him poiſon. He made uſe of a woman called <persName rend="italic">Locusta</persName>, who had accus'd ſeveral perſons of conſpiracies in that kind: But the poiſon not working <pb n="350"/> ſo quick as he expected, produc'd no other effect but a lask, and ſome Gripings in the Belly of <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName>, whereupon he caus'd <persName rend="italic">Locusta</persName> to be called, fell upon, and beat her with his own hands, and reproach'd her, that inſtead of poiſon, ſhe had given him an antidote; To which as ſhe excus'd her ſelf for having given it no ſtronger on purpoſe, that ſhe might the better conceal the impiety of the Fact, <q rend="italic">Why then</q>, ſaid he, <q rend="italic">Doest thou think I am afraid of the Law <foreign rend="italic">Julia</foreign> also?</q> and commanded her forthwith to make another preſently in his Chamber, that might be more violent and Mortal;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      which being perform'd accordingly, for experiment fake he gave it to a Kid, who not dying in less than five hours time, he caus'd it to be boyled over again and again, and then gave it to a Pig, which died immediately Judging it ſtrong enough then, and proper for his deſign, he commanded it to be brought into the room, and given to <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> as he ſate at Supper with him. <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> had no ſooner taken it, but he fell down, and no fooner was he dead, but <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> was ready with a lye, pretending to the Company, that it was a fit of the falling fickness with which he was commonly troubled; and the next day in great haſt hurried him away to his funeral in the midst of a fierce ſhower of rain without any Pomp or ſolemnity; And to the ſaid <persName rend="italic">Locusta</persName> for her good ſervice, he gave not only impunity for all the crimes ſhe had ever committed, but large poſſeſſions in lands, and permitted her to take Scholars, and to train them up in that pernitious Science.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      34. Not being able to endure the admoniſhment of his Mother, who (as he thought) look'd too narrowly into his actions, (being at firſt only offended) he pretended he would reſign his Government and <pb n="351"/> retire to <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName>, deſigning thereby to make her odious to the people. But at length he made ſo bold with her, as to deprive her of all the honour and authority ſhe formerly had; He took away her <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> Guards, turn'd her out of his Palace and company, omitting no miſchief whatsoever that might perplex her. Whilſt ſhe was in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> he ſuborn'd people to moleft her with ſuits, when ſhe was retired, he imploy'd others to interrupt her tranquillity with ill language or bitter ſcoffs as they paſt by that way, either by land or Sea.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But ſhe being a Princeſs of invincible magnanimity, ſhe terrified him ſo with her threats, and her violence, that he reſolv'd to diſpatch her. Having three times attempted her with poiſon, and perceiving ſhe was fortified with Antidotes, he contrived a way of looſning the roof of her Chamber artificially in the night, and letting it fall upon her: But this deſign being not kept private enough by ſome of the Conſpirators, he deviſed a Ship by the ſudden opening of which ſhe might fall into the Sea, or be knock'd on the head by the Fall of the Fore-Caſtle, where ſhe was to be. Having laid this Plot, he pretended a great deſire to reconcile himself to her, writ ſeveral Letters to her, full of civility and reſpect, inviting her very kindly to <placeName rend="italic">Baia</placeName>, that they might be preſent together at the ſolemnity of the <foreign rend="italic">Quinquatria</foreign> or feſtival in honour of <persName rend="italic">Minerva</persName>, and ſhe accepted of the invitation. In the mean time he had given order to the Captain of his Galleys, to overſet that Galley in which <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> ſhould come, as if he had fallen foul upon her by accident, and to give the more time for the Execution of this Enterprize, he protracted the feaſt as long as he could: When she returned to <placeName rend="italic">Bauli</placeName>, in ſtead of that Ship which was ſhatter'd as beforeſaid, he <pb n="352"/> made her an humble proffer, of his Veſſel with Machines, built on purpoſe for her deſtruction: Having waited upon her abroad, and accompanied her there for ſome time with many Careſſes and much chearfulness, kiſſing her Breaſts with all imaginable kindness when he took his leave;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      he paſt the reſt of the time in no ſmall anxiety, attending the ſucceſs of his deſign: But when the news arrived that all things went croſs, and that his Mother had ſwum to ſhore, and was ſafe, being utterly at a loſs and not knowing what to do next: as <persName rend="italic">L. Agernius</persName> one of his freed-men, brought him word with great joy, that she was alive, and very well; he commanded a Dagger to be conveyed near him privately, and then causing that to be diſcover'd, he order'd him to be apprehended and clapt in Chains, as one hired to murder him; at the ſame he diſpatch'd another to kill his Mother if it were poſſible; reſolving to give out that ſhe had made away her ſelf upon the fruſtration of her deſign, to avoid the punishment ſhe deſerved.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      There are Authors of very good authority, which report things more inhumane than theſe; as that upon tidings that his Mother was ſlain, as he had appointed, he had the curioſity to go ſee her Corps, to handle every part of it, ſome of which he found fault with, others he commended, and being thirſty, He drank in the interim. Nevertheleſs the fact being once done, all the applauſes, and Congratulations of the Souldiers, Senate, or People, could not prevent or relieve him againſt the perpetual remorſes of his Conſcience: he confeſt he was haunted with his Mothers Ghoſt, that he was tormented with the whips, and burning torches of the Furies; He applied himself to the Magicians, and endeavoured by one of their ſacrifices <pb n="353"/> to call up their Manes, and intreat them to forgive him: Having made a Voyage thorough <placeName rend="italic">Greece</placeName> to that purpoſe, he durſt not be preſent at the <foreign rend="italic">Eluſine</foreign> Ceremonies, when he heard the Cryer commanding with a loud voice, all impious and profane perſons to depart:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      Yet all this could not hinder from adding the Murder of his Aunt, to the Parricidie of his Mother. His Aunt being ill and not enjoying the benefit of Nature, he made her a viſit one day, and the good old Lady amongſt the reſt of her Careſſes taking him gently by the down of his beard, which as then was not cut, and hapning to ſay in Complaiſance, <q rend="italic">Might I but live to take up this hair when it is cut off, I could die with content.</q> He turn'd about to his Companions, and in deriſion reply'd he would have it cut off immediately for her ſake; and then gave order to the Phyſitians to purge her more ſtrongly; She was no ſooner dead but he ſeized upon all her Eſtate, and ſuppreſt her will, leſt any thing ſhould eſcape him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      35. Besides his firſt Wife <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, he had two others, the firſt was <persName rend="italic">Poppæa Sabina</persName> the Daughter of one who had been Quæſtor, and married formerly to a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight: The ſecond was <persName rend="italic">Statilia Meſſalina</persName>, Grand-daughter in the third degree to <persName rend="italic">Taurus</persName> who had been twice Conſul, and Triumph'd once; ſhe was married to <persName rend="italic">Atticus Vestinus</persName> the Conſul who was murder'd by <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>'s Command in the very time of his Conſulſhip, to make way for his injoyment of her. He quickly neglected the Converſation of <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, and being reproved by ſome of his friends, he made anſwer, <q rend="italic">That the Jewels and Ornaments of a Wife were ſufficient for her.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After he had many times attempted to ſtrangle her in vain, he divorc'd her under pretence of barrenneſs, and obſerving the people <pb n="354"/> diſſatisfy'd with what he had done, and murmuring againſt it, he baniſh'd her quite. At length he accus'd her of adultery, and put her to death; but the charge was ſo impudently falſe, that all the Witneſſes he caus'd to be examin'd, endur'd the Torture, and denyed it to the laſt; infomuch that he was conftrain'd to fuborn <persName rend="italic">Anicetus</persName> his own Page, who confeſt he had lyen with her, but it was by Circumvention.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The twelfth day after he had divorced <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, he married <persName rend="italic">Poppæa</persName>, and loved her entirely, yet he killed her with a kick, though ſhe was ſickly and with Child, for no other reaſon, but ſpeaking fomething ſharply to him for coming home late from a running of Chariots. By her he had a Daughter named <persName rend="italic">Claudia Augusta</persName>, who dyed very young:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He violated all the laws of Nature, and there was no fort of relation he had, which his cruelty excus'd. <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> refufing to marry him after <persName rend="italic">Poppæas</persName> death, he caus'd her to be flain, upon pretence of Conſpiracy against him and the State. In like manner he made away the reft which were any way allied, or near him in blood. Among whom <persName rend="italic">Aulus Plancus</persName> a young Gentleman, being one; He abus'd his body by violence firſt, and then caus'd him to be cut in pieces, giving out that he was his Mothers Gallant, and that ſhe had promis'd him the Empire, whereupon he ſaid in deriſion when he had the news of his death; <q rend="italic">'Tis well! let my mother kiss my Succeſſor now if she pleaſes.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      His Son-in-law <persName rend="italic">Rufinus Criſpinus</persName> the Son of <persName rend="italic">Poppæa</persName>, being as yet but a Lad, becauſe he was reported to perfonate Emperours and Captains in his recreations amongſt his playfellows, he corrupted his own ſervants to throw him headlong (as he was one day fiſhing) into the Sea. He baniſh'd <persName rend="italic">Tuſcus</persName>, his Nur<pb n="355"/>ſes Son, for that during his Superintendency in <placeName rend="italic">Ægypt</placeName>, he had the preſumption to bath himself in the Baths which the <placeName rend="italic">Ægyptians</placeName> had built on purpoſe againſt <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>'s arrival: He forced <persName rend="italic">Seneca</persName> (his Tutor) to kill himself, though he had sworn moſt ſolemnly to him ſeveral times, (both when he petition'd for liberty to depart the Court, and when he gave him his Eſtate) <q rend="italic">That he was ſuſpicious without reason, and that he would rather dye himſelf, than do him any prejudice or hurt.</q> <persName rend="italic">Burrus</persName> the Captain of his Guards, being troubled with a diſtemper in his throat, he promis'd him a remedy, and ſending him poiſon, was as good as his word: With the ſame inhumanity he uſed ſeveral of his Freed-men, eſpecially if they were antient and rich, poiſoning ſome of them in their meat, and ſome in their drinks, though they had not only been conſiderably inſtrumental in his Adoption, but aſſiſtant likewise, and of importance to him, in the Government of the State.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      36. Neither were Strangers and Foreigners more exempt from his fury, than his Friends; A Blazing-ſtar appearing about that time, (which being look'd upon as an infallible portent of misfortune to ſome Soveraign Power) <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> was under no ſmall trouble; but <persName rend="italic">Babilus</persName> the Aſtrologer having acquainted him, that among Monarchs it was uſual upon ſuch occaſions, to expiate thoſe ſad Omens, by ſome extraordinary Maſſacre, recollecting himſelf, he reſolv'd to turn that Judgement upon the heads of his Nobles, and to exterminate whatever he thought conſiderable in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>: which enterprize he undertook the more willingly, and with juſter cauſe, as it appear'd, by reaſon of the diſcovery of two Conſpiracies againſt him; one of them (and that the <pb n="356"/> moſt dangerous) was managed by <persName rend="italic">Piso</persName>, and his friends at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; the other at <placeName rend="italic">Beneventum</placeName>, by <persName rend="italic">Vinicius</persName>, and his party:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The Conſpirators were brought to their Trial, and pleaded in Chains; they unanimouſly acknowledged the fact, and ſome of them juſtified it, alledging, <q rend="italic">That the Emperour being ſo ſcandalouſly flagitious, they knew not any better way they could ſerve him, than by putting him to death.</q> The Children of ſuch perſons as were condemn'd, were expelled the City immediately, and afterwards made away either by poiſon, or ſterving. It is moſt certainly tranſmitted in Hiſtory, that ſome of them with their Tutors, and Book-keepers, were poiſoned at one meal, and that others were kept up from their meat, and ſtarved.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      37. After this, he obſerv'd no rule or moderation either in the choice or manner of Execution of whomsoever he pleas'd: Not to enlarge my ſelf too far, it was objected against <persName rend="italic">Salvidienus Orfitus</persName>, that he had let three rooms out of his House near the Forum, to Foreign Cities, as Lodgings for their Deputies. The quarrel against <persName rend="italic">Caſſius Longinus</persName> (a blind Lawyer) was, that he had ſet up the Picture of <persName rend="italic">C. Caſſius</persName>, one of the murderers of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> amongſt the reſt of his Ancestors. Against <persName rend="italic">Thraſeas Pætus</persName> he could find no fault, but that his countenance was ſevere, and he had the looks of a School-maſter.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He ſeldom or never gave above one hours time to any he condemned, and that there might be no protraction or delay, he ſent his Chyrurgions to them to cure them out of hand, (for ſo he call'd opening their veins, that they might bleed to death.) There was in his time a great Eater at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, who devoured raw fleſh, and whatever elfe they gave him: It is reported that <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> (what<pb n="357"/>ever happen'd to divert him) had a great fancy to have live-men torn in pieces, and thrown to him to be conſum'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Being not a little elated with theſe variety of ſeeming ſucceſſes, he became ſo inſolent, he aſſerted publickly, <q rend="italic">That none of his Predeceſſors had known their own power.</q> He took ſo little care of diſſembling his animoſity against the Senate, that he gave out many, and downright expreſſions, that his deſign was utterly to deſtroy that Order, and to put the Government of the Provinces and Armies into the hands of the Knights, and his Freed-men. Either at his going or coming, he vouchſafed to kiſs none of them, nor to return them ſo much as a common ſalute. In the Ceremonies before he began to cut the Iſthmus in <placeName rend="italic">Corinth</placeName>, in a great Aſſembly, he publickly wiſh'd, <q rend="italic">That the deſign might take, and turn to his advantage, and to the advantage of the Commonwealth;</q> not ſo much as mentioning the Senate at all.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      38. He ſpared neither the People, nor the Walls of his Countrey: One chancing in his private converſation to ſay in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>;
      <q rend="italic">What do I care, when I expire,
      If the whole Earth be mixt with Fire.</q>
      <q rend="italic">Nay rather</q>, quoth he, <foreign rend="italic">᾿Εμᾶ ζῶντο;</foreign>
      <q rend="italic">If I might have mine own deſire,
      I'de ſet it whilſt I live on Fire.</q>
      And ſo he did, for being diſpleaſed, as he pretended, with the deformity of the old Buildings, and the narrowness, and unhandſome windings of the Streets, he ſet it on Fire ſo publickly, that ſeveral <pb n="358"/> of his Officers being taken by the Conſulares in their houſes, as it were in the very act, with Fire and Flax in their hands, they let them go without daring to meddle with them: There being certain Store-houſes likewise about his Golden Palace (which ground he desired to have) not being ſo eaſily burnt, becauſe the Walls were of Stone, he caus'd them to be beaten down with his Engines of War.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In this manner the Fire continued for ſix dayes, and ſeven nights, the people being forc'd for refuge into the Tombs and Monuments of the dead: Beſides an infinite number of common houſes, there were conſum'd the Palaces of all the antient Commanders, (adorn'd at that very day with the Spoils of their Enemies;) the Temples alſo which were conſecrated by the Kings, and afterwards by the piety of our Ancestors, in the <placeName rend="italic">Punick</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Gallick</placeName> Wars; in ſhort, all the Noble Monuments of Antiquity, how memorable or magnificent ſoever they were, had the ſame fate and deſtiny in this barbarous Conflagration: Nevertheleſs <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> was ſo far from the leaſt touch of ſorrow or compaſſion, that he look'd upon the Fire all the while from the Tower of <persName rend="italic">Mæcenas</persName>, ſporting himſelf therewith, as an object of pleaſure and diverſion; and being as he ſaid, much taken with the proſpect of the Flame, he ſang the deſtruction of <placeName rend="italic">Troy</placeName>, in the very ſame habit he used to ſing upon the Stage.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      And leſt he ſhould not be ſo great a gainer, as he propos'd when he began it, he promis'd to carry out the rubbiſh and dead bodies at his own charge; and therefore he would not ſuffer any one to go about to extinguiſh the Fire, or to preſerve ſuch Goods as remain'd: Yet not contented with theſe rapines at home, he ruined <pb n="359"/> the Provinces, and private perſons abroad, with his Taxes and Impoſitions.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      39. To theſe deſolations and miſeries from their Prince, there were added ſome fortuitous calamities, which gave no ſmall affliction to the people: In one Autumn they were ſo furiously infeſted with the Plague, that there died above thirty thouſand perſons, as appear'd by the Records in the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Venus Libitina</persName>. In <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName> two of their principal Garriſons were ſack'd with great ſlaughter of the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName>, and their Allies. In the Eaſtern parts, their loſſes were accompanied with diſhonour; the Legions in <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName> being put under the yoke, and <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName> preſerv'd with very great difficulty. But that which was wonderful, and eſpecially to be taken notice of in all his occurrences, was his patience and unconcernment at all the Obloquies of the people, and that he should behave himſelf with the ſame equality and compoſedneſs, in the midſt of the Execrations of ſuch as had provok'd him with their Sarcaſms and Satyrs:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Many Verſes in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> and in <foreign rend="italic">Latine</foreign> were publickly thrown about, upbraiding him with the infamy and barbarity of his Actions: Some of them were theſe.
      <q rend="italic"><persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Oreſtes</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Alcmæon</persName> ſlew
      Their Mother: <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> first his Mother knew.</q>
      <q rend="italic">Quis negat <persName rend="italic">Æneæ</persName> magna de ſtirpe <persName rend="italic">Neronem</persName>?
      Suftulit hic matrem, ſuſtulit ille patrem.
      Dum tendit citharam noſter, dum cornua <placeName rend="italic">Parthus</placeName>,
      Noſter erit Pæan, ille Hecatebeletes.
      <placeName rend="italic">Roma</placeName> domus fiet: <placeName rend="italic">Veios</placeName> migrate Quirites,
      Si non &amp; <placeName rend="italic">Veios</placeName> occupat iſt a domus.</q>
      <pb n="360"/>
      <q rend="italic">That <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>'s of <persName rend="italic">Eneas</persName> race, is clear,
      Their Sympathy and Actions makes't appear:
      <persName rend="italic">Æneas</persName> made his Fathers way, and tho th'other
      (In imitation) made away his Mother:
      <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> doth with his Harp like <persName rend="italic">Pæan</persName> ſhow,
      The <placeName rend="italic">Parthian</placeName>-like <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName> with his Bow.
      <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>'s but one House: To <placeName rend="italic">Veii</placeName> fly, leſt e're
      You reach that Town, the House it ſelf gets there.</q>
      But he never ſo much as enquired after the Authors; and when ſome of them were diſcover'd to the Senate, he would not ſuffer them to be puniſh'd ſeverely.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Iſidorus</persName> the Cynick ſeeing him paſs by in publick one day, he told him aloud, <q rend="italic">That he could ſing the ill actions of <persName rend="italic">Nauplius</persName> well enough, but of his own good qualities he could make no use at all.</q> And <persName rend="italic">Datus</persName> an Actor in the <foreign rend="italic">Atellane</foreign> Farces, in his part in which were theſe words in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>, <q rend="italic">Farewel Father, and Farewel Mother</q>, pointed ſo plainly at the deaths of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, that he used the poſtures of one drinking now, and anon of another a ſwimming; and in the laſt concluſion, theſe words, <foreign rend="italic">Orcus vobis ducit pedes</foreign>, <q rend="italic">Now <persName rend="italic">Pluto</persName> carries forth your feet</q>, he addreſs'd ſo particularly to the Senate, it was no hard matter to know whom he intended. But <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, whether he did really ſlight and deſpiſe all ſuch kind of reflection, or diſſembled his reſentment for fear of irritating them, proceeded no further againſt either the Philoſopher, or Droll, than to drive them both out of <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      40. At length after the world had groan'd under the Tyranny of this Emperour for little leſs than 14. years, it began to deſert him: The firſt that revolt<pb n="361"/>ed were the <placeName rend="italic">French</placeName>, under the Conduct of <persName rend="italic">Julius Vindex</persName> who govern'd that province at that time under the quality of Pro-Prætor:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The Aſtrologers having told him long before that he ſhould one day be diſtreſt, and forſaken, he made uſe of this expreſſion frequently in greek.
      <q rend="italic">Let it be ſo, a Man of worth and Art,
      In every Country meets with his deſert.</q>
      Intimating that he was to be excus'd for applying himself ſo earneſtly to be perfect at his Harp, which was a diverſion to him now he was Emperour, and might be his ſubſiſtance another day, if he ſhould become a private man. Yet ſome of them promis'd him the Empire of the Eaſt, and ſome of them particularly the Kingdom of <placeName rend="italic">Hieruſalem</placeName>, but moſt of them reſtitution to his former authority: and being inclin'd to hope, what was moſt for his advantage, having reduc'd <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName> to their obedience, he look'd upon all their Prophecies as accompliſh'd, and concluded there was nothing then left for him to fear.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      But after he had conſulted the Oracle of <placeName rend="italic">Delphos</placeName>, and received anſwer, <q rend="italic">That he should have a care of Seventy three</q>, not conſidering <persName rend="italic">Galba's</persName> years, he perſwaded himself that was to be the term of his life; inſomuch that he conceived ſo great aſſurance not only of his living to be an old man, but of being perpetually happy till then; That having loſt ſeveral things of great value in a Shipwrack, he was ſo vain as to ſay amongſt his friends, <q rend="italic">The very fiſh would bring them again.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Being at <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>, on the ſame day on which his Mother was murder'd, he had news of the inſurrection of the <placeName rend="italic">Gauls</placeName>, but he was ſo little affected with it, that <pb n="362"/> he ſeemed rather to rejoice, as in an occaſion of pillaging thoſe opulent Provinces by the right of war; and going forthwith into the Gymnaſium, he beheld the Champions with great earneſtneſs and delight: At ſupper he received new Letters, more preſſing and importunate than the former, but without any further emotion than a bare threatning of the revolters. In ſhort having given no anſwer, nor deliver'd out any Orders to any one for eight days together, he ſuffer'd things to go as they would, and ſlubber'd all over in ſilence.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="362"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      41. Nevertheleſs the ſeveral Edicts publiſh'd by <persName rend="italic">Vindex</persName> to his diſhonour, and in contempt of his Authority, awakened him at laſt, ſo as he writ a Letter to the Senate recommending to them the Vindication of his intereſt and the Republicks, excuſing his own abſence, with the pretence of an Inflammation in his Throat. But nothing troubled him ſo much, or gave him ſo great a diſquiet, as that they call'd him pitiful Harper and <persName rend="italic">Ænobarbus</persName>, inſtead of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>: whereupon he proteſted he would quit his adopted Name, and reaſſume that of his family, ſeeing they had reproach'd him with it as a thing he was aſhamed of. His other imputation he refell'd with no other argument, than that they were fools, and ignorant of an Art which he had refin'd by his own induſtry and pains, and therewithal examin'd them one by one very ſeriouſly, if ever they had known a more excellent Muſician than himſelf.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But the alarm increaſing, and Poſt upon Poſt coming in with ill news, he left <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName> in great terrour and return'd to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. However his heart was ſomething reviv'd by the way and that upon a very frivolous preſage, for having obſerv'd a Tomb upon the road on which there was engraven a <placeName rend="italic">French</placeName> <pb n="363"/> Souldier overcome by a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight, who dragg'd him about by the hair, he was tranſported with joy, and gave thanks to the Heavens for ſo good an Omen. At his arrival, he was ſo careleſs that inſtead of aſſembling the Senate, or People, he only ſummoned ſome of the principal men to his own houſe, where after a ſhort and haſty debate, he ſpent the reſt of the day in carrying them about to ſee ſome inſtruments he had lately invented which play'd only by the water: and having ſhown them all, and diſcourſt particularly of the reaſon and workmanſhip of each of them apart, he promis'd he would produce them ere long upon the Theatre, if <persName rend="italic">Vindex</persName> would give him leave.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      42. Underſtanding afterwards of the Commotions in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> under <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, he was ſo much dejected at the news, that he remain'd a long time without either motion or voice as he had been almoſt dead; and when he came to himſelf again, he tore his clothes, beat himſelf about the head, and cryed out, <q rend="italic">He was undone, he was undone.</q> His Nurſe endeavoring to comfort him, and to put him in mind that the like accidents had befallen other Princes before him, he reply'd, <q rend="italic">That his misfortunes were above all preſident, for he was living, and ſaw his Empire loſt.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      And yet for all this, he was ſo ſordidly infatuated, that even in ſo great a diſorder of his affairs, he continued his former debauches, and led the ſame life he had done before. If he received good news out of the Provinces, though never ſo little to his advantage, he fell a feaſting immediately; drolling and ſinging verſes againſt the heads of the rebellion at his own table, and ſeconding his voice with laſcivious and idle geſtures. Being privately convey'd into the Theatre one time, and obſerving one of the <pb n="364"/> Actors to do his part to the ſatisfaction of the whole houſe, he fell into ſo great an emulation of him, he ſent him word, <q rend="italic">That he invaded the recreations of his Emperour.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      43. Upon the firſt alarm of theſe troubles, it is credibly believed he deſigned horrible things, and ſuch as were ſuitable to the cruelty of his Nature. His reſolution was, to ſend perſons into all the Provinces and armies to ſucceed, and maſſacre thoſe which commanded in chief, under pretence of conſpiracie and combination; to cut the throats of all baniſh'd men, and to murder all <placeName rend="italic">French</placeName> men which ſhould be found in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. (The firſt leſt they ſhould joyn with the Revolters, Theſe as Complices and favourers of their Country men) To give up all <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName> to the plunder of his Army; To poiſon the whole Senate at an entertainment; to burn the City, and to turn out wild Beaſts amongſt the people, that ſo obſtructing their quenching of the fire, their deſtruction might be more inevitable.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      If he did not proſecute his deſigns, it was not out of compunction ſo much, as out of deſpair of effecting them. Being convinc'd that an expedition into thoſe parts was but neceſſary, he turn'd out the Conſuls before their term, and entred himſelf upon the Conſulſhip in their ſteads, as if the fates had decreed, the <placeName rend="italic">French</placeName> ſhould never be ſubdu'd but by one Conſul. Having taken upon him the Rods as Marks of his Conſulary authority, he march'd out of his Dining-room after dinner, leaning upon the ſhoulders of his moſt particular friends, and aſſuring them, that as ſoon as he arrived in the province, he would preſent himſelf naked without his Arms, before the Armies, and do nothing but weep. And <pb n="365"/> that the rebels ſubmitting, and giving teſtimony of their repentance, he would ſing ſongs of mirth and of Triumph amongſt them; which ſongs it was high time for him to begin to Compoſe.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="44">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      44. Amongſt all the preparations for his voyage, the greateſt care he took, was for Wagons convenient for the carriage of his Muſical Inſtruments for the Theatre: to cut the hair of his Concubines after the faſhion of men, and to arm them like <foreign rend="italic">Amazons</foreign> with Battle Axes and ſhields. The next thing he did, was to cite the Tribes of the City, for the taking of the Oath, and no body appearing who was fit to bear arms, he commanded the Maſters to ſend him in a certain number of ſlaves, ſelected out of the moſt approved perſons of every family, not excepting either the ſtewards, or Secretaries.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He required likewiſe all Orders and Degrees to contribute part of their Eſtates towards the expedition, according as they were rated in the Cenſors book. Lodgers alſo, and Tenants of the meaneſt houſes he compell'd to pay an annual penſion into his Exchequer: He was mighty rigid and curious in Money, not vouchſafing to receive any but what was rough and new coin'd, none but the faireſt Silver, none but the fineſt Gold. Whereupon moſt people oppos'd themſelves openly againſt this contribution, unanimouſly petitioning that all informers ſhould be ſearch'd rather, and forc'd to refund whatever they had received for their informations.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="45">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      45. That which rendred this Emperour more grievous and inſupportable was the unſeaſonable gain of the Monopoliſts, who made no ſmall advantage by the ſcarcity of Corn. For it hapning by accident that during this general dearth a Veſſel from <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName> laden with Sand, for the Wreſtlers of his Court, arriving, The people conceived ſo great a <pb n="366"/> hatred againſt <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, that they flew out into all the bitter and reviling expreſſions they could think of.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      On the top of one of his Statues, they placed a Chariot with this inſcription in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>, <q rend="italic">Here lies the ſtreſs, and pull away.</q> To the neck of another there was ty'd a Leather bag, with theſe words about it: <q rend="italic">Alas, what could I do? 'Tis you deſerv'd the bag as a Parricide.</q> Upon one of the Columns there was this Motto (alluding either to the <placeName rend="italic">French</placeName>, or Cocks, by reaſon of the ambiguity of the Word <foreign rend="italic">Gallus</foreign>, which ſignifies both) <q rend="italic">Etiam Gallos eum cantando excitaſſe</q>, <q rend="italic">That he had ſung ſo loud he had awakened the <placeName rend="italic">French</placeName>, or the very Cocks themſelves;</q> and people pretending to quarrel and chide their ſervants, they were heard to cry out all night long (according to their uſual expreſſion when they were abuſed) a <persName rend="italic">Vindex</persName>, a <persName rend="italic">Vindex</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="46">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      46. Beſides all theſe viſible tokens of the hatred and contempt of the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName>, he was terrifi'd with horrible dreams, and all manner of ill preſages. When he had Murder'd his Mother, he dream'd (which he ſeldom or never had done before) that he was governing a Ship, and the Helm was wreſted violently out of his hands; That his Wife <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, drew him by force in very narrow and dark places. One while he dream'd that he was cover'd over with multitudes of winged Ants. Another time that the Statues of noble men dedicated in the Theatre of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, encompaſs'd him round, and hindred his progreſs. That a Pad-Nag in which he took ſingular delight, was in his hinder part transformed into an Ape, and that having no part left entire but his head, he ſeemed to ſing as he neighed.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The doors of the Mausoleum flying open of themſelves a voice was heard, calling him diſtinctly by his name. <pb n="367"/> Upon the Calends of <foreign rend="italic">January</foreign>, his Houſhold-Gods were no ſooner trickt up and adorned in preparation to a Sacrifice, but they fell down to the ground. As he was at his Ceremony in obſerving the Birds, upon his entrance into the Conſulſhip, <persName rend="italic">Sporus</persName> preſented him with a Ring, upon the Stone of which was engraven the raviſhment of <persName rend="italic">Proſerpina</persName>. All the Orders being met in great numbers, to make the accuſtomed Vows, the Keys of the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> were very hardly to be found.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He made an Oration againſt <persName rend="italic">Vindex</persName> in the Senate, and concluding it with theſe words, <q rend="italic">The wicked ſhould be puniſh'd, and in a ſhort time be brought to an end ſuitable to their actions;</q> they all cryed out, <q rend="italic">Tu facies Auguſte</q>, <q rend="italic">It will be your caſe <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>.</q> It was obſervable alſo, that the laſt Play which he acted, and ſung publickly, was <q rend="italic">OEDIPUS BANISH'D</q>, and that concluded with theſe words;
      <q rend="italic">My Father, Mother, Wife, and all,
      In juſt Revenge conſtrain my fall.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="47">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      47. As he was at Dinner one day, Letters being brought him, importing the defection of the reſt of the Armies, he tore them in pieces, overturn'd the Table, and broke two fair Cryſtal Cups, which he took great delight in, and call'd his <foreign rend="italic">Homericks</foreign>, in reſpect of certain Verſes out of <persName rend="italic">Homer</persName> engraven upon them. And then having receiv'd poiſon of <persName rend="italic">Locuſta</persName>, he put it up in a Golden Box, and went immediately into the Orchards of the <persName rend="italic">Servilii</persName>, from whence he diſpatch'd the Freed-men which he had moſt confidence in, to <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName> to prepare his Fleet; and in the mean time he ſounded the <pb n="368"/> Tribunes, and Centurions of his Guards, whether they would accompany him in his flight:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But ſome of them ſhifting, and making difficulties, others poſitively refuſing, one cryed out,
      <q rend="italic">Uſque adeone mori miſerum eſt?</q>
      <q rend="italic">Is it ſo ſad a thing to dye?</q>
      He was in a ſtrong debate with himſelf, had ſeveral thoughts what to do, but could not reſolve whether he ſhould addreſs himſelf to the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName>, or <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, in a ſupplicatory way; or whether he ſhould put himſelf in Mourning, appear publickly before the <placeName rend="italic">Roſtra</placeName>, and with all poſſible humility and dejection implore their forgiveneſs for what was paſt, and if he found them inflexible, to beg then that at leaſt they would vouchſafe him the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Ægypt</placeName>: To this purpoſe there was an Oration found afterwards amongſt the reſt of his Papers, but 'tis ſuppoſed he was deterr'd from delivering it, by an apprehenſion of being pull'd in pieces before he ſhould come to the Tribunal.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Having in this manner put off all thoughts till the next day, he was awaken'd about midnight, and underſtanding his Guards were drawn off and retired, he leap'd out of Bed, and ſent about to his Friends for News; but receiving nothing from any of them, he went attended by very few to their ſeveral houſes, where the doors being all ſhut, and no body to anſwer, he return'd to his Chamber, from whence his Guards were not only gone, but had taken away the Box with the poiſon, and all, to the very Clothes upon the Bed. In this deſperate condition he ſought for <persName rend="italic">Spicillus</persName> a Gladiator, or ſome other ſuch <pb n="369"/> perſon, to be ſlain by them; but no body being to be found, <q rend="italic">Ergo</q> (ſays he) <q rend="italic">nec amicum habeo, nec inimicum?</q> <q rend="italic">What then? have I neither Friend nor Foe?</q> and away he ran out, as if he would have thrown himſelf headlong into the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="48">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      48. But that humour having ſpent it ſelf, he began to think of ſome private place where he might lye cloſe and obſcure; whereupon one of his Freed-men called <persName rend="italic">Phaon</persName>, offer'd him a Countrey-houſe of his, about four miles from the City, betwixt the <placeName rend="italic">Salarian</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Numentan</placeName> Roads. Bare-footed as he was then, and only in his Waſtcoat, he threw an old dirty Cloak over himſelf, cover'd his head, and holding a Handkerchief before his face, he got on Horſeback with only four perſons in his Company, of which <persName rend="italic">Sporus</persName> was one.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      No ſooner was he upon his Journey, but he was infinitely diſmay'd by a violent trembling of the Earth, and prodigious flaſhes of Lightning; and paſſing by the Camp, he heard a great noiſe of Souldiers curſing him, and wiſhing all good fortune and proſperity to <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>. He heard a Paſſenger ſay alſo as he went by, <q rend="italic">Theſe people are in purſuit of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>:</q> And another ask'd him, <q rend="italic">What news of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> in the City?</q> His Horſe ſcenting a dead carcaſs, which by accident at that time lay ſtinking in the way, ſtarted aſide, and ſhaking off the covering of his face, he was known and ſaluted by one <persName rend="italic">Miſſicius</persName> a Prætorian Souldier.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Being come to the next turning, they forſook their Horſes, and betaking themſelves to the buſhes and bryars, thorow a ſmall path in a reed ground, with much difficulty, and glad to put his Clothes under his feet, they arriv'd at laſt at a Wall over againſt the houſe. In the mean time, <pb n="370"/> whilſt he could find out a way to convey him in with more ſecrecy, <persName rend="italic">Phaon</persName> intreated him to conceal himſelf in a Sand-pit; but he refus'd, and told him, <q rend="italic">He would never be buried alive:</q> Then ſtaying a little while, till a more private acceſs to the houſe was prepar'd, being dry, he took up water out of a ditch with his hand, and drinking he ſaid, <q rend="italic">This is <persName rend="italic">Nero's</persName> decoction.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Then clearing himſelf of the bryars, which had torn and hung upon his Cloathes, he march'd like a Beaſt upon all four, to a ſtrait hole, thorow which he was drawn into the houſe: Being got into a Chamber, he threw himſelf upon a Bed with nothing but a pitiful Mattrice, and an old Cloak for a Coverlet: By degrees he began to be hungry and dry, whereupon they brought him a ſort of brown courſe bread, which they had in the houſe, but he refuſed to eat it, only he ſupped a little lukewarm water.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="49">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      49. All thoſe who were about him, ſollicited him very earneſtly to prevent thoſe dangers and affronts which hung over his head; whereupon he commanded a Grave to be made in his preſence, the full dimenſion of his body, and gave order that what pieces of Marble-ſtones could be found, ſhould be laid together, and that proviſion ſhould be made of Water and Wood, ready for the waſhing and burning of his body; weeping at every word, and repeating ſeveral times, <q rend="italic">What an Artiſt will the World loſe!</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Whilſt theſe things were in agitation, a Meſſenger came in with Letters for <persName rend="italic">Phaon</persName>, which he ſnatch'd out of his hand, and reading in them, <q rend="italic">That he was declared Enemy to the State by the Senate, and that he was to be ſought after and puniſh'd according to <pb n="371"/> Cuſtom:</q> He demanded what kind of puniſhment that was; and being told, that he was to be ſtript ſtark naked, that his head was to be held up with a Fork, and in that poſture to be whipt to death, he was ſo terrified, that he ſnatch'd up a couple of Daggers, which he carried about him, and trying their points, he put them up again, pretending his Fatal hour was not yet come:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      One while he deſir'd <persName rend="italic">Sporus</persName> to begin his plaints and lamentations, another while he turned about to ſuch as were near him, and deſired that ſome of them would inſtruct him how to dye, by killing themſelves firſt, ſometimes he would blame and condemn his own puſillanimity, in theſe words, <q rend="italic">I live, 'tis true, but baſely and diſhonourably it is not handſome, <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, it is not handſome; in ſuch caſes as this you muſt be watchful: Courage <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, rouze up thy Spirits.</q> Whilſt he was in this conflict, he heard the noiſe of the Horſemen, which were ſent with order to bring him alive to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; then more frighted than ever, he cry'd out in a <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> Verſe,
      <q rend="italic">A diſmal noiſe of Horſes ſtrikes mine ear;</q>
      clapt a Dagger to his throat, but not having heart enough to thruſt it in, he was forced to be beholding to <persName rend="italic">Epaphroditus</persName> his Secretary for his aſſiſtance.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Before he was quite dead, an Officer came in, and feigning he was come to his relief, he ſtopt his Cloak in the wound, and endeavour'd to ſtench the bloud; to whom <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> gave no anſwer but this, <q rend="italic">'Tis too late</q>, and <q rend="italic">Is this your Fidelity and Allegiance?</q> with which expreſſion he expired, his eyes fix'd and ſtaring out of his head, to the terrour and amazement of all that were preſent. That which he recommended, and moſt importunately deſired of the Company which attended<pb n="372"/> him, was, That his Head might not be cut off and given to any body, but that by all means his whole body might be burnt together: And <persName rend="italic">Icelus</persName> (a Freed-man of <persName rend="italic">Galba's</persName>, who not long before was deliver'd out of Priſon, where he had been put upon the noiſe of the firſt tumult) granted his deſire.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="50">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      50. His Funerals were perform'd at the expence of 200000 Seſterces, his Corps being covered with white Silk Tiſſued with Gold, (the ſame he had worn upon the Calends of <foreign rend="italic">January</foreign>;) His aſhes were put by <persName rend="italic">Ecloge</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Alexandria</persName>, his Nurſes, and <persName rend="italic">Acte</persName> his Concubine, into the Monument belonging to the Houſe of <persName rend="italic">Domitii</persName> his Anceſtors, which is yet to be ſeen out of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName> his Field, upon the top of a Hill in the Hortyards; the foundation of which Sepulchre is of Porphyre, the Altar upon it of Marble of <placeName rend="italic">Luna</placeName>, fenc'd about with <placeName rend="italic">Thaſian</placeName> Stone.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>



        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>