<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>
            <pb n="437"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      THE EIGHTH BOOK, Being the LIFE OF <persName rend="italic">Flavius Veſpaſianus Auguſtus</persName>, THE TENTH Emperour of <placeName rend="italic">ROME</placeName>.
    </p>
    <p>
      1. THE Empire which for a long time had been tottering, and unſetled, by the rebellion and ſlaughter of three Emperours ſucceſſively, was at length fix'd and eſtabliſh'd by the Family of the <persName rend="italic">Flavii</persName>. True it is, its original was not very illuſtrious, as not being able to glory in the Grandeur of its Anceſtors:
      <pb n="438"/>
      Nevertheleſs the Commonwealth had no cauſe to be aſham'd of it, though <persName rend="italic">Domitianus</persName> was made an Example for his cruelty and avarice.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Titus Flavius Petro</persName> was a Citizen of <placeName rend="italic">Reate</placeName>, and a Centurion in the Civil Wars with <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>; whether he ſerv'd voluntarily, or by compulſion, is not known; but this is certain, he fled home to his own houſe after the Battle of <placeName rend="italic">Pharſalia</placeName>, and having made his peace, and diſcharg'd himſelf from the Army, he took imployment under the Farmers of the Revenue, and Collected their Taxes. His Son, ſurnamed <persName rend="italic">Sabinus</persName>, either unskillful in matters of War, or (as ſome will have it) releas'd of his Military Oath, upon occaſion of his ſickneſs, when he was a Centurion, was a Partiſan in <placeName rend="italic">Aſia</placeName>, where he gather'd the Cuſtoms and Impoſitions called <foreign rend="italic">Quadrageſima</foreign>, with ſo much integrity, that there were Images erected by the Cities in his memory, with this inſcription, <foreign rend="italic">καλῶς τελωνήσαντι</foreign>, <q rend="italic">To the honeſt Publican.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      After this he went into <placeName rend="italic">Helvetia</placeName>, where he put out Money to Intereſt, and died, leaving his Wife <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſia Polla</persName>, and two Children behind him, the elder of which was called <persName rend="italic">Sabinus</persName>, and arrived at the Government of the City; the younger called <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>, attain'd to be Emperour. <persName rend="italic">Polla</persName> was born of honourable Parents in <placeName rend="italic">Nurſia</placeName>, her Father being <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſius Pollio</persName>, a perſon that had three times been Military Tribune, and Mareſchal du Campe, and his Brother a Senator firſt, and afterwards honoured with the dignity of the Prætorſhip. Six miles from <placeName rend="italic">Nurſia</placeName>, in the road to <placeName rend="italic">Spoletum</placeName>, upon the top of a high Mountain, there is a place which bears the name of <placeName rend="italic">Veſpaſiæ</placeName> to this day, in which there are ſo many, and conſiderable Monuments of the <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſians</persName> to be ſeen, as do clearly ivince the ſplendor and
      <pb n="439"/>
      antiquity of that Family.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      I will not deny but it is reported by ſome Authors, that the Father of <persName rend="italic">Petro</persName> was born beyond the <placeName rend="italic">Po</placeName>; that he drove a great Trade amongſt the Labourers, who uſed to come yearly out of <placeName rend="italic">Umbria</placeName>, into the Territory of the <placeName rend="italic">Sabines</placeName>, for the Tillage of their Ground; that his habitation was in the Town of <placeName rend="italic">Reate</placeName>, at which place he married his Wife: But for my own part, I have ſearch'd with ſufficient curioſity, and could never find the leaſt track of Authority to perſwade me to believe it.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> was born in the Dominion of the <placeName rend="italic">Sabines</placeName>, beyond <placeName rend="italic">Reate</placeName>, at a little Town called <placeName rend="italic">Phalacrine</placeName>, the ſeventeenth of November towards the Evening, in the Conſulſhip of <persName rend="italic">Q. Sulpicius Camerinus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">C. Poppæus Sabinus</persName>, five years before the death of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>. He was educated by his Grandmother by the Fathers ſide, in a houſe ſhe had about <placeName rend="italic">Coſæ</placeName>; which place when he was Emperour afterwards, he did conſtantly frequent, the houſe being preſerv'd as it was in his youth, that his eyes might not be deprived of any thing they had been accuſtomed formerly to ſee. The memory of his Grandmother was ſo dear to him, that in all Feſtival and Solemn days, he drank out of a Silver Cup which had been hers, and no other.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having put on his Virile Gown, he had an averſion a long time for the Senators Robe, though his Brother had taken it upon him; nor could he be prevail'd with at laſt, but by the compulſion of his Mother, who wrought upon him not ſo much by her perſwaſions, or authority, as by her gibes and reproaches, calling him oftentimes by way of deriſion, his Brothers Uſher.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He ſerv'd as a Military Tribune in <placeName rend="italic">Thrace</placeName>: Being Quæſtor, the Provinces of <placeName rend="italic">Crete</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Cyrene</placeName> fell to
      <pb n="440"/>
      him by Lot; and when he ſtood Candidate to be Ædilis, and Prætor, he obtain'd the Ædileſhip with much difficulty, and in the ſixth place; but the Prætorſhip was granted him at the firſt. Being in poſſeſſion of that place, and animated exceedingly againſt the Senate, he endeavoured by all wayes to inſinuate himſelf into the favour of <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName>; for which reaſon, he deſir'd that he might be permitted to exhibite extraordinary Plays in his honour, upon the Victory he had gain'd in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>; and being conſulted in the Senate againſt the Conſpirators, he advis'd that their bodies ſhould be left unburied, as an addition to their former puniſhments: beſides which, in the preſence of the whole Senate, he gave <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> thanks, for having done him the honour to admit him to his Table.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. While theſe things were in agitation, he married <persName rend="italic">Flavia Domitilla</persName>, who had been Servant to <persName rend="italic">Statilius Capella</persName>, a Gentleman of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, born in <placeName rend="italic">Sabrata</placeName> in <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName>: but afterwards ſhe was made free, and Citizen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, with all the formalities, upon the ſecurity of her Father <persName rend="italic">Flavius Liberalis</persName>, born at <placeName rend="italic">Ferentinum</placeName>, and never advanc'd higher than to a Treaſurers Clerk. By her he had two Sons, and a Daughter, <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Domitianus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Domitilla</persName>: He out-lived both his Wife, and his Daughter, and was but as it were a private perſon when they dyed. After his Wifes deceaſe, he receiv'd into his company again <persName rend="italic">Cænis</persName> a Freed-woman, and Amanuenſis to <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName>, whom he had paſſionately loved before, and afterwards when he was Emperour, kept her in his houſe as his lawful Wife.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. In the Empire of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, being made Lieutenant of a Legion by the favour of <persName rend="italic">Narciſſus</persName>, he was diſpatch'd into <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, from whence being Poſted
      <pb n="441"/>
      into <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName>, he fought three conſiderable Battles, took twenty ſtrong Towns, and upwards, and reduc'd the Iſle of <placeName rend="italic">Wight</placeName>, which is an Iſland adjacent: Part of which Exploits he performed under the Conduct of <persName rend="italic">A. Plautius</persName>, Lieutenant to the Conſul, and partly under <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> himſelf;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and as a recompence for his diligence, he was honoured with the Triumphal Ornaments, and in a ſhort time with two Sacerdotal Dignities, beſides a Conſulſhip, which he executed only the two laſt months of the year. In the interim, till he was made Pro-conſul, (having ſome apprehenſions of <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, who at that time was very potent with her Son, and abhor'd all perſons which had had any intimacy with <persName rend="italic">Narciſſus</persName>) he lived privately without any Charge.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Afterwards the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName> falling to his ſhare, he manag'd it with integrity and honour, only once in a Sedition at <placeName rend="italic">Adrumetum</placeName>, he had Turneps thrown at him by the people. At his return he was no richer than when he went; for his Credit being at ſtake, and his Creditors preſſing for their Money, he was forc'd to Mortgage all his Eſtate to his Brother, and to make advantages by ſelling and ſwopping of Horſes, for the ſupport of his dignity; whereupon they call'd him commonly the <persName rend="italic">Horſe-Courſer</persName>. It is reported likewiſe, that he was convict of having extorted 200000 Seſterces from a young Gentleman, for making him a Senator againſt his Fathers will, for which action he was ſeverely rebuk'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      In the Voyage <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> made into <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName>, he was one of his Train; but incurr'd his diſpleaſure exceedingly, in not attending with that admiration and reverence (as in good manners he ought to have done) when he was ſinging, it being his uſual cuſtom either to ſteal privately out of the room, or
      <pb n="442"/>
      fall aſleep in the midſt of his Muſick. Upon which account he was not only forbid the Court, but to ſalute the Emperour publickly; whereupon he retir'd into a little Town out of the way, where he kept himſelf cloſe againſt the vengeance of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, till he was offer'd the Command both of a Province and Army.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      There was an opinion ſpread all over the <placeName rend="italic">Eaſt</placeName>, and it had obtain'd very much, <q rend="italic">That by inevitable Decree thoſe who came out of <placeName rend="italic">Judea</placeName> about that time, were to have the Empire of the World.</q> The <persName rend="italic">Jews</persName> miſtaking the Propheſie, and applying it to themſelves, (which the Event ſhew'd afterwards was intended of the Emperour of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>) fell into a Rebellion, ſlew their Governour; and the Conſulary Lieutenant of <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, bringing him relief, they fell upon him, routed him, and took from him his Imperial Standard. To reduce theſe Rebels to their Obedience, it was fit they ſhould provide themſelves with a more puiſſant Army, and a General of ſuch Conduct and Experience, as they might ſafely commit an affair of that conſequence into his hands. In this deliberation, <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> was pitch'd upon as a perſon who had given ample expreſſions of himſelf, and was not to be ſuſpected, for the humility of his Extraction:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      Having therefore reinforc'd the Army with two Legions, eight wings of Horſe, and ten Cohorts of Foot, he march'd for <placeName rend="italic">Judea</placeName>, accompanied by his eldeſt Son, who was one of his Lieutenants. At his firſt arrival, he made himſelf admirable to all the Provinces adjacent, for his Regiment, Diſcipline, and the invincibleneſs of his Courage; for in his two firſt Engagements, he behaved himſelf moſt honourably, and at the ſtorming of a Caſtle, he receiv'd an unlucky blow upon his knee with a Stone, beſides ſeveral Arrows upon his Target.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <pb n="443"/>
    <p>
      5. After the death of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, whilſt <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> were in diſpute for the Soveraignty, he was confirm'd in the hopes (which a long time he had conceiv'd) of attaining it himſelf, by theſe prodigies following.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In a Countrey houſe belonging to the <persName rend="italic">Flavii</persName>, not far from the City, there was an old Oak conſecrated to <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>; this Tree at three ſeveral times, when <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſia</persName> Lay-in, put forth each time a bough out of its Trunk on a ſudden, giving thereby a manifeſt prognoſtick of the deſtiny of every one of them as they came into the World; The firſt was but ſlender, and quickly dried up: and ſo her Daughter which was her firſt born, lived not a compleat year. The ſecond tough and long, and preſag'd great felicity. But the third was great, like a Tree; whereupon it is ſaid, that his Father <persName rend="italic">Sabinus</persName> having been confirm'd before, by one of the Southſayers, told his Mother, <q rend="italic">That ſhe had a Grandchild now born which would be Emperour</q>; and that ſhe only laught when ſhe heard it, and declar'd, <q rend="italic">That ſhe could not but wonder (her ſenſes being ſtill good) her Son ſhould doat and talk idly already.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> having advanc'd him to the Ædileſhip, and being angry one day for his remiſneſs in ſeeing the ſtreets kept clean, he commanded the Soldiers to take up ſome of the durt and beſmear him, which they did, and threw it into the lap of his Embroidred Robe, which by ſome people was interpreted as a token, <q rend="italic">That the time ſhould come when the Common-wealth being forſaken and trodden under foot by ſome Civil diſſention, ſhould have recourſe to him for protection, and ſeek its ſanctuary in his boſom.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      As he was at dinner another time, a ſtrange Dog came into the room, with a mans hand in his mouth; and laid it under the Table. Again being at Supper, an Oxe which had been at Plough, ſhak'd
      <pb n="444"/>
      off his Yoke, broke into the room, and having frighted and diſpers'd his ſervants, (as if he had been tyred of a ſudden) laid himſelf down gently by him, and put his head to his feet, as a teſtimony of ſubmiſſion. In an eſtate which belong'd to his Anceſtors a Cypreſs Tree was pull'd up by the roots, and thrown down without any tempeſt or violence, and the next day found growing again, with more verdure and firmneſs than before.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      When he was in <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName>, he dream'd that the felicity and good fortune of himſelf and family ſhould commence as ſoon as <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> ſhould loſe a Tooth; and it came to paſs, that going to Court the next day, one of the Emperours Phyſicians ſhew'd him a Tooth which he had newly drawn.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      In <placeName rend="italic">Judea</placeName>, Conſulting the Oracle of the God <persName rend="italic">Carmel</persName>, his anſwer was ſo favourable, that it promis'd him infallible ſucceſs in whatever he projected were it never ſo great. There was one of the moſt honourable of his Captives called <persName rend="italic">Joſephus</persName> alſo, who being by his order clapt into Priſon, affirm'd boldly that in a ſhort time he ſhould be ſet at liberty by the ſame perſon, but he ſhould be Emperour firſt.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
    <p>
      From <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> alſo he receiv'd tidings of ſeveral preſages: One among the reſt was, That <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> about the end of his days, was advertis'd in a dream to remove the ſacred Chariot of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> from the Chappel where it ſtood, to <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian's</persName> houſe, and from thence into the Circus. And not long after, at the ſolemn aſſembly for <persName rend="italic">Galba's</persName> ſecond Election into the Conſulſhip, the Statue of <persName rend="italic">Julius Cæſar</persName> turn'd about of it ſelf towards the <placeName rend="italic">Eaſt</placeName>. And juſt before the Battle at <placeName rend="italic">Bebriacum</placeName>, two Eagles being ſeen fighting in the air till one of them was beaten, upon a ſudden there appear'd a third from the <placeName rend="italic">Eaſt</placeName>, which drove away the Conquerour.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. Nevertheleſs, though his friends were ready,
      <pb n="445"/>
      and ſollicited him very earneſtly to declare, he could never be brought to attempt any thing, till he found himſelf favour'd and invited by ſome perſons who were both abſent and unknown.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Two thouſand men drawn out of three Legions, and ſent to the relief of <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName>, having intelligence that he was defeated, and had kill'd himſelf, they gave no credit to the report, but advanc'd as far as <placeName rend="italic">Aquileia</placeName>; being there, they took their opportunity, and gave themſelves over to all ſort of licentiouſneſs and rapine; afterwards apprehending they might be called to an account at their return, and poſſibly receive the reward of their violences, they took up a reſolution to Elect and Create an Emperour of their own, alledging that they were not inferiour either to the <placeName rend="italic">Spaniſh</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Prætorian</placeName>, or <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> Armies, who had advanc'd <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName>, to the Empire.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Having named all the Conſular Lieutenants, who were in command at that time, and had great conteſtation; Certain Soldiers of the third Legion who about the end of <persName rend="italic">Nero's</persName> reign had been removed out of <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, into <placeName rend="italic">Mæſia</placeName>, took occaſion to recommend <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>; The Character being well received on all hands, by common conſent he was concluded worthy of the Empire, and forthwith they inſcrib'd his Name upon all their Enſigns. At firſt it was thought fit to conceale it, that they might recollect themſelves by degrees, and renew their diſcipline. But when it was divulg'd, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius Alexander</persName> the Governour of <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, was the firſt which forc'd the Legions to take an oath of fidelity to <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>; which happening to fall out upon the firſt day of July, the firſt day of July was held for the firſt day of his Empire for ever after. On the eleventh of July, the Army with him in <placeName rend="italic">Judea</placeName>, took the ſaid oath in his preſence alſo.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Theſe
      <pb n="446"/>
      Enterprizes were very much promoted by the Copy of a Letter (true or falſe) which <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> was reported to have writ to <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>, exhorting and conjuring him to revenge his death, and to reſcue the Common-wealth from Captivity: Beſides, it was ſpread abroad, that <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> was reſolved, if he were Conquerour, to change the Winter Quarters of his Legions, and to remove thoſe in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName> into the <placeName rend="italic">Eaſtern</placeName> parts, where the War was moſt eaſie and ſecure. Moreover <persName rend="italic">Licinius Muſianus</persName> depoſiting the animoſity which he had had for him till that day, (upon an emulation of his greatneſs) promis'd him his Army in <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, and <persName rend="italic">Vologeſus</persName> King of the <persName rend="italic">Parthians</persName> 40000 Archers.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. The Civil War being commenc'd in this manner, and his Captains ſent before with his Troops into <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, he paſt over himſelf to <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, to ſeize upon the avenues into <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>; whilſt he was there, he entred privately into the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Serapis</persName> alone, to receive the Auſpices touching the firmneſs and ſtability of his Empire; and having endeavoured by all formalities to render that God propitious, he turn'd himſelf about according to the rites of adoration; and to his thinking beheld Vervain Crowns, and loaves of Bread (as is uſual in that place) preſented to him by <persName rend="italic">Baſilides</persName>, a Freed-man, though it was known no perſon admitted him into the Temple, that he had been long ſo ill of a weakneſs in his Nerves, he was ſcarce able to go; and beſides that, he was at that time a great diſtance off that place. Immediately hereupon Letters were brought to him, importing the defeat of the <persName rend="italic">Vitellian</persName> Army, near <placeName rend="italic">Cremona</placeName>; and that <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> himſelf was murdered at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having been advanc'd in this unexpected manner, and made Emperour on a ſudden,
      <pb n="447"/>
      he wanted ſomething of that Majeſty and authority, which is neceſſary in ſo great a Prince but his good fortune preſented him with an opportunity to ſupply himſelf even with that. A blind and lame man, of mean condition, and the common rank of the people, preſenting themſelves to him, as he was ſitting upon his Tribunal, beſeeched him moſt humbly that he would vouchſafe to cure them, for they had been admoniſh'd by their God <persName rend="italic">Serapis</persName> in a dream, that if he pleas'd but to ſpit upon the eyes of the one, and but touch the other with his heel, both of them ſhould recover and be well.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> had not faith enough to believe them, nor to hope for any ſuch ſucceſs, ſo as he could ſcarce be perſwaded to make the experiment; but at laſt being over-rul'd by the importunity of his friends, he tryed both ways, and was anſwer'd by the effect. At the ſame time at <placeName rend="italic">Tegea</placeName> in <placeName rend="italic">Arcadia</placeName>, by the intimation and impulſe of the Prophets, they digg'd in a ſacred place, and found ſeveral Veſſels very antique, among which there was an Image exactly reſembling <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. Being returned to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, full of glory and reputation, he Triumph'd over the <persName rend="italic">Jews</persName>, and added eight Conſulſhips more, to what he had exercis'd before: He took upon him the Office of Cenſor likewiſe, and during the whole courſe of his Empire, his principal care was, firſt to re-eſtabliſh, and ext, to readorn the Common-wealth.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The Soldiers (part in confidence of their Victory, and part in ſenſe of their ignominy) ran out into all kind of licentiouſneſs. The Provinces, the free Towns, and even ſome Kingdoms, began to mutiny; to regulate thoſe diſorders, he caſhier'd ſeveral of the <persName rend="italic">Vitellians</persName>, and corrected others, and as for thoſe who were inſtruments
      <pb n="448"/>
      and partners in his Victory, he was ſo far from giving them any recompence extraordinary, he was ſomething tedious in paying them their due.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He omitted no occaſion of reforming the diſcipline of the Armies. A young man to whom he had given a conſiderable Command, waiting upon him one day to give him thanks, ſmelling very fragrantly of rich Oyls, and Perfumes, he look'd ſeverely upon him, and (with a voice that ſignified his indignation) told him, <q rend="italic">he had rather he had ſmelt of Garlick</q>, and ſo took away his Commiſſion. The Sea-men which were wont to run on foot by turns from <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, Petitioning that they might have ſome certain allowance appointed them for ſhooes; (as if it had not been enough to ſend them packing without any anſwer) he ordain'd that for the future they ſhould diſcharge their duties without any ſhooes at all; and ſince that time they ran barefoot accordingly.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Having taken away their rights and liberties in <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Lycia</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Bizantium</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Samos</placeName>, as likewiſe in <placeName rend="italic">Thracia</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Cileſia</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Comagene</placeName>, (which till that time had been all of them under the domination of Kings) he reduc'd them into the form of Provinces. He diſpatch'd new Legions into <placeName rend="italic">Cappadocia</placeName>, to ſecure it againſt the irruptions of the Barbarians; and inſtead of a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight, he gave the Government to one which had been Conſul.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> having loſt much of its ſplendor and beauty by the late Ruines, and Conflagration, if the Proprietors neglected to build in any Competent time, he permitted any other perſon that would do it, to enter and take poſſeſſion of their Ground. He reſerv'd the repairing of the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> to himſelf, and for encouragement to other people, was the firſt which put his hand to the work, and carried out
      <pb n="449"/>
      the firſt rubbiſh upon his own ſhoulders; he undertook to reſtore three thouſand Tables of braſs which had been burnt, having with great induſtry ſought out their true Copies, they being as it were the Regiſters of the Empire, in which were recorded all Decrees of the Senate, all Ordinances of the people, all Treaties, Alliances, and Priviledges granted to any Perſon or Corporation whatſoever; in ſhort, all remarkable occurrences from the very foundation of the City.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. Beſides theſe, he built ſeveral other very honourable Buildings, as the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Peace</persName>, not far from the Market-place; the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, upon the Mount <placeName rend="italic">Cælius</placeName>, which had been begun by <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, but was almoſt entirely demoliſh'd by <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>; and an Amphitheatre in the middle of the Town, as <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> had deſign'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The moſt honourable Orders (of Senators and Gentlemen) which had been exhauſted by infinite Maſſacres, and defil'd by the negligence of the preceeding Emperours, he purg'd and refin'd by a general review of them both; in which he turn'd out ſuch as he found unworthy, and ſupply'd their places with the moſt honourable perſons he could meet with, either in <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, or the Provinces. And (that it might be known, that the difference betwixt thoſe two Orders, did not conſiſt in any advantage of Liberty, ſo much as in Dignity) a Senator and Gentleman having fallen out, and given one another ill language, upon their complaints and applications to him, he gave Judgement in theſe words; <q rend="italic">It is not lawful to give a Senator ill words firſt but if a Senator begin, it is not only lawfull, but civil (for a Gentleman) to reply.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. The number of Proceſſes and Suits in Law was grown ſo great, that old Actions were left un-
      <pb n="450"/>
      determin'd, by a long vacation and intermiſſion of Juſtice, and by the acceſſion of new quarrels, ariſing from the tumults and diſorders of thoſe times: To remedy this Grievance, he elected certain perſons by Lots, and qualified them as Judges, to reſtore ſuch to the poſſeſſion of their Eſtates, as had been diſpoſſeſs'd during the Wars; to determine extraordinarily in Cauſes before the <foreign rend="italic">Centumviri</foreign>, which were become ſo numerous and tedious, a Client could ſcarce hope to live to ſee an end of his Suit; and to reduce and digeſt them into as ſhort a number as might be.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. The Manners of men being moſt deplorably corrupted by all manner of Luxury, to put a check to their debaucheries, he prevail'd with the Senate to make a Decree, That what woman ſoever joyn'd her ſelf to another mans Servant, ſhould loſe her own liberty, and become a Vaſſal her ſelf; That no Uſurer ſhould recover any money of young Heirs, that was lent to be repaid with advantage upon the deceaſe of their Fathers. In other matters he uſed great clemency, from the beginning to the latter end of his Empire.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. He was ſo far from concealing the mediocrity of his former condition, he diſcours'd of it many times himſelf; and when ſome went about to derive his Pedigree from the very Founders of <placeName rend="italic">Reate</placeName>, and the Companion of <persName rend="italic">Hercules</persName>, whoſe Monument is ſtill to be ſeen in the <placeName rend="italic">Via Salaria</placeName>, he laugh'd at them, and derided them for their pains. He was ſo far from delighting extravagantly in any exteriour Ornaments, or Honour, that on the day of his Triumph, being tired out with the tediouſneſs of the formalities, he could not forbear uttering his diſquiet in theſe words; <q rend="italic">That he ſuffered but juſtly, for having at his age
      <pb n="451"/>
      ſo ſottiſhly deſir'd to Triumph, as if it had been due to his Anceſtors, or ever hoped for by himſelf.</q> Neither did he accept the Tribunitial Authority, or the Title of <persName rend="italic">Pater Patriæ</persName>, but with great difficulty; and for the cuſtom of ſearching ſuch as came to ſalute him, he left that off before the Civil Wars were ended.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. He concern'd himſelf but little either at the liberties of his Friends, the gibes and reflections of the Lawyers, or the downright rudeneſſes of Philoſophers. <persName rend="italic">Licinius Mucianus</persName>, a man of known unnatural chaſtity, preſuming upon his merits, and carrying himſelf irreverently towards him, <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> never rebuk'd him but in private; and complaining of him upon a time, to a common friend to them both, he came in with this cloſe, <q rend="italic">Yet I am a man.</q> <persName rend="italic">Salvius Liberalis</persName> in defence of a Rich man which was his Client, had the impudence to ſay, <q rend="italic">If <persName rend="italic">Hipparchus</persName> be worth a hundred millions of Seſterces, what is that to <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>?</q> Yet he was ſo far from being diſguſted with it, that he gave him thanks for what he had ſaid. After the Philoſophers had been baniſh'd the City, <persName rend="italic">Demetrius</persName> the Cynick meeting him upon the road, would not vouchſafe to riſe up or give him a ſalute, but inſtead of that, began to revile him; but the Emperor contented himſelf to call him <q rend="italic">Dog</q> only, alluding to the name of his Sect.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. His reſentment either of ſudden offences, or old animoſities, was ſo ſmall, that he married the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> (his inveterate Enemy) very honourably, and gave her a Dower, and accoutrements ſuitable to her quality beſides. Being forbid the Court in the time of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, in great terrour, and not knowing what to do, he demanded whither he was to go; one of the Uſhers thruſting him rudely out of the Chamber, told him, he might <q rend="italic">go hang
      <pb n="452"/>
      himſelf</q>: After he was created Emperour, this Fellow coming to beg his pardon, <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> was provok'd no farther, than to bid him be gone almoſt in the ſame terms he had offended him. He was ſo far from being carried away by ſuſpicion, or fear, to the deſtruction of any perſon, that when he was admoniſh'd by his Friends, to have an eye upon <persName rend="italic">Metius Pompoſianus</persName>, who was born by report under a Conſtellation that promis'd him the Empire; he made him Conſul, againſt the advice of them all, aſſuring them, <q rend="italic">That when time ſhould ſerve he could not but remember that good office.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. There was ſcarce ever any innocent man puniſh'd in his time; if there were, it was when he was either abſent, or deceiv'd. <persName rend="italic">Helvidius Priſcus</persName>, the only perſon who ſaluted him by the name of <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>, at his return from <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, and one that made not the leaſt mention of him, in any of the Edicts which were publiſh'd during his Prætorſhip, could not provoke him by theſe affronts, till at length in his moſt inſolent altercations, he endeavour'd to make him no better than an ordinary man: Yet him alſo (though he was baniſh'd before, and Orders given out afterwards for his Execution) he endeavour'd to have ſaved, ſent to countermand the Executioners, and had preſerved him without doubt, had he not been deceiv'd by falſe intelligence, that he was dead before his Meſſengers came. Furthermore, he was ſo far from pleaſing himſelf in the deſtruction of any man, that he could not ſo much as look upon the ſufferings of a Criminal, without ſignifying his compaſſion by his ſighs and his tears.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="452"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. The only thing deſervedly imputable to him, was his immoderate love of Money. He was not content to revive the old Impoſitions, which had
      <pb n="453"/>
      been remitted under <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>; to add new, and more grievous Tributes to ſeveral of the Provinces; but he drove a Trade publickly, which would have been diſhonourable to a private perſon, bartering and buying Commodities, that he might ſell them to advantage.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Neither did he ſcruple the ſelling of any Office, nor the pardoning any condemn'd perſon for money whether he was guilty or not. It is ſuſpected alſo, that it was his cuſtom to advance the moſt griping and rapacious of his Officers, to the moſt profitable Charges, on purpoſe that he might ſqueeze them when they were grown rich: And of theſe perſons it was ſaid he made uſe as of Sponges, <q rend="italic">wet them when they were dry, and ſqueez'd them when they were wet.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Some ſay he was covetous by nature, and that he was upbraided with it by an old Neat-herd, who petitioning earneſtly at his inveſtiture into the Empire, to have his Liberty <foreign rend="italic">gratis</foreign>, and being denied, cry'd out publickly, <q rend="italic">The Woolf might change his hair, but never his qualities.</q> Others there be which believe, he was compell'd to thoſe Rapines and Extorſions, by the impoveriſhment of his Exchequer which he teſtified at his arrival at the Government, by a publick Declaration, <q rend="italic">That the Commonwealth could not poſſibly ſubſiſt, without a ſupply of a hundred &amp; forty millions of Seſterces.</q> And this indeed is the moſt probable opinion, becauſe however he came by his money, he imploy'd it always to good uſe.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. He extended his Liberality to all ſorts of people; he compleated the Eſtates of the Senators; he allow'd Penſions of 500 Seſterces to every perſon which had been Conſul, and was grown indigent; ſeveral Towns that had been ruin'd by Fire, or Earthquakes, in divers parts of the World, he reſtor'd to their former luſtre and condition.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <pb n="454"/>
    <p>
      18. But his more particular bounty, he expreſſed towards the Profeſſors of all Arts and Sciences; he was the firſt which ſettled a Salary of a hundred thouſand Seſterces, upon the Teachers of Rhetorick both Greek and Latine, to be paid yearly out of the Exchequer; he invited the moſt excellent Maſters in Poetry, and other Artificers, to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, by conſiderable Allowances; alſo made the Repairer of the Coloſs a large Preſent, and a fair Allowance. An Engineer which undertook to convey certain Columns of vaſt weight, into the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, at a ſmall charge, he rewarded well for his invention, but excus'd him for performing it, telling him, <q rend="italic">That he ſhould let the poor live.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      19. The Scaffolds of the Theatre of <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName> being repair'd, upon the day of its dedication, certain Plays being repreſented, <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> according to antient cuſtom reſtor'd the Songs with Muſick, and Ludicrous recitations. To <persName rend="italic">Apollinaris</persName> the Tragedian he gave four hundred Seſterces to <persName rend="italic">Terpnus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Diodorus</persName>, two Players upon the Harp, he gave two hundred; to others one hundred ; and to them which had leaſt, he gave forty Seſterces, beſides a good number of Crowns of Gold, which he caus'd to be diſtributed amongſt them. His Feaſts and Entertainments were frequent, for the moſt part noble and magnificent, that the Butchers and ſuch as ſold Victuals might thrive. As he gave Preſents to the Men at the <foreign rend="italic">Saturnalian</foreign> Feaſts, ſo he preſented the Women on the Calends of March; and yet with all this, he could not avoid the infamy of his former avarice.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The Alexandrines perſiſted in calling him <foreign rend="italic">Cybioſactes</foreign>, after the name of one of their Kings, who was eminent amongſt them for his inſufferable parſimony. And at his very Funeral, <persName rend="italic">Favour</persName> the chief
      <pb n="455"/>
      Mimick repreſenting his perſon, and imitating his words and actions when he was alive, according to cuſtom, demanding aloud of ſuch as had the inſpection and charge of the Ceremony, <q rend="italic">What the expence of his Obſequies would be?</q> being told they would amount to 1000000 Seſterces, he cry'd out, <q rend="italic">Give me the money and throw my body where you pleaſe, though it be into <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      20. He was of a middle ſtature, his limbs firm and robuſt, his countenance ſomething conſtrain'd, which gave occaſion to one of the Wits of that age, to break an unhappy jeſt upon him; for <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> deſiring him to ſpare him no more than the reſt of the Company, but to ſpeak ſome waggiſh thing or other upon him too, <q rend="italic">That I will,</q> quoth he, <q rend="italic">when you have done going to the Stool.</q> He enjoy'd his health very well, though he uſed no other means than rubbing his jaws, and other parts of his body, a certain number of times in the <foreign rend="italic">Spheriſterium</foreign> or Tennis-Court, and one day in a moneth abſtained from all manner of food.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      21. This for the moſt part was the Order of his life; when he was Emperour, he ſate up very late, and wak'd very early in the morning; then having perus'd his Letters and Diſpatches, and over-look'd the Breviaries of all his Officers, he admitted his Friends, and whilſt they were ſaluting and entertaining him, he dreſs'd himſelf, to the very putting on of his own ſhooes; after which having diſpatch'd all his affairs, he allotted ſome time for Exerciſe, and then to his repoſe, in which he had moſt commonly one of his Concubines lay by him, which he had choſen in great numbers to ſucceed <persName rend="italic">Cænis</persName>, who was deceaſed: From thence he paſs'd privately into his Baths, and from them to the room where he eat.
      <pb n="456"/>
      He was never better humour'd, than at ſuch times as theſe; whereupon his Servants watch'd alwayes for ſome ſuch opportunity, when they had any thing extraordinary to beg.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      22. At Supper and at all times elſe, he was pleaſant and facetious with his friends, and indeed ſo much given to drolling, that he would be ſcurrilous and ſordid, and ſometimes guilty of ſuch words, a young Gentleman of fifteen years old would have been aſham'd of: Yet there are ſome ſayings of his, which are innocent and witty enough; <persName rend="italic">Meſtrius Florus</persName>, a man of Conſular degree, having advis'd him to ſay <foreign rend="italic">PLAUSTRA</foreign>, rather than <foreign rend="italic">PLOSTRA</foreign>, the next day he ſaluted him by the name of <foreign rend="italic">Flaurus</foreign>. A certain Courtezan having perſecuted him with her Love, and perſwaded him ſhe ſhould dye without his compaſſion, he yielded at laſt, enjoy'd her, and gave her 400 Seſterces for her pains: The Keeper of his Privy-Purſe coming afterwards to him, to know how it ſhould be entred in his Accompts, he told him he would have it ſet down, <q rend="italic">For <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian's</persName> being belov'd.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      23. He made uſe of Greek Verſes many times, and that very appoſitely: Speaking of a man which was very tall, but ill natur'd and ill proportion'd withall, he apply'd a Verſe out of <persName rend="italic">Homer</persName> to him, which correſponded exactly with the deſcription of the man. Upon <persName rend="italic">Cerylus</persName> (one of his Freed-men, who being grown rich, and had taken the name of <persName rend="italic">Laches</persName> upon him, and pretended to be free-born, to avoid ſome payment in the Exchequer) he paſs'd a Greek Diſtich to this purpoſe; <q rend="italic">O Laches, Laches, when thou art dead thou wilt be <persName rend="italic">Cerylus</persName> again.</q> Above all things he affected jeering and gibeing, to cover the deformity of the gain he made in trifling and unſeemly
      <pb n="457"/>
      things, that he might elude the envy of his practices by ſome ridiculous cavil.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      One of his principal Officers and Favourites, coming to him one day to beg a Stewards place, for one which he pretended was his Brother, he put him off for the preſent, and caus'd him to be call'd to him which deſir'd the preferment; from whom having receiv'd the ſum himſelf, which was to have been paid to the other for his mediation, he ordain'd him his Steward; and when the Petitioner complain'd, he told him, <q rend="italic">You muſt e'en go find out another Brother, for this perſon whom you thought to be yours, proves at laſt to be mine.</q> Another time being upon the road, and ſuſpecting his Coachman who drove his Chariot, had ſtopt under pretence of ſhooing his Mules, for no other reaſon but to give opportunity to one that had buſineſs in Law, and was coming to ſspeak with him, he ask'd his Muliteer, <q rend="italic">What was the price of a ſhooing?</q> and articled for half.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      His Son <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName> reprehending his invention of an Impoſt upon Urine, he took out ſome of the firſt money he had receiv'd, and holding it to his Noſe, he demanded if the ſmell offended him; being anſwer'd, <q rend="italic">Not at all</q>; he reply'd, <q rend="italic">And yet this comes out of the Urine.</q> Certain Ambaſſadors having brought him word, That there was a conſiderable ſum of money decreed for erecting a Statue for him in the form of a Coloſſus, <q rend="italic">Where is it?</q> (ſayes he) <q rend="italic">give it me preſently</q>; and holding out the palm of his hand, he told them, <q rend="italic">This Pedeſtal is alwayes ready.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      In his extream perils and apprehenſions of death, he could not forbear his raillerie; when amongſt other Prodigies, he was told the Mausoleum of the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> had ſuddenly open'd of it ſelf, and that a Blazing-ſtar appear'd in the air, he laugh'd at the Omen, and perſwaded them, the one belong'd to
      <pb n="458"/>
      <persName rend="italic">Junia Calvina</persName>, who was of the race of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and the other to the King of the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName>, who wore his hair long; and when he was firſt ſeiz'd with his malady, he cry'd, <q rend="italic">If I be not miſtaken, I am going to be a God.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      24. In his ninth Conſulſhip, being in <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, he was ſurpriz'd with ſome light motions of a diſtemper, which oblig'd him to repair forthwith to the City, from whence he went to <placeName rend="italic">Cutyliæ</placeName>, and an Eſtate he had about <placeName rend="italic">Reate</placeName>, which he viſited uſually every Summer. In this place, beſides the diſtemper upon him, (having corrupted his Entrails by the uſe of cold water) he nevertheleſs gave himſelf up to the affairs of the Empire as before, giving Audience to Ambaſſadors as he was lying upon his Couch; but being ſuddenly taken with a Lask, and brought to ſuch a weakneſs he was ready to faint, he cry'd out, <q rend="italic">An Emperour ought to dye upon his feet</q>; and endeavouring to riſe, he ſank down, and went away in their hands which were helping him up. He died upon the 24th of June, when he had lived ſixty nine years, one month, and ſeven dayes.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      225. The common opinion is, he was ſo well aſſured of his own fate, and his Childrens, that in ſpight of the frequent Conſpiracies againſt him, he had the confidence to affirm to the Senate, <q rend="italic">That either his Sons ſhould ſucceed him or no body.</q> It is reported alſo, that he dreamt upon a time, that he ſaw a pair of Scales hanging in an exact Æquilibrium, in the middle of the Porch of his Palace, with <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> in one Ballance, and himſelf and his Sons in the other: Nor was he miſtaken in the event of his Viſion, for the Reign and Dominion both of the one ſide and the other, was preciſely of an equal duration.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>