
<TEI>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
<pb n="148"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      The Patrician Family of the <persName rend="italic">Claudians</persName> (for there is another of the Plebeians no leſs conſiderable for its power and wealth) came originally from <placeName rend="italic">Regilli</placeName>, a Town of the <placeName rend="italic">Sabines</placeName>; from whence (the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName> being newly form'd into a Republick) they removed to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, by the encouragement of <persName rend="italic">Titus Tatius</persName> Partner with <persName rend="italic">Romulus</persName> in his Kingdom: or (which is moſt generally receiv'd) by the invitation of <persName rend="italic">Atta Claudius</persName>, the principal perſon of that Family, about ſix years after the expulſion of their Kings. There they were ranked among the Patricians, and had lands aſſigned them beyond the River <placeName rend="italic">Anien</placeName>, for their Followers; and a place of Burial for their Anceſtors, under the Capitol. In proceſs of time, this Family had eight and twenty Conſulſhips, five Dictatorſhips, ſeven Cenſorſhips, ſeven Triumphs, and two Ovations.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      It produc'd ſeveral eminent perſons; and though their variety of ſurnames diſtinguiſh'd them into ſeveral Branches, we ſhall inſtance only the ſurname of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, which in the <placeName rend="italic">Sabine</placeName> language ſignifies ſtrong, and valiant.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      And as they have deſerv'd very well of the Common-wealth, in many great and conſiderable performances, ſo the crimes of which they are convict are as many: <persName rend="italic">Appius The Blind</persName> perſwaded the Common-wealth from an Alliance with King <persName rend="italic">Pyrrhus</persName>, as an unſafe and diſhonourable thing. <persName rend="italic">Claudius Caudex</persName> was the firſt man that paſs'd the Straits with a Fleet, and drove the <placeName rend="italic">Carthaginians</placeName> out of <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>. <persName rend="italic">Claudius Nero</persName> cut off <persName rend="italic">Afdrubal</persName>, as he was coming with a great Army out of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> to the aſſiſtance of <persName rend="italic">Hannibal</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      On the other ſide, the crimes of which they are convict are as many. <persName rend="italic">Appius Claudius</persName> the Decemvir, was the chief cauſe that the Ten Tables of the Laws were not aboliſh'd, though their time was expir'd; and going about to force a free-born Virgin, her Father was neceſſitated to kill her, to preſerve her honour. <persName rend="italic">Claudius Druſus</persName> having his Statue erected with a Diadem at <placeName rend="italic">Appii Forum</placeName>, attempted the Kingdom of <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>. <persName rend="italic">Claudius Pulcher</persName> going to Sea, and taking his Augurie, becauſe the Fowls would not feed, in contempt of Religion he commanded them to be thrown into the Sea, <q rend="italic">That they might drink, ſeeing they would not eat</q>; and giving battel immediately, was defeated.
    </p>
  </div>
  <pb n="149"/>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      We know likewiſe, that the <persName rend="italic">Claudii</persName> have been alwayes ſevere aſſertors of the dignity and pre-eminence of the Patricians; and ſo violent and contumacious againſt the Commons, that there was never any of them (except <persName rend="italic">P. Clodius</persName>, who for his own particular advantage, having cauſed himſelf to be adopted by a Plebeian, that he might thruſt <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> out of the Town) but oppoſed them with all their might.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The ſame <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> being to go General againſt the Enemy, when the Tribunes of the People would have hindered him, he cauſed them to be cudgelled out of the Court.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      From this Family was <persName rend="italic">Tiberius Cæſar</persName> deſcended, and that by both ſides: by his Fathers ſide from <persName rend="italic">Tiberius Nero</persName>; and by his Mothers, from <persName rend="italic">Appius Pulcher</persName>, who were both of them the Sons of <persName rend="italic">Appius The Blind</persName>. Beſides, he was ingrafted into the Family of the <persName rend="italic">Livii</persName>, by the adoption of his Mothers Grand-father: Which Family, though Plebeian, was nevertheleſs of great authority and eminency in the State; having had eight Conſulſhips, two Cenſorſhips, and three Triumphs; beſides the honour of having been created Dictator, and General of the Horſe.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      It was famous alſo for the eminent perſons it produc'd, particularly <persName rend="italic">Salinator</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>. <persName rend="italic">Salinator</persName> having in his Cenſorſhip reprov'd all the Tribes for their inconſtancy, in making him Conſul and Cenſor, whom they had condemned and baniſh'd before. <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> for fighting and killing <persName rend="italic">Draüſus</persName> the General of the Enemy, in a ſingle combat, brought the ſurname of <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> to his poſterity. It is reported likewiſe of this <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, that being Proprætor in <placeName rend="italic">Gaul</placeName>, he recovered the Gold which had been given formerly to the <placeName rend="italic">Senones</placeName> at the ſiege of the Capitol, and which <persName rend="italic">Camillus</persName> is reported to have reſcued by force. His great Grand-ſon for his eminent ſervices againſt the <persName rend="italic">Gracchi</persName>, was ſtiled the Patron of the Senate.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      But the Father of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> being Quæſtor to <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſar</persName>, and Commander of his Fleet in the <placeName rend="italic">Alexandrine</placeName> War, contributed highly to his Victory. Whereupon he was made Pontifex in the place of <persName rend="italic">P. Scipio</persName>, and ſent to plant ſeveral Colonies in <placeName rend="italic">Gaul</placeName>, amongſt which were <placeName rend="italic">Narbon</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Arles</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After the murther of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>, when the reſt of the Senators for fear of a tumult, had voted an amneſty and oblivion of what was paſt, he declar'd, That he thought it neceſſary the Conſpirators ſhould be rewarded. Being Prætor, at the end of the year, there ariſing a difference betwixt the Triumviri, he retained the Badges of his Authority beyond the time, and following <persName rend="italic">L. Antonius</persName> the Conſul (who was Brother to the Triumvir) to <placeName rend="italic">Peruſia</placeName>, he was left by him alone; when the Town was delivered up.
    </p>
  </div>
  <pb n="150"/>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      From thence he eſcaped to <placeName rend="italic">Præneſte</placeName>, and from <placeName rend="italic">Præneſte</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>; where having by a promiſe of liberty, drawn the Slaves to his Party, he fled into <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName> to <persName rend="italic">Sextus Pompeius</persName>; but being badly receiv'd, and disgusted that he could not immediately be admitted to the preſence of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, he removed into <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName> to <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName>: with whom a general peace being concluded, he returned to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and yielded up his Wife <persName rend="italic">Livia Druſilla</persName> (though ſhe was then big with Child) to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, who had a particular deſire to her: A while after he died, leaving two Sons behind him, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> was born in the Conſulſhip of <persName rend="italic">M. Æmilius Lepidus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Munacius Plancus</persName>, (both Conſuls the ſecond time) upon the ſixteenth of the Calends of <date rend="italic">December</date>, in the Palace on the <placeName rend="italic">Palatine</placeName> Hill. Though there are ſome who have reported him to have been born at <placeName rend="italic">Fundi</placeName>, but that without reaſon, only becauſe his Mothers Grand-mother was of that place, and a Statue of Felicity was erected there by a decree of the Senate. But it is manifeſt by the Publick Regiſters, that he was born at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      His infancy and childhood were accompanied with much trouble and danger, accompanying his Parents in their flight, where he was twice in great hazard of betraying them by his crying; once at <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>, as they were running by night to the Sea-ſide, for fear of being ſurpriſed; and again, when they fled from <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName> out of the hands of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, to <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being brought about <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName> by his Parents, and recommended to the protection of the Lacedemonians, he was in danger of his life, by a fire that brake out in the night time, and burnt the Wood of the Houſe where they lay, ſcorching the hair and clothes of his Mother <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Returning to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he was adopted by <persName rend="italic">M. Gallius</persName>, a Senator; whose Eſtate he receiv'd, though he would not assume his Name, becauſe <persName rend="italic">Gallius</persName> was of the contrary party to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>. At nine years of age, he pronounced a Funeral Oration from the Roſtra, in commendation of his Father. 
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      And growing up, he attended upon <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> in his Triumph after the <placeName rend="italic">Actiack</placeName> Victory, riding upon the left hand of his Chariot, whilſt <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName> rode upon the right. Preſently after, he preſided at the Publick Playes; and in the <foreign rend="italic">Trojan</foreign> exerciſes in the Circus, he was the Commander of the bigger Boys.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Having put on his Virile Robe, he ſpent the rest of his youth, and the remainder of his life in theſe practices. He exhibited combats of Gladiators, in memory of his Father and Grand-father; the firſt in the Forum, the other in the Amphitheatre: to which he brought Fencers of the chiefeſt reputation, and pay'd them a hundred thouſand Seſterces apiece. He appointed publick Games alſo, but was abſent himſelf: and all this with great magnificence, being supplyed out of the Coffers of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <pb n="151"/>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He married <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">M. Agrippa</persName>, and Grand-daughter to <persName rend="italic">Cecilius Atticus</persName>, a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight, (to whom the Epiſtles of <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> are directed). By her he had a Son called <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>; but ſhortly after, when she was with Child again, he was forc'd to part with her, and to take <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>, the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>; which he did with great reluctancy, having a great kindneſs for <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, and disliking the character of <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>, who had before made offers to him, even whilst her former Husband was alive.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      After the Divorce, he retained ſo great an affection for <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, that meeting her by chance in the ſtreets, he fix'd his eyes upon her with ſuch tokens of paſſion and concernment, that <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> took order they ſhould never meet again. With <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> he liv'd quietly at firſt, but afterwards they grew to greater variance; insomuch that after the death of their Child (which was born at <placeName rend="italic">Aquileia</placeName>) he lay from her constantly.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      His firſt entrance into the Courts of Juſtice, was to defend King <persName rend="italic">Archelaus</persName>, and the <placeName rend="italic">Theſſalians</placeName>; and the Citizens of <placeName rend="italic">Tralles</placeName>, who implored the aſſiſtance of the Senate. For the <placeName rend="italic">Laodiceans</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Thyaterians</placeName> (whoſe Cities were ruined by an Earthquake) he interceded to the Senate for relief. He accuſed <persName rend="italic">Fannius Cæpio</persName>, who conſpired with <persName rend="italic">Murena</persName> againſt <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and got him condemned of High Treaſon. Afterwards he had the charge of providing the City with Corn: then of visiting the Inne-keepers and Victuallers throughout <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, to prevent their abuses.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      His firſt Military expedition was againſt the <placeName rend="italic">Cantabrians</placeName>, in which he served as a Tribune of the Souldiers. After that he march'd with an Army into the East, and reſtor'd the Kingdom of <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName> to <persName rend="italic">Tigranes</persName>, placing the Crown upon his head from the Tribunal. Beſides this, he recovered the Enſignes which the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName> had taken from <persName rend="italic">M. Craſſus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For a whole year together, he was Governour of the <placeName rend="italic">Hairy Gaul</placeName>, which was much infeſted with the incurſions of the Barbarians, and the mutinies of the Inhabitants. Afterwards he had the Command of the <placeName rend="italic">Rhætian</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Vindelician</placeName> Wars; as also of the <placeName rend="italic">Pannonian</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> Expeditions.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In the <placeName rend="italic">Rhætian</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Vindelician</placeName> Wars, he subdued the Nations of the Alpes. In the <placeName rend="italic">Pannonian</placeName>, he conquered the <placeName rend="italic">Breuci</placeName>, and the <placeName rend="italic">Dalmatæ</placeName>. In the <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> War, he led an Army of fourty thouſand men over the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, and forced the <placeName rend="italic">Sicambri</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Suevi</placeName> to a submiſſion. For which atchievements, he entered the City in Triumph, and Ovation; and was made Conſul, and Tribune.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Whilſt he was in the height of all his glory, and flouriſhing in his youth and proſperity, he retir'd on a ſudden, and reſolv'd to with-draw himſelf. Whether out of a diſguſt to his Wife, whom he durſt not accuſe, nor repudiate; or out of a deſire to render himſelf the more deſiderate to the Common-wealth, by an absence that might ſhew how uſeful he had been, is uncertain.
    </p>
  </div>
  <pb n="152"/>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Some are of opinion, that the Children of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> being grown up, he yielded up the ſecond place in the Government (which for a long time he had poſſeſs'd) as a man that intended them no injury: following the example of <persName rend="italic">M. Agrippa</persName>, who when <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName> was preferred to publick charges, retired to <placeName rend="italic">Mitylene</placeName>, that his preſence might not seem to eclipſe him. And this <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> himſelf confessed afterwards: though at that time, his pretence was only to refreſh himſelf after his fatigues, and enjoy some quiet. So he preſſed earnestly for a dismission, and obtained it at length; neither his Mothers prayers, nor the complaints of his Father-in-law in the Senate, being able to divert him. Upon their resolute refuſal to permit his departure, he forbore eating four days together.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      At last he was permitted to go; and leaving his Wife and Son at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he departed for <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>: returning not one word of anſwer to any that accompanied him; nor kiſſing so much as one of them at his parting.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      From <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>, coasting along the shore of <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, he receiv'd news of the ſickneſs of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>; which cauſed him to ftop: but finding reports of his expecting the Emperour's death to succeed him, he set sail again, though the wind was extremely contrary, and arrived at <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName>; a place he had been much pleaſed with formerly, when he put in there in his return from <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Here he contented himſelf with a small houſe, and an estate not much larger than the condition of a private man; walking up and down the <foreign rend="italic">Gymnaſium</foreign> without his Lictors, or usual attendants; and conversing familiarly with the <placeName rend="italic">Grecians</placeName> almost every day.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      It happened one morning, as he was disposing of the business of the day, he declar'd, That he had a deſire to viſit the ſick people in the City. Which being miſunderſtood by his Officers, they brought all the ſick perſons in the Town into a publick Portico, and ranked them according to the qualities of their diseases. At which he was exceedingly surpriſed, and stood amazed for a good while; but at laſt he went to them all, and excused the mistake even to the meanest of them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      Only one instance there is of his exercising his Tribunitial power: Conversing constantly in the Schools and Auditories of the Philoſophers, an altercation aroſe amongſt the Sophisters; and one of them reflecting upon him as partial in the dispute, he rose up, went home, and fetching his Lictors, cited him before his Tribunal, and commanded him to Priſon. After this, he had advertisement from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, that his Wife <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> was condemned for Adultery; and divorc'd in his name by the Command of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>. Though he was glad of the news, yet he thought it his duty to intercede for her.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      The time of his Tribuneship being expired, he desir'd leave to return to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, alledging, that he retired only lest his presence should be an offence to <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName>; but they being now grown up, and the second place in the Common-wealth remaining entire to them, his absence was unnecessary. But <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> refuſed him peremptorily, and bad him <q rend="italic">Lay aſide all care of his relations, since he was so ready to abandon them before.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <pb n="153"/>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Whereupon he remained at <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName> much against his will; and not without danger: for <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> passing by the Island to take possession of his Province in the East, he waited upon him at <placeName rend="italic">Samos</placeName>, where he found him much alienated from him, through the calumnies of <persName rend="italic">M. Lollius</persName> his Governour.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He grew ſuſpicious also that he was obnoxious to the displeaſure of <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> his Officers; for it was told him, that at a Banquet one of them profered <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, <q rend="italic">If he would but command him, he would go instantly to <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName>, and fetch him the head of the Exile</q>; (for so <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> was usually called). Finding himſelf in hazard, he imploy'd the moſt earnest prayers, and his Mothers utmost interest, to get leave to return.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      At last he obtained it, by the assistance of <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, who chanced to be disgusted with <persName rend="italic">Lollius</persName>, and was the more easily perswaded: but it was upon condition he should not intermeddle with the affairs of the Common-wealth. Thus in the eighth year of his retirement he return'd to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, animated by a great confidence he had in his destiny, and the predictions of <persName rend="italic">Thraſyllus</persName> the Astrologer; who assuring him of the Empire, he took him into his family.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He had other presages also: for returning to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, an Eagle perched upon the top of his house; and as he was coming aſhore in <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, a flame of fire sprang out of the embers of a sacrifice that was dead.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Return'd to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he introduc'd his Son <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> into the Forum; and removed himſelf from the Palace of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, to the Gardens of <persName rend="italic">Mæcenas</persName>. For some time he gave himſelf up wholly to his ease, performing only the private offices of a friend, without any publick intermedling.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> dying both in three years time, he was adopted by <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, together with <persName rend="italic">M. Agrippa</persName>; being first oblig'd to adopt <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, the Son of his Brother <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>. After his adoption, he intermitted nothing of his respect and obedience as a Son; keeping nothing proper to himſelf, but surrendering the Inheritance of his Father, and whatever came to him by other legacies.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      From that day, he recovered his former greatneſs, and became more eminent than before; it being decreed, that he should administer the Tribunitial power with <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> for five years.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Whereupon he was immediately dispatch'd into <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>; from whence the <placeName rend="italic">Illyrian</placeName> Ambassadors returning, and declaring that they came to <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, they were ordered to expect him: He having the administration of the Provinces and Armies committed to him by a special Decree of the Senate.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Having reduced the <placeName rend="italic">Illyrians</placeName>, he march'd into <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName> again; but hearing <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> was faln deſperately ſick, he return'd in all haſte, and found him living, but almoſt paſt ſpeaking: with whom he remain'd in private a whole day.
    </p>
  </div>
  <pb n="154"/>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Not long after, <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> dying, he concealed his death till he had dispacht young <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>. This <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> was kill'd by a Tribune of the Souldiers who had the guard of him; but whether by the order of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, or the command of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> (to prevent any tumult that might arise), is uncertain. When the Tribune brought him word, that his orders were executed, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> anſwered, <q rend="italic">That he gave no ſuch command, and that the Tribune muſt answer it to the Senate</q>: thereby to avoid the present Odium of the Fact; though he never proſecuted the matter afterwards.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      The Tribunitial dignity being conferr'd upon from the ſecond time for five years longer, he was ſent to pacifie the troubles in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>: And the <placeName rend="italic">Parthian</placeName> Ambaſſadors had Orders as ſoon as they had had Audience of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> to repair forthwith to him in his Province: But having News of the defection of <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName> he remained from thence to manage this War, which, proved the moſt dangerous and troubleſome of all the Forreign Wars, ſince that with the <placeName rend="italic">Carthaginians</placeName>: His Army conſiſted of fifteen Legions, and as many Auxiliaries, which he commanded three years together in conſtant extremity of all things, but eſpecially of Corn:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      And though he was often preſs'd to return, he would never give it over, as apprehending he ſhould have had a neighbouring and Potent Enemy quickly upon his back, who would have miſtaken his retreat, and interpreted it a flight. And indeed he was well rewarded for his perſeverance, for he reduc'd all the Country of <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName> which lies betwixt <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> the Kingdoms of <placeName rend="italic">Noricum</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Thrace</placeName>, and betwixt the River <placeName rend="italic">Danubius</placeName> and the <placeName rend="italic">Adriatick</placeName> Sea.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Nor was the defeat of <persName rend="italic">Quin. Varus</persName> and his three Legions (which were cut in pieces about that time 
      <pb n="169"/>
      in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>) a ſmall advantage and accumulation of his Glory, no body doubting but the Victorious <placeName rend="italic">Germans</placeName> would have joined with the <placeName rend="italic">Pannonians</placeName>, had not <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName> been ſubdued. For theſe noble exploits he had a Triumph decreed for him, beſides ſeveral other honours;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      ſome advised to have him call'd as his ſur-name, <persName rend="italic">Pannonicus</persName>, others to give him the Epithete of <foreign rend="italic">Invincible</foreign>, others of <foreign rend="italic">Pious</foreign>. But <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> oppoſed himſelf to all thoſe Titles, aſſuring them that <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> would be content with what he would leave him at his death. As for his Triumph, he put that off himſelf, the City of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> being at that time in great affliction for <persName rend="italic">Varus</persName> his defeat. Nevertheleſs he made a publick Entry into the City in his <foreign rend="italic">Prætexta</foreign> or imbroidred Robe of Purple, with a Chaplet of Lawrel upon his head: and a Tribunal being erected for him in the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martius</placeName>, and the Senate ſtanding by, he went up into it, and plac'd himſelf (with <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>) between the two Conſuls, after which he ſaluted the people, and was honourably conducted round about the Temples.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      The next year being returned into <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, and underſtanding that the loſs of <persName rend="italic">Quint. Varus</persName> and his Legions proceeded meerly from his own negligence and temerity, he reſolved to act nothing but by the advice of his Council, (He which before followed his own judgment alone, began now to Communicate with ſeveral perſons in the management of his War.) His care from this time was greater than formerly. Being about to paſs the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, he ſtood himſelf upon the bank of the River, and having preſcrib'd certain Rules and Directions for his proviſions, he would not let any of them paſs, till he had examined the load of every Waggon, leſt 
      <pb n="170"/>
      any thing elſe ſhould be carryed but what was neceſſary or allowed.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      On the other ſide the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, his courſe of life was ſo moderate and incurious, that he dined many times upon the Ground without a Cloth, and ſlept whole nights without Tent or Pavillion. His Orders for the next day (or if any thing happened unexpectedly) he gave alwayes in little Tickets, with this admonition, that if they doubted of any thing they ſhould apply themſelves to no perſon but himſelf for interpretation, to whom they might repair at all hours in the night.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He was a ſevere exactor of Military Diſcipline; and to the end it might be the more punctually obſerv'd, he revived all the old and obſolete puniſhments and diſgraces which were practiſed in ancient times; in ſo much as he diſparaged a Lieutenant of a Legion, for having ſent Souldiers with a Freeman of his, a hunting on the other ſide of the River. Though he expos'd himſelf but ſeldom to the hazzards of a Battle, yet he engaged with more confidence, if whilſt he was watching in the night, the Candle fell down of it ſelf without any impulſion, and went out, it being an Omen (as he ſaid) which had been fortunate both to him and his predeceſſors, in all their Expeditions. Yet nevertheleſs one day, after his uſual ſucceſs, he had like to have been killed by a private man, who being obſerv'd about his Perſon with ſome terrour in his countenance, was ſeiz'd upon immediately, and confeſs'd the whole deſign being put upon the Rack.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Two years after, being return'd out of <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he made his Triumph, which he had put off till then, attended by the Lieutenants for 
      <pb n="171"/>
      whom he had obtained the Triumphal Ornaments: Before he entred into the Capitol, he deſcended from his Chariot, and threw himſelf at <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> his feet, who ſat then as Preſident. The ſolemnity being paſt, he diſpatch'd <persName rend="italic">Bato</persName> the General of the <placeName rend="italic">Pannonians</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Ravenna</placeName>, after he had rewarded him with magnificent Preſents, in recompence of his kindneſs in permitting himſelf and his Army to eſcape out of a dangerous place, in which they were encompaſs'd. After this he made a ſolemn Dinner for the people, and allow'd them a thouſand Tables, beſides a diſtribution of three thouſand Seſterces a man; and out of his ſpoils he dedicated a Temple to <persName rend="italic">Concord</persName>, and another to <persName rend="italic">Caſtor</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Pollux</persName>, in his own name, and his Brothers.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Not long after, by order of the Conſuls, he was joyn'd in the Government of the Provinces with <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and was imploy'd alſo about inſpection into the Names and Revenues of all the Citizens, with him; after he had diſcharged the ſaid Office, he was departed for <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName>, but being call'd back on a ſudden by the way upon <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> his ſickneſs, he found him irrecoverable, but yet ſo ſenſible, he had private conference with him a whole day together.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      I know it is reported, that after <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> was gone out from him, the Servants attending on <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> in his Chamber, ſhould hear him ſpeak theſe words; <q rend="italic">Miſerum populum Romanum, qui ſub tam lentis maxillis erit.</q> <q rend="italic">Oh unhappy people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, that is to be under ſo ſlow a pair of grinders.</q> Nor am I ignorant what ſome have written, That <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> was ſo ſenſible of his ill nature, that in the midſt of his mirth, and pleaſant diſcourſe, he would ſtop and take up ſometimes, if he ſaw him coming into the room: And that 
      <pb n="172"/>
      either the importunity of his Wife had prevail'd for his adoption, or elſe he was acted by an ambition of making his death more regretted, by the badneſs of his ſucceſſor.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Nevertheleſs I cannot be perſwaded, that a Prince of his ſagacity and prudence, ſhould proceed ſo ſlightly in an affair of that importance. I rather believe, that having weigh'd both his Vices, and Virtues, he thought his Virtues did preponderate; eſpecially when I conſider, that in a publick Aſſembly he ſwore, that he adopted him for no other cauſe, but out of his affection to the Common-wealth; and in ſome of his Epiſtles commended him, not only for an excellent Captain, but as the only ſtay and ſupport of the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; out of which I have thought good to inſert ſome of his expreſſions as an inſtance,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">Farewel, my moſt dear <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, may you be happy in your Enterprizes, fighting (as you do) for me and the Muſes: and may I be happy, as you are a moſt valiant and accompliſh'd Captain.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">Adieu, have a care of your Summer Quarters; as for my own part, my <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, I believe confidently amongſt ſo many difficulties and diſorders, amongſt ſo much remiſsneſs and cowardiſe in the Army, no man could have carried himſelf with more prudence than you have done, in ſo much that all perſons which have had the honour to be near you, do unanimouſly acknowledge, that this Verſe cannot more properly be apply'd to any man living, than to your ſelf: <foreign rend="italic">Unus homo nobis vigilando reſtituit rem.</foreign> What many had loſt before, by dire miſchance, Is now reſtor'd by one mans vigilance.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      And in another place; <q rend="italic">Whether (ſays he) I be 
      <pb n="173"/>
      ſeriouſly to conſider of an affair, or whether any thing falls out which I ought to reſent, I want my <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> immediately, and this ſaying of <persName rend="italic">Homer</persName> comes conſtantly into my mind, By this mans conduct and prudence, we might both of us eſcape, even out of the fire.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">As often as I am told how much you are fallen away by your indefatigable labour, may I periſh if I do not tremble to hear it. Let me deſire you therefore to have more care of your ſelf for the future, leſt the firſt news of your ſickneſs, be the death of your Mother, and me, and the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> run a great hazzard of loſing their Empire. My own health is not conſiderable to me, unleſs you be well alſo. I beg of the Gods that they would preſerve you in perpetual health for our benefit, if they have no prejudice or animoſity to the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He did not ſuffer <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> his death to be publiſh'd, till he had caus'd young <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> to be ſlain. He was killed by a Military Tribune, (in whoſe cuſtody he was at that time) after he had read the Warrant for his Execution to him. Which Warrant, whether left by <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> when he died, to prevent any troubles that might happen upon his death, or whether contrived by <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> in <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> his name, with or without the privity of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, is a thing uncertain to this very day: This is moſt true, that when the Tribune brought him word, he had executed his Commands, he told him, <q rend="italic">He had no ſuch Command from him, and that he ſhould give an account of it to the Senate.</q> But it was only to put off the ſcandal for the preſent, for it was afterwards forgotten, and no more mention made of it at all.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      After this, as he was Tribune of the people, he made uſe of the authority of his Office, to con<pb n="174"/>vocate the Senate; and having begun a conſolatory Oration to them, he ſtopt on a ſudden in the beginning of his Speech, as unable to reſtrain the violence of his ſorrow, and with a moſt profound ſigh wiſh'd to God, <q rend="italic">That not only his voice, but his life would fail him;</q> and at the ſame time gave his Notes to his Son <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> to read out. This done, the laſt Will and Teſtament of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> was brought into the Council, but none of the Witneſſes admitted in, except ſuch as were Senators; the reſt being commanded to acknowledge their Hands and Seals in the Chambers without, to which purpoſe it was read amongſt them by one of his Freemen: The beginning of it was thus; <q rend="italic">For as much as it was my ill fortune to have <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> (my Sons) taken from me, I do by theſe preſents make <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> my Heir in two thirds of my Eſtate.</q> From whence their opinion was much fortified, who believ'd he choſe him his Succeſſor more out of neceſſity, than Election, otherwiſe he would have forborn ſuch a Preface as that.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Though he made no difficulty of aſſuming the Dominion, as appear'd by his Guards, which is a mark of violence and ſoveraignty, yet he refus'd it moſt impudently for a long time, rebuking his friends ſometimes which ſollicited him, and telling them, <q rend="italic">They knew not how unmanageable a Beaſt an Empire was.</q> Sometimes by the ambiguity of his anſwers, he held the Senate in ſuſpence, who were at his feet all the while, begging and conjuring him to accept of it; till at laſt, one impatient of his jugling, cry'd out in the midſt of the tumult, <q rend="italic">Let him take the Empire, or leave it.</q> Another declar'd in his preſence, <q rend="italic">That other people perform ſlowly, what they readily promiſe, but he promiſed but ſlowly, what 
      <pb n="175"/>
      he had already perform'd.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      At laſt, as if over-power'd and complaining of the miſerable burden and ſervitude which they had brought upon him, he accepted the Government, but ſo as he gave them hopes he would one day reſign. His own words were theſe; <q rend="italic">I will accept and keep it, till ſuch time as you in your great prudence ſhall think fit to give repoſe to my old age.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Yet it was not without reaſon he was deliberating ſo long, conſidering the dangers impending from all parts. It was often his expreſſion, that <q rend="italic">he had a Woolf by the ear;</q> and he was not much in the wrong, for a Servant of <persName rend="italic">Agrippa's</persName> (<persName rend="italic">Clement</persName> by name) was gotten at the head of no inconſiderable body of men, to revenge the death of his Maſter: And <persName rend="italic">Lucius Scribonius Libo</persName>, a perſon of honour and quality, was forming a party againſt him: Beſides which there was a double mutiny in his Army, one in <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName>, the other in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, in both places the Souldiers inſiſting upon things beyond all cuſtom or preſident;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      but above all thoſe in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName> preſt hard, that they might have the ſame pay with his Prætorian Troops. Others would by no means have a Prince, but of their own making, and put it home upon <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> (who at that time commanded them) to take upon him the Government, which he would never admit. This being the greateſt of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> his apprehenſions, he remonſtrated to the Senate, that one man was not ſufficient for the whole adminiſtration, that it was neceſſary he ſhould have one Colleague at leaſt, and therefore deſired they would depute him ſome perſon or other, as they pleas'd themſelves.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He pretended infirmities likewiſe, that <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> might with the more patience expect his ſpeedy ſucceſſi<pb n="176"/>on, or at leaſt, to be made his aſſociate in the Government. The ſeditions being compoſed, he managed his deſigns ſo well, that he circumvented <persName rend="italic">Clemens</persName> and got him into his hands. <persName rend="italic">Libo</persName> (becauſe he would not ſeem ſevere in the beginning of his Empire) he reprehended ſharply in the Senate, but it was two years after his offence, during which time he contented himſelf to have an eye over him, and to ſtand upon his Guard, For as they were ſacrificing one day amongſt the reſt of the Pontifices, he gave order that <persName rend="italic">Libo</persName> ſhould have a leaden knife given him inſtead of his Cleaver, and having deſired to ſpeak with him in private, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> would not admit him but in the preſence of his Son <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, and then whilſt they were walking together he held him by the right hand, as if he were leaning upon him, which poſture he continued to the end of their Diſcourſe.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Being delivered from his fears, he comported himſelf very civilly at firſt, and with more moderation than if it had been a private perſon. Of many and extraordinary honours which were offered him, he accepted but few, and thoſe of the meaneſt ſort. His birth-day falling out in the time of the Plebeian Games exhibited in the Circus, he would not ſuffer to be celebrated with any addition extraordinary, more than a Chariot and two Horſes. He forbad any Temples, or Prieſts or Flamins to be decreed for him, that any Statues ſhould be erected for him but by his own permiſſion, which he granted only upon condition they ſhould not place them among the Images of the Gods, but amongſt the Ornaments of their Houſes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He prohibited likewiſe all ſwearing to the obſervation of his Acts, and that the Month <date rend="italic">September</date> ſhould be called <date rend="italic">Tiberius</date>, or <date rend="italic">October</date>, 
      <pb n="177"/>
      <date rend="italic">Livius</date>. He refus'd alſo the Titles of <foreign rend="italic">Emperour</foreign> or <foreign rend="italic">Father of his Countrey</foreign>, and would not admit the Civick Crown to be ſet up before his Houſe. He never took upon him the name of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> though it was hereditary, but in his Letters to Kings and great Potentates, nor exercis'd the office of Conſul more than three times, the firſt for few days, the ſecond for three months, and the third to the Ides of <date rend="italic">May</date>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      For flattery he had ſo great an averſion, that he never admitted any Senator to make him any Complement, or to diſcourſe with him about any ſerious affair when he was in his Litter. A perſon that had been Conſul humbling himſelf to him upon ſome offence, and endeavouring to throw himſelf at his feet, he avoided him ſo haſtily, he fell down upon his back. If in common converſation, or any ſolemn Oration any thing was ſpoken with more than ordinary Complaiſance, he not only interrupted, but reprehended the ſpeaker. One calling him <foreign rend="italic">Dominus</foreign>, he corrected him immediately, and deſired him not to mention him any more in deriſion; another calling his imployments <foreign rend="italic">ſacred</foreign>, he intreated him to change his Epithete and to name them <foreign rend="italic">Troubleſome</foreign>; and a third having ſaid that he entred into the Senate by his <foreign rend="italic">Authority</foreign>, he commanded him to alter his note, and let it be <foreign rend="italic">perſwaſion</foreign>:
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      All ſlanderous reports, libells, and lampoons, either of him, or his, he endured with ſo much patience, it was his uſual expreſſion, <q rend="italic">In a free City, the thoughts and tongue of every man ought to be free.</q> And when the Senate propos'd to him upon a time to have ſuch offenders examined, he replyed; <q rend="italic">We have not time enough to ingage our ſelves in ſuch trifles. If you open this door once to ſuch informations, there will 
      <pb n="178"/>
      be nothing elſe to be done, under that pretence, every man will revenge himſelf upon his adverſary, by accuſing him to you.</q> Beſides this there is reported a very modeſt expreſſion of his ſpoken in the Senate, upon occaſion of ſome bodies ſpeaking ill of him. <q rend="italic">If ſo be (ſays he) he ſpeaks of me otherwiſe than well, I will give as good an account of my words and actions as I can, and if he perſiſts, I will hate him again.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      In one reſpect theſe libells were the more abominable; becauſe he himſelf was ſo careful in giving every man his proper Title, and reſpect, that he almoſt exceeded the civility of the reſt of mankind. Having diſſented in his opinion from <persName rend="italic">Q. Haterius</persName> in the Senate, <q rend="italic">Pardon me I beſeech you (ſays he) if as a Senator I ſpeak againſt you with more liberty than ordinary</q>, and then turning to the whole Aſſembly, he ſaid, <q rend="italic">Moſt Grave Fathers, what I ſay now, I have ſaid many times before, a good and prudent Prince, to whom you have given ſo great and abſolute a power, ought to be ſerviceable not only to the Senate, and the body of the City, but many times to every particular Citizen: nor do I repent of any thing I have ſaid in this Nature, having taken you alwaies (as I do ſtill) for my good, juſt and moſt gracious Lords.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He introduc'd alſo a certain ſhow, and appearance of liberty, in preſerving both to the Senate and Magiſtrates, their antient Majeſty and Power. Nor was there any thing little or great, either of publick or private importance which he referr'd not to the Senate, All matters of Taxes, Cuſtomes, Monopolies, building or repairing of Houſes, raiſing or disbanding of forces, muſtering of Legions, and Auxiliaries, prolonging, or granting Commiſſions 
      <pb n="179"/>
      upon any extraordinary war, as alſo in what manner and form it was convenient to return an anſwer to the Letters of Kings: An Officer which had the command of a Wing of the Army, being accus'd of violence and extorſion, he conſtrained him to anſwer it before the Senate. He never entred into the Senate, but alone, and when upon occaſion of an indiſpoſition he was brought in once in his Litter, he Commanded all his Company to retire.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      If things were decreed ſometimes againſt his judgment, and advice, he complained not at all: as when he had declared his opinion that a Magiſtrate deſigned, ought not to be abſent, but that his preſence was neceſſary, for the better acceptation, and execution of his honourable office, yet one that was a Prætor deſigned, obtained the favour of Free Embaſſage. Having propos'd another time that a certain ſum of Money left as a Legacy to the <placeName rend="italic">Trebeians</placeName> for the building a new Theatre, might be imploy'd towards the reparation of High-waies, he could not prevail; but the Will of the Teſtator was performed. An Act of the Senate being to be paſt by the plurality of Voices, and he going over to the weakeſt ſide, no man took ſo much notice of his inclination as to follow him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Other matters were managed by their Magiſtrates alſo, and in the ordinary way of Juſtice; the authority of the Conſuls being ſo great, that certain Ambaſſadors from <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName> addreſſed themſelves to them for diſpatch, complaining that they had been delay'd by <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>, to whom they were ſent; and no wonder, for he did not only riſe up to the Conſuls when they came in where he was, but if he met them in the ſtreets, he would turn out of the way himſelf, that they might paſs with more freedome.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
<pb n="180"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He rebuk'd ſuch of the Conſulares as were Generals of Armies, that they gave the Senate no accompt of their proceedings, and that they addreſs'd themſelves to him in the diſtribution of Military Preſents, as if they themſelves had not a right of conferring them as well as he: He commended a Prætor for that upon his entrance upon his charge, he had reviv'd an old Cuſtom of commemorating his Anceſtors in his Harangue. The obſequies of ſome Noblemen he honoured with his company to the very Grave.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      An equal moderation he ſhew'd always both to ſmaller perſons and affairs. The Magiſtrates of <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName> having ſent their publick Letters to him without any ſubſcription, he call'd them before him, and without any ill words or correction, admoniſhed them only to be more careful for the future. A Grammarian called <persName rend="italic">Diogenes</persName>, who was wont to read publickly every Saturday in <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName>, underſtanding that <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> was coming to hear him upon an extraordinary day, he would not ſuffer him to enter, but ſent him word by a Servant, to come ſeven days after; which Grammarian being come to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and ſtanding before his door to ſalute him as he came forth, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> ſaid nothing but, <q rend="italic">You may come ſeven years hence.</q> When the Preſidents, and the Governours of Provinces, advis'd him to lay new Taxes upon them, he ſent them word back again, <q rend="italic">That a Good Shepherds duty was to ſhear, not fley his ſheep.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      By degrees he proceeded to the exerciſe of his Soveraign Authority, and though he were long of an ambiguous character, yet was he moſt commonly inclinable to ſuch things as were for the convenience and advantage of the Publick.
<pb n="181"/>
      At firſt he interpos'd only ſo far, as to ſee that nothing was done irregularly or unjuſtly, in order to which he reſcinded ſeveral Conſtitutions of the Senate. When the Magiſtrates were ſitting in their Courts, he would oftentimes offer himſelf to them as a Counſellor, placing himſelf ſometimes amongſt them, and ſometimes directly before them. If any Criminal was reported to be like to eſcape, by any favour or connivance, he appear'd in the Court unexpected, and either from the Inquiſitors Tribunal above, or out of his Curule Chair below, admoniſh'd them very gravely of the Law, Religion, and the Crimes which were before them; and if any corruption or depravation was crept into the publick manners and cuſtomes of the people, he took the care upon himſelf to ſee them reformed.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He reſtrain'd the immoderate expences in Plays, and Spectacles exhibited to the people, retrenching the Salaries of the Comedians, and reducing the Gladiators to a preciſe number. The prices of <placeName rend="italic">Corinthian</placeName> Veſſels growing extravagant, and the luxury of Entertainments to ſo wilde an exceſs, that 30000 Seſterces were given for three Mullets, he complain'd of it much, and propounded that there might be ſome bounds ſet to the expences of Furniture; and that the prices of Proviſions in the Markets, might be annually regulated at the diſcretion of the Senate; with injunction to the Ædiles, to inhibit all Victualling-houſes and Taverns, the ſelling of any ſort of Junkets whatſoever. And that his own example might encourage other people to be parſimonious and frugal, he had many times at his moſt ſolemn Entertainments, meat brought to him which had been dreſt and cut up the day before, and uſually amongſt other things, half a Boar, affirming, <q rend="italic"><foreign rend="italic">Omnia eadem habere quæ totum</foreign>, That every part had the ſame taſte as the whole.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
<pb n="182"/>
      He put forth a Proclamation, prohibiting the kiſſes which were daily given by way of Salutation, and would not ſuffer the intercourſe of New-years-gifts to hold any longer than the Calends of <date rend="italic">January</date>: He was wont to give four times as much for New-years-gifts, as was given to him, and with his own hand; but being offended that for a whole month together he was diſturb'd by thoſe which could not come near him upon the day of his Entertainment, he never gave more after.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He decreed likewiſe, that (according to the antient cuſtom) the Parents by common conſent ſhould chaſtiſe ſuch married Wives as proſtituted themſelves, and were not publickly accus'd by any body elſe. A <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight having ſworn that he would never put away his Wife, he diſpenc'd with his Oath, and gave him permiſſion to part with her, for having been taken in Adultery with her Son-in-law.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having been inform'd that ſeveral women of ill reputation, had profeſs'd themſelves Bawds, and diveſted themſelves of the rights and priviledges of married women, thereby to evade the penalty of the Laws, and that the moſt looſe and debauch'd young men of both Orders, had voluntarily embrac'd the note of infamy, that with the more impunity they might mingle themſelves with the Comedians and Gladiators, he baniſh'd them all, that they might have no refuge and evaſion in thoſe frauds, as they deſign'd. He took away the Purple Robe from a Senator, who had quitted his Lodgings, and removed into the Gardens before the Calends of <date rend="italic">July</date>, that when the ſaid day was paſt, he might hire another at the cheaper rate; 
<pb n="183"/>
      and he diſcharg'd a Quæſtor of his Office, for having married a woman the day before his Election, and diſmiſt her the next day.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He ſtopt the courſe of Foreign Ceremonies, as alſo the <placeName rend="italic">Egyptian</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Jewiſh</placeName> Rites, compelling all ſuch as inclin'd to thoſe Superſtitions, to burn the Veſtments and Furniture belonging to their Religion. He liſted the <placeName rend="italic">Jewiſh</placeName> Youth, and under pretence of a Military Oath, he ſent them into the moſt peſtilent and unwholeſome Provinces under his Command, obliging the remainder of that Nation, and ſuch as follow'd their footſteps, to depart the City upon pain of perpetual ſervitude. His reſolution was to have done as much to the Aſtrologers, but upon their humble deprecations, and their promiſes of quitting that profeſſion for the future, they were continued.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      The thing he had moſt in his eye was, the preſervation of the Peace, and the protection of the Countrey from Robberies and Seditions. He plac'd Guards all through <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, and in more places than was formerly uſed: He commanded a Camp to be pitch'd in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, for his Prætorian Bands, which before that were quarter'd up and down in the Inns of the Town.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Such popular tumults as were begun, he corrected ſeverely; ſuch as were immature, and as yet only in deſign, he prevented as carefully. A murder being committed at a Play, he baniſh'd the Authors, and the Comedians, (the occaſion of the quarrel) nor could ever be brought to recall them, by all the prayers and ſollicitations of the people.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The Inhabitants of <placeName rend="italic">Pollentia</placeName> not ſuffering the body of an Officer of the Army to be buried, nor ſtirr'd out of the Market-place, till they had extorted a ſum of money from his Heirs for the ſpectacle of the Gladiators;
<pb n="184"/>
      to chaſtiſe their inſolence, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> commanded two Cohorts to march thither, one out of the City, the other out of the Kingdom of <placeName rend="italic">Cotius</placeName>, with orders to conceal their deſign, and not diſcover their Armes till they were come to the Town; not being ſtrictly enough obſerv'd, they entred by the ſeveral Gates with their Trumpets ſounding before them, poſſeſs'd themſelves of the place, and caſt moſt of the people and Magiſtrates into perpetual impriſonment. He aboliſh'd the priviledges of Sanctuaries whereſoever they were. The <placeName rend="italic">Cyziceni</placeName> having committed ſome violences upon the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Citizens, he deprived them of the freedom which they had obtain'd in the War againſt <persName rend="italic">Mithridates</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      After this time he never undertook any Expedition himſelf; if there happen'd any Commotion, he ſuppreſs'd it by his Lieutenants, and not then neither, but with delays, and upon neceſſity. When any Kings were ſuſpected of ill affection to the Republick, his way of repreſſing them was rather by complaint and commination, than force; ſome of which he allured to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> by his fair words, and large promiſes, but kept them there when he had them, as <persName rend="italic">Maraboduus</persName> the <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName>, <persName rend="italic">Thraſcypolis</persName> a <placeName rend="italic">Thracian</placeName>, and <persName rend="italic">Archelaus</persName> a <placeName rend="italic">Cappadocian</placeName>, whoſe Kingdom alſo he reduc'd into the form of a Province.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      For two years together after he was arrived at the Empire, he never ſet foot out of the Gates of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>: afterwards he went but to the Towns adjacent, and when furtheſt, but to <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName>, and that very ſeldom, and for a few dayes only;
<pb n="185"/>
      though he had often declared, he would viſit his Provinces and Armies abroad, and prepared almoſt every year for his journey, buying his Waggons, laying in his Proviſions in all municipal Towns and Colonies, and proceeding ſo far as to let the people make their ſolemn prayers for his happy journey and return; in ſo much as he was called generally <persName rend="italic">Callippedes</persName>, who according to the <placeName rend="italic">Greek</placeName> Proverb was one <q rend="italic">That was alwayes running, yet never advanc'd.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      But his two Sons being dead, <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> in <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, and <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he retired into <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, leaving the people in an univerſal opinion, that he would neither come back again thither, nor live long where he was; and they miſs'd but little of being in the right in both, for as he never return'd to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, ſo he eſcap'd death very narrowly, when but a few dayes after his departure, being at Supper in one of his Summer Houſes called <placeName rend="italic">Spelunca</placeName>, not far from <placeName rend="italic">Terracina</placeName>, ſeveral great Stones fell down ſuddenly from the roof, and kill'd the moſt part both of the Servants and Gueſts, without any hurt to him at all.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      When he had travell'd through <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, and dedicated the Capitol at <placeName rend="italic">Capua</placeName>, and the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> at <placeName rend="italic">Nola</placeName>, which he pretended was the cauſe of his journey, he withdrew himſelf into <placeName rend="italic">Capreæ</placeName>, taking much delight in that Iſland, becauſe there was but one (and that a ſmall) acceſs, the reſt being as it were hedg'd about with vaſt and prodigious Rocks, and a profound and almoſt bottomleſs Sea. But he had not been long there, before he was importunately ſollicited by the people to return, in reſpect of a ſad accident happen'd lately at <placeName rend="italic">Fidenæ</placeName>, where by the fall of an Amphitheatre at one of the Spectacles of the Gladiators, 20000 men periſh'd;
<pb n="186"/>
      upon which he paſs'd over to the Continent again, permitting all people to come to him, and that the rather, becauſe when he went out of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he forbad any body to interrupt him, and all the way he went he declin'd all communication.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Being returned again into the Iſland, he gave over all care or concern for the Commonwealth, not ſo much as filling up the Decuries of Horſe, not ſo much as changing the Military Tribunes, the Governours, or Preſidents of his Provinces. <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName> he ſuffer'd to be ſeveral years without Conſulary Lieutenants; and which was worſe, he neglected <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName>, and permitted it to be overrun by the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName>; <placeName rend="italic">Mæſia</placeName>, by the <placeName rend="italic">Daci</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Sarmatians</placeName>; and <placeName rend="italic">Gaule</placeName>, by the <placeName rend="italic">Germans</placeName>, to the great diſhonour, and no leſs danger of the Empire.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      To proceed, having now got the advantage of a private place, removed as it were out of the ſight of the World, he began to abandon himſelf to all thoſe vices, which with great diſſimulation he had till then palliated; the particulars follow. When he came firſt into the Field, in the minority of his Souldierſhip, he was ſo much given over to drinking, that inſtead of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, he was called <persName rend="italic">Biberius</persName>; for <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Caldius</persName>; for <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Mero</persName>. Afterwards when he was Emperour, at the very time whilſt he was reforming the manners of the people, he ſate up one night and two dayes, eating and drinking with <persName rend="italic">Pomponius Flaccus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">L. Piſo</persName>, to one of which he gave the Province of <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName> immediately, and to the other the Government of the City, ſtiling them in his Letters, <q rend="italic"><foreign rend="italic">Jucundiſſimos, &amp; omnium horarum amicos</foreign>, His Bon-compagnons, and friends for all hours.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
<pb n="187"/>
      <persName rend="italic">Seſtius Gallus</persName>, an old Debauch, who had been noted with infamy by <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> before, and ſmartly reprehended by himſelf in the Senate, inviting him to ſupper, he promis'd to come to him upon Condition that he altered nothing of his old way, and that they might be ſerved at the Table, by naked Virgins. He preferr'd a moſt ignoble Competitor for the Quæſtorſhip, of mean extraction, before ſeveral perſons of honour and quality, and for no other reaſon, but becauſe he had drank with him an incredible quantity of Wine at one Meal. He gave <persName rend="italic">Aſſellius Sabinus</persName> 200000 Seſterces for a Dialogue of his making, in which he repreſented a Combat or Conteſt betwixt the Muſhrome, the Ficedula or Beccafico, the Oyſter, and the Thruſh. To conclude, he erected a new Office for his pleaſures, which he called <foreign rend="italic">a voluptatibus</foreign>, and conferr'd it upon <persName rend="italic">T. Cæſonius Priſcus</persName> one of the Knights of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      During his retirement in <placeName rend="italic">Capreæ</placeName> he invented ſeats, and rooms for the more convenient exerciſe of his Luſt, and having furniſh'd them with wenches, old Catamites and contrivers of abominable motions, and poſtures in their Loves, (which perſons he called <foreign rend="italic">Spintriæ</foreign>) he took delight to ſee them in three ſeveral rows abuſe and pollute one another, that by that proſpect, his own languiſhing deſires might be revived, and he thereby excited to their imitation.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Moreover he had many Chambers plentifully furniſhed with Pictures and Statues, of the moſt laſcivious ſhapes, to which he added the books of <persName rend="italic">Elephantis</persName>, with the moſt immodeſt and impudent poſtures in the world, to the end that when any one had a mind to practiſe, he might not want a ſcheme or pattern to work by. He found out new places likewiſe in the woods, which he improved with great induſtry, and made proper for his Luſts, when the young people of both ſexes proſtituted themſelves 
<pb n="188"/>
      in the dens, and hollow Rocks, in the habits of Panicks, and Nymphs; In ſo much that in alluſion to the Iſland, he was called publickly <persName rend="italic">Caprineus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="44">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      And, as if by his ſtation, his wickedneſs was to have been greater than his ſubjects, there are things ſo deteſtably infamous reported of him, as are ſcarce to be told, heard or believed of any one, <foreign rend="italic">Viz.</foreign> That he ſhould inſtitute Children, in the prime of their tenderneſs (whom he called his fiſhes) and teach them to ſwim up and down, and play betwixt his legs, with their tongues and teeth, licking and chopping, and ſometimes ſucking like a Child not taken from the pap; and indeed both his Nature and age inclined him more violently to this kind of abomination.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Wherefore a Picture of <persName rend="italic">Parrhaſius</persName> work, in which <persName rend="italic">Atlanta</persName> was repreſented proffering her Mouth to <persName rend="italic">Meleager</persName> in that manner, being left to him as a Legacy, upon condition that if he liked not the deſign, he ſhould have a million of Seſterces paid him in its ſtead, he not only preferr'd it to the ſaid ſum, but with much ſatisfaction caus'd it to be hung up in his Chamber. It is reported alſo that as he was ſacrificing one time, he was ſo taken with the face of a boy which carried the Cenſer, he had much ado to contain till the ſolemnity was over, but that was no ſooner ended, but he took him aſide and deflowred him, and after him a Brother of his belonging to the Muſick. And having been inform'd that amongſt themſelves they did frequently reflect and upbraid one another with that impiety, he cauſed the thighs of both of them to be broken.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="45">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      How he was wont to abuſe even the moſt eminent and illuſtrious Ladies of thoſe times, and make them moſt infamouſly ſubſervient to his plea<pb n="189"/>ſures, is evident in the ſtory of <persName rend="italic">Mallonia</persName>; who being brought to him, and refuſing to Comply with his moſt unnatural humour, he ſuborn'd Witneſſes againſt her, and caus'd her to be accus'd, interrogating her ſtill as ſhe appear'd in Court, <q rend="italic">If ſhe did not repent her ſelf?</q> till at length, abominating his impudence, ſhe flung out of his preſence in a fury, went home, and ſtab'd her ſelf, after ſhe had upbraided the rammiſh old Fornicator with the obſcenity of his Mouth. Whereupon in a Play which was acted not long after, there was an expreſſion that took very well, and went up and down the Town; which was this, <q rend="italic">That the old He Goats lick'd the Nature of the She Goats.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="46">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      46. He was ſo covetous and tenacious of his Money, he never allowed any thing but diet, to ſuch as accompanied him in his Travels, and Military Expeditions. Yet once he was ſo liberal, I muſt confeſs, (but it was out of his Father-in-Laws bounty) That having divided them into three Ranks or Orders, according to their ſeveral qualities, he diſtributed to the firſt, 600000 Seſterces, to the ſecond 400000, to the third 200000, which laſt he called in contempt, <q rend="italic">the Order of his <placeName rend="italic">Greeks</placeName>, not of his Friends.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="47">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      47. All the while he was Emperour, he built nothing that was great or Magnificent. The Temple of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and the reparation of <persName rend="italic">Pompey's</persName> Theatre, which were the only things he ever undertook, he left both unfiniſhed after ſo many years. He exhibited no ſhows to the people himſelf, and was preſent but ſeldom at thoſe which other people made, for fear leſt any thing ſhould be demanded or expected from him, eſpecially after he had been conſtrained to infranchiſe <pb n="190"/> <persName rend="italic">Actius</persName> the Comedian. Having relieved the neceſſities of ſome few Senators, leſt others ſhould expect as much, he declared he would aſſiſt no more for the future, till they ſhould make their neceſſities appear to the Senate, by which ſtratagem he prevented the ſollicitations of all ſuch as had any ſhame or modeſty to deterre them: and among the reſt, of <persName rend="italic">Hortalus</persName> the Nephew of <persName rend="italic">Q. Hortenſius</persName> the Orator, who though his eſtate was ſmall, upon the incouragement of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, had brought up four Children.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="48">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      48. As concerning his publick Munificence, he never made the leaſt expreſſion of it but twice; the firſt time when he proffer'd to lend a hundred millions of Seſterces <foreign rend="italic">gratis</foreign>, for three years: The other, when upon the burning of ſeveral Houſes upon Mount <placeName rend="italic">Cælius</placeName>, he made them good to the Proprietors; The firſt of theſe he was compell'd to, by reaſon of the extream ſcarcity of Money, and the peoples importunity for ſupplies; and he had put the Senate upon the publiſhing a Decree, Commanding all Uſurers to lay out two parts of their Patrimonies in Land, and that the Debtors ſhould pay off as much of their Debts immediately; but this was not executed: The other (of the reprizal) he did to alleviate the atrocity of the times, yet with ſo much affectation of his own liberality that he order'd the name of Mount <placeName rend="italic">Cælius</placeName> to be chang'd, and to be called Mount <placeName rend="italic">Auguſtus</placeName> for the future.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After he had doubled the Legacies of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, which he gave unto the Souldiers, he never gave them any thing more, unleſs it were a thouſand deniers, amongſt his Guards, becauſe they had not ſided with <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>, and ſome certain preſents to the Legions in <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, for that they had not carried the Image of <pb n="191"/> <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName> in their Colours, as others had done. Nor did he diſcharge his old Veterans but very rarely, as lying at catch to make his advantage of their deaths. The Provinces had no greater ſhare of his liberality (except it were <placeName rend="italic">Aſia</placeName>) where ſome certain Towns had been demoliſh'd with an Earth-quake.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="49">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      49. In proceſs of time, he gave himſelf up to all manner of rapine, and extortion. It is well known that <persName rend="italic">Cn. Lentulus</persName> the Augur, who was a man of a vaſt Eſtate, was perſecuted by him to the death, and ſo terrified, that he made him his Heir; He condemned likewiſe <persName rend="italic">Lepida</persName> a Lady of quality, in favour of her Husband <persName rend="italic">Quirinus</persName> a Conſular man, very rich, and without Children, who having put her away before, accus'd her of a deſign to have poiſoned him twenty years ago;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Beſides this, ſeveral Princes of <placeName rend="italic">Gaul</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Greece</placeName>, and other parts were confiſcated upon ſo ſlight and inconſiderable informations, That againſt ſome of them nothing was objected but that part of their Eſtate was in ready Money. He took away alſo from ſeveral Towns and particular perſons, their old immunities, and priviledges, as likewiſe their rights in metals, and impoſts. But one of his greateſt injuries, was done to <persName rend="italic">Venones</persName> the King of the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName>, who being driven by force from amongſt his own people, had eſcap'd to <placeName rend="italic">Antioch</placeName> with great Wealth, where he continued for ſome time as he he thought under the protection of the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, contrary to all juſtice and faith, he was not only pillaged by his Order, but moſt treacherouſly ſlain.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="50">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      50. His averſion to his Kindred, he diſcover'd firſt in his carriage towards his Brother <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, by diſcovering a Letter of his written to himſelf, about Compelling <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> to reſtore the Common liberty. <pb n="192"/> And the ſame kindneſs he ſhew'd to the reſt; His wife <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> was baniſh'd, yet he was ſo far from doing her the leaſt good office to her Father, that whereas by her Fathers Order ſhe ſtood confined but to a Town, by his command ſhe was reſtrained to a ſingle Houſe, and forbidden all manner of converſe. He took away from her alſo that little which <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> had given her, and ſtopt her annual Penſions, pretending a juſt and exact obſervation of the Laws, becauſe <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> had not given any preciſe directions in that caſe.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being weary of <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> his Mother, as challenging an equal ſhare with him in the Government, he avoided her converſation as much as he could, and never entertain'd any long or private diſcourſe with her, (leſt he ſhould ſeem to be governed by her Counſels ;) when he did, it was but very rarely, and with ſome kind of conſtraint. He took it extreme ill, that the Senate had ordained by decree, That whereas he was called only the Son of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> before, he ſhould be called the Son of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> in his Titles hereafter.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Upon this ſcore it was he never ſuffer'd her to be called the Mother of her Countrey, nor to receive any remarkable honour in publick; admoniſhing her often, to have a care of medling in great affairs, and ſuch as were above the ſphear of a Woman: but more eſpecially when he heard, that when there happen'd a Fire near the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Veſta</persName>, ſhe her ſelf ran immediately among the people, encouraging and exhorting both them and the Souldiers, as ſhe was us'd to do in the dayes of her Husband.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="51">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      51. By theſe ſteps and gradations, he arrived at laſt at that perfection of wickedneſs, as to hate and deteſt her, and if we may believe report, upon this occaſion: <pb n="193"/> <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> having preſs'd him very earneſtly, to advance a perſon (which he had made a Citizen before) into the number of the Decuries, he refus'd abſolutely to do it, unleſs ſhe would permit it to be annex'd to the Roll, That it was extorted from him by his Mother: with which propoſition being highly diſpleas'd, ſhe immediately produc'd certain Letters which <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> had writ formerly to her, complaining of the contumacy and intolerable perverſeneſs of his manners, and caus'd them to be publickly read. Theſe Letters having been conceal'd ſo long by her, and produc'd ſo maliciouſly to upbraid him at that time, he took ſo hainouſly, that ſome are of opinion, it was one of the principal cauſes of his retirement.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But this is certain, that during his three years abſence from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, all which time his Mother was living, he never ſaw her but once, and then but a very ſhort time: And afterwards when ſhe was ſick; and upon her death-bed, he had no deſire to come near her, but delay'd the time ſo long, that ſhe not only dyed before he came, but they kept the body ſeveral dayes unburied, in continual expectation of him; till it putrified, and ſmelt. After ſhe was interred, he forbad that ſhe ſhould be Canonized, or receive thoſe Divine honours were uſually conferr'd, pretending her expreſs command to the contrary. He vacated her Will alſo, and perſecuted and afflicted her Friends and Familiars, not excuſing thoſe very perſons to whom ſhe had committed the care of her Funerals, at the very inſtant of her death, one of which being a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight, he condemned to the Bucket.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="52">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      52. He had no Fatherly affection, either for <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> his natural, or <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> his adopted Son. <pb n="194"/> The vices of <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> (as he pretended) offended him, for he was ſoft, and voluptuous; For which cauſe he was not much concern'd at his death; nor was it long after his Funeral, before he reaſſum'd his uſual imployments, prohibiting the vacation of Juſtice any longer upon that occaſion.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The Embaſſadors from <placeName rend="italic">Ilium</placeName> coming ſomething too late with their Complements of Condolency, as if the memory of his loſs had been already effac'd, he reply'd in deriſion, at their Audience, <q rend="italic">That he alſo could not but lament their misfortune, in having loſt ſo brave and eminent a Citizen as <persName rend="italic">Hector</persName>.</q> As for <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, he was ſo croſs and averſe to him in every thing, that he not only leſſen'd and vilify'd his moſt Noble Atchievements, but condemn'd the moſt glorious of his Victories, as pernicious and deſtructive to the Commonwealth. He made his complaint to the Senate of him likewiſe, for that upon a ſudden and violent Famine, he had paſs'd into <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName> without his order.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      It is believ'd alſo, that he was the cauſe of his death, and <persName rend="italic">C. Piſo</persName> his Lieutenant in <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, the Inſtrument; who being accus'd of it not long after, would as ſome think have produc'd the Commands of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, had not the importance, and ſecrecy of the tranſaction diſcourag'd him. Theſe ſorts of ſuſpicions rendred him ſo odious to the people, that he was oftentimes upbraided by them, and all night long they would frequently cry out, <foreign rend="italic">Redde Germanicum</foreign>, <q rend="italic">Give us our <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> again:</q> which jealouſie was much confirm'd afterwards, by the cruelty of his deportment towards the Wife and Children of the ſaid <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="53">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      53. <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> his Daughter-in-law, having (upon the death of her Husband) diſcours'd of <pb n="195"/> him with more than ordinary liberty, he took her by the hand, and telling her in a <placeName rend="italic">Greek</placeName> verſe, <q rend="italic">If you be not Empreſs, fair Lady, you think you are injured,</q> he let her go again, without vouchſafing her any further diſcourſe. Being at his Table one time, and ſhe refuſing to eat of certain Fruit which he gave her, he forbare inviting her for the future, pretending that ſhe ſuſpected he would poyſon her; when as indeed it was plotted and deſigned before hand on both ſides, both that he ſhould preſent it to her to try her, and ſhe refuſe it as her inevitable death.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      At length having aſpers'd her unjuſtly, as if ſhe would fly ſometimes for Sanctuary to the Statue of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and otherwhiles betake her ſelf to the protection of the Army, he ſent her Priſoner to the Iſle of <placeName rend="italic">Pandataria</placeName>; and in the height of her paſſion and reſentment, not being able to contain from giving him ill language, he order'd ſo many blows to be given her by a Centurion, that at laſt one of her eyes were ſtruck out: After which ſhe having taken a reſolution to ſtarve her ſelf to death, he made her mouth be open'd, and meat cramm'd down her throat by force. Nevertheleſs perſiſting in her deſign, ſhe put an end to her life and misfortunes, but not to the malice and cruelty of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, who reviled and perſecuted her even after her death, perſwading very earneſtly, that the day of her birth might be numbred amongſt the unfortunate dayes. Beſides this, he cry'd it up as an act of his favour and grace, that he had not commanded her to be ſtrangled before, and her body thrown to the Fowls of the air; and in memory of ſo ſignal a piece of clemency, he ſuffer'd a decree to paſs, that publick thanks ſhould be given him therefore, and a Preſent of Gold conſecrated to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
<pb n="196"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="54">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      54. Theſe two Sons being dead, there remained to him by <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> three Grandchildren, <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, and another called <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> by his Son <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>: The two eldeſt Sons of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, he recommended to the Senate, and celebrated the day of their introduction with a large Preſent to the people; but underſtanding afterwards that there were publick Vows made at the beginning of the year for their health and preſervation, he remonſtrated to the Senate, <q rend="italic">That ſuch Honours were not to be conferr'd, but upon perſons of greater years and experience.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After which, diſcovering the ſecret and internal malice of his heart, he expos'd them to the calumnies and reproaches of the World, by variety of artifice and fraud, inciting them to ill language, that under that pretended provocation, he might have occaſion to deſtroy them. He accuſed them alſo by his Letters, full of injurious invectives, and having declared them enemies to the State, he ſtarv'd them to death, <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> in the Iſle of <placeName rend="italic">Pontia</placeName>, and <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> in the lower part of the <placeName rend="italic">Palatium</placeName>. Some are of opinion <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> ſtarv'd himſelf, to defeat the Executioner, who preſented himſelf before him with his halter and hooks, as if ſent by authority of the Senate: But <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> was in ſuch exigence and diſtreſs, he attempted to eat the very flocks of his Bed, for want of other ſuſtenance, ſo inhumane was their diligence in keeping all kind of victuals from him; and as if this cruelty were defective, he caus'd their dead bodies to be diſmembred, and diſpers'd in ſuch ſmall pieces, it was no eaſie matter afterwards to recollect them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="55">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      55. Beſides his old friends and familiars, he had demanded twenty, out of the principal perſons of <pb n="197"/> the City, to be as a Council to him in his publick affairs: but of ſo great a number, there were not above three which eſcap'd, the reſt he deſtroy'd upon one pretence or another; among whom, with the ruine of ſeveral others, was <persName rend="italic">Ælius Sejanus</persName>, whom he had advanc'd to a Soveraign Dignity, not out of any affection or good will, ſo much as that he might have a man by whoſe Miniſtry and frauds he ſhould be able to circumvent <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> his Sons, and aſſure the ſucceſſion of the Empire upon his Grandchild by <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, which was his natural Son.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="56">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      56. Nor was his behaviour milder to the <placeName rend="italic">Grecian</placeName> Philoſophers, who convers'd daily in his Court, with whom he was moſt taken: One of them called <persName rend="italic">Zeno</persName>, diſcourſing very exquiſitely in his preſence, he ask'd him, What hard Dialect that was; and being anſwer'd, The <foreign rend="italic">Dorick</foreign>, he baniſh'd him into the Iſle of <placeName rend="italic">Cinaria</placeName>, imagining he had Satyrically reflected upon his antient receſs at <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName>, becauſe the <placeName rend="italic">Rhodians</placeName> ſpake that Dialect. In like manner being accuſtomed at Supper to propoſe ſuch queſtions as he thought good, out of his readings in the day, and underſtanding that <persName rend="italic">Seleucus</persName> the Grammarian had been fiſhing out of his Servants, what times and what Authors he read, that he might come the better prepared with his anſwers; <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> took it ſo hainouſly, he baniſh'd him out of the Verge of his Court, and drove him afterwards to a neceſſity of killing himſelf.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="57">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      57. From his Infancy he gave manifeſt tokens of his untractableneſs and cruelty, which <persName rend="italic">Theodorus Gadareus</persName>, his Maſter in Rhetorick, was the firſt that diſcovered, and as aptly reſembled, when by way of reprehenſion, he many times called him, <pb n="198"/> <q rend="italic">A maſs of Clay temper'd with blood.</q> When he was Emperour it appear'd much more, and that at the beginning, even whilſt he endeavoured to gain the good will of the people by a diſſembled moderation.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      A certain Droll or Buffon ſeeing a Corps paſſing by to burial about that time, he ſtopt the Hearſe, and lifting up the dead body, deſired him to tell <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, <q rend="italic">That the Legacies were not yet paid which he left to the people.</q> Whereupon <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> commanded him to be brought to him, and having paid him his full due, he caus'd him to be executed immediately, and required him to tell the truth of the ſtory to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> himſelf. Not long after a certain <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight called <persName rend="italic">Pompeius</persName> obſtinately denying ſomthing in the Senate which <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> deſired might have paſſed, he threatned to lay him by the heels, and told him, of a <persName rend="italic">Pompeius</persName> he would make him a <persName rend="italic">Pompeianus</persName>, playing moſt bitterly upon the mans name, and the misfortune of <persName rend="italic">Pompey's</persName> Party.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="58">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      58. About the ſame time the Prætor having ask'd him, whether he would be pleaſed to have the Judges aſſembled to hear and determine matters of High Treaſon, He reply'd, <q rend="italic">The Laws muſt have their courſe,</q> and he was as good as his word, for after that time they were executed ſeverely. A certain perſon having taken the head from the Statue of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, with deſign to ſet it upon another, the matter was brought before the Senate, becauſe it was not clear who was the Author; they proceeded to inquiſition by torture, and the party was diſcovered and condemned. By degrees this kind of Calumny became ſo dangerous, that it was judged a Capital Crime to have beaten a ſlave about the Image of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> to have chang'd his Clothes before the ſaid Image, to have carried his picture or impreſſion into any in<pb n="199"/>famous place, either in Money or upon a Ring; and laſtly to have offended againſt his Memory, by ſpeaking ill of the leaſt word or action of his life: To conclude, a perſon was executed for ſuffering in his own Colony, honours to be decreed to himſelf on the ſame day upon which they had been decreed formerly to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="59">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      59. Many other Barbarities he committed alſo, under pretence of gravity, and reformation of manners, but indeed in compliance with his own mercileſs inclination, which was ſo frequently ſevere, there were ſome perſons could not contain from reproaching him in verſe with the preſent calamities, and preſaging the miſeries he was like to pull down upon them for the future. The Verſes were theſe.
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">
        Aſper &amp; immitis, breviter vis omnia dicam ?<lb/>
        Diſperiam ſi te mater amare poteſt.<lb/>
        Non es eques. Quare ? non ſunt tibi millia centum<lb/>
        Omnia ſi quæras, Rhodus exſilium eſt.<lb/>
        Aurea mutaſti Saturni ſecula, Cæſar :<lb/>
        Incolumi nam te, ferrea ſemper erunt.<lb/>
        Faſtidit vinum, quia jam ſitit ipſe cruorem :<lb/>
        Tam bibit hunc avide, quam bibit ante merum.
      </q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">
        Adſpice felicem ſibi non tibi Romule Syllam :<lb/>
        Et Marium, ſi vis, adſpice, ſed reducem.<lb/>
        Nec non Antoni civilia bella moventis,<lb/>
        Nec ſemel infectas adſpice cæde manus.<lb/>
        Et dic Roma perit: regnabit ſanguine multo,<lb/>
        Ad regnum quisquis venit ab exſilio.
      </q>
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">
        Harſh and unkind, in one word to correct thee;<lb/>
        Ne're live, if thy own Mother can affect thee.<lb/>
        No Knight: and why? a Knight's Fee thou haſt none<lb/>
        And Rhodes thy Exile is, when all is done.
      </q>
    </p>
    <pb n="200"/>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">
        Cæſar, thou'ſt Saturn's Golden Days embas't<lb/>
        For whilſt thou liv'ſt the Iron Age will laſt.<lb/>
        Now Wine he ſcorns, doth for Blood only thirſt:<lb/>
        Drinks that as Greedily, as Wine at firſt.
      </q>
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">
        See Sulla th' Happy for Himſelf, not Thee!<lb/>
        And Marius, but return'd: good Romulus ſee!<lb/>
        And Anthony, who th' Civil Wars renew'd!<lb/>
        See Hands in frequent Maſſacres embrew'd!<lb/>
        Then ring Romes Knell. Great Blood-ſhed he portends,<lb/>
        Who to a Throne from Baniſhment aſcends.
      </q>
    </p>
    <p>
      At firſt he would have theſe verſes father'd upon ſuch as were impatient of the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Dominion, and that they expreſs'd more of their paſſion and malevolence, than of true ſentiment and opinion, in ſo much that he would often ſay, <q rend="italic">Oderint dum probent, Let them hate, as long as they Submit</q>: But at laſt his own actions verified them all.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="60">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      60. Not long after his arrival at <placeName rend="italic">Capreæ</placeName>, a fiſherman brought him a Mullet or Barbel, of an extraordinary bigneſs, which was intended as a preſent, but in regard the Fiſherman came in boldly on a ſudden, and ſurpriz'd him in ſome ſecret affair, he caus'd his face to be rubb'd over with the ſaid fiſh, (terrified with the conſideration, that from the back part of the Iſland through unfrequented and inacceſſible places, he had made his paſſage to him.) Moreover the poor man rejoycing during his puniſhment, that he had not brought a large Lobſter along with him, which he had taken at the ſame time, he Commanded his face to be batter'd and ſcrub'd with a Lobſter alſo. One of his Guards he puniſh't with death, for having ſtollen a Peacock out of an Orchard. In a certain journey he had taken, his Litter being intangled and retarded in the Buſhes, he caus'd <pb n="201"/> his Guide which was a Captain in his principal Guards, to be laid along upon the Ground, and beaten till he was almoſt dead.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="201"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="61">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      61. After this he brake out into all fort of cruelty, as never wanting matter to work upon; perſecuting in the firſt place the friends of his Mother, then of his Grand-children, and Daughter-in-law, and afterwards of <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>, and that with ſo much ſeverity, he ſpared very few which had but the leaft converfation or acquaintance with him: Then it was the World began to underſtand the extravagance of his cruelty, and that <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName> did not move or excite him to fuch actions, as had been executed by <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName> before; yet in a Compendious Commentary of his own life, he had the Confidence to write, <q rend="italic">That he had punish'd <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName> for nothing but his rage and animosity against the Children of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> his Son</q>, Though he himself caus'd one of them to be killed, whilst <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName> was under a Cloud, and the other after he was dead.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      To enumerate all his actions of this Nature, would be tedious and troublesome; ſome few Examples in General will be fufficient. There paſt not a day (either feſtival, or religious) without fome execution or other; He began the New-Year with the punishment of fome perfons: feveral were accused and condemned the fame day, with their wives and children: He forbad the Kinsfolk and Relations of fuch as were fentenc'd to dye, to weep or lament at their Execution; He order'd large rewards to the Informers, and ſometimes to Witneſſes themselves: He made it no dishonour or treachery in any perſon to discover;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      and brought all Crimes to be Capital, though but the ſpeaking of a few idle words. It was objected againſt a Poet, that he had fpoken ill of <persName rend="italic">Agamemnon</persName> in one of his <pb n="202"/> Tragedies, and to an Hiſtorian that he had called <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Caſſius</persName> the last of the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName> : upon which the Authors were immediately puniſh'd and their books burnt, though not many years before they had been read to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and received his approbation.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Some perſons committed to cuſtody, were denyed not only the diverſion of ſtudying, but the liberty of discourſing with any body. Such as were Cited into the Court to answer what should be objected, to avoid the vexation and infamy of their Sentence, which they knew would be Mortal, fome of them kill'd themſelves in their own houſes, others drank poyſon in the mid'ſt of the Senate, yet that could not excuſe them, their wounds were bound up, and they carried away panting and half dead into prifon. There was none of all thoſe which fuffer'd, but was drawn thither with hooks, and thrown into the <placeName rend="italic">Gemonie</placeName>, as twenty in one day, and among them ſeveral boys and women;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      And for as much as it was unlawful according to antient Cuſtome for Virgins to be ſtrangled, he caus'd them to be deflowr'd firſt by the Hang-man, and executed afterwards. To fuch as were willing to die, he ufed violence, and conſtrained them to live; For he look'd upon death, as fo flight a puniſhnent, that when he heard one of his prifoners call'd <persName rend="italic">Carnulius</persName>, had made away himself, and anticipated his execution, he cry'd out intheſe words, <q rend="italic"><persName rend="italic">Carnulius</persName> bas escap'd me</q>: and afterwards as he was viſiting and furveying his priſons, one of the prisoners begging to have his execution haſten'd, <q rend="italic">No Sir,</q> (Said he) <q rend="italic">You and I are not yet so good friends.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      A certain Conſular man writing his Annales, has inferted this paſſage, That <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> being at a publick entertainment (at which he himself was preſent alſo) <pb n="203"/> was on a fudden interrogated boldly by a Dwarf which was ſtanding by the Table amongst the Paraſites, and Buffons, <q rend="italic">Why <persName rend="italic">Paconius</persName> lived ſo long, being attainted of treason?</q> at preſent he reprehended the faucineſs of the queſtion, but in a ſhort time afterwards, he writ to the Senate to take Order with all fpeed for the Execution of <persName rend="italic">Paconius</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="62">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      62. The News, and regret he had for the death of his Son <persName rend="italic">Drufus</persName>, redoubled his rage, and made his cruelty more intenſe: for having believed formerly he died by his own diſſoluteneſs and intemperance, when he understood he was poisoned by the Confpiracy of his Wife <persName rend="italic">Livilla</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>; he was fo far tranſported, that he ſpared no body, but gave himself wholly to the examination of that buſineſs, he fate at it whole days together fo ferioufly, that when word was brought him that an inhabitant of <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName> (at whoſe house he had lodg'd, and whom by many kind Letters he had invited to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>) was arrived, he commanded him to be tortured immediately, as if (as a friend to the Confpirators) he had been attending at the Tryal, and afterwards underſtanding his error, he commanded him to be killed privately, left he ſnould divulge the injury he had received.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The place of his Executions at <placeName rend="italic">Caprea</placeName>, is ſtill to be ſeen, from whence fuch as were condemned, after long and intolerable torments, were in his prefence thrown headlong into the Sea, where a certain number of Seamen were difpofed beforehand with their Oars, and long Poles to knock them on the head. Amongst the reſt of the Torments which he invented, one of the moſt cruel was, to make perfons ſuſpecting nothing, drink down a large quantity of Wine, and forthwith to command their privities to be tied up faſt with a <pb n="204"/> Lute-ſtring, thereby doubling their pains by the ſtoppage of their Urine, and the ſtraitneſs of the Ligature.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Some are of opinion, that if death had not prevented him, and <persName rend="italic">Thrafyllus</persName> (pretending hopes of recovery on purpoſe) perſwaded him to fome delay, his barbarity had gone farther ſtill, and as is too probable he had scarce excuſed the rest of his Grand-Children, for he had a fufpicion of <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> already, and he deſpiſed <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> as a Bastard. And indeed it is too likely to be true, for he was often heard to fay, <q rend="italic">That <persName rend="italic">Priamus</persName> was a happy man, in that he outlived his whole race.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="63">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      63. Not only how odious and deteſtable theſe actions made him, but how timerous, and obnoxious to affronts, there are many inſtances. He forbad that any Southſayers ſhould be confulted in private, without witneſſes. He endeavoured likewise to demoliſh and fubvert fuch Oracles as were near the Town: But he was deterred by the miraculous accident at <placeName rend="italic">Præneste</placeName> for having removed the Lots to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, ſeal'd up in a Coffer, when he open'd it there was nothing to be found, till it was carried back again to the Temple.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having conferr'd the Government of two Provinces, on two perſons which had been Confuls, he was afraid to diſmiſs them, but detain'd them ſo long, that at laſt after ſome years attendance, he ordained new to fucceed them before their faces: Nevertheless they retain'd the Title of their Offices, received ſeveral of his Orders, which they derived to their Deputies and Adjutants, daily to be put in execution.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="64">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      64. After his Daughter-in-law <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, and his Grandchildren were condemned, they were never fuffer'd to remove from any place, but in <pb n="205"/> Chains, with their Litter ſew'd up clofe, and a Guard of Souldiers to prohibite all Paſſengers they ſhould meet upon the road, either to fpeak with, or look after them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="65">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      65. It was no ſmall pain to him to ruine the greatness of <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>, though he faw him defigning new alterations; for his Nativity was publickly celebrated, and his Images of Gold every where adored; and indeed what he did was rather by artifice and cunning, than any effect of his imperial power: For firſt, that under pretence of honour to him, he might keep him at further diſtance, he took him for his Colleague in his fifth Confulſhip, which in his long abſence from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> he affum'd on purpoſe; after which, having cajol'd him with hopes of his affinity, and the Tribunitial authority when he expected nothing lefs, he complain'd of him in a moſt ſhameful and poor-ſpirited Oration, in which amongst other things he begg'd of the Senate, <q rend="italic">That they would send one of the Confuls with a Convoy of Souldiers, to conduct a poor old man, forſaken by all people, into their prefence.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      And yet being diffident, and apprehending a tumult by the way, he gave order to have his Grandfon <persName rend="italic">Drusus</persName>, whom he kept Prifoner in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> to that day, to be fet at liberty, (if need were) and conſtituted General. Having prepared Ships likewife in readiness for his eſcape, he was contriving which of his Legions to fly to, keeping himself cloſe upon a high Rock, that he might discover what paſs'd at a diſtance, by the means of certain figns agreed of, to prevent any delay or treachery in the Meſſengers. Nay even after he had defeated the Confpiracy of <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>, his pufillanimity and apprehenfion was the fame; for, for nine months afterwards he never <pb n="206"/> had the courage to venture out of that Palace which was call'd the Palace of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="66">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      66. Besides theſe trouble and inquietudes, it was no ſmall addition to the anxieties of his mind, to underſtand the railings and invectives from all parts; for there was not one perfon condemned, which reproach'd him not with all forts of iniquity, either in his prefence, or elfe by Libels fet up or difpers'd in the <foreign rend="italic">Orchestra</foreign>, with which he was variouſly affected; fometimes he wiſh'd (for modeſty fake) his exorbitancies conceal'd, otherwhiles he ſeem'd to hug and delight himself in them, and of his own accord, without any occafion, to boaft of them publickly. He was reviled alſo by the Letters of <persName rend="italic">Artabana</persName> King of the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName>, as guilty of Parricide, Murder, Cowardife, and Luxury, and advised by a voluntary death to fatisfie the juſt indignation of the people with all convenient fpeed.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="67">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      67. At length being weary of his own wickedneſs, he made as it were a Confeſſion of his ill life, in the beginning of this Epiſtle to the Senate; <q rend="italic">What shall I write to you, moſt Reverend Fathers, or in what manner? or rather what shall I not write at this time? may the Gods afflict me worse than I daily find my self afflicted, if I know.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Some are of opinion he had great knowledge of future Events, and that of a long time he foresaw the misfortunes he ſhould lie under, and for that reaſon when he firſt entred upon the Imperial Authority, had obſtinately refus'd the Title of <foreign rend="italic">Pater Patriæ</foreign>, and would not fuffer any one to ſwear to the maintaining of his Acts, left to his greater diſgrace he ſhould be found afterwards unworthy of thoſe honours, <pb n="207"/>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      as may be collected out of his Oration upon both thoſe points, or where he ſayes, <q rend="italic">That he would alwayes be the fame man, and never change his manners, whilst his wits were at his own difpofing;</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">nevertheless to avoid the giving any ill Presidents, the Senate would do well not to oblige themselves to the Acts of any one, ſeeing all men were Subject to change.</q> And in another place; <q rend="italic">If at any time</q> (fayes he) <q rend="italic">you ſhall question or suspect the integrity of my deportment, and devotion for your ſervice, (which would be much more dreadful to me than death it self) what honour or advantage would the name of Father be to me? it would but reproach you of imprudence in giving me that appellation, or of inconstancy in changing your judgments of me.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="68">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      68. He was of a strong well-fet Stature, ſomething above the Ordinary tallneſs of Men, broad in the Breast and Shoulders, in the rest of his Members, from Head to Foot, very well proportioned; He had the moſt and beſt uſe of his left hand, in whoſe joynts he had fuch ſtrength, he would run one of his fingers through a green Apple, though never fo found, and brake the Head of a luſty Fellow with a fillop:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His complexion was clear and white, his hair long behind, ſo as it covered the Nape of his Neck, which was peculiar to that Family. His face and aſpect graceful, though he had feveral ſmall pimples upon it, and large goggle eyes, with which (though very wonderful) he could fee in the dark, and at midnight, but it was but for a ſhort time, when he firſt awak'd; preſently afterwards they would return to their old dimneſs again.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In his walk he marched with his head ſtiff, but bowing, his countenance fevere, and most commonly filent; when he did <pb n="208"/> ſpeak to thoſe which were next him, it was drawlingly, and with a certain motion and geſticulation of his fingers, which becomed him not at all. All which imperfections, and reputed indications of arrogance, <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> obſerved in him, and endeavoured many times to excuſe them to the Senate and People, repreſenting to them, <q rend="italic">That they were defects in his Nature, 'twas true, but no imperfections in his Mind.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He was very healthful, all the time he was Emperour ſcarce fick fo much as once, though from the thirtieth year of his age, he mannaged himself as he pleaſed, without the advice or aſſiſtance of any Phyſitian.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="69">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      69. To Matters of Religion or Divine Worſhip, he had no great Devotion, as being addicted to Aftrology, and perſwaded that all things were governed by Fate. Yet he had a great horror for thunder, and when the air was thick and portended a ſtorm, he alwaies clapt on a Crown of Laurel upon his head, becauſe that Tree is reported to be never blaſted with lightning.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="70">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      70. He was a great lover of the Liberal Arts in both kinds. In his ſpeaking of Latine he imitated <persName rend="italic">Corvinus Meſſala</persName>, whom being an old man, he had obſerved from his youth; but his affectation, and moroſity obfcured his ſtile, fo as he was eſteemed a better ſpeaker <foreign rend="italic">ex tempore</foreign>, than upon pre-meditation and ſtudy.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He made a Lyrick Poem likewise which he intituled, <foreign rend="italic">A Complaint for the death of <persName rend="italic">L. Cæfar</persName></foreign>, and ſeveral others in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>, in imitation of <persName rend="italic">Euphorion</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Rhianus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Parthenius</persName>, Poets whom he loved fo <pb n="209"/> well, and delighted in ſo much, he cauſed their writings and Statues to be dedicated in the publick Libraries, amongst the moſt antient and Celebrated Authors; upon which ſcore ſeveral learned men ſtrove and contended who ſhould preſent him with moſt Commendations of them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      But above all his Studies, he delighted in Fabulous Hiſtory and Romance, in which he was fo well verſed, there was not the moſt impertinent and ridiculous paffage which he had not at his fingers ends. His uſual Queſtions to the Grammarians (to which kind of profeffors he had a particular inclination as we have faid before) were fuch trifles as thefe; <q rend="italic">Who was <persName rend="italic">Hecuba</persName>'s Mother? What was <persName rend="italic">Achilles</persName> name, whilst he was among the Maids? What Songs it were the Syrenes or Mere-Maids did fing?</q> And the very firſt day that he entred into the Senate, after the death of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, as if he deſigned to perform the formalities of Piety and Religion at once, according to the Example of <persName rend="italic">Minose</persName> he facrificed with Frankincense, and Wine, but it was without Muſick, as <persName rend="italic">Minofe</persName> did at the death of his Son.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="71">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      71. The <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> tongue though he ſpake it readily, and with eaſe, yet he us'd it but ſeldom, eſpecially in the Senate; infomuch that being to name <foreign rend="italic">Monopolium</foreign>, he excus'd himself beforehand, for that he ſhould be conſtrained to make use of a forreign word; and again, in a Decree of the Senate, when the word <foreign rend="italic">Emblema</foreign> was read, he was of opinion it was to be changed for a Latine, and that if no one word could be found out to expreſs it, it ſhould be <pb n="210"/> done rather by circumlocution, than continue as it was. A <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> Souldier alſo being required to give in his Testimony, he commanded him to give it in Latine.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="72">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      72. In all the time of his retirement, he never endeavoured to return to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> but twice; once he came in a Galley as far as the Orchards, adjoining to the place where they fought their Naval Battels, but he firſt planted his Guards all along upon the banks of <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>, to keep off all perfons which came forth to meet him: Another time he came within ſeven miles by the way of <placeName rend="italic">Appia</placeName>, but having feen the Walls of the City, he contented himself, and went back again without approaching any nearer.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For what cauſe he did ſo at firſt, no body can gueſs, but the ſecond time he returned, he was frighted with a prodigie: For having a defire to feed a Dragon (which he took great delight in) with his own hands as he was accustomed to do, when he called for it, he found it was devour'd by Piſmires, and was admonished thereby to have a care of the multitude, whereupon he went back immediately, and fell ill at <placeName rend="italic">Aftura</placeName> in <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>; but finding himself ſomewhat better, he went forward as far as <placeName rend="italic">Circei</placeName>, and becauſe he would give no fufpicion or jealousie of his ſickness, he was not onely preſent at the Military games exhibited there, but he threw darts himself at a Bore which was let loose, and kill'd him;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      But having got a ſtitch in his fide with the violence he used, and taking cold by putting himself into a heat, he fell into a relapse, more dangerous than the condition he was in before; yet he carried it out pretty <pb n="211"/> well for a while, and being brought as far as <placeName rend="italic">Miſenum</placeName>, he omitted nothing of his uſual exerciſes, continuing his feaftings and other debaucheries, partly out of intemperance, and partly diſſimulation; <persName rend="italic">Charicles</persName> his Phyſician having got leave to depart, taking him by the hand to kiss it as he was going out of the Room, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> imagining it a deſign to feel his pulfe, perſwaded him to fit down again, and protracted the Supper. Nor did he forget his old Cuſtom, but at that time alſo ſtanding upon his feet in the middle of the room, with an Officer by him, he called them all by their names, and took his leave particularly of each of them when they departed.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="73">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      73. About this time, having read in the Records of the Senate, That Some Prisoners were discharg'd without so much as being heard, becauſe he had writ only in ſhort, That they were inform'd against, and no more: Storming to be ſo neglected, he refolv'd (come what would) to return to <placeName rend="italic">Caprea</placeName>, as not daring to attempt any thing, but in a place where he was safe! But being retain'd by ill weather, and his diſtemper increaſing, he died a while after in the Village of <persName rend="italic">Lucullus</persName> in the 78. year of his age, the 23. of his Reign, and the 16th of <foreign rend="italic">March</foreign>, <persName rend="italic">Cn. Acerronius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">C. Pontius Niger</persName> being Confuls.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Some there are of an opinion, that <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> gave him a flow-working Poyfon, which confum'd him by degrees; others, that though his Feaver was abated, they would give him no meat; and fome, that when he came to himself again out of a fwounding fit, and demanded a Ring which they had pulld <pb n="212"/> off his finger, they clapt a pillow before his mouth, and ftifled him: <persName rend="italic">Seneca</persName> writes, That finding himself going, he pulled off his Ring, and held it for fome time in his hand, as designing to give it to some body: then he put it on his finger again, and griping his left hand fast, he lay a long time without stirring; when on a sudden calling his fervants, and no body answering, he rose up out of his bed, but his strength failing, he fell down by the bed side and dyed.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="74">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      74. The laſt day he ever celebrated his own Nativity, having caused the Statue of <persName rend="italic">Apollo Temenites</persName> to be brought from <placeName rend="italic">Syracuse</placeName>, with intention to fet it up in the Library of the New Temple, as a piece of incomparable workmanſhipp and bigness; the faid God appear'd to him, as he thought, in his fleep, and told him, <q rend="italic">That he could not be dedicated by him.</q> And not many dayes before his death, the <placeName rend="italic">Pharos</placeName> or Watch-Tower at <placeName rend="italic">Caprea</placeName> fell down, by an Earthquake. And at <placeName rend="italic">Misenum</placeName>, the Coals which were brought to warm the Chamber, being put out, and cold for a confiderable time, broke out again on a fudden in the Evening, and continued shining a good part of the night.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="75">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      75. The people were ſo over-joyed with the tidings of his death, that at the firſt News they ran up and down the Street, ſome crying out, <q rend="italic">That <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> ſhould be thrown into the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>;</q> others, <q rend="italic">That fupplication was to be made to our Mother Earth, and the rest of the infernal Gods, that no place might be afforded him now he was dead, but amongst the moſt wicked and miferable perfons in that World:</q> Others threatned <pb n="213"/> his Corps with the hooks and <placeName rend="italic">Gemoniae</placeName>, as being exafperated (befides the memory of his former cruelties) with a new piece of inhumanity as it were, after his death;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For whereas by Decree of the Senate it was provided, That no perfon condemn'd, ſhould be executed till the tenth day after ſentence pronounc'd, it happen'd by accident, that the day of fome perfons punishment fell out on the fame day the news of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>'s death was known: The poor people begg'd hard for a Reprieve, but <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> being abfent, and no body there to whom properly any Petition in their behalf could be addreſs'd, the Keepers of the Priſon, that they might feem to comport exactly with the ſentence of the Senate, ſtrangled them of their own accord, and threw their bodies into the air;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      which action increas'd the hatred of the people against him, as if his cruelty had outlived him. As soon as his body began to be remov'd from <placeName rend="italic">Misenum</placeName>, the people cryed out, <q rend="italic">That they should carry him rather to <placeName rend="italic">Atella</placeName>, than to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and let him be half burnt there in the Amphitheatre, as less Malefactors had by his Order been feru'd before him.</q> Yet the Souldiers brought it to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, where it was burnt with publick folemnity.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="76">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      76. Two years before his death, he made his Will, of which there were two parts, one under his own hand, the other written by one of his Freemen, but both to the ſame purpoſe, and Witneſſed by perſons of very mean quality. By that Will he left Coheirs, <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> his Grandſon by <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> by <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, both in equal portions, ſubſtituting them ſucceſſively. He left Legacies likewiſe <pb n="214"/> to ſeveral others, amongſt the reſt to the Veſtal Virgins, to all the Souldiers, to every one of the Commons, and to the Maſters and Officers of every Ward, ſeverally and by themſelves.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>