<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>

            <pb n="217"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      1. <persName rend="italic">GErmanicus</persName> the Father of <persName rend="italic">Caius Cæſar</persName>, and Son of <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> by <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> the younger, was adopted by his Uncle <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, and immediately (though he wanted five years of the age required by the Laws) he exerciſed the Office of Quæſtor, and not long after, the Conſulſhip. Being ſent to Command the Army in <placeName rend="italic">Ger</placeName><pb n="218"/><placeName rend="italic">many</placeName>, about the time the death of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> was publiſh'd, all the Legions refuſing to acknowledge <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> for Emperour, and proffering him the ſole Government of the Commonwealth, it is a queſtion whether he reſtrain'd them with more piety, or reſolution; and a while afterwards, having vanquiſh'd the Enemy, he triumph'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being created Conſul the ſecond time, before he entred upon his Charge, he was (as it were) forc'd away to appeaſe ſome Commotions in the Eaſt: But after he had conquered the King of <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName>, and reduc'd <placeName rend="italic">Cappadocia</placeName> into the form of a Province, he fell ſick and dyed of a tedious and lingering diſeaſe, the 34. year of his age, in the City of <placeName rend="italic">Antioch</placeName>, and not without ſuſpicion of poiſon; For beſides the livid and blue ſpots which appear'd upon his body, and the foam which flow'd from his mouth; after he was burnt, they found amongſt his bones his heart incorrupt and intire, according to the general opinion, which reports it of ſuch a nature, that if it be the leaſt touch'd or infected with poiſon, it is never to be conſumed with fire.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. He dyed as was ſuppos'd by the contrivance of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, and the Miniſtery of <persName rend="italic">C. Piſo</persName>, who at the ſame time being Governour of <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, not diſſembling that he was of neceſſity to offend either the Father or Son, (as if there were no remedy) he treated <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> with great inſolence, even in his ſickneſs, in ſo much that when he return'd to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he eſcap'd narrowly being pull'd in pieces by the people, but was however condemned to death by the Senate.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. This is moſt certain, <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> was indued with all good qualities, either of the body or mind, and ſuch as were not to be found in any other <pb n="219"/> Prince. His comelineſs, courage, and ſtrength, were conſpicuouſly eminent; his eloquence unqueſtionably perfect, both in Latine and <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>, by which he gain'd upon all people; by the ſweetneſs of his carriage he conciliated love, and made it his buſineſs to oblige every body. All that could be excepted againſt in his ſhape, was that the ſmalneſs of his legs was not proportionable to the reſt of his members; but by degrees that objection was removed, and his legs brought to their correſpondence, by frequent riding after meals. He ſlew many of the Enemy with his own hand;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      he pleaded Triumphal cauſes; and amongſt other monuments of his ſtudies, he left certain Comedies in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>: he was equally civil both at home and abroad; and being univerſally beloved, he viſited ſuch Towns as were Free, or Confederate, without his Lictors, or ſuch like marks of his authority. He was ſo great an honourer of the memories of illuſtrious men, that wherever he ſaw any of their Tombs, he paid all due formalities to their Ghoſts. Having deſigned to bury the old and diſpers'd reliques of ſuch as were ſlain in <persName rend="italic">Varus</persName> his defeat, together in one grave, he himſelf was the firſt man which gather'd them with his own hand, and carried them to the place.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      So little inclination he had to revenge the moſt ſenſible injuries, that he permitted <persName rend="italic">Piſo</persName> to reſcinde his Decrees, and perſecute his Dependants, without expreſſing the leaſt indignation, till he found him leveling at his life, both with Magick, and Poiſon. Nor did he then proceed any further than to renounce his Friendſhip, and recommend it to his Domeſticks to revenge him, if any thing happen'd otherwiſe than well.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. All theſe qualities and perfections gain'd him <pb n="220"/> the love and eſteem of his relations in ſuch manner, that (without ſpeaking of the reſt) <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> was a long time in ſuſpence whether he ſhould make him his Succeſſor himſelf, or leave him to be adopted by <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>. Nor was he leſs dear to the people, who (as ſeveral report) were ſo paſſionately deſirous to ſee him, that as often as he departed or arrived at any place, he many times ran great danger of his life, by the throngs and crowds of ſuch perſons as attended him out, or went on purpoſe to wait upon him in. When (after he had appeas'd that ſedition) he return'd out of <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, all the Prætorian Cohorts advanc'd to meet him, though two only had Orders; and all the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, without diſtinction of Sex, Age, or Quality, were got in throngs upon the road for twenty miles together.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. But his death rendred his eſteem and reputation much more remarkable; for on the day he died, the people threw ſtones at their Temples, pull'd down their Altars, flung their Houſhold-gods out of doors, whilſt the New-born Babes were expos'd and in their indignation forſaken by their Parents. The Barbarians themſelves (if we may believe relation) who were at Wars with one another, nay even with us, reſenting ſo general a loſs, made a Ceſſation of their own accord, whilſt their Governours and Princes cut off their Beards ſome of them, and ſhaved their Wives heads in token of their ſorrow. The King of the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName> alſo left off his Hunting, and forbore his ordinary converſation amongſt the Princes and Grandees of his Court, which among the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName> is like the ſtopping of their Courts of Juſtice, and never uſed but upon extraordinary diſaſter.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. The <pb n="225"/> firſt news of his ſickneſs, had put the City in no ſmall conſternation; but whilſt they were ſadly attending for farther intelligence, on a ſudden about Evening a report was ſpread, (no body knew how) that he was recover'd and well. The people were ſo tranſported with joy, they ran immediately with their Torches, and Sacrifices to the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, and no little danger there was that the doors of the Temple had been broken open, in their impatience of paying the Vows which they had made for his recovery. <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> was awak'd out of his ſleep with the noiſe of their Congratulations, the multitude not being able to moderate their joy, nor contain themſelves from reſounding with one voice, <q rend="italic">Salva Roma, Salva Patria, Salvus eſt Germanicus</q>; <q rend="italic"><placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> is ſafe, and our Countrey is ſafe, ſince <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> is ſafe.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But at length, certain news of his death being arrived, they ſeem'd paſt all Conſolation, all the Emperours Edicts being unable to reſtrain the expreſſions of their ſorrow, which continued in deſpight of all the Feſtivals and Holy-dayes in <foreign rend="italic">December</foreign>. And that which was a great augmentation of the glory of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, and made him much more regretted, was the miſerable condition of the following times; for the cruelty of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> diſcovering it ſelf preſently after, all the World did rationally believe, it was the reverence, or fear of him, which had reſtrain'd him before.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. His Wife was <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">M. Agrippa</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>, by whom he had nine Children: Two of them died very young, and a third, a Youth very handſome and witty, whoſe Picture (drawn in the habit of <persName rend="italic">Cupid</persName>) <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> dedicated in the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Venus Capitolinus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> <pb n="222"/> (having it ſometimes in his Chamber) was wont to kiſs it conſtantly when he came in: The reſt of his Children out-lived their Father; three Daughters, <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Druſilla</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Livilla</persName>, born ſucceſſively in three years ſpace; and three Sons, <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſar</persName>, of which <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> were declared Enemies to the State, by the Senate, upon the complaint and accuſation of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſar</persName> was born the laſt of <foreign rend="italic">August</foreign>, his Father, and <persName rend="italic">C. Fonteius Capito</persName>, being Conſuls; as to the place of his birth, the diverſity of reports makes it uncertain: <persName rend="italic">Cn. Lentulus Getulicus</persName> writes, he was born at <placeName rend="italic">Tibur</placeName>; <persName rend="italic">Plinius Secundus</persName>, in the Countrey of the <placeName rend="italic">Treveri</placeName>, at a Town called <placeName rend="italic">Ambiatinum</placeName>, upon the meeting and confluence of the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, and the <placeName rend="italic">Moſella</placeName>; and as an inforcement of his opinion, he adds, there are ſtill Altars to be ſeen with this inſcription, <q rend="italic">OB AGRIPPINÆ PUERPERIVM.</q> For the delivery of <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>. But he being Emperour preſently after, and theſe Verſes publickly divulged, they would perſwade, he was born in the place where the Legions were at that time in their Winter Quarters; <q rend="italic">In Caſtris natus, Patriis nutritus in armis, Jam deſignati Principis omen erat.</q> <q rend="italic">Born in the Camp, Nurs'd in his Countreys War, Portends he was decreed an Emperor.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For my part I find amongſt the Records, he was born at <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName>; <persName rend="italic">Plinie</persName> refutes <persName rend="italic">Getulicus</persName> as a liar, and one who deſigned to flatter a young and ambitious Prince, by aſſigning him a Birth-place in a <pb n="223"/> Town which was conſecrated to <persName rend="italic">Hercules</persName>, and that he was the more audacious in his Hiſtory, becauſe <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> had lyen-in of a Son at <placeName rend="italic">Tibur</placeName> but a year before, whoſe name was <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſar</persName> likewiſe, of whoſe amiableneſs, and death, we have ſpoken already:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      As for <persName rend="italic">Plinie</persName>, the computation of the times is a ſufficient confutation of him, for thoſe who have writ the Hiſtory of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, aſſure us, that <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> was born before his Father <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> was ſent into <placeName rend="italic">Gaule</placeName>, after his Conſulſhip was expired; neither is the inſcription upon the Altars of any importance to his opinion, ſeeing <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> had two Daughters in that Countrey, and the word <foreign rend="italic">Puerperium</foreign> may be interpreted of either ſex; and beſides, in old time they us'd to call little Girls <foreign rend="italic">Pueræ</foreign>, as they did little Boyes <foreign rend="italic">Puelli</foreign>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      There is extant alſo an Epiſtle from <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> to <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> his Grand-daughter, writ not many months before his death, concerning this <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, (for there was no other Child at that time of that name) in theſe words; <q rend="italic">Yeſterday I gave order to <persName rend="italic">Talarius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Aſellius</persName>, to bring little <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> hither (if it pleas'd the Gods) on the 17th. of <foreign rend="italic">May</foreign>. I ſend with him (beſides) one of my Phyſicians, which (as I have writ to <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>) he may keep with him if he thinks good. Adieu, my dear <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, and make much of thy ſelf, that thou mayſt be well and in health when thou meeteſt with thy Husband.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      So that it appears abundantly, as I ſuppoſe, <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> could not be born in a Countrey into which he was convey'd from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, when he was near two years old. Which evidences are of no leſs authority againſt the Verſes, eſpecially conſidering the Author was never known. It remains therefore that we acquieſce in the Teſtimony of the publick Records, and the rather, becauſe <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> preferr'd <pb n="224"/> <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName> to all other places of pleaſure, and valued it continually as if it had been there (and no otherwhere) he was brought into the world: And 'tis reported, That being weary of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he reſolv'd once to have remov'd his Imperial Seat thither.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. The Sirname of <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> was given him in the Camp, by the Raillerie of the Souldiers, becauſe he was brought up amongſt them in the habit of a Common Souldier; by virtue of which education he had contracted their affection ſo, that upon a Mutiny after the death of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, his preſence appeas'd them, when they were at the height of their fury: Nor could they poſſibly be quieted, till they underſtood he was to be ſent away to the next City, leſt he ſhould be in any danger by their ſedition; but as ſoon as they underſtood that, repenting of what they had done, they ſtopt his Coach, excus'd their fault, and deprecated the diſpleaſure he might have juſtly conceiv'd againſt them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. He accompanied his Father in his Expedition into <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, from whence being return'd, his firſt reſidence was with his Mother, and (after her baniſhment) with his Great Grandmother <persName rend="italic">Livia Auguſta</persName>; who dying not long after, he made her Funeral Oration before the <placeName rend="italic">Roſtra</placeName>, though he was then but a youth, and in his Prætexta: from thence he went to his Grandmother <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName>, and afterwards when he was twenty years old, being ſent for by <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> to <placeName rend="italic">Capreæ</placeName>, he aſſum'd the Virile Robe, and ſhaved his Beard the firſt time, both the ſame day, without the honour and ſolemnity which his Brothers had received upon the like occaſion.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      When he was there, he was tempted by all tricks and <pb n="225"/> deſigns to complain, or talk more freely than was allow'd; but he was too wiſe for them all, paſs'd all by, as if he had forgot the misfortunes of his Family, and diſſembled his own ſufferings with incredible patience. In ſhort, he demeaned himſelf towards his Grandfather, with ſo much obſequiouſneſs, that it was ſaid of him, and not without reaſon, <q rend="italic">Never was there a better Servant, nor a worſe Maſter.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. Howbeit he could not, even then, maſter his ill inclinations, but took delight to be preſent himſelf at all puniſhments and Executions. He diſguis'd himſelf in the night, and ran up and down to Taverns and Brothel-houſes, in a Perriwig and long Gown, that no body might diſcover him. He delighted paſſionately in Dancing, Muſick, and ſuch Arts as belong'd to the Stage, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> willingly conniving, in hopes thoſe Exerciſes might by degrees ſoften and mollifie the cruelty of his Nature; which the cunning old Prince had ſo perfectly foreſeen, that he ſeveral times preſaged, <q rend="italic">That <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> lived for his deſtruction, and the ruine of them all, and that (in him) he brought up a Serpent for the People of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and a <persName rend="italic">Phaeton</persName> for the reſt of the World.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. Not long after he married <persName rend="italic">Claudilla</persName>, the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">M. Silanus</persName>, a Gentleman of antient extraction; and then being deſign'd Augur in the place of <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> his Brother, before his inveſtiture and inauguration, he was advanc'd to the Pontificate, with great ſhew of piety and good nature. As at that time there was no perſon at Court but himſelf, could make the leaſt pretence to the Empire, (<persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName> being ſuſpected already, and a while after deſtroy'd) he began to look about him, and to <pb n="226"/> conceive ſome hopes of his ſucceſſion;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and that he might fortifie and confirm them the better, his Wife <persName rend="italic">Junia</persName> being dead in Child-bed, he addreſs'd himſelf to <persName rend="italic">Ennia</persName> the Wife of <persName rend="italic">Mævius Macro</persName>, then Captain of the Prætorian Cohorts, and having debauch'd her by frequent ſolicitations, he ſwore to her, and promis'd her Marriage under his hand, if ever he came to be Emperour: having by her means inſinuated into the affection of <persName rend="italic">Macro</persName>, as ſome think, he attempted <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> with Poyſon; and having commanded his Ring to be taken off his finger, obſerving <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> to give ſome ſigns of reſiſtance, he caus'd a pillow to be clapt upon his mouth, and ſtifled him with his own hands. An action that ſeem'd ſo cruel to one of his Freedmen, he could not forbear crying out, but he had as good have been quiet, for he caus'd him to be hang'd up immediately.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Nor is it incredible, ſeeing there are Authors which affirm, that if he committed not that fact, yet he confeſs'd publickly he deſigned it; and as a mark of his piety and good nature, he boaſted, <q rend="italic">That to revenge the death of his Mother and Brothers, he went one time with a Dagger in his hand into <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> his Chamber, when he was aſleep; but being touch'd with compaſſion, he threw away his weapon, and retired: That <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> ſaw him well enough, but durſt neither examine nor revenge it.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. Having been known to moſt of the Provincials, and Souldiers, from his Childhood, and no leſs grateful to the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, for the memory of his Father <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, and in pity to his deſolate Family, he arrived at the Empire to the ſatisfaction of all parties: In order to which, as he removed from <placeName rend="italic">Miſenum</placeName>, though he was in Mourning, and <pb n="227"/> attended the Corps of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> with great gravity; yet could he not forbear marching amongſt the Altars, Sacrifices, and Torches which came out to meet him, being ſurrounded with an infinite number of people, teſtifying their joy by their acclamations, and calling him (beſides other lucky names) <q rend="italic">Sidus, Pullum, Puppum</q>, and <q rend="italic">Alumnum</q>, their Star, their Chicken, their Child, and their Darling.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. As ſoon as he had made his Entry into <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, the Senate being aſſembled, and the people thronging into the Council, by univerſal conſent he was declared Emperour, with abſolute power, contrary to the expreſs will of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, who left him but Coheir with another of his Grandchildren, who was then under age, and in his Prætexta. In ſhort, ſo great was their joy at his advancement to the Empire, that in leſs than three months time, there were Sacrificed by report above a hundred and threeſcore thouſand Cattel:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      A while after, upon his paſſage into the Iſles of <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, which were not far off, they made Vows for his return, omitting not the leaſt opportunity of expreſſing their care and ſolicitude for his ſafety. And when afterwards he chanced to be ill, the people throng'd whole nights about his Palace; ſome offer'd themſelves to Combate for his ſafety, ſome devoted themſelves to death if he recover'd, and ſet up Bills of their reſolutions in the Streets.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      To this infinite affection of the Citizens, the no leſs favour of Strangers was added; for <persName rend="italic">Artabanus</persName> King of the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName>, who had expreſs'd nothing but hatred and contempt of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, ſought his friendſhip himſelf, and coming to a perſonal Conference with one of his Legates, which had been Conſul, he paſs'd the <placeName rend="italic">Euphrates</placeName>, adored <pb n="228"/> the Eagles and other Enſigns of the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName>, and kiſs'd the Images of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. In this manner he inſinuated into their affection, and made himſelf acceptable to the people, by all ſorts of popularity. Having perform'd his laſt duty to <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, made his Funeral Oration with many tears, and exhibited his Obſequies with great and magnificent ſolemnity, he haſtned forthwith to the Iſlands of <placeName rend="italic">Pandataria</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Pontia</placeName>, to remove the aſhes of his Mother, and Brother, expoſing himſelf to the danger of ill weather, that his piety might be the more notoriouſly obſervable; and having gathered them with much reverence together, he put them into their Urnes with his own proper hands. With no leſs pomp and formality he carried them to <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName> firſt, ſetting up his Standard in the Poupe of his Galley, from thence to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, up the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>, and ſo had them convey'd by the moſt illuſtrious of the Equeſtrian Order, into the Mauſolium at noon-day. Beſides this, he ordained publick Services and Devotions, to be annually obſerv'd in their Commemoration: Moreover, for his Mother he inſtituted ſolemn Games in the Circus, and a Chariot in which her Image ſhould be carried in pomp:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and in memory of his Father, he called the month of <foreign rend="italic">September</foreign> <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>. Theſe Ceremonies being over, by an Act of the Senate he conferr'd upon his Grandmother <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName>, all the Honours which <persName rend="italic">Livia Auguſta</persName> had receiv'd in her whole life. He took for his Colleague in the Conſulſhip, <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> his Unkle by the Fathers ſide, who till that time was a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight, and no more. He adopted his Brother <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> the very day he put on his Virile Gown, and call'd him Prince of the Youth:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      As to his Siſters, he ordain'd in their favour, that they ſhould <pb n="229"/> be compriſed in all Oaths, and this clauſe for the future be added; <q rend="italic">Neither is my ſelf, or Children, dearer to me, than <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> and his Siſters</q>: and in the motions, or reports of the Conſuls, that they ſhould uſe this form; <q rend="italic">Quod bonum fælixque ſit <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſari</persName>, Sororibuſque ejus, And may it be good and happy to <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſar</persName>, and his Siſters.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      With the ſome artifice and popularity he reſtor'd ſuch as ſtood condemn'd, or baniſh'd, forgiving all paſt crimes, if there were any which remain'd unpuniſh'd. All Regiſters and Records, relating any way to the proceedings againſt his Mother and Brothers, (leſt there ſhould be room left for fear, or apprehenſion in any of their Informers) he caus'd to be brought publickly into the Market-place; and having call'd the Gods to witneſs, that he had never read, nor ſo much as touch'd them, he threw them into the fire and burnt them. And this kindneſs which he hitherto had ſhewn them, was the reaſon he refus'd a Note which was offer'd him, tending to the diſcovery of a Conſpiracy againſt him, alledging for his reaſon, <q rend="italic">That he was not conſcious of any thing might deſerve the hatred of any body</q>; and, <q rend="italic">That he had no ears for Informers.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. He reſolv'd to have caſt the <foreign rend="italic">Spintriæ</foreign> or inventers of abominable recreations into the Sea, and when at laſt he was perſwaded from that ſeverity, he baniſh'd them from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. He ſuffer'd ſuch as were curious to ſearch for, and peruſe the writings of <persName rend="italic">Titus Labienus</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Cordus Cremutius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Caſſius Severus</persName>, which had been prohibited and ſuppreſt by Order of the Senate, it being for his intereſt to have all paſſages tranſmitted to poſterity. The eſtabliſhment or Model of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> his adminiſtration, which had been neglected by <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, <pb n="230"/> he caus'd to be publiſh'd;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He gave a free juriſdiction to the Magiſtrates, without reſerving any appeal to himſelf. He took a ſtrict view of the Gentry of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, taking away their horſes before all people, when he found any of them guilty of any infamous wickedneſs: But for peccadilloes, and ſuch perſons as had but ſmall offences to anſwer, he only paſt over their names as the rolls were read, without further puniſhing them. To relieve the Judges who at that time were overlaid with the multitude of buſineſs, to the four before, he added a fifth Decurie. He endeavoured alſo to reſtore the antient manner of Elections of Magiſtrates by the ſuffrages of the people.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Though the laſt Will and Teſtament of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> was declared Null: and that of <persName rend="italic">Livia Auguſta</persName> ſuppreſt by the ſaid <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, yet he caus'd all their Legacies to be punctually paid, without either clamour on the one ſide, or fraud on the other. He remitted the impoſition call'd <foreign rend="italic">Centeſima</foreign>, which was rais'd upon all bargains and ſales in <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>. He made good the loſſes which ſeveral people received by fire, and if he reſtored their Kingdomes to any Princes who had been diſpoſſeſs'd, he not only gave them their Eſtates, but an exact account and reſtitution of all their revenue from the time they were diſſeiſed; As particularly to <persName rend="italic">Antiochus Comagenus</persName> he returned a hundred Millions of Seſterces, which had been confiſcated,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      and that he might appear an incourager and favourer of all good examples, he gave to a Libertine Woman 80000 Seſterces, for having indured the moſt exquiſite torments, without diſcovering the crime of her Patron: for which good actions, among other honours done unto him, there was a ſhield of Gold bearing his Buſt or half Image, decreed <pb n="231"/> to be carried annually upon a certain day by the Colledges of the Prieſts into the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>; The Senators following in their ranks, and the Noblemens Children of both Sexes ſinging and chanting verſes in praiſe of his Virtues. Beſides which it was ordain'd, that the day on which he was advanced to the Empire, ſhould be called <foreign rend="italic">Palilia</foreign>; implying a new foundation of the City, the firſt having been likewiſe on that day.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. He was Conſul four times, the firſt, two Months from the firſt of <foreign rend="italic">January</foreign>; the ſecond, from the firſt of <foreign rend="italic">January</foreign> to the thirtieth, the third, to the Ides of <foreign rend="italic">January</foreign>, and the fourth, to the ſeventh day before the ſaid Ides: Of all theſe he held the two laſt ſucceſſively, but the third he entred upon at <placeName rend="italic">Lyons</placeName> alone, not as ſome think out of vain glory, or negligence, but becauſe his Colleague dyed juſt upon the day of the Calends, ſo as he could have no knowledge of his death.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He gave a Largeſs to the people of 300 Seſterces a piece, twice, and as often he made a Magnificent Entertainment for the Senators, and the Knights, with their Wives and Children; in the latter of which, he gave the Men Robes, the Women and Children favours of Purple, or violet colour ribbons; and to augment the publick joy in perpetuum, he added a day to the <foreign rend="italic">Saturnals</foreign>, and call'd it <foreign rend="italic">Juvenalis</foreign>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      18. He exhibited Gladiators, partly in the Amphitheatre of <persName rend="italic">Taurus</persName>, and partly in the <placeName rend="italic">Septa</placeName>, in the field of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>: amongſt which divertiſements he introduc'd certain Troops of <placeName rend="italic">African</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Campanian</placeName> Champions, ſelected out of both Countries. He preſided not alwaies himſelf in theſe ſpectacles, but ſometimes transferr'd that Office upon the Magiſtrates, and ſometimes upon his friends.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For Farces <pb n="232"/> and Comedies, he repreſented them frequently to the people, and in ſeveral ways, ſometimes in the night, with lighted torches burning all about the ſtreets: He cauſed Money and Medals to be flung many times among the people, and baskets of Bread and Meat to be diſtributed man by man: in one of which feaſts obſerving a certain Gentleman who ſate over againſt him, to feed chearfully and with a good Stomach, he ſent him his ſhare alſo. And to a Senator for the ſame Cauſe, he ſent his Letters Patents, by which he deſigned him Prætor extra Ordinem.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He preſented them alſo with ſeveral Circenſian Games, which continued from morning to night, interpoſing ſometimes the baiting of Panthers, ſometimes Juſtings and Turnaments a la <foreign rend="italic">Troyenne</foreign>: His Principal Entertainments in that kind were ſo Magnificently ſumptuous, the Circus was cover'd over with Vermilion and Borax, and no perſon admitted to manage the Chariots, under the degree of a Senator. Some alſo he exhibited <foreign rend="italic">ex tempore</foreign> and without any preparation, at the importunity of ſome perſons, who were ſtanding in the Balconies near him, whilſt he was looking upon the furniture of the Cirque, out of the houſe <placeName rend="italic">Gelotiana</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      19. Beſides theſe Ordinary Games, he invented one, ſuch as was never heard of before; for having got together a vaſt number of Boats, he faſtned them in a double rank with their anchors, all the ſpace betwixt <placeName rend="italic">Bajæ</placeName>, and the dams of <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName>, and having covered them with earth, he made a Bridge of 3600 paces, after the faſhion of the <placeName rend="italic">Via Appia</placeName>;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      upon which Bridge he paſt to and fro, two dayes together: The firſt day mounted upon a ſtately Horſe with rich Trappings, a Chaplet of Oaken <pb n="233"/> Branches upon his Head, his Battle-axe in one hand, his Target in the other, his ſword by his ſide, and his Imperial Mantle of Cloth of Gold upon his ſhoulders: The next day he appeared in the habit of a Charioteer, in a Chariot drawn by two ſtately Horſes, carrying before him <persName rend="italic">Darius</persName> a youth, and one of the <placeName rend="italic">Parthian</placeName> Hoſtages, attended by a Squadron of his Guards and ſeveral of his friends mounted likewiſe in their Chariots.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      I know it is the common opinion, that <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> built this Bridge in imitation of <persName rend="italic">Xerxes</persName>, who made a moſt wonderful one of planks over the <placeName rend="italic">Helleſpont</placeName>, but not altogether ſo broad as this. I know likewiſe there are others believe, that being then upon the point of making War upon the <placeName rend="italic">Germans</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Brittains</placeName>, he had a mind to terrifie them by the report of ſome extraordinary work. But I have heard my Grand-father ſay, when I was but a Boy, that ſome Courtiers which were in great favour with the Emperour, told him, that the true reaſon was from certain Aſtrological Predictions of <persName rend="italic">Thraſyllus</persName>, who finding <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> unreſolved as to his Succeſſor, yet more inclinable to his own Grand-Son, than <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>; he told him, It was as hard a matter for <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> to be Emperour, as for him to ride on Horſe-back over the Gulf of <placeName rend="italic">Bajæ</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      20. Nor were his Exhibitions of this nature only in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, but in the Provinces, and ſtrange Countries likewiſe: In <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, at <placeName rend="italic">Syracuſe</placeName>, he preſented them with ſuch Games as were uſed in <placeName rend="italic">Athens</placeName>, and at <placeName rend="italic">Lyons</placeName> in <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName>, with mixt and irregular. Amongſt the reſt he ordain'd a ſolemn Contention in Eloquence, both in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> and in <foreign rend="italic">Latine</foreign>; requiring thoſe which were overcome, to give rewards <pb n="234"/> to the Conquerour, and to make ſome Compoſition or other in his praiſe: But for thoſe who gave no ſatisfaction at all, they were condemn'd to expunge what they had done, either with a Sponge, or their tongue, unleſs they would chooſe rather to be corrected with Ferula's or plung'd over head and ears in the next River.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      21. He finiſhed the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and the Amphitheatre of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, which <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> had left half undone. In the Territory of <placeName rend="italic">Tibur</placeName>, he began an Aquaduct, and an Amphitheatre near the Park, of which one was perfected by his Succeſſor <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, and the other was quite laid aſide. The Temples and Walls at <placeName rend="italic">Syracuſe</placeName>, which were fallen down with age, he rebuilt and repaired; he had a deſign likewiſe to build the Palace of <persName rend="italic">Polycrates</persName> at <placeName rend="italic">Samos</placeName> a new, to finiſh the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName>, call'd <placeName rend="italic">Didymeum</placeName>, at <placeName rend="italic">Miletum</placeName>, and to erect a New City upon the top of the <placeName rend="italic">Alpes</placeName>; but his chief project was, to cut the Iſthmus in <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName>, and make a paſſage betwixt thoſe two Seas, in order to which he ſent a conſiderable Officer in his Army, to ſurvey and take meaſure of the work.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      22. Thus far we have ſpoken of him as a Prince, hereafter we ſhall mention him no otherwiſe than as a Monſter. He aſſum'd ſeveral Surnames, and was called <foreign rend="italic">Pius, Caſtrorum Filius, Pater Exercituum</foreign>, and <foreign rend="italic">Optimus Maximus</foreign>; The moſt pious, The Son of the Camp, The Father of the Armies, and The moſt gracious and mighty <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>. As he treated one night at Supper certain Kings, which were come to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, on purpoſe to pay him their devoirs, hearing them in controverſie amongſt themſelves about the Nobility of their extraction, he interrupted them, and cry'd out in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>, <q rend="italic">Let there be but one Lord, and one King.</q> And he was once of the mind to have taken the Diadem immediately, and changed the Government <pb n="235"/> into the form of a Kingdom:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But being inform'd that he was already above the Dignity of all the Princes and Monarchs of the world, from that time forward he began to challenge the honour of a Divine Majeſty. And indeed he commanded, that the Images of thoſe Gods which were in moſt eſteem, either for the Devotions perform'd unto them, or the Excellence of the workmanſhip, and amongſt the reſt that of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Olympicus</persName>, ſhould be brought from <placeName rend="italic">Greece</placeName>, that their heads being taken off, he might place his own in their room. He enlarg'd and brought down one part of the <placeName rend="italic">Palatium</placeName>, as far as the Market-place; and altering the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Caſtor</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Pollux</persName>, into the model of a Portico, he placed himſelf oftentimes betwixt the divine Brothers, to be adored by all which came thither; ſome were ſo prophane as to ſalute him by the name of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Latialis</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      And it had been well if his impiety had reſted here: But he built a Temple, dedicated it to his own Divinity, and inſtituted Prieſts and Victims, the moſt exquiſite that could be thought on. In this Temple ſtood his Image in Gold, done to the life, habited in a Robe ſuch as he wore himſelf. The richeſt men of the City, either by bribery or favour, purchas'd the dignity of this Prieſthood, according as vacancies fell. The Sacrifices which they offer'd were Peacocks, Pheaſants, <placeName rend="italic">Numidian</placeName> Hens, and other Fowls, the moſt rare and delicate could be got, which they ſorted, and Sacrificed daily by kinds.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      When the Moon was in the Full, and shined bright, his cuſtom was to call to her continually, and to invite her to bed to him, that ſhe might taſte of his embraces. In the day time he would ſeem to talk privately with <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>, ſometimes <pb n="236"/> whiſpering to him, and then lending him his ear; ſometimes he would ſpeak aloud, and ſometimes threaten him, as once he was heard in theſe words, <q rend="italic">I'le ſend you packing into <placeName rend="italic">Greece</placeName></q>, At length overcome by the importunity of the Gods, who (as he told the ſtory himſelf) did inſtantly deſire his Company, he joyn'd the <placeName rend="italic">Palatium</placeName> to the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, by a Bridge which he built over the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>; and a while after, that he might yet be nearer, he laid the foundation of a New Houſe in the Court of the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      23. Being but of mean Parentage, he would not endure to be reputed the Grandchild of <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>; and was angry if any man, either in Verſe or Oration, reckon'd him of the Family of the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName>, affirming publickly, that his Mother was begotten inceſtuouſly by <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, upon his own Daughter <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>: and not content with this abominable aſperſion upon <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, he forbad the celebration of the Holy-dayes, inſtituted to the Commemoration of his Victories in <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, and at <placeName rend="italic">Actium</placeName>, condemning them as pernicious to the Commonwealth of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Livia Auguſta</persName> his Great Grandmother, he call'd, <q rend="italic">The Gown'd Ulyſſes</q>: And in a Letter of his to the Senate, had the confidence to find fault with her extraction, charging her Grandfather by the Mother ſide, to be no better than a ſimple Decurio of <placeName rend="italic">Fundi</placeName>, though it is evident by ſeveral Records, that <persName rend="italic">Aufidius Lurco</persName> had executed very conſiderable Offices in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. His Grandmother <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> deſiring to ſpeak with him one time in private, he would not vouchſafe, unleſs <persName rend="italic">Macro</persName>, the Captain of his Guards, might be by; with which indignities and affronts he haſtned her death, (if he gave her no poiſon) as ſome people report. When ſhe <pb n="237"/> was dead he afforded her no other honour, but to look upon her body whilſt it was burning, out of his Dining-room window.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He ſurprized his Brother <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> unawares, and commanded him to be killed by a Military Tribune. <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName> alſo his Father-in-law, he conſtrain'd to cut his own throat with a Raiſor; and excuſing himſelf in both, he alledg'd, that <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName> refus'd to go to Sea with him in a ſtorm, with deſign to have ſeized upon the Government, if any diſaſter had happened to him; And that <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> for fear of being poiſoned, had taken an antidote, which he diſcover'd by his breath: whereas the truth is, <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName> could not endure the Sea, and <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> had only taken Phyſick for a Cough, which he had been troubled with long. And for his Unkle <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, he kept him alive as a ſubject only for his mockery and laughter.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      24. He committed inceſt with all his Siſters, and at all his great Feaſts they lay with their heads in his boſome by turns, whilſt his Wife was plac'd above. Of theſe Siſters (as it is verily thought) he deflowr'd <persName rend="italic">Druſilla</persName> when he was but a Boy, and was taken in Bed with her by his Grandmother <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName>, in whoſe houſe they were brought up together. Afterwards ſhe was married to <persName rend="italic">Lucius Caſſius Longinus</persName>, a Conſular man, but he made bold to take her from him by force, and lived publickly with her, as she had been his own Wife, and being ſick he appointed her Heir both of his Empire and Eſtate.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      When ſhe died, he proclaimed a vacation of all Courts and proceedings in Law; and made it Capital for any man during that time, to laugh, bath, or eat with his friends. In ſhort, not being able to comport himſelf in ſo ſenſible a <pb n="238"/> loſs, he left the Town on a ſudden in the night, and paſſing in great haſte thorow <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, he went to <placeName rend="italic">Syracuſe</placeName>, from whence in as much haſte he returned with his hair and beard all over-grown: Neither did he ever ſwear afterwards upon any occaſion whatever, either in his Orations to the People, or Army, but by the Divinity of <persName rend="italic">Druſilla</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The reſt of his Siſters he neither loved with ſo true an affection, nor uſed with ſo much reſpect, as perſons whom he had proſtituted to his own Catamites, which he made uſe of as an excuſe for condemning them ſo eaſily in the caſe of <persName rend="italic">Æmilius Lepidus</persName>, charging them with Adultery, and being privy to ſeveral Conſpiracies againſt him. Nor did he only publiſh their diſhonours that way, but he conſecrated to <persName rend="italic">Mars the Revenger</persName>, the three Daggers which they had prepar'd for his deſtruction, with a writing containing the whole Narrative of the Conſpiracy.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      25. As to his Marriages, whether he contracted, diſſolved, or continued them with more diſhoneſty, is not eaſie to determine. Being preſent at the Marriage of <persName rend="italic">Livia Oreſtilla</persName> with <persName rend="italic">C. Piſo</persName>, after the ſolemnity was over, he commanded her to be brought to him as his own Wife; yet in a few dayes he turn'd her off again, and within leſs than two years baniſh'd her, upon a ſuſpicion ſhe had been with her Husband in the mean time. Others report, that on the Marriage-day, being ſet at Dinner over againſt <persName rend="italic">Piſo</persName>, he ſent him word, <q rend="italic">That he ſhould not touch his Wife</q>; and on a ſudden riſing from the Table, he took her along with him, and the next day publiſh'd an Edict, declaring, <q rend="italic">That he was Married according to the Examples of <persName rend="italic">Romulus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was enamoured alſo of <pb n="239"/> <persName rend="italic">Lollia Paulina</persName>, upon a bare relation of her Grandmothers excellent beauty, in ſo much that ſhe being with her Husband <persName rend="italic">C. Memmius</persName>, a Conſulary man, and General of the Army, he ſent for her preſently into the Province, forcing her from her Husband, and taking her to himſelf; but he not only put her away in a ſhort time likewiſe, but forbad her future matching with any man whatſoever.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Cæſonia</persName> was neither handſome nor young, and was the Mother of three Children by another man, yet being laſcivious, and addicted to all manner of luxury, he lov'd her ſo intirely, that he ſhew'd her many times to his Souldiers with her Caſſock, Target, and Helmet, habited like them, and riding on Horſe-back by his ſide; but to his Friends he went farther, and ſhew'd her naked. She being brought to Bed, he honoured her with the name of his Wife, in one day declaring himſelf her Husband, and the Father of the Child, which he call'd <persName rend="italic">Julia Druſilla</persName>, and having carried her round to all the Temples of the Gods, he put her into the armes of <persName rend="italic">Minerva</persName>, to whom he recommended her for education.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Neither was there any thing more aſſur'd him ſhe was his Daughter, than her natural fierceneſs, of which she gave already ſufficient indications, by ſcratching and clawing the eyes and faces of the little Children her play-fellows.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      26. After what we have related, it were vain to add how he treated his Friends. <persName rend="italic">Ptolomeus</persName> the Son of King <persName rend="italic">Juba</persName>, his Coſen-German, (for he was Grandſon alſo to <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> by his Daughter <persName rend="italic">Selene</persName>) and eſpecially <persName rend="italic">Macro</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Ennia</persName>, by whoſe aſſiſtance he gain'd and govern'd the Empire, were all of them put to death, in recompence of their affinity and good ſervices.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Nor was his reſpect and mode<pb n="240"/>ration greater toward the Senate; ſome of them perſons of quality, who had exercis'd the higheſt Offices in the Commonwealth, he ſuffer'd to run in their Robes by his Chariot ſide twenty miles together, and ſtand upon their legs waiting on him whilſt he was at Supper, ſometimes at one end of the Table, ſometimes at another, with Napkins before them as they had been his Servants. After he had murder'd others in private, he caus'd them to be cited, and call'd for as they had been alive, and a few dayes after pretended they had made away themſelves.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The Conſuls having forgot to publiſh an Edict for the Celebration of his Birthday, he turn'd them out of their Commands, ſo that for three days the Republick was without that Soveraign Magiſtrate. One of his Quæſtors being but named in a Conſpiracy, he order'd his Clothes to be pull'd off, and him to be laſh'd ſoundly with Rods, whilſt the Souldiers ſtood upon his Clothes, that they might ſtand the more firm, and have the better advantage to chaſtiſe him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      With the ſame pride and inſolence he handled the reſt of the Orders. Being diſturb'd by the noiſe which they made, who took up their places in the Circus at midnight, that they might pay nothing for them, he made them all be driven out with Cudgels; in which tumult there were above twenty <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knights, and as many Ladies, cruſh'd to death, beſides an innumerable company of the common people. Taking great pleaſure in ſowing diſcord betwixt the Gentry and the common people, he order'd his Stage plays and Comedies to begin ſooner than was uſual, with deſign that the Gentlemens places might be taken up be<pb n="241"/>fore they came, by the moſt vile and abject of the people.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      In the Combates of his Gladiators, when the Sun was hotteſt and moſt inſupportable, he caus'd the Curtains to be drawn open, and commanded that no body ſhould ſtir out. And having inverted the uſual Orders obſerv'd in the Election of the perſons which were to fight with the Beaſts, he ſubſtituted old miſerable Creatures in their places, ſuch Gladiators as had never been Criminals, or happily eſcap'd thoſe encounters before, and ſometimes poor Houſe-keepers, for having but the leaſt blemiſh or imperfection in their bodies; otherwhiles cauſing the publick Granaries to be ſhut up, he brought dearth and famine upon the people in extremity.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      27. The cruelty of his nature appear'd yet more, by theſe actions following. Obſerving it very chargeable to feed the Wild Beaſts which were kept to be baited, he mark'd out ſeveral Malefactors to be given to them; for viſiting his Priſons in perſon, he rang'd the Priſoners before him in a Gallery, and ſtanding himſelf in the midſt, he gave order to take away all, <foreign rend="italic">à Calvo ad Calvum</foreign>, from ſuch a Bald-pate (as he pointed to) to another, and to throw them to the Beaſts, without the leaſt reſpect to the quality of their Crimes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      A certain perſon having devoted himſelf to the Combate of the Gladiators for <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName>'s recovery, he forc'd him to make good his Vow, was preſent himſelf when he fought at ſharps, and would not ſuffer him to retire till he had got the Victory, and all the people had interceded for his diſmiſſion. Another having vowed to die upon the ſame condition, and being not over-forward in performing his promiſe, he caus'd him to be adorned with <pb n="242"/> Herbs and Ribbands like a Victim, and in that manner to be delivered to the Boyes, who requiring the accompliſhment of his Vow, as they hurried him along the ſtreets, threw him at laſt down a Precipice, and killed him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Nay ſo great was his inhumanity towards ſeveral perſons of good quality and Eſtate, that having mark'd them with hot Irons, he condemn'd them either to the Mines, to the reparation of the High-wayes, to the Combate with Beaſts, (ſhutting them up in cloſe low places, where they were forc'd to crawle on all four, like the Beaſts they were to fight with) or elſe ſaw'd them through the middle with a Saw. Nor was it for any weighty or grievous offence they ſuffer'd in this nature, but upon trifling occaſions, as, if they had not lik'd any of his Shows, or had never ſworn by his Genius.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He conſtrain'd the Parents to be preſent many times, and aſſiſtant at the Execution of their own Children: One of them pretending ſickneſs upon a time, and deſiring to be excus'd he ſent him a Litter: Another coming freſh from the murder of his Son, he made him ſit down at his Table, and entertain'd him with all poſſible pleaſantneſs and mirth, as if he had deſign'd to divert him. The Maſter of his Sword-fights, and Beaſt-baitings, having diſpleas'd him, he caus'd him to be beaten with Chains in his preſence for ſeveral dayes together, not permitting him to be quite diſpatch'd till offended with the ſmell of his putrified Brain, he could endure him no longer. He caus'd the Author of a <foreign rend="italic">Latine</foreign> Farce, to be burnt in the midſt of the Amphitheatre, only for a witty Verſe which was capable of a double interpretation. A <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight alſo being leading to the Wild Beaſts by his appointment, and crying out as he went along, <q rend="italic">He was innocent, he was innocent</q>; he caus'd him <pb n="243"/> to be brought back to have his tongue cut out, and then return'd him again to the place of Execution.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      28. Having called home a perſon who had been baniſhed a long time, he demanded of him how he had ſpent his time in his baniſhment, who replying in flattery, <q rend="italic">I pray'd to the Gods continually, that <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> might die and you ſucceed him in his Empire, as is hapned ſince.</q> He imagined the reſt which remained in exile prayed as heartily for his death, and upon that bare imagination, ſent officers on purpoſe about the Iſlands, to put them all to the ſword. A fancy coming into his head to ſee ſuch a Senator mangled and flaſh'd, he ſuborn'd certain perſons, ſome to fall upon him as he entred the Court, to call him <q rend="italic">Enemy to the State</q>, and ſtabbing him with their Styletto's to deliver him over to the reſt of their companions to be cut in pieces, nor could his cruelty be ſatiated till his Members and Bowels, after they had been drawn about the Streets, were brought before him, and piled up into a heap.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      29. And if he was barbarous in his actions, he was little better in his words; He was wont to ſay There was nothing in this nature he commended ſo much as (in his own words) his <foreign rend="italic">adiatrepſian</foreign>, or unrelenting at the ſight of Executions. His Grandmother <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> admoniſhing one day; as if his diſobedience had been nothing at all, <q rend="italic">Remember</q> (ſays he) <q rend="italic">I may do what I pleaſe, with whom I pleaſe.</q> Having a deſign to poiſon his own brother, and ſuſpecting he uſed Antidotes, <q rend="italic">How</q> (ſays he) <q rend="italic">is there any Antidote againſt <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>?</q> Having baniſh'd his Siſters, he threatned them, <q rend="italic">That he had Swords as well as Iſlands.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      A Prætorian Citizen, who by reaſon of an indiſpoſition, had got leave to retire into the Iſle of <placeName rend="italic">Anticyra</placeName> deſiring <pb n="244"/> to have his leave prolong'd, was ſo far from obtaining his petition, that <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> commanded him to be killed, adding withal, <q rend="italic">That letting of blood muſt of neceſſity do him good, who had taken Hellebore ſo long without any ſucceſs.</q> Every tenth day he ſigned Warrants for the Execution of what priſoners he thought good, which he called Clearing of his Accounts. Having at on time condemned certain <placeName rend="italic">Gauls</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Greeks</placeName> together, he cryed out by way of exſultation, <q rend="italic">Gallo Græciam ſeſe ſubegiſſe, That he had ſubdued <placeName rend="italic">Galligræcia</placeName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      30. He took great delight to kill people by degrees, not on a ſudden, or at one blow, but with little and reiterated ſtrokes, that according to his uſual Expreſſion, <q rend="italic">They might be ſtruck ſo, as they might be ſenſible of their death.</q> Being miſtaken (upon a time) in the name of a man, and cauſing him to be executed inſtead of another, when he underſtood his errour; <q rend="italic">'Tis no matter</q> (ſays he) <q rend="italic">he deſerved it as well as the other.</q> In ſhort, ſo unlimited and boundleſs was his inhumanity, he would often make uſe of that expreſſion of the old Tragedian, <q rend="italic">Oderint dum metuant, Let them hate me as they pleaſe, ſo they do but fear me.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He upbraided the whole Senate at once, as the Creatures and dependants of <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>, or betrayers of his Mother, and Brothers; and producing ſuch papers as he pretended was burnt, he juſtified the ſeverity of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, as but neceſſary upon ſo many informations. The Gentry alſo he twitted in the Teeth with their too immoderate devotion to Spectacles, and Stage-plays. Being highly offended with the people for favouring his adverſaries, he cryed out, <q rend="italic">Would to God the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> had but one neck.</q> <persName rend="italic">Tetrinius</persName> being accuſed of Theft, he affirmed, <q rend="italic">They were all Thieves which accuſed him.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Five of thoſe Gladiators who <pb n="245"/> uſed to fight with Nets in a certain kind of Coats, having yielded without fighting to the ſame Number of <foreign rend="italic">Secutores</foreign> or followers, he commanded them to be ſlain, but one of the five ſnatching up his arms, kill'd all the Conquerours, which <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> look'd upon as a cruel action, lamented in a publick Edict, and curs'd all thoſe which had patience to ſee it.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      31. Beſides this he uſed frequently to complain of the unhappineſs of his time, <q rend="italic">Becauſe not afflicted with any conſiderable calamity, to make it remarkable</q> Lamenting <q rend="italic">That the Reign of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> was memorable, for the overthrow of <persName rend="italic">Varus</persName>; <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> his, for the fall of the Amphitheatre at <placeName rend="italic">Fidenæ</placeName>, but ſuch was his unfortunate proſperity, he was in great danger to be forgotten;</q> in ſo much that he many times wiſh'd for the deſtruction of ſome of his Armies, Famine, Peſtilence, Fire, or ſome ſuch opening of the Earth, as would ſwallow up a good luſty proportion of his people.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      32. When he was even in his ſports or entertainments, he uſed the ſame wildneſs both in his words and actions. Whilſt he was at Dinner or Collation, he many times cauſed ſerious matters to be extorted with torments before his face, and ſome Criminals to have their heads cut off by a Soldier who had great skill and dexterity in that recreation. At <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName> when he dedicated the bridge (which as we ſaid before was his own invention) inviting ſeveral perſons which ſtood upon the banks, and making ſigns to them to come to him, on a ſudden he threw them all over into the Sea; ſome of them endeavouring to lay hold upon the Helms, he made them be thruſt off with their Oars and their Hooks.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      At a publick feaſt in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, a ſervant having ſtoln a thin ſilver plate from the Tables, he delivered him preſently to the <pb n="246"/> Hang-man, that cutting off his hands, and hanging them about his neck, with an inſcription of his crime pin'd upon his Breaſt, he might lead him about the ſeveral Tables in that poſture, on purpoſe to be ſeen. One of the Fencers called <foreign rend="italic">Myrmilliones</foreign> playing at foines with him in jeſt, and falling at his feet by way of Complacency, he took him at the advantage and ſtabb'd him with a dagger, then taking a branch of Palm in his hand, he ran up and down exſulting, as he had conquered him indeed.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      A Sacrifice being brought to the Altar, and ready to be offered, he came himſelf to the Altar in the habit of a Prieſt, and lifting up the Mallet as he would have knock'd down the Beaſt, he knock'd an Officer on the head which ſtood by with the Knife. Falling ſuddenly into a great laughter as he was one night at Supper, the Conſuls who ſat near him, deſired him mildly to know the reaſon, <q rend="italic">For what think you</q> (ſays he) <q rend="italic">but to consider that I can have both your throats cut, with the least nod of my head.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      33. Amongſt the reſt of his merriments, as he ſtood by the Image of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, he ask'd <persName rend="italic">Apella</persName> the Tragedian, which of them two he thought the moſt auguſt, and finding him heſitate, he cauſed him to be whipp'd, Commending his voice whilſt he was crying for mercy, and proteſting it was ſweet even in the midd'ſt of his groans. He never took his Wife or Miſtriſs about the neck, but he had this ſaying, <q rend="italic">As ſmooth and as lovely as this is, I can take it off when I pleaſe.</q> And did many times proteſt, <q rend="italic">That he would rack <persName rend="italic">Cæſonia</persName>, but he would know what it was, made him love her ſo entirely.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      34. Neither was the envy and malice inferiour to the cruelty and pride which he exerciſed againſt perſons almoſt of all ages. The Statues of illuſtrious <pb n="247"/> men which <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> (finding the Court of the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> not large enough to contain) had removed into the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martius</placeName>, he batter'd and defac'd in ſuch manner, that they could never be put together again, ſo as to make their inſcription legible. Beſides which he order'd no Statues or Images ſhould be ſet up for any man living, but by his expreſs Order and Authority.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      It was once in his thoughts to have ſuppreſt <persName rend="italic">Homers</persName> works; <q rend="italic">For why?</q> (ſaid he) <q rend="italic">ſhould not I have as much liberty as <persName rend="italic">Plato</persName>, who baniſh'd him out of his Common-wealth.</q> He wanted not much alſo of throwing the Images and Writings of <persName rend="italic">Virgil</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Titus Livius</persName> out of all Libraries, looking upon the firſt, as a man of no wit, and as little learning; and upbraiding the other, with his verboſity and negligence in his Hiſtory. And as to the Lawyers (as if he meant to take away all uſe of their knowledg, and cunning) he was often heard to ſay, <q rend="italic">He would certainly bring things to that paſs, that they ſhould have nothing to ſay, but what he thought Equitable and Juſt.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      35. He took away the antient badges of honour, from the nobleſt Families of the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName>; as from <persName rend="italic">Torquatus</persName>, the Chain, from <persName rend="italic">Cincinnatus</persName>, the lock of Hair, from <persName rend="italic">Cn. Pompeius</persName> of very antient extraction, the Title of <persName rend="italic">Great</persName>. <persName rend="italic">Ptolomy</persName>, (of whom I have ſpoken before) being call'd by him out of his Kingdome, and at his arrival received with great honour, as he entred into the Theatre one day to behold the Plays which <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> exhibited to the people, being obſerved to draw the Eyes of the whole houſe upon him by the luſtre of his purple Caſſock, the Emperour taking notice of it, caus'd him to be ſlain without any other provocation.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      As often as he met any perſons that were comely, or had handſome heads of hair, he caus'd the hinder part of their heads to be <pb n="248"/> ſhaved, on purpoſe to deform them. A certain Gentleman called <persName rend="italic">Eſius Proculus</persName>, whoſe Father had been firſt Captain of his Guards, was ſo perſonable a man, and ſo eminent for the tallneſs of his Stature, that he was called <foreign rend="italic">Coloſſeros</foreign>, or the lovely <foreign rend="italic">Coloſſus</foreign>; <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> envying him that honour, as he was beholding their Plays, cauſed him to be pulled down out of the Gallery into the Pit, and conſtrained him to fight immediately with a <placeName rend="italic">Thracian</placeName> firſt, who was armed but lightly, then with another who had both Sword and Buckler, and having got the victory againſt them both, he caus'd him to be pinnion'd, ty'd faſt, and dirty old Clothes to be put upon him by force; after which, he order'd him in that poſture to be led about the ſtreets, as a ſpectacle to the Women, and his throat to be cut when he had done.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In ſhort there was no perſon of ſo mean and abject a condition, whoſe good fortunes he not only envyed but oppoſed. The King <persName rend="italic">Nemorenſis</persName> having enjoyed and executed the Sacerdotal dignity for ſeveral years, he could not ſuffer him any longer, but without any other occaſion rais'd him up a Competitor, more Maſterly than he. Being preſent at a publick Spectacle, and obſerving one <persName rend="italic">Porius</persName> a Chariotier to receive an extraordinary applauſe, for having manumitted a ſlave of his, who had fought a prize with ſucceſs, he was ſo highly diſpleaſed, he flung himſelf out of the Theatre in a fury, and his foot catching by accident in his Gown, he fell down tumbling from one ſeat to another, crying out with indignation, <q rend="italic">That the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> (Lords of all other Nations) gave more honour to a pitiful Fencer, than to Conſecrated Princes, nay than to himſelf, who was then present before them.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      36. He regarded neither his own Chaſtity nor <pb n="249"/> other peoples. It is ſaid he maintain'd a moſt infamous commerce with <persName rend="italic">M. Lepidus</persName> <persName rend="italic">Mneſter</persName> the Mimmick or Buffon, and with other perſons alſo who were left with him in hoſtage. <persName rend="italic">Valerius Catullus</persName>, a young Gentleman of a Conſular Family, being weary of his continual embraces, cry'd out publickly, that he was unnaturally abus'd by him, and that he had tyred him out quite with his abominable Sodomy. Beſides his inceſt with his Siſters, and his notorious amours with <persName rend="italic">Pyrallis</persName> a common Proſtitute, there was ſcarce a Lady of any quality extraordinary, which eſcap'd him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His way was, to invite them with their Husbands to Supper, and then commanding them to march by before him in turns: He conſider'd them carefully, like a Horſe-Courſer, lifting up their heads with his hand, when the modeſty of any of them would not ſuffer them to hold them up themſelves; Having pleas'd his Fancy, he took the perſon he lik'd beſt and went out of the room, a while after he would return, with the marks of his immodeſty upon him, and without the leaſt ſhame or remorſe, commend or diſcommend her publickly; reckoning up the defects or perfections of her body, and telling all the ſhameful particularities of their Embraces. To ſome he ſent Bills of divorce, in the name of their Husbands who were abſent, and caus'd them to be Regiſtred, and remain upon Record.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      37. In Luxury, and Riotous expence, he out-did the inventions of all the prodigals of that age; having contriv'd new ways of bathing, and found out moſt prodigious diſhes for his entertainments. His Baths were of ſweet Oyls, ſometimes hot and ſometimes cold; his Drink was Vinegar, in which the richeſt and largeſt Pearls could be got were diſſolv'd; <pb n="250"/> and his Bread and meat of pure Gold, affirming, <q rend="italic">That a man was to be either a good husband or an Emperour.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Beſides this for ſome dayes together from the top of <persName rend="italic">Julia's</persName> Tower, he caſt down a conſiderable ſum of money among the people. He built certain Galleys of Cedar wood, the Sterns adorned with precious ſtones, the Sails of divers colours, the Cabines and Galleries large, and convenient, with great variety of Vines and Apple-trees, under the ſhade of which as he ſate at dinner in the day time amongſt his Voices and Muſick, he would many times coaſt along the ſhore of <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, in great pleaſure and delight.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In all his buildings both of Palaces, and Houſes of pleaſure, he conſider'd nothing but his own fancy, and deſigned nothing ſo much, as what other people thought impoſſible. He laid his foundations where the Sea was moſt deep, he cut his way thorow rocks of the moſt impenetrable flint, he levelled Mountains, elevated plains, and all with incredible expedition, puniſhing the leaſt lazineſs or delay with preſent death; and that I may not trouble you with every particular, in leſs than a years time he conſumed that vaſt maſs of Treaſure left him by <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, which was computed at ſeven and twenty hundred Millions of Seſterces.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      38. Having drain'd and exhauſted himſelf by theſe extravagancies, and nothing left to continue them, he betook himſelf to all manner of rapine, inventing ſeveral ſorts of penalties, confiſcations, and impoſts. He deny'd that any body was legally a Citizen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, whoſe predeceſſors grant ran in theſe terms <foreign rend="italic">ſibi poſteriſque</foreign>, to him and his poſterity, unleſs he was his Son, the word Poſterity being not to be extended beyond that degree; And when the Patents of <persName rend="italic">Julius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> were produc'd; he <pb n="251"/> rejected them as ſuperanuated:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      ſuch as by any accident were grown rich, or were any way mended in their fortunes, he accuſed of having given in a falſe return of their eſtates. He made the Wills void of all the firſt Captains of the Prætorian Cohorts, from the beginning of the reign of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, to that time, unleſs they had made <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> or him their Heirs, and charg'd them with ingratitude, as alſo of all other people, if ſo much as one witneſs did but affirm that the deceas'd party deſign'd to make <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> his Heir.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The terrour of theſe proceedings oblig'd many people (which were ſtrangers) to name him their Heir among their friends; and ſeveral parents among their Children; but he call'd them Cheats and mockers for their pains, for preſuming to live on after ſuch a nuncupation, and to ſome of them he ſent poiſon'd Cakes to diſpatch them. Such cauſes as theſe he took Cognizance of himſelf, firſt reſolving upon the Fine, and then fitting in Court to hear the Caſe argued, and when the penalty was pronounc'd, then he would go away and not before.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      In theſe kinds of proceedings he was ſo impatient of delay, that by one ſentence at one time, he condemned above forty perſons, which were accuſed of ſeveral crimes, boaſting to his Wife <persName rend="italic">Cæſonia</persName> when ſhe wak'd, how much buſineſs he had diſpatch'd, whilſt ſhe was taking her afternoons nap. Having publiſh'd a ſale, he expoſ'd all the furniture which remain'd of his Spectacles and Shews, ſetting the prices himſelf ſo high, that ſome men being forc'd to buy them at ſo exceſſive a rate, and utterly ruined thereby, cut their own Veins and bled to death. All the world knows that <persName rend="italic">Apollonius Saturninus</persName>, being aſleep among the ſeats, <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> admoniſh'd the Cryer not to forget that per<pb n="252"/>ſon who had been Prætor, and made many nods to him with his head; neither would he ſuffer the Auction to be ended till <persName rend="italic">Apollonius</persName> wak'd, who (though ignorant of what had paſs'd) was forc'd for thirteen Gladiators, to pay nine Millions of Seſterces.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      39. He did as much likewiſe in <placeName rend="italic">Gaule</placeName>, where he ſold at an exceſſive rate all the Jewels, Houſholdſtuff, Servants, and all to the very Freed-men of his Siſters, after their Condemnation: But being allured thereunto by the conſideration of gain, what ever Furniture belong'd to the Old Imperial Court, he reſum'd again by Orders ſent from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, for the Carriage of which, beſides common Waggons which were to be hired, he preſs'd the very Horſes which belong'd to the Mills and Bake-houſes, in ſo much that there wanted Bread many times in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; and the Countrey Attorneys, and other perſons ingag'd in the Law, wanting their conveniences of coming up to the City, loſt their Cauſes for Nonappearance, whilſt others forfeited their Securities.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For the better diſpoſing of theſe Goods, there was no ſort of fraud or diſſimulation which he ſcrupled to uſe: Sometimes upbraiding every body with their Covetouſneſs, and that they were not aſham'd to have more Riches than he; otherwhiles he ſeem'd to repent that he had expoſ'd to private perſons, the Goods which appertain'd to the Empire. Being inform'd that a wealthy Provincial had given 200000 Seſterces to the Officers which called ſuch as dined at his Table, on condition (that by ſome fallacy or other) they would place him there among the reſt, he was not at all troubled to admit him, nor to underſtand he valued that honour at ſo high a rate. The next day, the ſame Provincial <pb n="253"/> being ſet at the place where the Sale was made, he ſent him ſome certain trifles, and order'd them to be deliver'd to him for 200000 Seſterces, with injunction to tell him, <q rend="italic">That if he brought thoſe things, he might Sup with <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>, by his own Invitation.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      40. His new and unheard of Impoſts, he levied firſt by his Publicans, or Farmers, but they gaining too much, he collected them afterwards by his Centurions, and Prætorian Tribunes; no perſon, nor no Commodity whatever eſcaping, without paying ſome Tribute or other. For ſuch Victuals as was ſold in any part of the City, the rate was certain. For all Actions or Proceſſes in Law, in what place ſoever they were commenc'd, he exacted the fortieth part of the thing in controverſie, and ordain'd a penalty for all ſuch as ſhould be convicted, either of compounding, or letting fall the Suit. He receiv'd likewiſe the eighth part of the Porters and Carriers daily gains; and from every woman that proſtituted her ſelf for money, as much as was given her for one time. It was inſerted alſo in the beginning of the Law, that not only common Strumpets and Bawds ſhould be liable to this Tribute, but Married perſons alſo, and all women which had any knowledge of man.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      41. Theſe Impoſitions being ſignified only by publick Cry, and not by Proclamation, or any thing in writing ſet up in the Streets, it happen'd many things were committed by pure ignorance, which he turn'd to his advantage; at length upon the importunate ſupplication of the people, he ſet up his Proclamation, but in ſo ſmall Characters, ſo illegible a hand, and written ſo cloſe, no man was able to read or copy it out. And that he might be in<pb n="254"/>experienc'd in no kind of Extortion, he ſet up a Brothel-houſe in his own Palace, with ſeveral Chambers diſtinct, and furniſh'd according to the dignity of the place, in which the Ladies and young Gentlemen paſs'd away their times. He ſent his Officers which knew the names of the Citizens, to all publick places in the City, to invite both young and old to thoſe recreations, of which at their entrance he receiv'd money as his intereſt, and had his Officers on purpoſe to enter every mans name in his Books, as perſons well affected to <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>, and Contributers to the advancement of his Revenue.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Playing at ſmall games, rather than ſtand out, he deſpiſed not the gain was to be gotten by Play, in which he got the more, by lying, and perjury. Having deſired one of his fellow Gameſters, to play for him upon his turn, he went out into the Courtyard belonging to his houſe, in the mean time, and obſerving two <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knights of great Eſtates paſſing accidentally by, he caus'd them both to be apprehended, and their Goods to be confiſcated, returning with joy, and boaſting when he came back, <q rend="italic">That he never had a better hand at Dice in his life.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      42. Having a Daughter born about that time, he complain'd publickly of his poverty, not only as an Emperour, but as a Father, and made bold to receive, and apply to his own uſe, all the Preſents and Contributions given by the people, towards the Education and Portion of the Child. He publiſh'd likewiſe by Edict, that he would receive Newyears-gifts the next New-year, and accordingly on the firſt of <foreign rend="italic">January</foreign>, he ſtood himſelf in the Porch of his houſe, to receive the Preſents which the people with full hands and laps poured out before him; <pb n="255"/> in fine, he was ſo inflam'd with covetouſneſs, and the deſire of money, that he would many times walk barefoot, and rowl himſelf upon heaps of Gold, which he had accumulated in a large and ſpacious room.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      43. In all his life he never was actually in the Wars, but one time, and then more by accident than deſign; for in his progreſs to <placeName rend="italic">Mevania</placeName>, to ſee the River and Forreſt of <placeName rend="italic">Clitumnus</placeName>, being advis'd to compleat the number of the <persName rend="italic">Batavians</persName>, which were then about him as his Guards, he took a fancy on a ſudden to make War upon the <placeName rend="italic">Germans</placeName>, and immediately having called his Legions and Auxiliaries to a Rendezvouz, made new Levies with great diligence, and furniſh'd himſelf with Proviſions ſo as never any before him; he put himſelf upon his journey, marching ſometimes in ſuch fury and haſte, that the Prætorian Cohorts were conſtrain'd to diſpoſe their Standards (contrary to all Cuſtom and Example) upon the backs of their Sumpters, to be brought after; other times again ſo ſlowly, and in ſuch ſtate, that cauſing himſelf to be carried in a Litter upon eight mens ſhoulders, he ſent before and commanded the neighbouring Cities, to have their High-wayes well ſwept and water'd againſt he came by, to defend him againſt the duſt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="44">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      44. As ſoon as he was once arrived in his Camp, that he might ſhew himſelf a grave and ſevere Captain, he diſmiſs'd thoſe Lieutenants (who had brought up their Auxiliaries with the lateſt from ſeveral parts) with ignominy and diſgrace. In the Muſter of his Army, he caſhier'd ſeveral old Officers, ſome of which had already ſerv'd out their time, and others within few dayes of it, pre<pb n="256"/>tending they were too old and feeble to do any ſervice.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He retrench'd the rewards of the Veteran Souldiers, and having reproach'd them with their covetouſneſs, he reduc'd their Aſſignations when they were emerited, to ſix thouſand Seſterces: Having perform'd nothing in this mighty Expedition, more than the receiving of <persName rend="italic">Adminius</persName> the Son of <persName rend="italic">Cinobellinus</persName> King of <placeName rend="italic">Great Britain</placeName>, into his protection, who being baniſh'd by his Father, was fled to him with a pitiful party. Nevertheleſs he forbore not to write Letters to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, full of vanity and triumph, as if he had conquer'd and poſſeſs'd himſelf of the whole Iſland; enjoyning the Meſſengers which carried them to go directly thorough the Market-place to the Court, and not to deliver them to the Conſuls, but in the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, and in a full Senate.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="45">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      45. Not long after having no other Martial imployment, he commanded certain of his <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> Guards to croſs the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, and hiding themſelves till he had dined, to return then in a great tumult and hurry, with an Alarm that the Enemy was at hand; which being accordingly perform'd, he ran immediately with ſome few of his friends, and a ſmall party of his Prætorian Horſe into a Neighbouring Wood; where having cut down the branches of Trees, and adorned themſelves with them as if they had been Trophies, he returned by Torchlight with great courage, reproaching them with timidity and lazineſs, who omitted to follow him. But for his Comerades who went along with him, and had indured the brunt of the day, he honoured them with a new ſort of Crowns, diſtinguiſh'd from the other, by ſeveral figures of the Sun, Moon, and Stars, and called them for more parti<pb n="257"/>cular diſcrimination, <foreign rend="italic">Exploratorias</foreign>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Another of his Noble Atchievements was this, certain hoſtages being by his appointment taken violently from a place where they were at School, and ſent privately before; being at Supper when the News was brought him, he pretended to be ſo much concerned for their eſcape, that he aroſe ſuddenly from the Table, and mounting immediately he purſued them with a conſiderable party of horſe, as if they had been fugitives, and having taken them by great fortune, he brought them back again in Chains, expreſſing himſelf in this enterlude no leſs idle and intemperate, than in the former. Being ſate down again to Supper, thoſe perſons which brought him word that his Army was ready, and drawn up, he commanded them to ſit down as they were, in their arms, and advis'd them in a Verſe of <persName rend="italic">Virgil</persName>,
      <q rend="italic">Durarent, Secundiſque rebus ſe ſervarent.</q>
      <q rend="italic">To've patience, and reſerve their ſwords, Till fortune better things affords.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      And at the ſame time he put forth a moſt ſharp and ſevere edict againſt the Senate, and people, reproaching them, <q rend="italic">That whilſt <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> was fighting, and expoſ'd to ſo many dangers, they indulg'd their riotous feaſtings and could not abſtain from their divertiſements both in the Circus, Theatres, and all the houſes of pleaſure about the Town.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="46">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      46. Laſt of all having drawn up his Army, (as it had been for the Final determination of the War) he march'd them down to the Sea-ſhore, and having diſpoſed his Artillery and Machines to the beſt advantage, as if <pb n="258"/> which no man could imagine, he commanded them on a ſudden to fall a gathering of Cockles, and to fill their laps, and head-pieces with them, calling them the ſpoils of the Ocean, due to the Palace, and Capitol; and as a token of Victory, he caus'd a high Tower to be erected, from whence as from a watch Tower, by ſetting up lights, Ships might be direct-ed to Steer their Courſe in the night; and after-wards having proclaimed a largeſs to the Soldiers of a hundred Deniers a piece, as if he had outdone the liberality of all his Predeceſſors; <q rend="italic">Now go your ways</q> (ſays he) <q rend="italic">and be merry, Go your ways and be rich.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="47">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      47. After ſo honourable an expedition, he thought of nothing but preparation for his triumph, beſides his priſoners, and ſome few fugitive Barba-rians, for the greater Magnificence of his Pomp, he not only choſe the propereſt and moſt ſightly of the <placeName rend="italic">French</placeName>, but he ſelected ſome of the Nobles and principal perſons of that Nation, compelling them to colour their hair red, to let it grow long, to learn the <foreign rend="italic">German</foreign> language, and take upon them their barbarous names. He commanded likewiſe that the Galleys, in which he had put out to Sea, ſhould be convey'd to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and for the moſt part by land. He writ alſo to his Officers, <q rend="italic">That they ſhould prepare for his Triumph with as little expence, as was poſsible, but yet with as much pomp and magnificence as ever, eſpecially ſeeing every mans eſtate was at their mercy and diſpoſing.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="48">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      48. Before his departure from this Province, he entred upon the moſt wicked and bloody-deſign which had ever been heard of, and it was to mur-der all thoſe Legions who had mutinied after the death of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and as it were beſieged his Fa-ther <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, and himſelf as then but an infant. <pb n="259"/> No ſmall matter it was to perſwade him from de-ſtroying them every one, but he could never be di-verted by all the importunity could be us'd, from his reſolution of killing every tenth Man; in which he perſiſted ſo obſtinately, that having called them together without their arms, as it were to an Ha-rangue, he cauſed them to be ſurrounded by a Bo-dy of Horſe, well armed;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But obſerving that his deſign was ſuſpected, and that many of them ſlipt away to recover their arms, in caſe of any vio-lence, he fled out of the Aſſembly, and went imme-diately to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, turning all upon the Senate, and threatning to revenge on them the ignominious re-ports which were ſpread of him; complaining a-mongſt other things, that he was by their fault de-frauded of his Triumph; though not long before, he had forbad them upon pain of death for med-ling, or concerning themſelves at all, in any of his honours.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="49">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      49. Being encountred on the way by Ambaſſa-dors, from that moſt conſiderable Order, with their humble requeſt to him, to make haſte: <q rend="italic">I will come,</q> (ſays he) <q rend="italic">I will come, and bring this along with me,</q> clapping his hand ſeveral times upon the Hilt of his Sword. By an Edict alſo he declared, <q rend="italic">That he would return, but it ſhould be only to the Gentry and Commons, who deſired it;</q> as to the Senate, he would be neither a Prince, nor Citizen for the future;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and for-bad any of the Senators to meet him: in this man-ner either omitting his triumph quite, or deferring it to another time, he contented himſelf to enter into the City on foot, by way of Ovation on his Birth day, without any further Ceremony. With-in four months after, he came to his end, having attempted and perpetrated moſt notorious cruel- <pb n="260"/> ties, and deſign'd greater, had he not been prevent-ed. He reſolved to have removed his Court to <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName> firſt, and then to <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, but it was after he had model'd the two principal Orders (of Senators and Gentlemen) and cut off ſuch of them as he thought convenient to deſtroy.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      And that no body might doubt of the verity of this re-port, there were two books found in his Cabinet, one with the Title of <foreign rend="italic">Gladius</foreign> the Sword, the other of <foreign rend="italic">Pugio</foreign> the Dagger, both of them containing the marks and names of ſuch perſons as he deſigned for execution. There was found likewiſe amongſt the reſt of his ſtores, a large Cheſt of ſeveral forts of Poiſons, which after his death being by <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> his Orders thrown into the Sea, prov'd of that vio-lent malignity, they infected the Waters, and kil-led abundance of the fiſh, as appear'd the next Tide by what were caſt up upon the ſhore.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="50">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      50. His Stature was tall, his Complexion pal-lid, his proportion irregular, having a fat groſs bo-dy, with a neck and thighs immoderately ſlender; his eyes and his temples were hollow, his forehead large and grim, his hair thin, eſpecially on the Crown: In all other parts of his Body, it was ſhag-ged and long. Whereupon as he paſt by at any time, it was taken as a hainous and Capital of-fence, to look down upon him from any high place, or to name a Goat upon any occaſion whatever. His viſage was naturally fierce, and ſevere, yet he endeavoured with all poſſible induſtry to make it worſe, compoſing it and ſetting it by a glaſs, to diſcover in which poſture it was moſt horrid and terrible.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was neither healthful in body nor mind. When he was but a boy he had the falling ſickneſs, in his youth patient of labour, and travel <pb n="261"/> yet ſo as he would be taken ſometimes with fainting fits, ſuch as diſabled him to go, ſtand, or hold up his head. The infirmity of his mind he was ſo ſen-ſible of likewiſe, in ſo much that he reſolv'd to retire for the purging his brain. It is believed by ſome people he was poiſoned by his Wife <persName rend="italic">Cæſonia</persName> with a Philtre, or love-potion, which took away his Wits.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He was much troubled for want of ſleep, never reſting above three hours in a night, and that not over quietly, but fearful, ſubject to dreams, and odd imaginations, amongſt which he fanci-ed once, he ſaw ſomething in the ſhape of the Sea, which talk'd and diſcours'd with him; wherefore he paſt a great part of the night in continual diſtur-bance, ſometimes ſitting right up in his bed, ſome-times riſing and wandring up and down the Galle-ries, longing and praying for day.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="51">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      51. Nor will it be improper if to the weakneſs of his mind, I attribute ſeveral of his vices, as his in-comparable confidence, and his inexpreſſible fear; for though he regarded not religion, nor ſcrupl'd the contemning of the Gods, yet at the leaſt thunder or lightning he ſhut his Eyes, and pull'd his head un-der the Clothes; but if the Claps were extraordi-nary, he leap'd out of a ſudden in his ſhirt, and hid himſelf under his bed. In a Voyage into <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, ha-ving mock'd and derided the miracles in other pla-ces, he was ſo frighted at the ſmoak and noiſe of Mount <placeName rend="italic">Etna</placeName>, that he had not courage enough to ſtay at <placeName rend="italic">Meſſana</placeName> to run away by day.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was a great man alſo in threatning the Barbarians, yet be-ing on his March on the other ſide of the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, and hapning in his Chariot in a ſtrait lane where his Squadrons were forc'd to crowd to get through; One of his attendants ſaying, <q rend="italic">That ſhould the Ene-</q> <pb n="262"/> <q rend="italic">my appear, their Confuſion would be great;</q> he left his Litter, took horſe, and turning immediately to the Bridges, finding them ſtopt with the Servants and Baggage, and not being able to attend one mo-ment, he made them hand him from one to another, and convey him over their heads.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      A while after, underſtanding the revolt of the <placeName rend="italic">Germans</placeName>, he ſeiz'd upon all the Ships he could get, in order to his eſcape; comforting himſelf in this, that he ſhould keep his tranſmarine Provinces, though the Enemy ſhould poſſeſs himſelf of the <placeName rend="italic">Alpes</placeName>, (as the <persName rend="italic">Cim-brians</persName> had done) or of the City it ſelf, as the <persName rend="italic">Senones</persName> had formerly. And I do verily believe, his puſillanimity and want of courage, gave occa-ſion to thoſe which kill'd him, to pretend to the Souldiers who were ready to mutiny, that he had ſlain himſelf, upon the news of the ill ſucceſs of his Army.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="52">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      52. Neither his Clothes, nor his Shoes, or other Ornaments, were after the faſhion of a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName>, or Citizen, or man, or indeed of humane condition; He appear'd in publick many times in a figur'd Mantle, adorned with precious Stones, over a Robe with long ſleeves, and rich Bracelets upon his wriſts; ſometimes he would be ſeen in Silks, or Fardingales, in Pantofles, or Buskins; otherwhiles in Broges, like the common Souldiers, and anon in Pumps, or Pinſons, after the faſhion of women. For the moſt part he appear'd with the Enſigns of the Gods, as with a golden Beard, holding either Thunder, a Trident, or a Caduceus in his hand, and ſome-times in the very habit of <persName rend="italic">Venus</persName>. He aſſum'd his Triumphal Ornaments, even before he began his Expedition, and wore them all the while it continued; and now and then he wore the <pb n="263"/> Corſlet of <persName rend="italic">Alexander the Great</persName>, which he had caus'd to be taken for that purpoſe out of his Tomb.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="53">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      53. He gave himſelf but little to Philology, va-luing nothing amongſt all the liberal Arts, in com-pariſon of Eloquence, which he ſtudied very much, though he had a natural fluency and dexterity of tongue; eſpecially if he were to declame againſt any one, and was angry, he had words and ſenſe at will. His voice and pronuntiation was ſo good, he was heard at a great diſtance; and his zeal and vehemence ſuch, he could not ſtand ſtill in a place whilſt he was ſpeaking:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      When he was to make an Oration, he would threaten, <q rend="italic">To let fly at them with the darts of his lucubrations.</q> He was ſo great a de-ſpiſer of the ſmooth and polite way of writing, that he ſaid of <persName rend="italic">Seneca</persName>, a perſon of much reputation in thoſe times, <q rend="italic">That his Writings were meer ſtrong lines, and like Sand without Lime.</q> It was his cu-ſtom to write Anſwers to ſuch Orators as had per-form'd with applauſe, and to undertake the accu-ſations or defences of the moſt conſiderable Crimi-nals before the Senate, to which he was either Friend or Foe, according as his ſtile fell out to be impetuous or otherwiſe, and invited the Gentlemen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> to come and hear him, by publick Procla-mation.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="54">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      54. He took delight likewiſe in ſeveral other Exerciſes, which he practis'd moſt ſtudiouſly: He was a Fencer, a manager of Chariots, Sung and Danc'd well; he fought well in Armes, and or-der'd his Chariot in the moſt difficult place of the Cirque. He ſuffer'd himſelf to be ſo far tranſported with Singing and Dancing, that even in the pub-lick Shews, and Theatres, he could not forbear <pb n="264"/> ſinging along with the Tragedian, and imitating the Players by way either of correction, or applauſe.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Nor when he was kill'd, was there any other viſi-ble reaſon for his appointing a Watch that night, but that by the licentiouſneſs of that time, he might take his oportunity to be the firſt upon the Stage. He Danc'd alſo very frequently in the night, and being once in that humour, he ſent for three per-ſons which had been Conſuls, out of their Beds, about three or four of the Clock in the morning: and whilſt they were trembling in apprehenſion of ſome extremity, he plac'd them aloft upon a Scaf-fold, and then on a ſudden with a great noiſe of Pipes and Caſtagnettoes, he came leaping out in a long Robe reaching down to his ankles; and at laſt dancing to the air of an excellent voice, he departed as he came. Yet this perſon, who was ſo docile and apt to every thing elſe, could never by any art be taught how to ſwim.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="55">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      The paſſion and kindneſs he had for ſuch as he lik'd, was ſo indecently fond, that he kiſs'd publickly <persName rend="italic">Mneſter</persName> the Mimick in the midſt of a Play; and if any one made the leaſt noiſe whilſt he was dancing, he caus'd him to be pull'd immediately out of his place, and ſcourg'd him with his own hand. A <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight giving ſome di-ſturbance whilſt the ſaid <persName rend="italic">Mneſter</persName> was upon the Stage, he ſent him word by a Centurion, to be gone forthwith to <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>, and from thence to carry Let-ters which he would ſend to <persName rend="italic">Ptolomy</persName> King of <placeName rend="italic">Mauri-tania</placeName>, the Contents whereof was to this purpoſe; <q rend="italic">Do not trouble your ſelf to do this Bearer either good or hurt.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      55. He gave the Command of his <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> Guards to a ſort of Gladiators, call'd <foreign rend="italic">Thraces</foreign>; but for the <foreign rend="italic">Mirmillones</foreign>, he took away their Armes. One of <pb n="265"/> them call'd <persName rend="italic">Columbus</persName>, having been victorious in a Combate, and gone off with a ſlight cut only, he caus'd poiſon to be poured into his wound, and call'd it afterwards by his name <foreign rend="italic">Columbinum</foreign>, as appear'd by the inſcription upon a Glaſs, amongſt the reſt of his poiſons. His affection was ſo great to the party of Green Coachmen, that he ſupp'd ordinarily in their Stable, and lodg'd with them. To <persName rend="italic">Cithicus</persName> a manager of Chariots, he gave at one time at a Collation, in the laſt Service amidſt the Fruit, which they us'd to carry home, two millions of Seſterces.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Nay he was ſo exorbitant in his affection to a Horſe he had, which he call'd <persName rend="italic">Inci-tatus</persName>, that the day before the Circenſian Games, he was wont to give notice to the neighbourhood by his Souldiers, that they forbore making any noiſe for fear of diſturbing him. Beſides that, his Stable was built of Marble, his Manger of Ivory, his Houſing-clothes of Purple, and a rich Collar of precious Stones which he wore for his Poictrell; he allow'd him a houſe very well furniſhed, and a Family to attend him, for no other end, but that ſuch as were invited in his name, might be received and entertained with the more mag-nificence and elegancy; and it is reported, that he had a deſign to have made his Horſe a Conſul.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="56">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      56. In the midſt of theſe extravagancies, ſeveral perſons were inclin'd to aſſaſſinate him, whilſt others were remiſs for want of opportunity; but two Conſpiracies having been diſcover'd, a third was perpetrated by the correſpondence of two perſons, who communicated their deſign with the moſt conſiderable Freed-men, and Officers of his Guards; who embrac'd it the more willingly, be- <pb n="266"/> cauſe they found themſelves named (though falſly) as partakers in another Conſpiracy, and per-ceiv'd they were not only ſuſpected, but hated by him: for he had drawn the Odium of the people upon them exceedingly, when ſetting them by him, with his Sword naked in his hand, he proteſted publickly, <q rend="italic">That if they thought him wor-thy of death, he was ready to lay down his life with all his heart.</q> After which time he ceas'd not to accuſe them one to another, and to create jea-louſies and animoſities among them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      It being re-ſolv'd to attaque him during the Palatine Games, as he went out of the Theatre to Dinner, <persName rend="italic">Caſſius Chærea</persName> Tribune of one of the Prætorian Co-horts, deſired the firſt part in the Action, in re-venge of the continual affronts he receiv'd from him: for though he was ancient, and well ſtricken in years, yet <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> in moſt oppro-brious manner abus'd him, as wanton and effe-minate; coming to him one while for the word, he gave him (by way of mockery) <persName rend="italic">Priapus</persName>, or <persName rend="italic">Venus</persName>: And when he addreſs'd himſelf to him, to give him thanks for any thing, he thruſt out his hand for him to kiſs, but it was alwayes in a moſt obſcene and immodeſt form.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="57">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      57. His death was foretold by many remark-able Prodigies: As by his order they were pulling down the Statue of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, to convey it to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, on a ſudden the Image fell into ſuch a laughter, that the Scaffolds fell down, and the Workmen ran away in confuſion; and immediately a perſon, one <persName rend="italic">Caſſius</persName> by name, appeared, affirming, <q rend="italic">That he was warned in a Dream to come thither, to ſacrifice a Bull to Ju-</q> <pb n="267"/> <q rend="italic">piter.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> at <placeName rend="italic">Capua</placeName> was ſtruck with Lightning, upon the Ides of <foreign rend="italic">March</foreign>, and the Porters Lodge belonging to the Imperial Palace at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. Some there were which conjectured, that by one of theſe Prodigies, danger was por-tended to the Maſter of the houſe from his Guards; and by the other, ſome eminent Mur-der, ſuch as had been committed in former times upon the ſame day. And conſulting <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> the Aſtrologer about his Horoſcope, he aſſur'd him, <q rend="italic">His death was moſt certainly at hand.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In like manner the Oracle at <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName> admoniſh'd him, <q rend="italic">To have a care of <persName rend="italic">Caſſius</persName></q>: upon which intimation he ſent on purpoſe to have <persName rend="italic">Caſſius Longinus</persName> (at that time Proconſul of <placeName rend="italic">Aſia</placeName>) put to death, not remembring that <persName rend="italic">Chærea</persName> was named <persName rend="italic">Caſſius</persName> too. The day before his aſſaſſi-nation, he dreamt that he was in Heaven, ſtanding by the Throne of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, and that <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> ſpurning him with the great Toe of his right foot, tumbled him down headlong to the Earth. Some accidents alſo which happen'd that very day, were look'd upon as preſages.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      As he was ſacrificing a Phænicopterus, the blood flew upon him, and beſprinkled him; <persName rend="italic">Mneſter</persName> the Mimick acted the ſame Tragedy, which <persName rend="italic">Neoptolemus</persName> acted when <persName rend="italic">Philip</persName> King of <placeName rend="italic">Mace-don</placeName> was ſlain. It happen'd again, that in a Farce, where the principal Actor making violent haſte to diſ-ingage himſelf from ſome imminent ruine, vomited blood; the Actors of the ſecond form endeavouring to do the ſame, the whole Stage became cover'd with blood: Beſides all which, the Maſque prepar'd for that night, was a repreſentation of <placeName rend="italic">Moors</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Ægyptians</placeName>, who <pb n="268"/> were to explicate and repreſent all the Fables of Hell.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="58">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      58. Upon the ninth day before the Calends of <foreign rend="italic">February</foreign>, about one a Clock in the After-noon, finding his ſtomach oppreſſed with what he had eat the day before, he was in great debate with himſelf, whether he had beſt riſe to Dinner or not; at length over-perſwaded by his Friends, he got up, and went forth. In a Cloyſter thorow which he was to paſs, certain young Gentlemen which were ſent for out of <placeName rend="italic">Aſia</placeName> to Act upon the Stage, being brought thi-ther for him to ſee, he ſtood ſtill a while to ob-ſerve and encourage them, and had not the chief of them complain'd he was cold, he would have preſently gone back, and ſeen them acted.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      What fell out afterwards, is reported two ſeveral wayes; ſome ſay, that whilſt he was in diſcourſe with theſe Boyes, <persName rend="italic">Chærea</persName> came behind him, and with his Sword gave him a mortal blow on the back part of his head, giving him theſe words as he was ſtriking, <q rend="italic">Hoc age, Think upon this</q>: after which another of the Tribunes call'd <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Sabinus</persName>, one of the Conſpirators likewiſe, ran him clear through the body. Others ſay, that the Centu-rions who were privy to the deſign, having re-moved the multitude from about him, <persName rend="italic">Sabinus</persName> went to him, as uſually, for the word, and that <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> giving him, <q rend="italic">Jupiter</q>, <persName rend="italic">Chærea</persName> cry'd out, <q rend="italic">Accipe ratum, Take it ſure</q>; and as <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> look'd behind him, <persName rend="italic">Chærea</persName> cut off his Jaw at one blow, and ſtruck him to the ground;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      where, as he lay along tumbling and gathering up his limbs, he cry'd out ſeveral times, <q rend="italic">He was ſtill alive</q>; but the reſt of the Conſpirators fell in, and diſpatch'd <pb n="269"/> him with thirty wounds, their word amongſt themſelves being, <q rend="italic">Repete, To him again</q>; in which ſome of them were ſo zealous, they ran him into the very Privities: at the firſt noiſe and alarm of the tumult, his Litter-men came in with their Litter-ſtaves to his reſcue, and preſently after them, his <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> Guards, who kill'd ſome of the Conſpirators, and amongſt them ſome innocent Se-nators alſo.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="59">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      59. He lived nine and twenty years, reigned three years, ten months, and eight dayes. His body was convey'd privately into the <placeName rend="italic">Lamian</placeName> Orchards, where being but half burnt upon a pile erected in haſte, it was cover'd over lightly with earth for the preſent; but afterwards his Siſters being return'd from their baniſhment, they took it up again, burnt it to aſhes, and ſo-lemnly interr'd it. This is moſt certain, before that was done, the Keepers of the Orchards were continually moleſted with apparitions: In the houſe where he was kill'd, there was not a night paſs'd without ſome dreadful Viſion or other, till at laſt it was burnt down to the ground. His Wife <persName rend="italic">Cæſonia</persName> was ſtabb'd alſo by a Centurion, and his Daughter (an Infant) had her brains beaten out againſt a wall.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="60">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      60. What the condition of thoſe times were, any one may collect from theſe very particulars; upon the firſt report, his death was not believ'd, it being ſuſpected to be given out by himſelf, to diſcover the affections of the people towards him. Neither had the perſons engaged in the Conſpi-racy, deſigned any other body to ſucceed him: The whole Senate was ſo unanimouſly diſpos'd to their ancient Freedom, that the Conſuls would <pb n="270"/> not call them at firſt into the Ordinary Court, be-cauſe it was call'd <placeName rend="italic">Julia</placeName>, but convented them in the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>. Some were of opinion, to aboliſh the very memory of the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName>, and to pull down their Tem-ples. And it is particularly remarkable, that all the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> whoſe firſt names were <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, died by the Sword, from that very <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> who was kill'd in the dayes of <persName rend="italic">Cinna</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>