<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>

<pb n="973"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      DRUSUS the Father of <persName rend="italic">Claudius Cæſar</persName> was firſt called <persName rend="italic">Decimus</persName>, and afterwards <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>; he was the Son of <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>, who was brought to bed of him within three Months after ſhe was married to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, by adultery with whom being his Father in Law, afterwards it was ſuppoſed he was <pb n="474"/> gotten: however it was, this <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> Verſe flew about,
      <q rend="italic">Τοῖς ὀντυχῶσι κὶ τρίμηνα παιδία.</q>
      <q rend="italic">The Happy, and men in high place
      May Children have in three Months ſpace.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      1. This <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> being Quæſtor, and Prætor, was made General of an Army, againſt the <placeName rend="italic">Rhetians</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Germans</placeName>, and was the firſt <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Captain that ever ſail'd upon the Northern Ocean. He it was who made the new and prodigious Trenches on the other ſide the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, which are called <foreign rend="italic">Foſſe Druſinæ</foreign> to this day. He defeated his Enemies ſeveral times, purſuing them into the Deſerts, and uninhabited places, neither had he given them over ſo, had he not been forbidden by a Phantaſm in the likeneſs of a Barbarian Woman (above humane ſtature) which appear'd to him, and admoniſh'd him in the <foreign rend="italic">Latin</foreign> Tongue, to give over the purſuit: For theſe ſo noble atchievements he had the honour of an Ovation, and liberty to wear the Triumphal Ornaments:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Afterwards at the Expiration of his Prætorſhip, being entred upon the Conſulſhip, he undertook a ſecond Expedition, but he fell ſick of a diſtemper, and <pb n="275"/> dyed in his Summer Camp, which was called <foreign rend="italic">Scelerata</foreign>, unfortunate, from that day: His body was carried to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> by the principal perſons of the Municipal Towns and Colonies, all the Decuries coming out to meet it, and at laſt was honourably buried in the Field of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>; The Souldiers ſetting up a Tomb for him, about which every year afterwards they were to meet upon a preciſe day, and hold their Courſes and Turnaments in honour to his Memory; and the Cities of the <placeName rend="italic">Gauls</placeName>, to make publick Proceſſions and Prayers. Beſides this, amongſt many other Teſtimonies of their affection, they ordered a Triumphal Arch of Marble to be ſet up in the <placeName rend="italic">Via Appia</placeName>, and the Surname of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> to be given to him and his Heirs.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He was thought to be a perſon no leſs Magnanimous, than civil, for beſides the vaſt Spoils and Victories he obtain'd, he expoſ'd himſelf often times, and purſued the Generals of the Enemy all over the field. Nor could he hold from profeſſing, that if ever it fell into his power, he would reſtore the Common-wealth to its priſtine Eſtate. Upon which grounds ſome there are, who imagine he was call'd back from his Province, by an Expreſs from <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and poiſon'd, for not making ſo much haſt as was required:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      which I have inſerted here, rather out of a reſolution to paſs by nothing, than that I think there is any truth or likelihood in it, ſeeing <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> loved him ſo tenderly whilſt he was living, that he alwaies made him Co-heir with the reſt of his Sons declared it long before publickly in the Senate: and when <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> was dead, in a funeral Oration which he made in his praiſe, he beg'd of the Gods, <q rend="italic">That they would ſend him ſuch Children as <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, and that they would vouchſafe him as honourable an Exit one day, as they had conferr'd upon him.</q> Nor contented with that Elegy, he cauſed an Epitaph in Verſe of his own compoſition, to be engraven upon his Tomb, beſides the Commentaries of his Life, which he writ in Proſe afterwards.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      He had ſeveral Children by <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> the Younger, but he left behind him but three, <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Livilla</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> was born at <placeName rend="italic">Lyons</placeName>, the firſt of <foreign rend="italic">Auguſt</foreign>, in the Conſulſhip of <persName rend="italic">Julius Antonius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Fabius</persName> <pb n="276"/> <persName rend="italic">Africanus</persName>, on the very day wherein an Altar was dedicated to the Memory of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>: He was called at firſt, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius Claudius Druſus</persName>, but not long after, his elder Brother being adopted into the Family of the <persName rend="italic">Julii</persName>, he took upon him the Surname of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being left an Infant by his Father, and continuing ſickly, during all his Childhood and minority, by the tediouſneſs of his Diſtemper, he was ſo infeebled, both in body and mind, that he was look'd upon as incapable of any publick imployment; for ſuch was his weakneſs, a long time after he was at age, that he was kept under the Tutelage of a Governour, of whom he complained in a book of his, <q rend="italic">As of a Barbarous perſon, who had been formerly a Groom, and was ſet over him on purpoſe to plague and chaſtiſe him upon every trivial occaſion.</q> Upon the ſcore of his indiſpoſition, he preſided in the Sword-Plays, which his Brother and he exhibited to the people in memory of their Father, wrap'd up after a new way in a Muffler, and when he aſſumed the Virile Robe, he was carried to the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> in a Litter, about midnight without any honour at all.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. Howbeit from his very Childhood he took no ſmall pains in the ſtudy of the Liberal Sciences, and gave frequent and publick teſtimonies of his proficiency in them all: Yet could he not with all his learning acquire the leaſt dignity, or extinguiſh the ill opinion conceived of him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His Mother <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> call'd him uſually <foreign rend="italic">Portentum Naturæ</foreign>, &amp;c. <q rend="italic">The prodigy of Nature, which ſhe had begun, but not finiſhed;</q> and when ſhe had a mind to upbraid any one for his dulneſs or ſtupidity, ſhe would ſay, <q rend="italic">He was a greater fool than her Son <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>.</q> Nor had his Grandmother <persName rend="italic">Auguſta</persName> any better thoughts of him, who never <pb n="277"/> ſpake to him, but unwillingly, and never admoniſh'd him, but in a ſharp, though ſhort note, or elſe by a Meſſenger on purpoſe, and when his Siſter <persName rend="italic">Livilla</persName> underſtood he was like to be Emperour, ſhe could not forbear lamenting, and publickly deteſting, the unhappy fortune of the People of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. And no wonder, for to the end that the judgment his Great Unkle <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> had of him, might more certainly appear, I have thought good in this place to ſet down ſome particulars which I have met with in his Epiſtles: <q rend="italic">I have</q> (ſays he) <q rend="italic">my dear <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>, communicated with <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> according to your deſire, about what is to be done to your Nephew <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, at the ſolemnity of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>;</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">and we are both of us of opinion, that a reſolution muſt be taken, what courſe we are to ſteer with him; If he has no weakneſs or infirmities upon him, we ought without all doubt to advance him by the ſame ſteps and degrees as his brother was rais'd; On the contrary, if we find any feebleneſs or incapacity, either in his body, or wit, we muſt not give occaſion to the World (which is too prone naturally to ſuch things) to mock and deride both him, and us otherwiſe we ſhall be in a perpetual uncertainty, if we deliberate every moment whether he be capable, or not.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">Nevertheleſs as to thoſe things in which you deſire my advice, I hold it not amiſs, if at the ſolemnity of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, he ſuperinſpects, and gives Orders for the entertainment of the Prieſts, upon condition he will ſuffer himſelf to be admoniſh'd by the Son of <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName>, (his Kinſman) who will inſtruct him, and prevent his doing any thing may be notoriouſly ridiculous.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">But I am utterly againſt his ſeeing the Circenſian Games, from ſo eminent a place as the <placeName rend="italic">Pulvinar</placeName>, becauſe being as it were in the face of the Theatre, he will be too much expoſ'd to the <pb n="278"/> Eyes of the Spectators It ſeems to me no leſs inconvenient that he ſhould go up to the Albane Mount, or remain in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> upon the Feſtivals of the <placeName rend="italic">Latines</placeName>: For, if he be able to follow his Brother to the Mountain, Why is he not as fit to have the Government of the City? Thus (my dear <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>) we have given our Judgments, which is, to come to a reſolution at once, upon the whole matter, and not to hang always in ſuſpence betwixt hope and fear. And this part of our Letter, if you pleaſe, you may ſhow to <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      Again, in another Letter, <q rend="italic">During your abſence I ſhall conſtantly invite young <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> to my Table, that he may not ſup alone with his <persName rend="italic">Sulpitius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Athenodorus</persName>. I wiſh with all my heart the poor boy would propoſe to himſelf the Example of ſome well-bred Gentleman, and imitate him in his Geſture, Habit, and Miene; For though he has no great eſteem amongſt men of deep learning, yet if his thoughts be not wandring, the nobleneſs of his heart is viſible enough.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      And in a third, <q rend="italic">Let me not live (my <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>) if I do not admire how your Nephew <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> could pleaſe me ſo fully in his Declamation, for I am not able to comprehend, how a perſon which talks ſo ill as he does, ſhould Declaim with that life and perſpicuity.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
    <p>
      Theſe imperfections were the cauſe, that <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> honoured him with nothing more than the Sacerdotal dignity of the Augurs, mentioned him in his will amongſt his Heirs in the third degree, (who were almoſt extraneous) and that not ſo much as in a ſixth part of his perſonal Eſtate, leaving him in ready Money but a Legacy only of not above 800 Seſterces.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, his Unkle by the Fathers ſide, when he deſired ſome honourable advancement or other, never gratify'd him any further, than with the Ornaments of a Conſul; and when he preſt and <pb n="279"/> importuned for any real preferment; he writ him back word only this for all, <q rend="italic">That he had ſent him forty pieces of Gold againſt the <foreign rend="italic">Saturnalia</foreign>, for Playing Money, and to lay out in the <foreign rend="italic">Sigillaria</foreign>, as he pleas'd:</q> Upon this anſwer, and not before, he laid aſide all hopes of riſing to any conſiderable imployment in the Common-wealth, whereupon he retired ſometimes to his Gardens in the Suburbs, ſometimes to a Countrey houſe he had in <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, and by his Converſation with mean and diſſolute Company, beſides the old ſcandal of lazineſs which lay upon him, he acquired the imputation of a Gameſter, and a Drunkard.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. Notwithſtanding he lived at this rate, he never wanted the honour and reſpect of the people, both in publick and private: The Equeſtrian Order choſe him their Patron twice, in buſineſs which concerned them particularly. Once when they petition'd the Conſuls to permit them to carry the Body of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> upon their Shoulders; The ſecond time, when they congratulated to them the deſtruction of <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>. Beſides this, when they ſaw him enter into the Theatre at any time, they not only aroſe and ſtood up, but they pull'd off their Mantles, and laid them by, in teſtimony of their reſpect. It was voted alſo in the Senate that he ſhould be added (extraordinarily) to the fraternity of the <foreign rend="italic">Auguſtales</foreign> (into which before him, never any was choſen but by lot) that a houſe of his which by accident had been burnt, ſhould be re-edified at the publick charge, and that he ſhould have a deliberative voice, amongſt thoſe who had been Conſuls.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> pretending his weakneſs and <pb n="280"/> imbecillity, and promiſing to make good his loſſes by the fire, out of his own liberality, That Vote, and Decree of the Senate was aboliſh'd. Yet the ſame <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> when he came to dye, named him one of his Heirs in the third rank, to a third part of this Eſtate, and left him a Legacy of about two Millions of Seſterces, beſides which he recommended him particularly to the Army, the Senate, and the People of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. At length in the Reign of <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, his Brothers Son, (who at his coming to the Empire, endeavoured to gain a reputation and intereſt among the People, by all manner of indulgence) he was firſt admitted into Office, and exercis'd the Office of Conſul with him two months together: during which Conſulſhip, it happened the firſt time he entred into the Forum with his rods, an Eagle being upon wing, came and pearch'd upon his right Shoulder. He was drawn alſo for the Conſulſhip four years after, and preſided now and then in the Spectacles and Shows, in <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> his room, receiving the acclamations and benedictions of the People, partly as he was Unkle to the Emperour, and partly as he was Brother to <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. Yet all this could not exempt him from affronts: for if he came to ſupper never ſo little of the lateſt, he was hardly admitted, and glad to take ſeveral turns about the Chamber before he could have a place to ſit down: if he took a Nap after meat (as he uſually did) the Drolls and Wits threw the ſtones of Olives and Dates at him, in ſport, ſometimes they would wake him with a Ferula, or Whip, and ſometimes put his Pumps upon his hands as he lay ſnorting, that when he awak'd, he might rub his face with them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      <pb n="281"/> 9. Neither was his life ſo quiet and ſerene, but he had his troubles and dangers like other men. As firſt, he was almoſt turn'd out of his Conſulſhip, for not ordering the Statues of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, (the Brothers of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>) to be ſet up, with that diligence as was required: After this he was divers times diſturb'd by the informations of ſtrangers, ſometimes of his own ſervants: When the Conſpiracy of <persName rend="italic">Lepidus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Getulicus</persName> was diſcover'd, being deputed amongſt other perſons into <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, to congratulate the Emperours deliverance in the name of the City; he was in no ſmall danger of his life, for <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> took it in ſo great indignity, that they ſhould ſend his Unkle to him of all people, as it were to govern a Child; that as ſome have ventured to report, he was thrown headlong into a river by his Order in the ſame habit he arrived:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      from which time forwards he never gave his opinion in the Senate, but the laſt of all thoſe which had been Conſuls, being (by way of ignominy and contempt) the laſt always which was ask'd. There was a charge brought in againſt him likewiſe, for ſetting his hand and ſeal to a forged will; and laſt of all, not being able to pay eight Millions of Seſterces, (which was his fine upon his entrance into his new Office of Prieſthood) he was driven to ſuch ſtreights, he was forc'd to abſcond, and the Officers of the Treaſury made out Proceſs, for the ſeiſing his Eſtate.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. Having paſt in this manner the greateſt part of his time, at the fiftieth year of his age, by a moſt admirable accident, he arriv'd at the Empire: Being ſhut out amongſt the reſt of the people, by the murderers of <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, upon pretence that deſiring to be private, he had order'd to clear the room; <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> withdrew into a Dining-room, called <placeName rend="italic">Hermæum</placeName>; <pb n="282"/>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      not having been long there, before he had the alarm of <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> his death, he ſtole up into a Chamber in a great fright, and hid himſelf behind the hangings, but his legs being ſeen by a common Soldier coming that way by accident, he had the curioſity to ſee who it was, and pulling him out in ſuch a fear, that he threw himſelf at his feet, he knew him, and ſaluted him Emperour: from thence he carried him to his fellow Souldiers, who were in great rage, and diſtraction, but could not reſolve what was to be done; They put him into his Litter, and (his ſervants being fled) carried him upon their Shoulders by turns, into the Camp, in no ſmall apprehenſion; The people pitying him, as he had been an Innocent going to Execution:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Being receiv'd into the Camp, he paſt that night in the Main-Guard, amongſt the Souldiers, with leſs hopes than aſſurance of good uſage: For the Conſuls, the Senate, and the Militia of the City having ſeiſed upon the Forum, and Capitol, in order to the re-aſſerting the common liberty; he was invited to the Senate by the Tribune of the People, to give his concurrence in ſuch things, as he ſhould approve, but he writ them word, <q rend="italic">He was under a force, and deſir'd to be excuſed.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The next day the Senate growing cooler in their buſineſs, by reaſon of certain differences and diſſentions amongſt them, and the continued clamors and inſtances of the common people, crying out for a ſingle perſon, and that <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> might be the man; He call'd the Soldiers together in their arms, ſuffer'd them to take an Oath of Allegiance to him, and promis'd them fifteen Grand Seſterces a piece, which was the firſt time any of the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> gave Money to the Souldiers, to bribe them to their duties.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. Being ſettled in his Empire, the firſt thing he <pb n="283"/> was moſt ſollicitous of, was to aboliſh the Memory of thoſe two days, in which the change and alteration of the Government was ſo fervently debated; wherefore he cauſed an Act of Indemnity and Oblivion to be paſt for all words, and actions whatſoever in that time; and he obſerv'd it ſtrictly; contenting himſelf with the Execution of ſome few Tribunes, and Centurions, who were Complices in the conſpiracy againſt <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, as well in terrorem to others, as becauſe he was certainly inform'd they had laid their deſigns againſt his life alſo.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      From theſe things he betook himſelf wholly to Offices of Piety and Goodneſs. The moſt common, and moſt ſacred Oath he us'd at any time, was <q rend="italic">BY AUGUSTUS</q>: He gave Order that a Decree ſhould be paſt for the giving divine honours to his Grandmother <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>, and that ſhe ſhould be allowed at the Circenſian Games, a Chariot drawn with Elephants, as <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> had before. Beſides this, he inſtituted publick Sacrifices to the Manes or Ghoſts of his parents; particularly upon the birth of his Father, Circenſian Games every year; and upon his Mothers, a Chariot, with her Image to be drawn thorow the Cirque, and the Surname of <persName rend="italic">Auguſta</persName> inſcrib'd upon it, which was refus'd by his Grandmother.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He omitted no occaſion of celebrating the Memory of his Brother, to which (beſides the ordinary formalities) he added a <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> Comedy, to be acted amongſt the reſt of the Exhibitions at <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>, where he conſtituted Judges, and gave the Crowns and Prizes, according to their ſentence and determination. Neither did he paſs by <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> without his due honours, and a moſt grateful mention and remembrance, declaring one time in an Edict, <q rend="italic">That he did with the more earneſtneſs deſire, the Nativity of his Fa<pb n="284"/>ther <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> might be celebrated, becauſe it was the ſame day on which his Grandfather <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> was born alſo.</q> He finiſh'd the Marble arch likewiſe near <persName rend="italic">Pompey's</persName> Theatre, which the Senate had order'd to be ſet up long before, but it had been neglected: And though he reſcinded and made Null all <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> his Acts, yet he would not ſuffer the day of his aſſaſſination to be plac'd amongſt the feſtival days, notwithſtanding it was the Commencement of his Authority and Empire.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. In aſſuming, and arrogating to himſelf, he was always very modeſt and ſparing; he refuſed the Title of Emperour, he rejected all extravagant honors, and celebrated the Nuptials of his daughters, and the nativity of his Grandſon in private, with the ſolemnity of his own family and no more. He never recall'd any perſon from baniſhment but by the authority of the Senate, to whom he condeſcended ſo far, as to deſire their Conſent, that he might bring the Captain of his Guards, and the reſt of his Tribunes, and the Superiour Officer along with him into the Court, and that they would ratifie and confirm what his Delegats had done, in determining of Cauſes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He ask'd leave of the Conſuls to have the power of eſtabliſhing Fairs, and Markets, in his own private Eſtate. In the hearing and examination of Cauſes, he was frequently preſent, and as diligent as if he had been a Counſeller of the Court; when the ſaid Magiſtrates exhibited any plays, or ſpectacles, he roſe up always with the reſt of the people, and honoured them with the applauſes both of his voice, and his hand.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The Tribunes of the people coming one day to attend him, when he was on his Tribunal, he excuſed himſelf to them, that there was not room enough to <pb n="285"/> make them ſit down; by which manner of deportment he gain'd ſo much upon the favour and affection of the people in a ſhort time, that upon a bare report of his being ſlain by ſurprize, in his journey to <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>, in great tumult and conſternation they ran up and down the Town, calling the Souldiers, Traitors, the Senate, Parricides; and with horrible imprecations, curſing all perſons which were acceſſary to it; nor could they poſſibly be appeaſed, till not one, or two, but ſeveral Meſſengers were produc'd at the <placeName rend="italic">Roſtra</placeName>, to aſſure them he was living, and would be amongſt them in a ſhort time.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. Yet for all this he was not free from Conſpiracies, and perplex'd not only by the plots of Parties, and particular Men; but with the miſeries and calamities of an Inteſtine War. Once there was an ordinary fellow found at midnight about his Chamber, with a Dagger in his pocket; another time two Gentlemen were apprehended in the ſtreet, armed with a Staff-Rapier, and Huntſmans Skeyn, on purpoſe to attack him, one attending as he was to come out of the Theatre, the other as he was to ſacrifice in the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Gallus Aſinius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Statilius Corvinus</persName> (the Grandchildren of <persName rend="italic">Pollio</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Meſſala</persName> the Orators) having corrupted ſeveral of his freed-men and ſervants, entred into a Confederacy with them, for the raiſing of new troubles, and making an inſurrection. The Civil war was commenc'd by <persName rend="italic">Furius Camillus Scribonianus</persName>, his Lieutenant in <placeName rend="italic">Dalmatia</placeName>; but in five days time he was deſerted by his Legions, who having taken an Oath of fidelity to him, repented immediately, upon an Omen, or Point of Religion; for when they had received Orders to march towards their new Emperour, either by ſome ſtrange accident, or ra<pb n="286"/>ther by Divine influence, it fell out ſo, that they could neither adorn their Eagles, nor remove their Enſigns from the places where they had ſtuck them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. Beſides his firſt Conſulſhip, he was Conſul four times afterwards; the two foremoſt, joyntly and immediately one after the other; the reſt, with the diſtance and interval of four years. The laſt time he was Conſul, he continued ſix months, the reſt but two only; and the third time of his Conſulſhip, he was ſubſtituted in the place of a Conſul that died, (of which there had never been any preſident in an Emperour before.) He adminiſtred Juſtice with great diligence and aſſiduity, as well after, as in the time of his Conſulſhip, neither excuſing himſelf on the dayes which were dedicated to him and his, nor ſometimes on the ſolemn Feſtivals which had been celebrated from all antiquity. He did not alwayes tye himſelf up to the letter of the Law, but temper'd the ſeverity, and moderation of their Mulcts, as in his judgment he thought equitable and juſt. For ſuch as before inferiour Judges had loſt their Actions, for want of form in their Declarations, he gave them leave to take out new Proceſs, and begin <foreign rend="italic">de novo</foreign>: and on the other ſide, if any were convict of more than ordinary fraud or colluſion, he ſtrain'd the penalty of the Law, and condemn'd them to the Beaſts.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. In the examination and deciſion of Controverſies, he was very various and unequal; ſometimes cautious, and circumſpect, otherwhiles precipitate, and raſh, and ſometimes impertinent, and like a mad-man. As he was reforming the Decuries upon a time, one of the Judges having anſwer'd to his name, and not pleaded his Exemption by the <pb n="287"/> number of his Children, he diſmiſs'd him forthwith, as a perſon too much affected with that dignity.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Another being queſtion'd by his Adverſaries before <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>, in a buſineſs betwixt him and them, and denying the Caſe to lye any where legally, but before the Ordinary Judge, <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> commanded him immediately to anſwer before him; to demonſtrate by his own Caſe, how equitable a Judge he would be in another mans. A woman being unwilling to own her Son, and the proofs of either ſide not being clear, he adjudg'd her to marry him, and by that award brought her to acknowledge him. He was ordinarily more favourable to ſuch as appear'd, and were preſent in Court, than to thoſe who were abſent, without conſidering at all whether their abſence was excuſable or not.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      One crying out publickly, at the tryal of one indicted for Forgery, <q rend="italic">Let both his hands be cut off</q>; he commanded the Executioner to be ſent for immediately, with his Hatchet and Block. Another being accus'd of an undue and illegal pretence, and uſurpation of the Rights of a Citizen, the Advocates on both ſides not agreeing whether he was to plead in the habit of a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName>, or a Stranger, he believ'd he had fallen upon a moſt exact piece of Juſtice, when he commanded, that his habit ſhould be chang'd, and that he ſhould wear a Cloak when he was accus'd, and a Gown when he made his defence. His impertinence was viſible in an affair, where he gave his judgement in writing after this manner; <q rend="italic">That he was on their ſide who had ſpoken the truth.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Theſe trifling rendred him contemptible in all places, and to all perſons wherever he came. A certain man excuſing a Witneſs, for whom <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> had ſent out of one of his Provinces, and alledging that he could <pb n="288"/> not poſſibly be preſent in time, <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> demanding the cauſe, and he diſſembling it for a while, at laſt reſolv'd him, <q rend="italic">That he was dead at <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName>.</q> Another giving him thanks that he had permitted an accus'd perſon to defend himſelf, added withal, <q rend="italic">and yet it is uſual.</q> And I have been told by antient people, that the Lawyers were wont to abuſe his patience ſo much, that as he was going down from the Bench, they would not only call him back again, but lay hold of his Gown, and ſometimes catch him by the feet; and that no body may think this ſtrange, there was a pitiful <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> Lawyer, who pleading earneſtly before him, had the impudence to tell him to his face, <foreign rend="italic">σὺ γέρων κὶ μωρὸς</foreign>, <q rend="italic">Thou art an old man, and a fool into the bargain:</q> And this is moſt certain, one of the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knights being accus'd of unnatural obſcenity with women, (though unjuſtly) and ſeeing that his Enemies (not being able to make good their charge) were forc'd to ſuborn common Strumpets to give in Evidence againſt him, (whoſe depoſitions <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> receiv'd very readily) he was not contented to upbraid him by his ſottiſhneſs and cruelty, but threw his Style and Table-book ſo heartily at his head, that he cut a great gaſh in <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> his cheek.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. He exerciſed the Cenſorſhip alſo, (which had been diſcontinued a long time, from the Cenſorſhip of <persName rend="italic">Paulus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Plancus</persName>) but with the ſame inequality, both as to his mind, and ſucceſs. In his review of the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Gentlemen, he diſmiſs'd a young Spark, who was moſt notoriouſly vitious, becauſe his Father teſtified otherwiſe, telling him only, <q rend="italic">That he had a Cenſor of his own.</q> Another who was infamous for Adulteries, and debauching of Virgins, he only admoniſh'd, <pb n="289"/> <q rend="italic">Not to give his youth ſo much liberty, or elſe to do it more warily;</q> adding withal, <q rend="italic">For why muſt I needs know who is your Miſtris?</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having at the requeſt of ſome of his familiar friends, taken off a Note of infamy which he had ſet upon ones name, he ſaid, <q rend="italic">Yet the blot may remain.</q> A conſiderable perſon, and one of the principal in the Province of <placeName rend="italic">Greece</placeName>, being ignorant of the <foreign rend="italic">Latine</foreign> tongue, he not only put him out of the number of Judges, but took away his freedom in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and reduc'd him to the condition of an Alien. Neither permitted he any body to render an account of his life, by Counſel or Proxy, but every man made his relation with his own mouth, as well as he was able. Several perſons he noted with diſgrace, (upon a new occaſion) and ſome of them when they thought little of it, becauſe without his knowledge and Paſs-port, they had preſum'd to go out of <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>. And among the reſt, one for no other reaſon, but for having accompanied a King in his Province: alledging the example of <persName rend="italic">Rabirius Poſtumus</persName> in old time, who for following <persName rend="italic">Ptolomy</persName> into <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, (though but to ſecure certain ſums of money which he owed him) was accus'd of High Treaſon.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He endeavour'd to have diſgrac'd ſeveral others, but by the great negligence of the Inquiſitors, and to his own greater diſhonour, they were found innocent: For they whom he accus'd of Cælibacy, want of Children, and Poverty; made it appear that they were Married, had Children, and Eſtates: And one there was, who being queſtion'd for ſtabbing himſelf, ſtript himſelf ſtark naked, and ſhew'd him his body to convince him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The moſt remarkable paſſages in his Cenſorſhip, were theſe: He caus'd a magnificent Chariot of Silver, wrought very richly, <pb n="290"/> and expos'd to ſale in the Street called <placeName rend="italic">Sigillaria</placeName>, to be brought, and broke in pieces before his face: He exhibited alſo twenty Edicts, or Proclamations, in one day; two of them to this purpoſe: the firſt, <q rend="italic">That in reſpect there was like to be plenty of Grapes, all people ſhould ſee their Veſſels well pitch'd.</q> The other, to let them know, <q rend="italic">That againſt the ſtinging of a Viper, nothing was ſo good as the juice of the Yew-tree.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. He never undertook but one Expedition, and that not very conſiderable; but that which put him upon it, was this; The Senate having decreed him Triumphal Ornaments, he imagined that honour beneath the Majeſty of an Emperour, and reſolving with himſelf to undertake ſome honourable Enterprize, which might entitle him to a juſt and legitimate Triumph, he choſe <placeName rend="italic">Great Britain</placeName> as the moſt convenient place, as not having been medled with ſince <persName rend="italic">Julius Cæſar's</persName> dayes, and then in a mutiny, becauſe ſeveral Fugitives were not delivered up to them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Sailing therefore from <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>, he had twice like to have been drowned by the violence of a ſtrong Southern wind, once off of <placeName rend="italic">Genoa</placeName>, and the other time near the <placeName rend="italic">Stæchades</placeName>, (which are three Iſlands within the mouth of the <placeName rend="italic">Rhoſne</placeName>:) whereupon having chang'd his deſign, and travell'd by Land from <placeName rend="italic">Marſailles</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Calais</placeName>, he croſs'd the Seas, and went from thence into <placeName rend="italic">England</placeName>; from whence he returned without any Battel or Bloodſhed, (part of the Iſland having ſubmitted within few dayes) and within ſix months time after his departure, he made his Triumph in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, with great ſplendor and magnificence;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      and that the Spectacle might be the more honourable by the confluence of people, he not only gave leave to the Governours <pb n="291"/> of Provinces to be preſent at it, but permitted ſeveral perſons which were baniſh'd, to return home, on purpoſe to behold it. Amongſt the ſpoils of his Enemies, he put a Naval Crown upon the top of his Palace, hard by the Civick, in token of his Victory over the Sea, when he croſs'd it. His Wife <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName> in her Chariot, follow'd him in his Triumph: Next her were thoſe who had acquired Triumphal Ornaments upon the ſame occaſion: The reſt followed on foot in their rich Robes garded with Purple. <persName rend="italic">Craſſus Frugi</persName> had the priviledge to be on Horſe-back, well mounted, with rich Trappings and Capariſons, himſelf in an embroydered Mantle of State, upon conſideration that this was the ſecond time he had had the honour to attend in a Triumph.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      18. He had always a particular care of the City, and eſpecially that it ſhould not be unprovided with Victuals. At what time the <placeName rend="italic">Emilian</placeName> buildings were on fire, he remain'd two nights together in the place where they made the diſtributions for Suffrages, and obſerving the Souldiers, and his familiar friends, (who were working hard to quench it) to grow weary, and unable to do any more, he cauſed the common people to be called together by the Magiſtrates, from all quarters of the City, and having plac'd Cheſts of Money before him, he exhorted them to do their utmoſt, promiſing to reward every man according to his deſert.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The barrenneſs and ſterility of ſeveral ſucceſſive years, having caus'd great dearth, he was ſtopt one day in the Forum by the multitude, and not only reviled and traduc'd, but ſo pelted with Cruſts of Bread, that he had much ado to eſcape to his Palace by a Poſtern-gate. After which he took order, <pb n="292"/> that even in Winter he had his Proviſions brought conſtantly in, giving all encouragement to the Merchants; aſcertaining their Profit, by making good any loſs they ſhould receive, by ill weather or otherwiſe; and giving great advantages to ſuch as built Ships for Traffick, according to every mans condition that built them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      19. He diſpenc'd with, and exempted them, if Citizens, from the Law <foreign rend="italic">Papia Poppæa</foreign>; he granted them, if <placeName rend="italic">Latines</placeName>, the freedom of the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName>, and allow'd their Wives the Priviledges of them which had four Children; which Conſtitutions are obſerv'd, and in force at this day.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      20. He finiſh'd ſeveral works, which were more magnificent than neceſſary: The principal of them all were the Water-work which <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> had begun, and a Sluce to let the water out of the Lake <placeName rend="italic">Fucinus</placeName>, and the Haven at <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>; though he was not ignorant that <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> had refus'd to do one of them, at the importunity of the <placeName rend="italic">Marſians</placeName>, and the other had been ſeveral times deſigned by <persName rend="italic">Julius Cæſar</persName>, but given over as a thing of too great difficulty and expence. He brought the two <placeName rend="italic">Claudian</placeName> Fountains, (one of them called <placeName rend="italic">Cæruleus</placeName>, the other <placeName rend="italic">Curtius</placeName> or <placeName rend="italic">Albudinus</placeName>) as alſo the new River of <placeName rend="italic">Anio</placeName>, in Pipes or Canals of Stone into the City, and divided them there into ſeveral large and conſiderable Ponds.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He attempted the draining of <placeName rend="italic">Fucinus</placeName> too, and with as much hope of Gain, as ambition of Glory, ſome private perſons offering to undertake it at their particular expence, if they might have the ground for their pains, when they had drain'd it. He finiſh'd the Canal hardly, and with much labour, digging ſometimes, and other whiles hewing thorow a Rock for three miles together, <pb n="293"/> in which work he imploy'd thirty thouſand men conſtantly, for eleven years together.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He made the Harbour at <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName> likewiſe, building a Mole round about it from the right hand to the left, and at the entrance ſinking the Veſſel in which the great Obelisk was brought out of <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, as a foundation for the Piles, upon which he rais'd a high Tower, according to the model of the Pharos at <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, to give light and directions to ſuch Ships as were at Sea in the night.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      21. He gave Largeſſes frequently to the people; he exhibited ſeveral magnificent Shews, not only uſual, and in the accuſtomed places, but ſome newly invented, and others that had been antiquated and loſt, which he then ſhew'd where never any were ſeen before. Having rebuilt the Theatre of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, which was burnt, he celebrated certain Games at its dedication, and gave the Signal himſelf out of a Tribunal erected in the Orcheſtra; having firſt finiſh'd his Devotions in the Temple above the Theatre, and coming down amongſt the people who were ſitting in the Pit, he obſerv'd there was not one of them aroſe to ſalute or applaud him, but every man ſate ſtill, without ſpeaking a word.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He cauſed the Secular Sports alſo to be repreſented to the people, pretending they had been anticipated by <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and not reſerv'd for the due time: Though he writes himſelf in his own Hiſtory, <q rend="italic">That thoſe Games having been intermitted for ſome time, <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> by a diligent computation of the year, reduc'd them into order once more:</q> Whereupon the Cryer was laugh'd at, when he invited the people in ſolemn manner to the Plays, <q rend="italic">Such as</q> (he ſaid) <q rend="italic">never any man had ſeen before, and ſuch as never any would ſee again;</q> becauſe there were ſome perſons then living, <pb n="294"/> which had ſeen them before, and ſome Actors which had acted the ſame Parts upon the ſame occaſion. He repreſented the Circenſian Games frequently in the <placeName rend="italic">Vatican</placeName>, interpoſing baiting of Wild Beaſts, every five Courſes:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He beautified the Grand Cirque with Barriers of Marble, and Goals of Gold, which in former times were made only of Earth and of Wood, and order'd particular Seats for the Senators, who till that time ſate promiſcuouſly among the people. Beſides the Courſes with Chariots and four Horſes, he repreſented the Warlike divertiſements after the manner of the <placeName rend="italic">Trojans</placeName>; and the huntings of Panthers, by a Troop of his Prætorian Horſe, under the Command of the Tribunes, and himſelf at the head of them. He produc'd alſo <placeName rend="italic">Theſſalian</placeName> Horſemen, baiting Wild Bulls about the Circus till they were tired, who then leaping upon their backs, pull'd them down by the Horns.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He gave them Prizes, and Combates of Gladiators, in ſeveral places, and at ſeveral times: Every year they had one in the Prætorian Camp, but without any baitings, or extraordinary pomp. Another they had perfect and intire in the <placeName rend="italic">Septa</placeName>, and a third in the ſame place, which though it was an extraordinary one, held but for a few dayes, and began to be called <foreign rend="italic">Sportula</foreign>, becauſe when he firſt preſented it to the people, he publiſh'd, <q rend="italic">That he invited them only to a ſhort and ſudden Repaſt, without any preparation at all.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      He was never better pleas'd, nor in better humour, than at theſe kind of Exhibitions; in ſo much that when pieces of Gold were given to the victors, to expreſs his joy, he would count it amongſt the common people with his own hand, and encouraging them to be merry, he would call them (my Maſters) and interſperſe his diſcourſe <pb n="295"/> with Raillerie, and Jeſts, though to ſpeak truth, they were but flat, and far fetch'd for the moſt part. As for example, when he promis'd them, who deſired a Gladiator called <persName rend="italic">Palumbus</persName>, <q rend="italic">That he would give them him, when he was taken.</q> Another time, having freed one of them from the profeſſion of a Gladiator, at the importunity and ſupplication of four of his Children, and obſerving the multitude to be generally taken with the indulgence, he publiſh'd a Proclamation immediately, repreſenting to the people, <q rend="italic">How careful (in common prudence) they ought to be to have Children, ſeeing what aſſiſtance and ſupport they had been even to a Sword-player.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      In the field of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, he gave them the repreſentation of the taking and ſacking of a Town, after the manner as it happens in a real and veritable War, with the ſurrender, and ſubmiſſion of the Kings of <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName>; ſitting as Preſident himſelf in his Paludamentum, or Imperial Coat of Arms. Before he went about to drain the Lake <placeName rend="italic">Fucinus</placeName>, he exhibited a Naval Fight in it, and the Mariners, and ſuch as were deſigned for the Combate, crying out to him in theſe words, <q rend="italic">Farewell, good Emperour, farewell, they who are going to dye ſalute you;</q> he anſwer'd them in their own language, and no otherwiſe, <foreign rend="italic">Avete vos</foreign>, <q rend="italic">Fare you well alſo:</q> by which words imagining he had excus'd them from that Combate, they ſtood ſtill by conſent, and not one of them would fight. <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> inraged with this affront, ſitting a long time deliberating with himſelf, whether he ſhould deſtroy them all with Fire, or Sword, at length leaping down from his Seat, and ſtaggering moſt ungracefully about the Banks of the Lake, by threatning partly, and partly <pb n="296"/> by fair words, he prevail'd with them to the skirmiſh: In this Spectacle the <placeName rend="italic">Sicilian</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Rhodian</placeName> Fleets incountred, conſiſting of twelve Galleys a piece, and (which was very handſome, and wonderful) a Triton of Silver, ariſing by an artificial Machine out of the midſt of the Lake, founded a charge on a ſudden, and gave the ſignal to fall on.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      22. He not only corrected certain points relating to religious Ceremonies, Military, and Civil manners, and the State and Condition of all Orders of perſons, both at home and abroad; but he reſtored alſo ſome that had been diſuſed, and inſtituted new, where he ſaw occaſion. In the Election of Prieſts (which was done by Colledges) he nominated no body, till he had taken the Oath. He preciſely obſerv'd as often as there was any Earthquake in the City, to require the Prætor to aſſemble the People, and proclaim a Feſtival: and when any unlucky or ominous Bird was ſeen either in the Capitol, or the Town, he ordain'd publick Prayers, and proceſſions, marching himſelf before in the quality of High-Prieſt, after he had made an Harangue to the people from the Roſtra, and diſmiſt the throng of Mechanicks and Slaves.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      23. He chang'd the Order of the hearings, and pleadings in law, commanding they ſhould be diſpatch'd at all times of the year, notwithſtanding they had been antiently reſtrained to particular Months, both in the Winter, and Summer. He ordain'd likewiſe that the jurisdiction in matters of truſt, (which in former times was wont to be annually exerciſed by the Magiſtrates, and that only in the City) ſhould be perpetual for the future; and he committed <pb n="297"/> the care and cognizance of it to the Governours of his ſeveral Provinces: He abrogated that Article which <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> had inſerted into the law <foreign rend="italic">Papia Poppæa</foreign>, importing that men of threeſcore years old were not capable of Generation:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He decreed that the Conſuls (contrary to former Orders) ſhould appoint Tutors to ſuch as were Pupils, and under age; and that ſuch as were baniſh'd the Provinces by the Magiſtrates, ſhould be interdicted the City of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and all <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> alſo. Some perſons he confin'd, himſelf, and (after an unuſual manner) obliged them not to go above three miles from the Town.
    </p>
    <p>
      When any important and extraordinary affair was tranſacted, he plac'd himſelf in the Tribunes ſeat, between the Conſuls Chairs; and as to the Paſports or Tickets for travelling, or being abſent, which were wont to be received from the Senate, he would not ſuffer the Citizens to be beholding to any body for them, but himſelf.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      24. He granted the Conſulary Ornaments, to his Ducenarie Procurators, (whoſe Salary or Penſion extended no further than two hundred Seſterces) and took away the dignity of Knight-hood from ſuch as refuſed the honour of being of the Senate. Though he had proteſted in the beginning of his Empire, never to chooſe any one into the Senate, that was not a Citizen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> of three deſcents: yet he gave the Laticlave, or Senators Robe, to the Son of a Libertine, but it was upon condition, that he ſhould be firſt adopted by a Gentleman of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. Nevertheleſs apprehending the worſt, and to ſecure himſelf from the reproach of the People as well as he could, he alledged the Example of <persName rend="italic">Appius Cæcus</persName>, (from whom he was deſcended) who in the time of his Cenſorſhip, <pb n="298"/> elected the Sons of ſeveral Libertines into the Senate; not conſidering that then, and for ſome time after, they were not called Libertines which were manumitted and made free, but the ingenui which were deſcended from them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He injoyn'd the Colledg of Quæſtors, inſtead of paving the ſtreets and keeping the Highwayes in repair, to repreſent a Sword-play to the people. Having taken from them the provinces of <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Gaule</placeName>, he reſtored them to their old adminiſtration in the Treaſury of <persName rend="italic">Saturn</persName>, which had been executed in the interval by ſuch as either were or had been Prætors.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He granted the Triumphal Ornaments to <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName> (who was contracted to his Daughter) though he was not arrived at fourteen years old. But he granted that priviledge to elder perſons ſo often and ſo eaſily, that in an Epiſtle to him in the name of all the Legions (which is ſtill extant) they begg'd, <q rend="italic">That with the Command of the Army, he would confer the triumphal Ornaments upon the Conſuls Lieutenants, that they might not ſeek occaſion for War, upon the leaſt pretence in the World.</q> To <persName rend="italic">A. Plautius</persName> he decreed an Ovation for his greater honour, went to meet him himſelf, as ſoon as he was entred the City, and accompanied him by his ſide, both in the Capitol, and back again. <persName rend="italic">Gabinius Secundus</persName> having overcome the <placeName rend="italic">Chauci</placeName>, (a People in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>) he permitted him to aſſume the ſurname of <persName rend="italic">Chaucius</persName> ever after.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      25. He obſerv'd this Order in the management of his Cavalerie, after the Command of a Cohort, he gave that of a Wing, and after that, the Command or Tribuneſhip of a Legion. He inſtituted likewiſe an imaginary Militia, which was called Supernumerarie, <pb n="299"/> who though abſent, and with the name of Souldiers only; yet they received their pay as the reſt. By an Order of the Senate, he prohibited all Souldiers entring into the houſe of any Senator, upon pretence of ſaluting them. He confiſcated the Eſtates of ſuch Libertines, as call'd themſelves Gentlemen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. Such of them as were ingrateful, and of whom their Patrons complained, he deprived of their freedom, returned to their old ſervitude again, and declared to their advocates, that they ſhould have as little juſtice, againſt their freemen, another time.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Underſtanding that ſome Maſters being weary and impatient of the Cure of their Bondmen at home, ſent them over into the Iſland of <placeName rend="italic">Æſculapius</placeName> to recover their healths, he gave Order, <q rend="italic">That all ſuch as were ſent over, ſhould be made free ever after, and never return to their Maſters when they were well; and that if any Maſter choſe rather to kill his ſlave, than put him forth in this manner he ſhould be guilty of Murder.</q> He commanded alſo by Edict, <q rend="italic">That no Traveller ſhould paſs through any town in <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, but on foot, in a Sedan, or in a Litter.</q> <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName> being ſubject more than others to fires, he quarter'd a Cohort in each, on purpoſe to prevent them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He allowed not any ſtranger to uſurp the name of any family in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and cut off the heads of ſome perſons in the <placeName rend="italic">Eſquiline</placeName> field, for no other cauſe, but that they had pretended to the freedom of that City. The Provinces of <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Macedon</placeName>, which <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> had appropriated to himſelf, he reſtored to the Senate. He took away their Liberty from the <placeName rend="italic">Lycians</placeName>, by reaſon of their pernicious differences which were amongſt them; and reſtored it to the <placeName rend="italic">Rhodians</placeName>, upon their repentance, and acknowledgment of their former <pb n="300"/> offences. He favoured the <placeName rend="italic">Ilienſes</placeName>, as the founders of the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Nation, and remitted their tributes for ever; having caus'd an old Epiſtle in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> to be recited, written from the Senate and people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> to <persName rend="italic">Seleucus</persName> the King, promiſing him their friendſhip and alliance upon condition he would exempt the <placeName rend="italic">Ilienſes</placeName> from all manner of Taxes or Tributes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He turned the <placeName rend="italic">Jews</placeName> out of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, for that they were always in an uproar and tumult upon occaſion of the new religion of the <foreign rend="italic">Chriſtians</foreign>. Being taken with the courage and bluntneſs of the <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> Embaſſadors, he permitted them to ſit in the Orcheſtra, for they having been brought into the Popularia or Pit, and obſerving the <placeName rend="italic">Parthian</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Armenian</placeName> Embaſſadors upon the Theatre, they removed alſo and went among the Senators; affirming themſelves not inferiour to either of the two, either in virtue or quality.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      He utterly aboliſhed the inhumane religion of the Druids amongſt the <placeName rend="italic">Gaules</placeName>, which <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> had forbidden only to the Citizens of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. On the contrary he endeavoured to transfer the <foreign rend="italic">Eleuſinian</foreign> Ceremonies from <placeName rend="italic">Attica</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. He caus'd the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Venus Erycina</persName> in <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, which time had almoſt demoliſh'd, to be repaired out of the publick Treaſury of the City. He entred into Leagues, and made his Alliances with forreign Princes, in the Forum, with the antient formalities of ſacrificing a Sow, and the Proclamation of the Herauld at Arms. But theſe and the reſt, and indeed the greateſt part of the Actions of his Reign, were managed not ſo much according to his own mind, but by the fancy and direction of his wife and ſervants; he comporting himſelf always ſo, as conſiſted beſt with their profit or pleaſure.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="301"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      26. He was Contracted twice when he was but very young, once to <persName rend="italic">Æmilia Lepida</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> his great Grand-daughter, the ſecond time, to <persName rend="italic">Livia Medullina</persName>, ſurnamed <persName rend="italic">Camilla</persName>, as deſcended of the antient race of <persName rend="italic">Camillus</persName> the Dictator. The firſt he turn'd off a Virgin, becauſe her Parents had offended <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, and the other died the very day which was deſigned for her wedding.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After this he married <persName rend="italic">Plautia Urgulanilla</persName> whoſe Father had had the honour of a Triumph, and next <persName rend="italic">Ælia Petina</persName>, the Daughter of one who had been Conſul: Both of them he divorced; <persName rend="italic">Petina</persName>, upon a ſlight and trivial occaſion, but <persName rend="italic">Urgulanilla</persName> for immodeſty, and ſuſpicion of Murder. After all theſe he took <persName rend="italic">Valeria Meſſalina</persName> to his Wife, the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Barbatus Meſſala</persName>, his own Couſin German, who (beſides the reſt of her flagitious impieties) being found to have married her ſelf to <persName rend="italic">C. Silius</persName> alſo, and a dower conſign'd her in the hands of the Auſpices, he put her to death, and afterwards in a Speech he made to his Guards, he declared, <q rend="italic">That ſince he had been ſo unfortunate in his Marriages, he would live a ſingle life for the future, and if he continued not in that reſolution, he would not refuſe to be killed by their very hands.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Nevertheleſs he was not able to contain, but fell in treaty again with <persName rend="italic">Petina</persName> within a ſhort time, whom he had put away before, as alſo with <persName rend="italic">Lollia Paulina</persName>, which had been married to <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſar</persName>. But he ſuffered himſelf to be ſo carried away by the Careſſes, and blandiſhments of <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, the Daughter of his Brother <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, who having the liberty of kiſſing, and other dalliances (by reaſon of her Relation) inamoured him ſo, that in the next Senate he ſuborned perſons to move, <q rend="italic">That he might be compelled to Marry, (as a thing of great importance to the Common-Wealth) <pb n="302"/> and that according to his Example, all ſorts of people might be permitted to contract ſuch Marriages, which till that time were look'd upon as inceſtuous.</q> After it was decreed, he had ſcarce patience for a day before his Nuptials were celebrated, but not one perſon was found to follow his precedent, but one Libertine, and one of the Captains of his Guards, at whoſe Weddings, himſelf and <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> were both preſent, for the incouragement of others, as much as in honour to them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      27. He had Children by three of his Wives, by <persName rend="italic">Urgulanilla</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Claudia</persName>; by <persName rend="italic">Petina</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> by <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, and a Son which he call'd <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> firſt, and afterwards <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName>: <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> he loſt at a Town call'd <placeName rend="italic">Pompey</placeName>, before he was fourteen, and by a very ſtrange accident, for being at play with a Pear, and throwing it up into the air, he gap'd to catch it in his Mouth as it came down, which he perform'd ſo effectually, that it ſtuck faſt in his throat, and Choak'd him; to whom not many days before, he had contracted the daughter of <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>; which makes that which ſome people report improbable to me, as if he had been circumvented and killed by <persName rend="italic">Sejanus</persName>. And for <persName rend="italic">Claudia</persName>, though ſhe was born five months before the divorce, and by him put out to Nurſe; yet ſuſpecting her afterwards to have been gotten by one of his freemen, call'd <persName rend="italic">Boter</persName>, he caus'd her to be ſtript ſtark naked, and laid before her Mothers door:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Antonia</persName> he married, firſt to <persName rend="italic">Cn. Pompeius Magnus</persName>, and afterwards to <persName rend="italic">Fauſtus Sylla</persName>, both noble young Gentlemen, and of illuſtrious families. <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName> he beſtowed upon <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, his Wives Son, though ſhe had been formerly betrothed to <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName>. <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> was born twenty days after he came to the Empire, in the time <pb n="303"/> of his ſecond Conſulſhip; and being yet but an Infant, he us'd to take him frequently in his arms, and in a ſolemn Oration recommended him to the Souldiers; as likewiſe he ſhew'd him many times to the people at their Plays, either holding him in his lap, or placing him before him, whilſt they magnified him in their acclamations. Of all his Sons-in-law, he adopted only <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>; to <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName>, he was ſo far from doing that honour, that he caus'd them both to be murder'd.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      28. Amongſt all his Freemen he had the moſt kindneſs for <persName rend="italic">Poſides</persName> the Eunuch; to whom in his <placeName rend="italic">Britiſh</placeName> Triumph (amongſt the reſt of his Warriers, and Gallant men) he preſented a Spear without any iron upon it. Neither was his favour much leſs to <persName rend="italic">Felix</persName>, to whom he had given the Command of Cohorts, wings of Horſe, and the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Judæa</placeName>, which render'd him ſo great and conſiderable, that he was the Husband of three ſeveral Queens. To <persName rend="italic">Harpocras</persName> he granted the priviledge, to be carried in a Litter up and down the City, and to exhibite Plays to the people. <persName rend="italic">Polybius</persName> alſo was a learned man, and one he made great uſe of in his Studies; he was ſo grateful to him, that he permitted him many times to walk betwixt the two Conſuls. But the honours he conferr'd upon <persName rend="italic">Narciſſus</persName>, his Secretary, and <persName rend="italic">Pallas</persName> one of the Auditors of his Exchequer, were ſo vaſt and exceſſive, that beſides the large rewards which the Senate decreed them upon his recommendation, he vouchſafed them the Ornaments both of the Quæſtors, and Prætors; beſides all which, he gave ſo great a latitude to their Extortion and Rapine, that complaining one day his Coffers were exhauſted, he was anſwer'd very handſomly, <q rend="italic">He might be rich and <pb n="304"/> abound too, if his two Freed-men would but take him into their ſociety.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      29. Being thus exceſſively addicted to theſe kind of people, and to his Wives, he acted more like a Servant than a Prince; diſpoſing of honours, Armies, Immunities, and Puniſhments, as they were ſuitable with their intereſts or deſigns; conferring them for the moſt part without any conſideration. I ſhall not make a particular enumeration of his impertinencies, as of his Liberalities revok'd, his Judgments revers'd, his grants of Offices forged, or openly chang'd. <persName rend="italic">Appius Silanus</persName>, his Brother-in-law, and the two <persName rend="italic">Juliæ</persName>, one of them the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName>, and the other of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, he caus'd to be executed, without permitting them to plead to a Charge, which no body could prove againſt them: Neither far'd it any better with <persName rend="italic">Cn. Pompeius</persName>, who married his eldeſt Daughter, nor <persName rend="italic">L. Silanus</persName>, who was contracted to his younger.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Pompeius</persName> he caus'd to be ſlain, in the embraces of a young Lad he moſt ardently affected; and <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName> having been conſtrained to ſurrender his Prætorſhip, about the latter end of <foreign rend="italic">December</foreign>, was kill'd in the beginning of the year, upon the very day on which <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> were married. He put to death five and thirty Senators, and above three hundred <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Gentlemen, with ſo much eaſe and unconcernment, that one of his Captains bringing him word, <q rend="italic">That according to his Commands ſuch a Conſulary man was executed;</q> he denied he had given any ſuch Order, yet approved well enough of what they had done; his Freed-men affirming, the Souldiers had done well, in running of their own accord to the vindication of their Emperour.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      What he did at the Marriage of <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Silius</persName> her Adulterer, <pb n="305"/> is above all credit and belief; for he ſigned the Writings himſelf for the ſettlement of her Dower, induced as if they were but diſſembled, and that he might thereby avert, and transferr the Calamities, which certain Prodigies portended to hang over his head.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      30. He wanted not a Majeſty, and Comlineſs in his perſon, either ſitting or ſtanding, but eſpecially as he was aſleep: His ſtature was tall, but not ſlender, his complexion and hair white, which gave him the air and appearance of a comely old man; his neck round and plump: But his legs were not anſwerable, being ſcarce ſtrong enough to ſupport his body. As he was doing any thing, either ſeriouſly, or remiſly, many things diſparag'd him: An unbecoming laughter, an ungraceful way in his anger, foaming at the mouth, and running at his noſe, which render'd him exceedingly deform'd; beſides a ſtammering in his ſpeech, and a continual trembling of his head, eſpecially if he were in any action, though never ſo ſmall.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      31. Formerly he uſed to be very ſickly, but after he was Emperour, he was never ill, but once of a pain in his ſtomach, which took him ſo violently, that if we may believe himſelf, he had once a mind to remove his torment, by cutting his own throat.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      32. He was a great lover of Feaſting, made many Entertainments, large and magnificent, and in the moſt ſpacious places of the City, in ſo much that many times he had ſix hundred Gueſts together <pb n="306"/> at his Table; amongſt the reſt he had one Feaſt upon the Sluce of the Lake <placeName rend="italic">Fucinus</placeName>, where he had like to have been drowned, by a ſudden impetuoſity of the water, which brake out unexpectedly. At all his Treatments his Children were conſtantly preſent, and eat at his Beds-feet with other young Perſons of Honour of both Sexes, according to the cuſtom of old. One of his Gueſts, ſuppos'd to have made bold with a Cup of Gold, and carried it away, he invited him again the next day, and made him be contented with an Earthen Pot. It is reported likewiſe that being told of a modeſt perſon who had like to have kill'd himſelf with retention, he had thoughts once of publiſhing an Edict, whereby he would make it lawful to break wind at the Table, and to eaſe themſelves of any flatulency in any place whereſoever.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      33. He had ſo exorbitant an appetite, that he would eat or drink at all times, and in all places: As he was ſitting in Juſtice one day in the Palace of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, being ſurpriz'd with the ſmell of a good Dinner, that was preparing in the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName> (which was the next houſe) for the Prieſts called <foreign rend="italic">Salii</foreign>, he quitted the Tribunal immediately, went up, ſate down amongſt them, and laid about him as heartily as the beſt. He ſeldom went from the Table, but ſweating, and with his belly ſo full, that having laid himſelf preſently upon his back in order to a Nap, he gap'd ſo wide in his ſleep, that they uſually put a feather down his throat to make him diſgorge.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His ſleeps were but ſhort, for the moſt part waking before Midnight, by which means he ſlept ſometimes ſo heartily in the Court, that the Chancellors and Advocates, ſtraining their voices on purpoſe, had much ado to make him hear. His propenſity to women was extravagant, but to the other Sex he had no inclination. He plaid at Dice very often, and was ſo <pb n="307"/> affected with that recreation, that he writ a Book of the uſe of it. He order'd and adapted his Chariot in ſuch manner, that he could play commodiouſly, and without confuſion, as he travelled upon the road.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      34. How Sanguinary he was in his Nature, appear'd in ſmall things as well as in great. The torments of the Queſtion, and the puniſhment of Parricides, he caus'd to be publick, and was always preſent himſelf. Being at <placeName rend="italic">Tibur</placeName> upon a time, he took a fancy to ſee an Execution after the antient Mode, and there being no Executioner to be found, when the delinquents were faſtned to the ſtake, he ſent for one to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and ſtaid upon the place till night with great patience, in expectation of him: In all Spectacles of Gladiators, whether exhibited by himſelf or any other perſon, if any of the Fencers happen'd to fall down, let it be by what accident it would, he commanded him to be killed; but eſpecially if they were of the <foreign rend="italic">Retiarii</foreign>, becauſe then he could ſee them, and have the pleaſure to look upon their faces at the very moment they expired.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Two Combatants being fallen down dead in his preſence of the wounds they had given to one another, he commanded both their Weapons to be forg'd into little Knives, for his own private and ordinary uſe. He took ſo great pleaſure in the Combats againſt Beaſts, which were perform'd in the Morning, and ſuch other ſports as were repreſented about noon, that he would get up by break of day to go to a Spectacle, and continue there with patience till the people came back from dinner. Beſides ſuch as were appointed to fight, upon any ſlight or ſudden occaſion, he would ſet the Labourers and Carpenters to engage in Combat, if any of their Operas <pb n="308"/> or Machines had not taken effect. Once alſo he turn'd in a Nomenclator in ſuch haſt, he allow'd him not time enough to pull off his Gown, though he was to fight with the Wild Beaſts for his life.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      35. But to nothing was he ſo much ſubject as to timorouſneſs and diſtruſt: though he was a great pretender, and (as I have ſaid before) much affected with his own civility from his coming to the Empire, yet he never durſt come to any feaſt without his Guards about him with their Lances, and waiting at the Table inſtead of his Servants. He never made a viſit to any one that was ſick, till the Chamber was ſearch'd to the very Boulſter of the Bed. He ſuffer'd no man to come near him, upon the ſcore of ſalutation or otherwiſe, before his ſearchers had been with him, who ſpared no body, and ſometimes were very rude and ſevere in their Scrutiny.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      It was a long time before he could be perſwaded to excuſe the Women (and all ſuch perſons as wore Gowns (as the <foreign rend="italic">Prætextati</foreign>) whether Boys or Girles) from being ſearch'd in that manner, or to permit the Clerks or Secretaries to come near him, with ſo much as a Stile, or Pen-knife in his pocket. In the time of the Civil troubles, <persName rend="italic">Camillus</persName> knowing very well it was not neceſſary to be at the charge of a War, to make him afraid, he ſent him a Hectoring Letter full of injurious Comminations, commanding him to give up his Empire, and betake himſelf to a private and retired life; and ſo far was he terrified with it, that he aſſembled the principal perſons of his Council, to deliberate, whether he ſhould reſign to <persName rend="italic">Camillus</persName>, or not.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      36. Upon a bare and idle report of a Conſpiracy againſt him, he was ſo pitifully frighted, nothing could <pb n="309"/> ſerve his turn; but he would lay down his Crown: A perſon (as I have mentioned before) being apprehended near him with a Dagger in his pocket, as he was buſie at a Sacrifice, he was ſo alarm'd, that he aſſembled the Senate immediately, and having lamented the deplorableneſs of his Condition, (who could not think himſelf ſafe any where, if he were in danger at the Altar) he beg'd their reſentment, and appear'd not in publick of a long time afterward. Nor was it any Senſe or Concernment for the diſhonours <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName> had done him, which extinguiſh'd the ardent paſſion he had for her, and made him deſert her; but a certain fear and apprehenſion that the Adulterer <persName rend="italic">Silius</persName> would pretend alſo the Empire; which imagination had ſuch an influence upon him, that in a moſt puſillanimous and abject manner he fled away to the Camp, and his Conſternation was ſo great, he ſpake not a word all the way he was going, more than frequently to ask, whether he was ſtill Emperour, or not.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      37. There was no ſuſpicion ſo light, no informer ſo inconſiderable; but upon the leaſt ſcruple ſuggeſted, he was upon his Guard, and thought of nothing but revenge. A certain perſon who had a ſuit in law depending before him, having whiſper'd to him as he was ſaluting him, that he dream'd (the night before) he ſaw him killed, and a while after, his adverſary delivering a Petition to <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, he went to him, and told him that was the Murderer he had ſeen, whereupon he was apprehended, and carried immediately to Execution, as if he had been convicted.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In the ſame manner it is reported, that <persName rend="italic">Appius Silanus</persName> was made away; for <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Narciſſus</persName> having ſworn his deſtruction, they contrived <pb n="310"/> that <persName rend="italic">Narciſſus</persName> ſhould ruſh into <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> his Chamber one morning by break of day, as one frighted almoſt out of his wits, and that he ſhould tell him, he dream'd that <persName rend="italic">Appius</persName> would that night attempt to murder him; and that <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName> being as it were aſtoniſh'd with the relation, ſhould intimate very formally, that indeed ſhe alſo had had the ſame dream for ſeveral nights together: A while after, <persName rend="italic">Silanus</persName> having (by the artifice of his Enemies) being told he was to wait upon the Emperour, and coming ſuddenly in, it confirm'd his credulity ſo, that he made him be taken into Cuſtody, and carried to Execution out of hand: The next day, repreſenting the whole ſtory to the Senate, he gave his Freed-man thanks, for that he had been careful of his ſafety even in his ſleep.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      38. Being conſcious of his own natural inclination to haſtineſs and paſſion, he excus'd them both in a publick Edict, and promis'd, <q rend="italic">That the one ſhould be innocent and but ſhort, and the other never without reaſon.</q> Another time, having taken it very ill of the Inhabitants of <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName>, that knowing him to be abroad upon the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>, they ſent none of their Barges to attend him; having rebuk'd them ſeverely, as though it had been done in contempt, and they had diveſted him of his Prerogative, on a ſudden he recollected and pardon'd them, upon the leaſt ſatisfaction.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Some who had choſen an ill time to make their addreſſes to him in publick, he thruſt back with his own hand. He baniſh'd a Scribe who had been Quæſtor, and a Senator that had been Prætor, without any hearing, though they were both of them innocent; the firſt, for having been too bold with him in his expreſſions, when he was but a private perſon; the other, for that in his Ædileſhip he had fined certain of his Tenants, <pb n="311"/> for ſelling boil'd Meats contrary to the Statute, and whipp'd one of his Bailiffs that interpos'd: And as if their perſonal puniſhment were not enough, he took away the Coertion and Authority of the Ædiles over the Victualling-houſes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Nor could he contain himſelf from publiſhing his own folly, which (as he ſays himſelf, in ſome of his little Orations) he counterfeited in <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> his time, on purpoſe to eſcape his cruelty; and that without ſo doing, he had never come to the ſtation he was then in. But he could never make the world believe it, till a while after there was put forth a Book intituled, <q rend="italic">The Reſurrection of Fools</q>, and the Argument was, <q rend="italic">That no man counterfeits folly.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      39. Amongſt the reſt of the things which were admirable in him, his incogitancy and forgetfulneſs were two: Having caus'd <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName> to be put to death, and going to Dinner a while after, he ask'd Why his Wife did not come to Dinner alſo. Several of thoſe perſons which were Executed by his Order, he would invite frequently the next day either to Dinner, or Dice; and as if they had been tedious, he would ſend to them again, and upbraid them by their ſloth.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Reſolving to marry <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, againſt all principles both of Honour, and Religion, he gave out upon all occaſions, <q rend="italic">That ſhe was his Daughter, his Nurſling, and one that was born and brought up as it were in his boſome.</q> Deſigning likewiſe that <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> ſhould bear the name of his Family, as if it had not been blameable enough for him to adopt his Son-in-law, his own being adult, he publickly declared, <q rend="italic">That never any one had been adopted into the Family of the <persName rend="italic">Claudii</persName> before.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      40. He was oftentimes ſo careleſs and negligent both of his words and his actions, that he neither <pb n="312"/> knew nor conſider'd what he ſaid himſelf, nor to whom, nor in what time or place. When they were in diſcourſe in the Senate one time, about the Butchers and Vintners, he cry'd out before he was aware, <q rend="italic">And which of you is it that can live without a Morſel?</q> and then told them an impertinent ſtory, of the great number of antient Taverns, from whence he had his Wine a long time ago.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      As an irrefutable reaſon, why he gave his voice for a perſon who ſtood Candidate for the Quæſtorſhip, he declared amongſt other of his arguments, <q rend="italic">That being very ill one time, the Father of that perſon had given him cold water very opportunely which did him a great deal of good.</q> A woman being brought in as a witneſs before the Senate alſo, he told them, <q rend="italic">This was my Mothers Woman d' Attour, and dreſt her, but ſhe look'd upon me as her young Maſter alwayes, which I intimate the rather, becauſe I have ſome at home will not own me to be ſo.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Again, the Inhabitants of <placeName rend="italic">Oſtia</placeName> having preſented him one time with a Petition, as he was ſitting publickly in Court, he cry'd out in a great paſſion, <q rend="italic">That he knew no reaſon he had to oblige them, and that he was as free as any man elſe.</q> Theſe words he had uſually in his mouth, and as it were every hour of the day, <q rend="italic">What? doſt thou take me to be a Cokes? and Speak and Strike?</q> beſides many other weak and idle expreſſions, beneath the reputation of a private perſon, much leſs of a Prince, ſo far from being illiterate, that he had been a hard Student in the liberal Sciences, and was arriv'd at no ſmall perfection in Oratory.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      41. When he was but a Youth, he undertook to write a Hiſtory by the perſwaſion of <persName rend="italic">Titus Livius</persName>, and the aſſiſtance of <persName rend="italic">Sulpicius Flavus</persName>, which the firſt time he recited, and committed it publickly to <pb n="313"/> the judgment of his Auditors; he ſcarce could read it over, but put himſelf often out; For it happen'd ſome of the Benches breaking by the weight and corpulence of a perſon that was there, the whole Company fell a laughing, but after that was over, and all the reſt were recollected, he could not but remember the accident by fits, and fall out again into a laughter in the midſt of his reading, which was no ſmall interruption to them both.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      During the time of his Empire he writ ſeveral things and cauſed them to be recited by a Reader very often: His Hiſtory he began after the death of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> the Dictator, which he divided into two books; and the paſſages after the civil pacification, into forty and one, enlarging himſelf more upon that ſubject than upon the other, in reſpect that his Mother and Grandmother had often times rebuk'd him, and forwarn'd him of taking of too much liberty, in his deſcription of thoſe days.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He writ alſo ſeven Volums of his own life, with leſs prudence than Elegance. As alſo a defence of <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> againſt the writings of <persName rend="italic">Gallus</persName>, which was learned enough. Beſides this, he invented three Letters, and added them (as neceſſary) to the antient Alphabet; and having publiſh'd a book to recommend them to the people, when he was a private perſon, it was no hard matter for him to obtrude them upon them when he was advanc'd to the Empire. And that kind of writing, with thoſe Characters is at this day to be ſeen in ſeveral Records and Journals, as alſo in the Titles and inſcriptions of works.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      42. For the <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> Language he had ſo particular a value, that a certain ſtranger diſcourſing in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> and <foreign rend="italic">Latine</foreign>, he told him, <q rend="italic">You being skilful in both our Languages</q>, and in his recommendation of <placeName rend="italic">Achaia</placeName> to the Senate, he declar'd, <q rend="italic">That province was very grateful <pb n="314"/> and agreeable to him, by reaſon of their Commerce, and Community of their ſtudies.</q> He anſwer'd Embaſſadors many times in that language, and that with a long and continued Oration: many times he made uſe of Verſes out of <persName rend="italic">Homer</persName>, as he ſate upon his Tribunal; and whenſoever he had ſatisfied his revenge upon any Enemy or Traitor, when the Tribune or Officer came to him, according to cuſtom, for the word, he ſeldom gave any other than this in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign>;
      <q rend="italic">When one is injur'd firſt, 'tis like a Man
      To take his Vengeance any way he can.</q>
      In ſhort, he wrote ſome Hiſtories in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> alſo, as the Hiſtory of the <placeName rend="italic">Tyrrhenian</placeName> affairs in twenty books, and the Hiſtory of the <placeName rend="italic">Carthaginians</placeName> in eight.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Upon which conſideration, and to make them the more famous, he added a new School to the old one that was at <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName> before, and calling it by his own name, he ordain'd that his <foreign rend="italic">Tyrrhenicoon</foreign>, or book of the <placeName rend="italic">Tuſcan</placeName> affairs, ſhould be read in one of them, and his <foreign rend="italic">Charchedoniacoon</foreign>, in the other ſucceſſively, and that each of them ſhould be read out in their turns.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      43. Towards the latter end of his life, he gave evident tokens that he repented of his Marriage with <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, and his adoption of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>. For having condemned a woman for adultery, upon a certain time, and his freed men applauding his Juſtice very highly, he told them, <q rend="italic">That is was his Fortune to have all his Marriages unclean, but not unpuniſh'd.</q> And his Son <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> preſenting himſelf to him a while after, he embrac'd him with more than ordinary kindneſs, bad him <q rend="italic">Grow apace, and he would give him an account of all that he had done:</q> adding in <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> to this purpoſe, that it was his love which incited him; and deſigning <pb n="315"/> to give him the Virile Robe (though he was too ſmall in reſpect of his Stature) he added theſe words, <q rend="italic">That the People of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> might at laſt have a <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> indeed.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="44">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      44. It was not long after this but he made his Will, and atteſted it by the hands and ſeals of all the Magiſtrates, but before he could proceed any further in the advancement of his Son, he was prevented by <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, who was already tormented by the remorſe of her own Conſcience, and perſecuted by informers, which accus'd her of ſeveral crimes beſides this.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      It is agreed by all people, he died by poiſon, but as to the place or perſon by whom it was given, they are not ſo unanimous. Some ſay it was the Eunuch <persName rend="italic">Halotus</persName> his Taſter, which poiſon'd him, as he was eating among the Prieſts in the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>. Others will have it, That in a feaſt at his own houſe <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> knowing he was a great lover of Muſhromes, preſented him with one that was poiſoned. Nor are the Opinions leſs uncertain, upon the other circumſtances of his death.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Some report that he was taken ſpeechleſs, as ſoon as he had taken the poiſon, and that continuing all night in great torment, he died towards the morning. Others affirm, that he fell aſleep as ſoon as he had taken it, and that his meat riſing in his ſtomach, he brought up all; whereupon they redoubled his poiſon, but whether it was given in a Jelly, or Broath, under pretence of fortifying his ſtomach, or by Clyſter, to give him eaſe by that evacuation, is uncertain.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="45">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      45. His death was kept private, till all things were put in order for the eſtabliſhment of his Succeſſor. Vows were publickly made for his recovery, as if he had been but ſick only: and pretending he deſir'd to divert himſelf that way, his Comedians were <pb n="316"/> call'd for, to heighten the diſſimulation. He departed the thirteenth of <foreign rend="italic">October</foreign>, in the Conſulſhip of <persName rend="italic">Aſinius Marcellus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Acilius Aviola</persName>, in the ſixty fourth year of his age, and the fourteenth of his Empire. His Obſequies were performed with Magnificence ſuitable to an Emperour, attended in a pompous and ſolemn Proceſſion by the Magiſtrates, and plac'd in the number of the Gods; which honour being taken away, and aboliſh'd by <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> his ſucceſſor, was after ſome time reſtor'd to him by <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="46">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      46. The moſt remarkable preſages of his death, were a Blazing-ſtar, or Comet, which appear'd in the air; the ſplitting of his Father <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> his Monument, with Thunder and Lightning; and beſides theſe, the dying of ſeveral Magiſtrates that year, of all Orders and Degrees. But there are probable arguments, that he was neither ignorant of his approaching death, nor endeavour'd to diſſemble it; For in his deſignation of Conſuls, he ordained none of them to continue beyond the month in which he died; The laſt time he was preſent in the Senate, having in a long diſcourſe moſt earneſtly exhorted his children to agree, he humbly recommended the age of them both, to their care and protection; and in his laſt Judicial Seſſion upon the Tribunal, he declared ſeveral times, <q rend="italic">That he was now arrived at the end of his Mortality.</q> The people which heard him, abominating the Expreſſion, ſupplicated the Gods for the Continuation of his health.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>