<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>

            <pb n="461"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      THE EIGHTH BOOK, Being the LIFE OF <persName rend="italic">Titus Flavius Veſpaſianus Auguſtus</persName>, THE ELEVENTH Emperour of <placeName rend="italic">ROME</placeName>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">TItus</persName> who retain'd the Surname of his Father, had either ſo much good fortune, or ſo much artifice and addreſs in gaining upon the affections of all people, that he was called, <q rend="italic">The love and delight of mankind</q>; but that which was moſt admirable, and unuſual, was, that he ſhould inſinuate himſelf ſo
      <pb n="462"/>
      happily being Emperour, who when he was but a private perſon could not evade the malice, and aſperſions of the world.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. He was born on the thirtieth of December, in a year which was remarkable for the Murder of <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName>, near the <placeName rend="italic">Septizonium</placeName>, in a pitiful houſe, but a worſe Chamber, which is ſtill to be ſeen. He was brought up with <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> in the Court, and inſtructed in the ſame diſciplines, by the ſame Maſters: In which time it is reported that a Phyſiognomiſt being brought by <persName rend="italic">Narciſſus</persName> (one of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> his Freemen) to give his judgment upon <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName>, he confidently affirm'd that <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> ſhould never be Emperour, but that <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName> (who at that time ſtood by) moſt infallibly ſhould. Betwixt theſe two perſons there was ſo great a familiarity, it is confidently aſſerted that <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName> being at the Table when <persName rend="italic">Britannicus</persName> took the poiſon of which he died, he alſo had his taſt, and had much ado to recover. In Memory of which accident, he erected him a Statue of Gold afterwards in the <placeName rend="italic">Palatium</placeName>, and dedicated to him another on Horſe-back of Ivory, which is carried at this day publickly before the pomp and ſolemnity of the <foreign rend="italic">Circenſian</foreign> Games.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. The perfections and luſtre both of his body and mind, appear'd from his infancy, encreaſing afterwards more and more according to the degrees of his age. His aſpect was excellent, adorned with no leſs Majeſty than ſweetneſs. Though his Stature was but indifferent, and his belly turgid and fat, yet he was of a clean ſtrength and vigorous; his Memory was ſingular, and apt for all manner of arts, either of Peace or War.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was dextrous at his weapon, and an incomparable horſeman, ſo ready alſo both in the Latin and Greek tongues, that he did every
      <pb n="463"/>
      thing well, either in Proſe or in Verſe, and that extempore, without any præmeditation. Beſides this, he underſtood Muſick, ſung, and plaid upon the Harp with good judgment, and grace. I have heard many ſay, he writ ſhort-hand as faſt as any body could dictate, and that he did uſually contend by way of ſport with his Secretaries, who could imitate beſt whatever they ſaw, in which he proved ſo great a proficient, that he was wont to ſay, <q rend="italic">If he pleas'd, he could make the beſt Forger in the World.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. He commanded in the quality of a Military Tribune, both in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">England</placeName>, where he acquired no leſs honour for his Moderation than Vigilance, as appears by the Multitude of Images, and Statues, and Inſcriptions dedicated to his Memory in both Provinces.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      When he had given over the field, he betook himſelf to the Bar, and pleaded, but it was in Cauſes of the greateſt importance, and not conſtantly. About the ſame time he married <persName rend="italic">Arricidia Tertulla</persName> the Daughter of a Gentleman only, but one who had been formerly Captain of the Guards to an Emperour. When ſhe died he took <persName rend="italic">Marcia Furnilla</persName> to his Wife, a Lady of an illuſtrious family, but having had one Daughter by her, he put her away.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      From his Quæſtorſhip he was advanced to the Command of a Legion, and reduced <placeName rend="italic">Tarachæa</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Gamala</placeName>, two very ſtrong Towns in <placeName rend="italic">Judæa</placeName>; where in a certain Battle, having loſt his horſe under him, he mounted another immediately, that belonged to one of the Enemies ſide, which he had killed hand to hand.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. Not long afterwards being ſent towards <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> to congratulate his advancement; where-
      <pb n="464"/>
      ever he came he drew the eyes of all people upon him, as if he had been ſent for by <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> on purpoſe to be adopted; but having intelligence that the Commonwealth was fallen again into new troubles and diſorders, he gave over that Journey; and turning out of the way to viſit the Oracle of <persName rend="italic">Venus</persName> in <placeName rend="italic">Paphos</placeName>, conſulting her concerning the ſucceſs of his Navigation, ſhe ſecured him in the hopes of the Empire.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Which having attained to in a ſhort time after, and being left behind to reduce <placeName rend="italic">Judæa</placeName>, the laſt ſtorm that he made at <placeName rend="italic">Hieruſalem</placeName>, he ſhot twelve Arrows againſt the Town, and kill'd every time his Man, and at laſt took it, upon the birth day of his Daughter, with ſo much joy and applauſe from his Soldiers, that they ſaluted him Emperour in the heat of their acclamations, nor did their affections to him appear any leſs at his going away, they mingling Menaces with their Prayers and Importunities to prevail with him, <q rend="italic">To ſtay himſelf, or to take them along.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      And this was the occaſion of this ſuſpicion, that he had a deſign of revolting from his Father, and making himſelf Emperour of the Eaſt; which jealouſie was much increaſed by his Voyage to <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, where in the Conſecration of the Oxe <persName rend="italic">Apis</persName> at <placeName rend="italic">Memphis</placeName>, he wore a Diadem upon his head; true it is, he did it only by the Rites and Cuſtoms of that Religion, but there wanted not thoſe who interpreted it otherwiſe. To remove theſe falſe impreſſions, he return'd immediately for <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, paſſing by <placeName rend="italic">Rhegium</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName> in a Merchants ſhip, and from thence to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, with all poſſible expedition, where ſurprizing his Father with his arrival, he brake out into this expreſſion, <q rend="italic">I am come
      <pb n="465"/>
      dear Sir, I am come</q>, as if he deſigned thereby to fruſtrate and confute the reports which were raiſed of him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. From that time he acted not only as a partner, but as a Protector of the Common-wealth. He triumph'd with his Father, exercis'd the Cenſorſhip in conjunction with him, and was his Colleague in his Tribunitial dignity, and ſeven Conſulſhips. Having taken upon himſelf the care almoſt of all affairs, he dedicated all Letters and Diſpatches in his Fathers name, drew up all his Edicts and diſcharg'd the Office of Quæſtor or Chancellor, by reciting Orations in the Senate. He took upon him in like manner the charge of Major-dome or Steward of the Emperours houſhold, which was never executed before that time, but by a Knight of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. He managed it however with nothing ſo much moderation, and Civility as was expected; for having imploy'd people on purpoſe through both the Theatre, and Camp, to demand ſuch perſons as he had any ſuſpicion of, to be deliver'd up to him, and puniſh'd as Criminals; he without more ado put them to death, as it had been by conſent of his Father.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      An inſtance of this is to be found in <persName rend="italic">A. Cæcinna</persName> a Conſular Man, whom he invited to ſupper, and caus'd him to be killed afterwards, before he was well out of the room; And truly not without reaſon, for he had met with a Note under his own hand, which was the Copy of a Speech he had prepar'd to make to the Souldiers to excite them to ſedition. By this manner of proceeding, as he provided well enough for his own ſecurity for the future, ſo for the preſent he contracted ſo great an Odium, that
      <pb n="466"/>
      ſcarce ever any man arriv'd at the Empire with a worſe reputation, or greater repugnancy of the people.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. Beſides his cruelty, he was decried alſo for his luxury, in that he did uſually ſpin out his Treats and Collations with the moſt profuſe and diſſolute of his friends, till midnight, and paſt. Nor was he leſs talked of for his Luſt, by reaſon of the numbers of old Catamites, and young Eunuchs which he had about him; as likewiſe for the extraordinary paſſion he had for <persName rend="italic">Beronice</persName>, whom by report he had promis'd to make his Wife. He was ſuſpected alſo of Rapine and Extortion, and that in ſome Caſes he took bribes, and ſold the Judgment and Determination of his Father. In ſhort, he was not only looked upon privately as another <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, but pronounced ſo publickly by the people. But all theſe Calumnies proved to his advantage, all things turning to his praiſe, when they found no Vice, but many excellent Virtues in him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His feaſts were rather pleaſant than profuſe; The Election of his friends was with ſuch prudence and ſobriety, his Succeſſors made uſe of them when he was gone, as perſons neceſſary both for them, and the State. He was ſo great a Maſter of his paſſions, that he ſent away Queen <persName rend="italic">Beronice</persName>, though much againſt both their inclinations. Some of the chief Inſtruments of his Delights and Recreations, he ſent away alſo, though otherwiſe he loved them very well. His Dancers though they were skillful and artificial, and (a while after) carried away the prize upon the Stage, he not only forbore to Countenance and Careſs as he had formerly done, but to ſee them afterwards in any publick aſſem-
      <pb n="467"/>
      bly.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He was never the man that took any thing away from a Citizen, and was ſo little addicted to deſire what belonged to another man, that he would not receive the uſual preſents and contributions which were his due. And yet of all his Predeceſſors, none was more Munificent than he. After he had dedicated the Amphitheatre, and with admirable expedition finiſh'd the Baths hard by; he exhibited a Sword-play which was very Magnificent. He preſented the People with a Naval Battle, in the old <foreign rend="italic">Naumachia</foreign>, as alſo a Skirmiſh by his Gladiators in the ſame place; and one day caus'd 5000 wild beaſts of all ſorts to be baited.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. Being Naturally ſo bountiful, that (not conſidering an Order of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> according to which, the Emperours which ſucceeded might chooſe, whether they would ratifie and confirm the Grants which their Predeceſſors had made; and when they did it, it was commonly with ſuch formality, and circumſtance, as if they had given them themſelves) he was the firſt which by one General Edict confirm'd all at a blow, and would not ſuffer any man to apply to him for new. One of his principal Methods was, never to ſend any away without ſome hopes of ſucceſs in his deſires. And being advertiſed by his Domeſticks upon a time, <q rend="italic">That he had promiſed more than he could perform</q>, he replyed, <q rend="italic">That it was not fit that any one ſhould go away melancholy, who came from ſpeaking with a Prince.</q> Again, being admoniſh'd at Supper, that he had done nothing for any body that day, he expreſt his diſſatisfaction in this Memorable Apophthegm, <q rend="italic">AMICI, DIEM PERDIDI</q>, <q rend="italic">Then I have
      <pb n="468"/>
      loſt a day my Friends.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The People he treated conſtantly with ſo much kindneſs upon all occaſions, that having deſigned to give them the diverſion of their Gladiators, he publiſh'd, that it ſhould be exhibited, not after his own fanſie, but the pleaſure of the Spectators: and he was as good as his word, for he was ſo far from refuſing what they deſired, that he ſollicited them to know what it was. Moreover his Complaiſance was ſo great, that though in his Judgment he was really for the Thracian Fencers, yet he would many times join both by his Voice and Geſture with the Opinion of the people; never the leſs ſo as to retain the Majeſty of an Emperour, and to do no injuſtice in the diſtribution of the prizes. And that he might not be deficient in any point of popularity, he permitted the Common ſort of people to have acceſs into his Baines, when he was bathing himſelf.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In his Reign there fell out ſome accidents, no leſs unexpected, than deplorable; as firſt the burning of <placeName rend="italic">Veſuvius</placeName>, a Mountain in <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>. A fire in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> which laſted three days, and three nights continually: and ſuch a Peſtilence, as perhaps had not been known any where before. Nevertheleſs, in all theſe Calamities he behaved himſelf not only with the care of a Prince, but with the Bowels and Compaſſion of a Father, comforting the people with his Edicts, and ſometimes aſſiſting them, as his own Revenues would give him leave.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He choſe ſuch perſons by Lot, as had been Conſuls before, to take upon them the charge of ſeeing the ruines in <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName> repaired. Such Goods and Eſtate as was found to belong to perſons which had periſhed by the
      <pb n="469"/>
      ſaid Mountain, and had dyed without Heirs, he commanded ſhould be imployed towards the building of thoſe Towns which had ſuffered. As to the burning of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he declared publickly, <q rend="italic">that he would take the whole loſs upon himſelf;</q> and accordingly he deſign'd all the Ornaments and Furniture belonging to his own Palaces to the re-adornment of the Temples, and publick Houſes in the City: and that all things might be done with more certainty and expedition, he Commiſſion'd ſeveral <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knights, to ſee them executed as he Commanded. To Remedy the Sickneſs, and abate the Malignity of the Diſeaſe, there was no Courſe, either Humane or Divine, which he neglected; having ſought out all ſorts of Remedies and Sacrifices whatever.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      Amongſt the misfortunes of thoſe times, their Promoters and Informers may be numbred, who had their riſe from the Licentiouſneſs, and Impunity of the former. But <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName> made them Examples, Condemning them dayly to be whipt and beaten with Clubs in the Market-place, and then to be drag'd through the Theatre, and at laſt, part of them to be ſold as Slaves, and part tranſported into the moſt bitter, and uninhabitable Iſlands. And that no man might be ſo audacious for the future, he prohibited amongſt other things that the ſame caſe ſhould be tryed by ſeveral Laws; or that any one ſhould inquire into the Eſtate of any dead Perſon, after a ſet and preciſe Number of years.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. When he entred upon the Office of High Prieſt, he proteſted he did it <q rend="italic">to keep his hands
      <pb n="470"/>
      pure and undefiled.</q> Nor did he fail in his promiſe, for from that time he never was either Author or acceſſary to any mans death, though he wanted not occaſion ſome times of uſing his revenge; affirming, <q rend="italic">He had rather dye himſelf, than put another to death.</q> Two of Patrician Degree being convicted of aſpiring to the Empire, he proſecuted them no further, but admoniſhed them gently to deſiſt, telling them, <q rend="italic">That the Empire was given by deſtiny;</q> and if any thing elſe might ſatisfie them, he promiſed they ſhould have it;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      at which very time he diſpatcht a Meſſenger to one of their Mothers who was then a far off and in no ſmall anxiety for her Son, to aſſure her, he was out of all danger and well; and (as if this had been too ſmall an inſtance of his Clemency) he not only entertain'd them privately at Supper that night in his own Houſe, but the next day at a Spectacle of the Gladiators, having placed them by him on purpoſe, when the Weapons of the Combatants were preſented to him, according to the Cuſtome, he deſired them to Survey them, and give him their approbation. It is reported alſo, that having had their Nativities caſt, he told them, <q rend="italic">That they were both under imminent danger, but that it would happen to them another time, and that he was not to be the Author,</q> as afterwards it fell out.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      His own Brother conſpiring againſt him continually, and as it were openly ſolliciting the Army to a defection, in Order to which he was preparing to retire; he could not be perſwaded, either to execute, baniſh, or diſcountenance him by allowing him leſs honour than before; but on the contrary, he comported himſelf towards him as he had
      <pb n="471"/>
      done the firſt day of his Empire, giving him the Title of Companion, and Succeſſor, and with tears in his Eyes, beſeeching him in private, <q rend="italic">That at length they might live lovingly together like Brothers.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. Amidſt theſe actions he was cut off by death not long after, more to the detriment of the whole world, than to his own. When the ſolemnities were ended, in which he wept plentifully before the People, he retired into the Territories of the <placeName rend="italic">Sabines</placeName> ſomewhat more melancholy than formerly, becauſe as he was ſacrificing, the victim broke away, and beſides there happen'd a prodigious clap of thunder, though the day was bright and ſerene. The firſt Stage he came at he was ſurprized with the fit of an Ague, and being carried afterwards in his Litter, it is reported he put by the Curtains, and looking up to heaven complained, <q rend="italic">That he ſhould be taken away ſo undeſervedly,</q> and proteſting that in his whole life he did not know of any action but one he ought to repent of.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But what that at one action was, he neither declared himſelf, nor is it eaſie to conjecture; ſome are of opinion the unlawful converſation he had with his Brothers Wife, came then into his Memory. But <persName rend="italic">Domitia</persName> her ſelf made ſolemn proteſtations, there was never any ſuch thing, and if there had, ſhe would rather have gloried in it, than denied it, as ſhe did ordinarily in all other wickedneſs whatever.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. He died upon the Ides of September in the ſame Town where his Father died two years, two months and twenty days before, in the one and fortieth year of his age. His death being known and publiſh'd, the ſadneſs was as great and univerſal, as it had been a private family. The Senate had not pa-
      <pb n="472"/>
      tience to attend a legal Convocation, but ran all of them immediately to the Council Chamber, and ſhutting up the doors firſt for a while, they opened them again, and in ſhort, rendred him more thanks, and heap'd upon him more praiſes, now he was dead, than they had ever done whilſt he was living, and amongſt them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>