<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>
<pb n="379"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      THE SEVENTH BOOK, Being the LIFE OF <persName rend="italic">SER. SULPICIUS GALBA</persName>, THE SEVENTH Emperour of <placeName rend="italic">ROME</placeName>.
    </p>
    <p>
      THE Race of the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> failed in the perſon of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, which was preſaged by ſeveral ſigns, but eſpecially by two. Not long after <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> was married to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, having a deſire to viſit a Countrey-houſe which ſhe had in the Territory of the <placeName rend="italic">Veii</placeName>; as ſhe was in her journey an Eagle flying over her head, with
      <pb n="380"/>
      a white Chicken in her foot, and a branch of Laurel in its mouth, as ſhe had taken it from the Ground, it happen'd ſhe let it fall juſt into <persName rend="italic">Liviaes</persName> lap, <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> looking upon it as an Omen, gave order for the Chicken to be brought up, and the branch of Laurel to be planted. The young Hen proved ſo fertile, that from the multitude of Chickens which ſhe produc'd the houſe is called <foreign rend="italic">ad Galenas</foreign> to this day, and the Laurel encreas'd ſo faſt, That the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> being to triumph gathered their Laurel Crowns out of the Groves which proceeded from that branch; And whereas it was the cuſtom for all ſuch as were to triumph, to plant others immediately in the places of thoſe they had pull'd up: it was obſerved that near the time of their ſeveral deaths, the branches which each of them ſet, began to wither and die. Accordingly in the laſt year of <persName rend="italic">Nero's</persName> life, not only the branches which he had planted, but the whole Grove dryed up at the roots and periſh'd, and all the white Hens of that prodigious progeny, miſcarried and died. Not long after the Temple of the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> was ſtruck with lightning, the heads of all their Statues thrown down, and the Scepter alſo which <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> held in his hand.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. After <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> ſucceeded, who had no kindred or alliance with the Houſe of the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> though he was of noble and antient extraction without doubt: for in the Titles and inſcriptions upon all his Statues, he writ himſelf alwaies Great Grand-child to <persName rend="italic">Q. Catulus Capitolinus</persName>. And when he was Emperour he ſet up a Pedigree in his Court, by which he derived himſelf from <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> by the Fathers ſide, and from <persName rend="italic">Paſiphae</persName> the Wife of <persName rend="italic">Minos</persName> King of <placeName rend="italic">Crete</placeName>, by the Mother.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      To give a
      <pb n="381"/>
      particular account of the Statues and Elogies of his whole family, would be too long, I ſhall content my ſelf to touch only (and that but ſlightly) upon his own branch, and no more.
    </p>
    <p>
      3. Upon what ground or occaſion the firſt of the <persName rend="italic">Sulpicii</persName> took upon them the name of <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, is doubtful and uncertain. Some would have it, that having been kept out of a Town in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> for a long time, he ſet it on fire at length with bundles of ſticks rubb'd over with <foreign rend="italic">Galbanum</foreign>. Others, that in a long Diſtemper, he uſed Remedies wrapt up in Wool, which he called <foreign rend="italic">Galbeum</foreign>. Others, by reaſon of his fatneſs, which among the Gauls was termed <foreign rend="italic">Galba</foreign>. Or elſe on the contrary, becauſe he was ſlender, like the little worms in the <foreign rend="italic">Eſculi</foreign> which are named <foreign rend="italic">Galbæ</foreign> likewiſe.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      This family became very illuſtrious by <persName rend="italic">Sergius Galba</persName> who had been Conſul, and was eminent for the moſt eloquent man of his time, who by report was the cauſe of the War with <persName rend="italic">Viriatus</persName>; for having by perfidious treachery againſt the <placeName rend="italic">Portugals</placeName> caus'd thirty thouſand of them to be cut off, when he had the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> as Prætor: His Grand-child imputing the loſs of his Conſulſhip to the ill offices of <persName rend="italic">Julius Cæſar</persName> (whoſe Lieutenant he was in <placeName rend="italic">Gaul</placeName>) was in the Conſpiracy with <persName rend="italic">Caſſius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName>, for which he was afterward condemn'd by the Law <foreign rend="italic">Pedia</foreign>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      From this perſon the Grandfather and Father of <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> are deſcended. The Grandfather was more famous for his ſtudies, than for any authority he had in the Common-wealth; for though he was not advanc'd above the degree of a Prætor, yet he put out ſeveral Hiſtories very learned and elaborate. His Father paſt the honourable office of Conſul, though he was a very little man and hunch back'd, and though he had no great fa-culty
      <pb n="382"/>
      in Oratory, yet he pleaded with great induſtry at the Bar.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      His firſt Wife was <persName rend="italic">Mummia Achaica</persName> the Grand-daughter of <persName rend="italic">Catulus</persName>, the Great Grand-daughter of <persName rend="italic">L. Mummius</persName> who took <placeName rend="italic">Corinth</placeName> and raz'd it. His ſecond Wife was <persName rend="italic">Livia Ocellina</persName>, who though ſhe was very handſome and rich, deſir'd his alliance, becauſe of his Nobility, and the more paſſionately, after <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> had taken her aſide, and pulling off his Robe diſcovered to her the imperfection of his ſhape, that ſhe might not be deceived, and reproach him by it afterwards. By <persName rend="italic">Achaica</persName> he had two Sons, <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Servius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> the elder brother having waſted his eſtate with his extravagant profuſion, forſook the City and lived out of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; and being hindred by <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> from putting in his Lot for the Pro-Conſulſhip, in his year, he took it to heart, and made himſelf away.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. The Emperour <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> was born in the 22d. of December, <persName rend="italic">Mar. Valerius Meſſala</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Cn. Lentulus</persName> being Conſuls, in a Countrey Town at the foot of a hill near <placeName rend="italic">Terracinum</placeName> on the left hand of the road towards <placeName rend="italic">Fondi</placeName>. Being adopted by his Mother-in-law, he took upon him the name of <persName rend="italic">Livius</persName>, and the ſurname <persName rend="italic">Ocella</persName>, changing his prænomen alſo, for a while, afterward inſtead of <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> he call'd himſelf <persName rend="italic">Sergius</persName>, and retained that name till he came to be Emperour. It is reported for certain, that as he was one day amongſt other boys of his own age ſaluting of <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> laid his hand upon his Cheek, and told him in Greek, <q rend="italic">And thou alſo my Son ſhalt have a taſt of our Empire.</q> <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> underſtanding by Aſtrology that <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> ſhould be Emperour, but not till he was an old man: <q rend="italic">Let him live in Gods name</q> (ſaid he) <q rend="italic">ſeeing it concerns not us.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      One day
      <pb n="383"/>
      as his Grand-father was ſacrificing for the expiation of a flaſh of lightning, an Eagle ſnatch'd away the entrailes of the Victime out of his hands, and carried them hard by upon an Oak laden with Acorns. The South-ſayers being conſulted thereupon, gave anſwer that it portended Empire and Dominion in his Family, but that it would be long before it happen'd. He reply'd ſmiling, <q rend="italic">Yes indeed that will be when a Mule brings forth a Fole.</q> And afterwards when <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> attempted new troubles, nothing confirm'd and incourag'd him ſo much, as the Foleing of a Mule: For when every one beſides abhorr'd that Omen as obſcene, and execrable, he alone interpreted it fortunate, remembring the aforeſaid ſacrifice, and the expreſſion of his Grand-father.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      When he firſt put on his Virile Robe he dream'd one night that he ſaw <persName rend="italic">Fortune</persName>, and that ſhe told him, <q rend="italic">That ſhe was now ſtanding before his doors, very weary, and that if ſhe were not preſently received in, ſhe ſhould be a prey to the firſt that paſſed by.</q> When he wak'd in the morning, as ſoon as the Court gate was open'd, he found an Image of that Goddeſs in braſs about a Cubit long, lying before the door, which he took up, put it into his lap, and carried it to <placeName rend="italic">Tuſculum</placeName>, where he was wont to paſs away the Summer, and having conſecrated a part of his houſe, he paid his devotions to it once a Month, and adored it with a Vigil every year.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Although he had not attain'd to the age of a Man, yet he forbare not ſtrictly to obſerve an old cuſtom which was now obſolete, and not practis'd in the whole City, but in his houſe, which was to have his freed-men as well as Vaſſals preſent themſelves twice a day before him, in the morning to ſalute him, and the evening to bid him good night.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. He
      <pb n="384"/>
      was well vers'd in all the Liberal Sciences, as likewiſe in the Civil Law: He entred into the State of Matrimony alſo, but when his Wife <persName rend="italic">Lepida</persName>, and two Sons he had by her died, he continued a ſingle man ever after in ſpight of all the opportunities he had to advance himſelf, and the continual Solicitations of <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> (by the death of <persName rend="italic">Domitius</persName> become a Widow) who in his Wifes time had ſo great a paſſion for him, That in a meeting of the great Ladies, the Mother of <persName rend="italic">Lepida</persName> upbraided her with it, and gave her ſome cuffs with her fiſt into the bargain:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But above all he had the greateſt honour for <persName rend="italic">Livia Auguſta</persName> who had as great a value for him while ſhe lived, and at her death left him vaſt riches by her Will, and 50 Millions of Seſterces more than the reſt, but becauſe the ſum was ſet down in figures, and not at length, her heir <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> reduc'd his whole Legacy to half a Million, and that was never paid neither.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. He was advanc'd into places of truſt, before the age appointed by Law during his Prætorſhip. Amongſt the ſolemnities, and ſports called <foreign rend="italic">Floralia</foreign>, he introduc'd a new kind of entertainment, which was Elephants walking upon the Rope. A while after he was made Governour of <placeName rend="italic">Aquitain</placeName>, and executed it almoſt for a twelve month, and then the Conſulſhip for ſix months; and it happen'd in the adminiſtration of that office, <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> ſucceeded <persName rend="italic">L. Domitius</persName> the Father of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Salvius Otho</persName>, the Father of <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> the Emperour, ſucceeded <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, as it had been a preſage of what was to fall out afterwards, he hapning to be Emperour in the midſt betwixt their two Sons.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being ſubſtituted by <persName rend="italic">C. Cæſar</persName> in the place of <persName rend="italic">Gætulicus</persName>, the next day after he arrived at the Army, obſerving the Souldiers at a Spe-
      <pb n="385"/>
      ctacle giving their applauſes and approbations by an obſtreperous clapping of their hands, he reſtrain'd them forthwith, and gave them this Order, to keep their hands under their Cloaks: Whereupon this ſaying went round about the camp,
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">Diſce miles militare, Galba eſt, non Gætulicus.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">Come Souldiers learn ſtrict Diſcipline to fear,
      For Galba, not Gætulicus is here.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      With the ſame diſcipline and ſeverity, he commanded all perſons to their Colours, forbidding any application for paſ-ports or Tickets. Both the new and Veteran Legions, he kept in continual exerciſe, fortifying them thereby, and making them more able for the Wars. Afterwards with incredible diligence having repelled the Barbarians, who had made an inrode even as far as <placeName rend="italic">Gaul</placeName>, he ſo ſignalized himſelf and Army in the preſence of <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName>, That amongſt the multitudes of Troops which he had drawn together out of all his Provinces, there were none deſerv'd more honour, nor received greater recompence than they: And that which added much to his luſtre and reputation was, that he Marſhall'd the Juſts and Tournaments in the open field, with great Conduct and Decorum, bearing his Target in his hand all the while, and another time ran by the Emperours Chariot above twenty miles together.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. When the news of the murder of <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> arrived, many perſons excited him to take the advantage of that opportunity, and ſet up for himſelf; but he
      <pb n="386"/>
      preferred quietneſs and eaſe: by which action he wrought himſelf ſo much into the favour of <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>, that he received him into the number of his moſt intimate friends, and had ſo great an eſteem for him, that being upon an Expedition into Great <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName>, he put off the day ſet for his departure, upon a bare and ſlight indiſpoſition which befell <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> on a ſudden, <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName> being troubled with inteſtine diſorders, and the Tumults of the Barbarians, without drawing Lots according to Cuſtome, he was choſen Pro-conſul into that Province; where he remained two years, ſetled their affairs, and ordered all things with great juſtice and punctuality, even in the ſmalleſt tranſactions.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      There being a great ſcarcity of Victuals in this Expedition, one of his Souldiers was ſo covetous as to ſell a certain meaſure of Corn for a hundred Deniers, which ſaid meaſure was all he had remaining of his allowance: Whereupon <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> commanded, that when that Souldier ſhould want no perſon ſhould dare to ſupply him: and his orders being obey'd the Souldier was ſtarv'd. As to his impartiality in his adminiſtration of Juſtice, he gave a handſome example of it in determining about the propriety of a Horſe: for the proofs on either ſide being imperfect, and not ſufficient to diſcover the truth, he ordered the Horſe to be led with his head cover'd, to the Pond where he uſed to be watered, and that when he had drank, his head ſhould be uncover'd, and he ſhould be his Horſe to whoſe Stable he went directly afterwards.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <pb n="387"/>
    <p>
      8. To recompence his late Noble Exploits in <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName>, and his deportment of old in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, he was honoured with the Triumphal Ornaments, a Triple Sacerdotal dignity, and received into the Society of the <foreign rend="italic">Titii</foreign>, and <foreign rend="italic">Auguſtal</foreign> Prieſts. From that time, to the midſt of <persName rend="italic">Nero's</persName> reign, he lived for the moſt part privately and retired; never ſtirring abroad ſo much as to take the air, but he had a Chariot with him with a million of Seſterces of Gold in it (ready in caſe there ſhould happen any neceſſity of his flight) and in this condition he continued till he came to reſide in <placeName rend="italic">Fondi</placeName>, and the Regency of <placeName rend="italic">Hiſpania Tarraconenſis</placeName> was offer'd to him:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      At his entrance into that Province, as he ſacrificed in one of the Publick Temples, it happened a boy then Miniſtring among the reſt, and holding the Cenſor, had his head turned Grey of a ſudden; nor were there thoſe wanting who interpreted it to import ſome great revolution, and that an old man ſhould ſucceed a young, that is to ſay, <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> ſhould <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>. Not long after there fell a Thunderbolt into the Lake of <placeName rend="italic">Cantabria</placeName>, in which preſently thereupon there were twelve Axes found, an undoubted preſage of Soveraign Dominion.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. For eight years together he Governed his Province with great inequality; at firſt he was very rigorous and ſevere, and immoderate in his chaſtiſements. A Banker being convict of fraud and roguery in his profeſſion, he commanded both his hands to be cut off and nailed to his Compter. He cauſed a Guardian to be Crucified, for poiſoning his Pupil, as being his next Heir; The Criminal imploring the benefit of the Law, and urging himſelf a Ci-
      <pb n="388"/>
      tizen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, He ordered his Croſs ſhould be chang'd, and that inſtead of the Former, they ſhould ſet up another, much higher, and of a whiter colour than ordinary; as if that honour would have given him ſome eaſe and conſolation in his afflictions; By degrees he abated of this vigour, and became negligent, and careleſs, and all becauſe he would give <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> no occaſion of Jealouſie; it being his uſual expreſſion, <q rend="italic">That no man is oblig'd to give an accompt of his doing nothing.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      As he held his Judicial aſſizes in new <placeName rend="italic">Carthage</placeName>, he had intelligence that the Gaules were in Commotion, and as the Lieutenant in <placeName rend="italic">Aquitain</placeName> was begging ſupplies, there arrived Letters from <persName rend="italic">Vindex</persName> exhorting him, <q rend="italic">To declare himſelf in the behalf of all Mankind, and to take upon him the principal Command.</q> He embrac'd the propoſition without any conſiderable debate; partly out of fear, and partly out of hope; for beſides that he had diſcovered private Orders ſent by <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> to his Agents there, to make him away, he was much incouraged by ſeveral favourable Omens, but eſpecially by the Prediction of a young Virgin of good quality, which correſponded exactly with a Prophecie to the ſame purpoſe two hundred years before. The ſence of it was this, <q rend="italic">That one day the Soveraign Prince, and Lord of the whole earth ſhould ariſe out of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. He aſcended therefore into the Tribunal, as it were with deſign to enfranchize ſome of the ſlaves, and having the Images of ſeveral perſons ſet before him which had been condemned and executed by <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, and a young Noble Man by him, which he had ſent for on purpoſe from the neareſt Iſland of the <placeName rend="italic">Baleares</placeName>
      <pb n="389"/>
      where he was then in baniſhment; he deplored the lamentable condition of the times, and being ſaluted Emperour by general conſent, he proteſted, <q rend="italic">He was only a Servant and Lieutenant to the Senate and People.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After this having publiſhed a Vacation from all Judicial proceedings he liſted out of the meaner ſort of people in that Province certain Legions, and Auxiliary Troops to reinforce his old Army, which conſiſted of one Legion, two Wings and three Cohorts. Having finiſhed his Levies, he ſelected a certain number out of the principal perſons for age and experience, and diſpoſed them into the form of a Senate, to conſult and deliberate about affairs of the greateſt importance, as occaſion did offer.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He made choice likewiſe of ſome of the young Gentlemen of the Equeſtrian Order, who (retaining the uſe of their Golden Rings) ſhould be called <foreign rend="italic">Evocati</foreign>, or Appoints, and be as a Guard and Watch about his Chamber, inſtead of Souldiers. He ſent out his Edicts likewiſe through all the Provinces, inviting all perſons to join with him, and particularly to give what aſſiſtance they could, to the Common Cauſe.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      About the ſame time as they were fortifying a Town which he deſign'd for the ſeat of the War, there was a Ring found of great antiquity, upon the ſtone whereof was engraven the picture of Victory with a Trophy; and a while after an Alexandrian ſhip came into <placeName rend="italic">Dertoſa</placeName>, laden with Arms, without either Pilot, Seaman, or Paſſenger in it: ſo that no man could doubt the juſtice of a War commenc'd with ſo many favourable intimati-
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <pb n="390"/>
    <p>
      ons from the Gods. But all theſe hopes and deſignes had like to have been blaſted on a ſudden, by an unexpected diſorder, for as he approached the Camp, one of the Wings of Horſe repenting of the new Oath they had taken, endeavoured what they could to deſert him, and it was no ſmall pains to keep them to their duty. He eſcaped very narrowly likewiſe the conſpiracy of ſeveral ſlaves (with which a freed-man of <persName rend="italic">Nero's</persName> had preſented him on purpoſe) who had queſtionleſs ſlain him as he paſt through a narrow ſtreet to go to his Baths, had they not diſcovered themſelves by exhorting one another, not to loſe ſo fair an opportunity, for being interrogated what opportunity they meant, and not giving the ſatisfaction was expected, they were given the torture, and confeſt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. Upon the neck of theſe misfortunes followed the death of <persName rend="italic">Vindex</persName>; which reduc'd him to that deſperate conſternation, he was almoſt like a mad-man, and was once in the mind to have made himſelf away. But advice coming in from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> in the nick, aſſuring him that <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> was dead too, and all people had taken an Oath of Allegiance to him there; he laid aſide the name of Lieutenant, and aſſumed the Title of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>; after which he put himſelf upon his way, in his Imperial Coat, with a dagger faſtned about his neck, and hanging down before his breaſt; neither would he appear in a Robe or Gown, till all they who were contriving new troubles were defeated and cut off, as namely <persName rend="italic">Miniphedus Sabinus</persName>, Captain of the Guards at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; <persName rend="italic">Fonteius Capito</persName> Lieute-
      <pb n="391"/>
      nant in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, and <persName rend="italic">Clodius Macer</persName> in <placeName rend="italic">Africa</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. There was a rumour ſpread abroad both of his cruelty and avarice, by reaſon of the unuſual rigour he had exerciſed towards the Cities in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Gaul</placeName>, which had ſcrupled joining with him at firſt, by oppreſſing them with exceſſive tributes, diſmantling their Garriſons, cutting off the heads of their Governours, and not excuſing ſo much as their Wives and Children. The <placeName rend="italic">Tarraconenſes</placeName> having preſented him with a Crown of Gold taken out of the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, and weighing as they affirmed 15 pound, he cauſed it to be melted down, and finding it to be three ounces lighter than they pretended, he conſtrain'd them to make it good.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      This report was confirmed and increaſt at his entrance into <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; For he immediately reduced ſuch Marriners (as <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> had taken from the Oar, and liſted amongſt his Legal Souldiers,) to their former condition; and they refuſing with great contumacy and perverſeneſs to ſubmit to an order ſo much to their diſadvantage, demanded the Eagle, and military Enſigns moſt impudently, whereupon he commanded his Horſe to fall upon them and diſperſe them, and not contented with that, he caus'd them to be decimated afterwards. Beſides this he reform'd the German Cohort, which had been eſtabliſht by the <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> of old as a Guard to their Bodies, and good teſtimony they had given all along of their allegiance, and fidelity: notwithſtanding he diſmiſt them without any reward, and ſent them packing into their own Country, pretending they were more inclin'd to <persName rend="italic">Cn. Dola-</persName>
      <pb n="392"/>
      bella than him, becauſe they had encamped themſelves not far from his Gardens.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Many things are reported too, of the meanneſs, and wretchedneſs of his humour (but whether true or falſe I cannot tell) as that when his Table was better furniſh'd than ordinary, he would ſigh and weep; That when his Steward brought him an abſtract of his accompts one time he lik'd his frugality very well, and gave him a diſh of Peaſe for his pains; another time being much pleaſed with <persName rend="italic">Canoes</persName> playing upon the Flute, he pulled out five deniers out of his pocket, and gave them to him very nobly with his own hand.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. Upon theſe accompts his arrival at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> was not ſo grateful to the people, as it appear'd at the firſt ſpectacle after his Entrance, for the <foreign rend="italic">Atellan</foreign> Comedians having begun an old ſong with theſe words,
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">Venit io Simus à Villa.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">That Churliſh Simus, that old Clown,
      Has left his Village for the Town.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
      The Spectators took the Cue, and (as by common conſent) repeated the reſt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. This is moſt certain, he aſſum'd the Empire with more authority, and affection from the people, than he Govern'd it afterwards. For though he did many things worthy of ſo great a Prince, yet thoſe actions were not ſo acceptable as his other were odious.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He ſuffer'd himſelf to be manag'd abſolutely by three perſons, who having their Lodgings with him in his Palace, and being alwayes at his elbow, were commonly call'd his Pedagogues. Their names were
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. It was ſuppos'd likewiſe he had a deſign to limit and reſtrain the Continuation of the Offices of the Knights and Senators, to the ſpace of two years, and to conferr them upon none but ſuch as did ſeriouſly decline them. He revok'd the Liberalities of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>,<pb n="394"/> and reduc'd them to a tenth part, giving Commiſſion to fifty of his Roman Knights, to collect the remainder for him; with authority, That if any Comedian or Champion had ſold what <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> had given them, and imbezel'd or ſpent the Conſideration they received, in that Caſe they might exact and recover it upon the perſons which had purchas'd it.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      On the contrary, there was not any thing, but by the mediation of his Favourites and Freed-men, he ſuffer'd either to be bought for money, or granted for favour; as Taxes, Exemptions, puniſhment of Innocents, impunity for Criminals, &amp;c. Amongſt others he pardon'd <persName rend="italic">Halotus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Tigillinus</persName>, (two the moſt notoriouſly pernitious Inſtruments which <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> imploy'd) though the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> were very ſolicitous to have had them puniſh'd. And as if this had not been ſufficient to diſoblige them, he preferred <persName rend="italic">Halotus</persName> to a moſt honourable Charge; and appear'd ſo far in the juſtification of <persName rend="italic">Tigillinus</persName>, that he publiſh'd an Edict in his behalf, and upbraided the people with their ſeverity.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. Theſe injuſtices repreſented him very black to moſt Degrees, but principally to the Souldiers; For when they who were appointed in his abſence to tender them the Oath, did promiſe in his Name a larger Donative than was ordinary, he not only refus'd to confirm it, but declar'd openly, <q rend="italic">It had been his cuſtom to chooſe, not to purchaſe his Souldiers</q>; by which means he exaſperated all of them, as well thoſe which were abſent, as preſent. Moreover he provok'd his Prætorians not a little, by caſhiering ſeveral of them a while after, upon a bare ſuſpicion of Confederacy with <persName rend="italic">Nymphidius</persName>. But the Army in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName><pb n="395"/> mutiny'd more than the reſt, complaining that they were defrauded of their Rewards, for the good Services they had done both againſt <persName rend="italic">Vindex</persName>, and the Gauls.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      They were the firſt therefore which brake out into open diſobedience; for having the firſt of January, refus'd to ſwear Allegiance to any but to the Senate, they immediately diſpatch'd a Meſſage to the Prætorians, to remonſtrate, <q rend="italic">That they could not acquieſce in an Emperour made in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, and that they would proceed to the Election of ſuch a one, as might be acceptable to all the Armies.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> no ſooner underſtood theſe tranſactions, ſuppoſing they deſpiſed him more for want of Children, than his Old Age, he reſolv'd to adopt one; and caſting his eye upon <persName rend="italic">Piſo Frugi Licinianus</persName>, (a young Gentleman for whom he had alwayes a great eſteem, and in all his Wills had made him his Heir) he took him out of the throng, which were come at that time to bid him Good morrow, and pronouncing him his Son, he carried him to the Camp, and in the preſence of the Souldiers adopted him, but without any mention of the Largeſs they had been promis'd before: By which he gave ſo fair an occaſion to the deſignes of <persName rend="italic">Salvius Otho</persName>, that he accompliſhed them within ſix dayes after the ſaid adoption.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      18. From the very beginning of his Empire, his misfortunes were denounc'd by frequent and conſiderable Prodigies: As he was on his Journey to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, all the Towns through which he paſs'd, doing Sacrifice for his happy arrival; a Bull being amazed and affrighted with the blow of the Axe, and breaking<pb n="396"/> the Ropes wherewith he was tyed, ran violently upon his Chariot, and leaping upon him with his fore-feet, all dedaub'd him with blood: And as afterwards he alighted, one of his Guards being puſh'd forwards by the Crowd, had like to have wounded him with his Lance. His entrance into the City, and Palatium both, was attended with a great trembling of the Earth, and a noiſe like the Lowing of a Beaſt.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After which there follow'd other preſages, more manifeſtly dreadful: Amongſt all his Jewels he had ſelected and laid by one, ſet very rich with Pearls and Precious Stones, which he intended to preſent as an Ornament to his Goddeſs <persName rend="italic">Fortune</persName> at <placeName rend="italic">Tuſculum</placeName>; but on a ſudden, conceiving it worthy of a more magnificent place, he dedicated it to <persName rend="italic">Venus Capitolina</persName>: The next night he dream'd, he ſaw the Image of <persName rend="italic">Fortune</persName> complaining, that ſhe had been defrauded of her Preſent, and threatning in the ſame manner to take from him, what ſhe had formerly beſtow'd. Being affrighted at this Viſion, he got up by break of day, in order to his Expiation, diſpatching his Officers before to <placeName rend="italic">Tuſculum</placeName> to prepare all things ready for a Sacrifice at his arrival: But when he came thither, he found nothing but a few warm Embers upon the Altar, and an Old Man in black ſitting hard by, with Incenſe in a Glaſs Veſſel in one hand, and Wine in an Earthen Cup in the other.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      It was obſerv'd alſo, that when he Sacrificed upon the Calends of January, his Crown fell off of his head; as he took his Auſpices, the Pullets flew away. On the day of the aforeſaid adoption, when he was to make a Speech to the Souldiers, by the forgetfulneſs of his Servants, his Caſtrenſian Chair was not ſet before the Tribunal according to Cuſtom; and when he was to ſit down in the Senate, his Curule Chair was<pb n="397"/> placed perverſly with the back towards him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      19. Not long before he was ſlain, as he was Sacrificing one morning, he who had the inſpection of the Entrails, admoniſh'd him ſeveral times to have a care, for there was danger impending, and his murderers were not far off. A while after, word was brought him, that <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> had poſſeſs'd himſelf of his Guards Camp, whereupon he was adviſed by his Friends to repair immediately to them, ſeeing by his preſence and authority he might poſſibly compoſe them; but inſtead of following their Counſel, he reſolv'd only to look to the ſecurity of his Perſon, by rallying up his Legionary Guards, which were at that time diſperſed in their Quarters. He put on alſo a Linen Curaſs well quilted, yet not ſufficient (as he ſaid himſelf) to defend him againſt the points of ſo many Swords.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But the Conſpirators to draw and allure him abroad, into the open Streets, had ſpread abroad falſe reports, that the Tumult was appeaſed, that the Authors were kill'd, and that the reſt were coming to congratulate his ſucceſs, and to promiſe him all dutiful obedience for the future; whereupon giving too much credit to their intelligence, he went forth to meet them, with ſo much confidence and ſecurity, that a Souldier boaſting publickly, he had ſlain <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> with his own hand, he ſtopp'd him, and demanded, <q rend="italic">By whoſe Authority;</q> and advanc'd immediately into the <placeName rend="italic">Forum</placeName>. The Horſe-men who had order to kill him, having diſpers'd the Peaſants, and put them out of the way, put on, till perceiving him at a diſtance, they made a Halt for a while; but then clapping Spurs again to their Horſes, they fell upon him and murder'd him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
<pb n="398"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      20. Some there are which report, that at their firſt inſult, he cryed out to them, <q rend="italic">Fellow Souldiers, What do you do? am not I yours, and you mine?</q> and to that he promiſed them their Donative; but moſt of Authors aſſure us, that he ſubmitted his throat freely to them, and willed them, (ſince it was their pleaſures) to do their work, and ſtrike without fear. It was not a little ſtrange, that amongſt all that were preſent, not one perſon attempted any thing in his reſcue; and that the Souldiers which were ſent for, rejected his Orders, except only one Troop of German Horſe, who in acknowledgement of the care he had taken of them in their ſickneſſes, and fatigues, ran to him with all ſpeed; but miſtaking their way, they arrived too late.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was ſlain not far from the Lake <placeName rend="italic">Curtius</placeName>, and his body left as they had kill'd him, till a Common Souldier returning from Forrage, laid down his burden, and cut off his head: and becauſe by reaſon of his baldneſs, he could not take it by the hair, he hid it in his lap, and by and by thruſt his thumb into the mouth of it, and in that poſture carried it to <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName>; who gave it to the Pedees, and Servants of the Camp; and they having fixed it upon a Spear, carried it with great acclamations round about the Camp, repeating theſe words very often, <q rend="italic">Now Galba you may take your ſportful Time.</q> That which provok'd them eſpecially to that inſolent expreſſion, was, that there was a Story among the people, how not many dayes before, hearing one commending the ſhape and vigour of his body, <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> was ſo vain as to ſay, <q rend="italic">I am yet luſty and in prime</q>; of them, a Freed-man of <persName rend="italic">Patrobius Neronianus</persName> bought the head, for a hundred pieces of Gold, and flung it into the ſame place where his Patron (<persName rend="italic">Patrobius</persName>) was formerly Executed by the Command<pb n="399"/> of <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>. At length (though late) his Steward <persName rend="italic">Argius</persName> buried both his Head and his Trunk together, in his private Gardens near the way <placeName rend="italic">Aurelia</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      21. His Stature was indifferent, neither too low, nor too tall, his head bald, his eyes grey, his noſe aquiline, his hands and feet noded, and diſtorted with the Gout, inſomuch that he could neither endure a ſhooe upon one, nor had ſtrength to hold a book, or turn over the leaves with the other: beſides on his right ſide he had an excreſcence of fleſh, which hung down ſo, as it was hardly to be kept up with a ſwathing band.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      22. He was reported to be a great feeder, and that in winter time he had his breakfaſt uſually before it was day. As to his ſuppers they were ſo plentiful, that the relicks and reverſions being gather'd together in heaps, he commanded them to be carried about and diſtributed amongſt thoſe which ſtood waiting at his feet: he was too much inclined to an unnatural affection for Boyes, eſpecially ſuch as were old, and paſt the Concupiſcence of other people; if we may believe what was publickly diſcours'd in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, <persName rend="italic">Icelus</persName> one of his old Catamites bringing him word that <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> was ſlain, he not only received him with a thouſand Careſſes, but intreated him to have his hair pluckt immediately, according to the Cuſtome of thoſe kind of perſons, and took him aſide when he had done.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      23. He was ſlain in the ſeventy third year of his age, and the ſeventh Month of his Empire. The Senate upon their firſt opportunity Decreed him a Statue, to be ſet up upon a pillar adorned with the Stems of Ships, in that part of the <placeName rend="italic">Forum</placeName><pb n="400"/> where he loſt his life; but <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> repealed that Decree, upon an opinion that <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> had formerly brib'd, and diſpatch'd a certain perſon privately out of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> into <placeName rend="italic">Judæa</placeName> on purpoſe to murder him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>