<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>
            
<pb n="403"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      THE EIGHTH, Being the LIFE OF <persName rend="italic">MARCUS SALVIUS OTHO</persName> THE EIGHTH Emperour of <placeName rend="italic">ROME</placeName>.
    </p>
    <p>
      THE Anceſtors of <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName>, had their Original in a Town called <placeName rend="italic">Ferentinum</placeName>; it was an antient and honourable Family, and deſcended from the Princes of <placeName rend="italic">Etruria</placeName>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">M. Salvius Otho</persName>, the Grandfather, (whoſe Father was of the Equeſtrian Order, though his Mothers condition was ſo mean, it is not known whether ſhe was Free-born or not) was brought up in the houſe of <persName rend="italic">Livia Auguſta</persName>, and by her Favour made a Senator, but arriv'd to no higher Charge than the Prætorſhip: His Father, <persName rend="italic">Lucius Otho</persName>, was Nobly deſcended by the Mother ſide, had ſo many and ſo conſiderable Allies, was ſo dear to <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, and reſembled him ſo much, that many believ'd he was his Son.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="404"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He acquitted himſelf very worthily, and with the reputation of a ſtrict Magiſtrate, in all his Offices in the City, in his Pro-Conſulſhip in <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName>, and in his extraordinary Commands. Certain Souldiers having repented themſelves of being engaged in the Sedition of <persName rend="italic">Camillus</persName>, killed their Captains as Authors of that revolt againſt <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName>; but <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> who was then in <placeName rend="italic">Illyrium</placeName>, had the courage to command their heads to be cut off, not only in his own preſence, but in the midſt of the Camp, though he underſtood very well, that <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> had approv'd, and advanc'd them for what they had done.
    </p>
    <p>
      This action of his augmented his Glory, but was for ſome time a diminution to his Favour; yet he ſoon recover'd it, by the detection of a Conſpiracy againſt <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> by a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight, whoſe Servants had diſcover'd it to him. The Senate conferr'd an extraordinary honour upon him, erecting a Statue for him in the <placeName rend="italic">Palatium</placeName>; and <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> having rais'd him to the Rank of the Patricians, after he had commended him largely, concludes with this Elogie, <q rend="italic">He is ſo excellent a perſon, I would not wiſh to have any better Children of my own.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
      His wife was called <persName rend="italic">Albia Terentia</persName>, a very honourable Lady, by whom he had two Sons, <persName rend="italic">L. Titianus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Marcus</persName> who carried the Surname of his Father. He had likewiſe by her one Daughter, which he contracted to <persName rend="italic">Druſus</persName> the Son of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, before ſhe was marriageable.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="405"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. The Emperour <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> was born the 27th. of April, <persName rend="italic">Camillus Arantiu</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Domitius Ænobarbus</persName> being Conſuls; From his very youth he was ſo prodigal and perverſe, his Father was conſtrain'd to chaſtiſe him ſeveral times. It is reported, he had a Cuſtom of running up and down the Streets in the night, and where he met with any unable to reſiſt him, either being too weak, or in drink, he ſeized upon him, ſpread his Cloak upon the ground, and putting him into it, had him toſſed in the air.
    </p>
    <p>
      His Father dying, not long after he addreſs'd himſelf to a Lady of the Court, in no ſmall favour with the Emperour; and that his Courtſhip might turn to the better accompt, he pretended a moſt paſſionate affection, though his Miſtreſs was ſo old, ſhe was almoſt decrepit. By her means he inſinuated into the favour of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, and preſerv'd himſelf without much difficulty among the chiefeſt of his Friends, by reaſon of the conformity of their humours, and (as ſome ſay) their mutual proſtitutions. In effect, his intereſt and authority was ſo great, that having contracted for a conſiderable recompence, if he brought off a man of Conſular degree, (who was at that time queſtion'd for Extortion) he had the confidence to bring him into the Senate to give them thanks, before they had fully granted his reſtitution.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. Being his Privado in this manner, and acquainted with all his intrigues, that day which <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> deſigned for the killing of his Mother, he invited them both to a Supper, and treated them with all poſſible magnificence, to avert all ſuſpicion from himſelf. Beſides this, <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> having a great affection for <persName rend="italic">Poppæa Sabina</persName>, his Miſtreſs at that time, took her away from her Husband, and ſent her to <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName>, who receiv'd her into his houſe under colour of Marriage; And
      <pb n="406"/>
      not content to have corrupted her, he became ſo fond on her, he had not patience to endure the Emperour to be his Rival. It is confidently affirm'd, that he not only refus'd ſuch as were ſent from <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> to demand her, but that he coming himſelf upon the ſame errand one day, <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> ſhut him out of his Gate, though he begg'd of him to deliver her to him, and added threats to his importunity. Upon this repulſe, <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> thought of nothing more than ſeparating theſe two Lovers, and diſſolving their pretended Marriage; and accordingly he diſpatch'd <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> on an Embaſſie into <placeName rend="italic">Portugal</placeName>, well conſidering that a greater and more ſevere puniſhment of his inſolence, might diſcover the whole intrigue: Yet ſo far it was known, that this Diſtich was made and diſperſed;
    </p>
    <p>
      <foreign rend="italic">Cur Otho mentito ſit quæritis exul honore?<lb/>
      Uxoris mœchus cœperat eſſe ſuæ.</foreign>
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">Why's Otho to this falſe preferment brought?<lb/>
      Cauſe with his own dear Wife he would be naught.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
      He was only Quæſtor, before he was advanced to this Province; yet he govern'd it with ſingular integrity and moderation.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. But at laſt, occaſion of revenge being preſented, he was the firſt who went over to <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, and from that very moment revolving with himſelf the condition of affairs, he conceiv'd great hopes of attaining the Empire for himſelf; but his greateſt encouragement was from the prediction of <persName rend="italic">Seleucus</persName> the Aſtrologer, who having promis'd him of old, that he ſhould be Emperour, arrived unexpectedly at that time, and aſſured him it ſhould be then very ſuddenly. After that, he omitted no kind of courteſie which might
      <pb n="407"/>
      gain him the affection of all people. Whenever he made an Entertainment for the Emperour, he diſtributed Money amongſt his Guards, and oblig'd the other Souldiers all ways he could think of. One of them being in Suit with his Neighbour, about the bounds and limits of their Lands, and he being choſen as Umpire, he bought the whole Eſtate, and gave it freely to the Souldier; inſomuch as there was ſcarce a man, which had not ſo much honour and eſteem for him, as to declare publickly he was the only perſon worthy to ſucceed in the Empire.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. His firſt hopes were that he ſhould be adopted by <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, and that he expected every day; But after <persName rend="italic">Piſo</persName> was preferr'd, and himſelf defeated that day, he turn'd his thoughts upon violence, contriving to eſtabliſh himſelf by force, to which he was excited (beſides the trouble of his mind) by the conſideration of his debts, which he was no other way ever able to pay. Nor was he aſhamed to declare, <q rend="italic">That if he was not Emperour he could not ſubſiſt, and that it was all one to him whether he fell by his Enemy in the Field, or by his Creditors in the Courts of Law.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
      A few days before, he had ſqueez'd out of one of <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> ſervants 25000 Crowns, for a Stewardſhip he had procured for him; by the ſtrength and aſſiſtance of which ſum, he began his enterprize; The firſt he communicated withal, were five Archers of the Guard, and ten others which they recommended, (every one two) to each of which he paid down 10000 Seſterces, and promis'd them 50000 a piece more. Theſe ingag'd others, but not many, as being aſſured of greater numbers, when the deſign came to be put in execution.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. Immediately after <persName rend="italic">Piſo</persName> was adopted, his reſolution was to have poſſeſſed himſelf of the Camp where
      <pb n="408"/>
      the Guards quarter'd, and ſet upon <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> as he was at Supper in the Palace, but he was diverted from that, by the reſpect he had to the Cohort which was then upon the Guard, as apprehending he ſhould make it too odious, ſeeing by misfortune the ſaid Cohort had been already upon the Guard both when <persName rend="italic">Caligula</persName> was kill'd, and <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> deſerted; beſides ſome certain religious ſcruples which he had, and <persName rend="italic">Seleucus</persName> his advice prevail'd with him to protract for ſome time; but at laſt the day being ſet, and his accomplices admoniſh'd to be in the <placeName rend="italic">Forum</placeName> and to attend him under the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Saturn</persName>, exactly by the Golden Miliarium, he went to ſalute <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> in the Morning, and according to Cuſtom was received with a kiſs, and admitted to be preſent at his ſacrifice, and to hear the predictions of his Southſayers; at length one of his freed men bringing him word (as was agreed) that the Architects were come, he departed as he pretended to ſee a houſe which was to be ſold, and ſlipt in great haſt, through a poſtern-gate in the Palace, to be preſent at the Rendezvouz; Others reported he counterfeited a fit of an Ague, and deſired thoſe who were by to make his excuſe if he was ask'd for; then clapping himſelf cloſe in a kind of a Sedan or womans Litter, he made directly for the Camp, but his Chair-men being tired, he was forc'd to forſake his Chair, and betake himſelf to his feet; his ſhooe being looſe, gave him ſome ſtop, but the Souldiers impatient of loſing more time, ran to him, caſt themſelves about his neck, ſaluted him Emperour, and brought him to the Principia, or chief quarter in the Camp, with their ſwords drawn, and ſuch General acclamations, as if every one which followed him, had been a partner in the Conſpiracy. Having from thence diſ-
      <pb n="409"/>
      patch'd inſtruments for the killing of <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Piſo</persName>, and made a Speech to the Souldiers, to Cajole them, and work himſelf into their favour, he told them, <q rend="italic">That he would neither accept nor pretend to any thing but what they in their prudence ſhould leave him.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. About the ſhutting in of the day, he went into the Senate, and having in a ſhort narration repreſented to them how he was publickly arreſted in the <placeName rend="italic">Forum</placeName>, and conſtrain'd to take the Empire upon him, which he promis'd to manage to the common ſatisfaction, he retired to the Palace. Beſides the Titles which his flatterers gave him, and ſuch as congratulated his advancement to the Empire, the common people called him <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, which he was ſo far from diſguſting, that ſome ſay in all his firſt diſpatches to the Governours of the Provinces, his Grants, and his Letters, he ſubſcrib'd <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> as his Surname. This is moſt certain that he ſuffer'd the Statues and Images of <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> to be ſet up again in their old places, and reſtored his ſervants and freed-men to the Offices they enjoy'd before; and that the firſt Warrant he ſigned, was for 50 millions of Seſterces, for finiſhing the Golden Palace which <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> had begun.
    </p>
    <p>
      It is ſaid that the ſame night being frighted in his dream, he fetch'd ſeveral profound ſighs in his ſleep, upon which his ſervants running into his Chamber, found him by his Bedſide upon the Ground, after which there was no ſort of expiation which he did not try to appeaſe the Ghoſt of <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, who ſeemed to beat and puſh him ſo rudely out of the bed. The next day as he was at his Auſpices, a tempeſt ariſing became ſo violent, it blew him down, upon which he was heard to mumble this Greek Proverb oftentimes to himſelf.
    </p>
    <p>
      <foreign rend="italic">Τί γάρ μοι κὶ μακρῖς αύλεις ;</foreign>
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">What does this mean? I cannot ſee,<lb/>
      How this wind Inſtrument relates to me.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="410"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. About the ſame time the Armies in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName> took an Oath of fidelity to <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName>, which coming to his ear, he propos'd to the Senate that they would depute ſome perſon or other to go to them, and let them know that they had choſen an Emperour already, to exhort them to be quiet and continue the concord betwixt them. Yet in the mean time, by Meſſengers and private Letters he offer'd <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> a moiety of the Empire, and to marry his daughter beſides. But war being declar'd, and the troops which <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> ſent before, drawing near, he aſſay'd the affection and allegiance of his Prætorians to the ruine and deſtruction almoſt of the whole Order of the Senators.
    </p>
    <p>
      Orders being given for carrying a certain quantity of arms on Shipboard to be tranſported to ſome other place, as they were removing out of the Camp in the night, ſome of the Souldiers apprehending there might be treaſon in the buſineſs, gave the alarm to the reſt, and immediately they ran to their arms, and marching in a tumultuous manner to the Palace, without any officer to command them, they demanded liberty to put the whole Senate to the Sword. The Tribunes oppos'd themſelves to this tumult, but were repulſt, ſome of them kill'd, and the Souldiers (all bloody as they were) ran up in a throng into the room where <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> was at Supper, crying out, <q rend="italic">Where is the Emperour, where is the Emperour</q>, and would not be ſatisfied till they had ſeen him themſelves. In the mean time <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> prepared for his March with all poſ-
      <pb n="411"/>
      ſible diligence, but without any care or reſpect of religion, not ſo much as to the Ceremony of the <foreign rend="italic">Ancilia</foreign> or ſacred Shields, that were removed out of their proper place, but not reſtored again at that time; which in old time was lookt upon as ominous or unfortunate. Upon that very day alſo, the Prieſts and Miniſters of (<persName rend="italic">Cybele</persName>) the Mother of the Gods began to make their lamentations and complaints. To conclude, beſides theſe circumſtances, the Auſpices were croſs and averſe; for thoſe victims which were ſacrificed to <persName rend="italic">Pluto</persName> were favourable, whereas in thoſe kind of ſacrifices the more contrary they are, the more happy they are eſteemed. And at the beginning of his March, he was delay'd by the inundation of <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>, and twenty miles further the way was ſtopt up with the ruines of houſes which by accident were fallen down.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. With the ſame temerity, (though it was the judgment of all people it was his intereſt to temporize, and protract, in reſpect the enemy was preſt with ſcarcity of Victuals, and ingaged in ſtreight and very incommodious places,) he reſolv'd nevertheleſs to give them battle upon the firſt occaſion, either that he was precipitated by his impatience, and hoped to defeat them more eaſily before <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName> ſhould come up, or elſe becauſe he was not able to reſtrain the ardour of his Souldiers, who preſt him to fight. Yet was not he preſent himſelf at that conflict, but ſtaid at <placeName rend="italic">Brixillum</placeName>. In three ingagements he had the better, but they were but ſmall ones. The firſt was near the Alps, the next not far from <placeName rend="italic">Placentia</placeName>, and the third at a place called <placeName rend="italic">Caſtoris</placeName>, but in the laſt and moſt conſiderable battle at <placeName rend="italic">Bebriacum</placeName> he was circumvented by treachery, and overcome. For Overtures having been made, and the Souldiers brought
      <pb n="412"/>
      out as it were to Careſs one another, whilſt the conditions of the accommodation were under debate, in the very time of their ſalutations, the enemy fell upon him on a ſudden and routed him.
    </p>
    <p>
      Upon this misfortune he took up a reſolution of making himſelf away, and ſome do rationally believe, it was rather out of ſhame and an unwillingneſs to expoſe the lives of ſo many men, in aſſerting of his ſoveraignty any farther, than out of any deſpair or diffidence of his forces, ſeeing there were freſh troops remaining entire, which he had reſerv'd with himſelf for a ſecond tryal of his fortune, beſides others upon their March to him out of <placeName rend="italic">Dalmatia</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Pannonia</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Mæſia</placeName>. Neither were thoſe which were beaten, ſo cowed or dejected, but that to expiate their diſgrace, and revenge themſelves of the Treachery of their Enemies, they would have attempted any thing alone of themſelves, without farther Supplies.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. In this Battle my Father <persName rend="italic">Suetonius Lenis</persName> was preſent, Commanding in the thirteenth Legion as <foreign rend="italic">Tribunus Auguſticlavius</foreign>, or Tribune of the ſecond degree: He told us many times afterwards, that <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> from the time he was but a private perſon, deteſted all manner of Civil War ſo highly, that one day as he was at Dinner, a certain perſon happening to ſpeak ſomething of the end of <persName rend="italic">Caſſius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName>, he fell into a fit of trembling, with the horrour of it. Nor would he have undertaken to have diſpoſſeſs'd <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, had he not been aſſured to effect it without coming to a War.
    </p>
    <p>
      He added likewiſe, that the ſaid <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> was incited to a contempt of his life, by the example of a private Souldier, who having brought him the News that his Army was defeated, and no body believing him, but on the contrary charging him as a Liar ſometimes, and ſometimes as a Coward,
      <pb n="413"/>
      and one that had run from his Colours, he fell upon his Sword at the Emperors feet; who admiring that inſtance of his courage and fidelity, cryed out, <q rend="italic">That for the future he would no more bring ſuch Worthy and Gallant men into danger, upon his ſcore.</q>
    </p>
    <p>
      After this he called his Brother, Nephew, and Friends, and exhorting them particularly to ſhift for themſelves, he kiſs'd and embrac'd them, and then ſent them away; when they were gone, he withdrew himſelf into a private room, writ two Conſolatory Letters to his Siſter, and one to <persName rend="italic">Meſſalina</persName>, who had formerly been married to <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>, and whom he had deſigned for his own, recommending his memory and aſhes to her. That done, he burnt whatever Letters or Papers he had, leſt falling into the hands of the Conquerour, they might be made uſe of to the prejudice of any body; and laſt of all, he diſtributed what Money he had in his Treaſury at that time, amongſt his Domeſticks.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. Prepared in this manner, and reſolved to dye, a Tumult ariſing, he perceiv'd the Souldiers ſtopping and upbraiding thoſe who were ſtealing away, as Traytors, and deſerters of their Soveraign; whereupon he ſaid, <q rend="italic">Nay then let us add this night to our life,</q> with which words, he forbad any more violence to be uſed, and ordering his Chamber to be left open until it was very late, he allow'd free entrance to all which had a mind to ſee him. After this, having quench'd his thirſt with a draught of cold water, he took two Daggers, and having tryed, and choſen the ſharpeſt, he laid it under his pillow, and the doors being made faſt, he fell into a moſt profound ſleep; being awak'd about break of day, he gave himſelf a ſtab under the left pap, and when at the firſt groan his Servants ran in, he dyed, ſometimes concealing, and
      <pb n="414"/>
      ſometimes diſcovering his wound. According as he had commanded, he was buried immediately, having left this life in the thirty eighth year of his age, and the ninety fifth day of his reign.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. To have ſeen the perſon and habit of <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName>, would have made one ſworn he had not been ſo couragious: For 'tis reported, his ſtature was very ſmall, his feet ill, and going inwards with his toes: His neatneſs and finicalneſs, had more of the woman than man; the hair of his body was pull'd off conſtantly; in reſpect that his hair was very thin upon his head, he wore a Border or Cap ſo exquiſitely well fitted, it was not to be known from his own: He ſhaved every day, and rubb'd his face over with ſteep'd bread, which cuſtom he had uſed from the time he began firſt to have a Beard, on purpoſe that he might have none. It is ſaid alſo, that he many times celebrated Divine Service to <persName rend="italic">Iſis</persName> openly, in a Religious Veſtment of fine Linen. For which reaſons (in my opinion) it is, that his death appear'd the more wonderful, becauſe ſo diſcrepant and unſuitable to his life. Moſt of the Souldiers who were preſent about him, after they had kiſſed his hands and his feet, and given him the character of a moſt magnanimous and ſingular Emperour, they kill'd themſelves about his Funeral Pile. Thoſe alſo who were abſent, underſtanding the deplorable news, were ſo ſenſibly affected therewith, that they ſlew one another. In ſhort, many who whilſt he was alive, deteſted and abhorr'd him, applauded and cry'd him up as much when he was dead; and it was a common opinion and diſcourſe among the people, <q rend="italic">That it was not ſo much ambition, and immoderate deſire of Rule, that made him depoſe <persName rend="italic">Galba</persName>, as a deſign to reſtore and re-eſtabliſh the Liberty of the Commonwealth.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>