<TEI><text><body><div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Ulius Cafar was but fixteen years old when his Father died: The next year he was defigned Flamen Dialis, or High Priest of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, and having divorc'd himself from <persName rend="italic">Coffutia</persName> (whoſe birth was not ſo eminent as her fortune, and to whom he had been contracted in his Minority) he Married <persName rend="italic">Cornelia</persName> the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Cinna</persName> (who had been four times Conful) by whom he had his Daughter <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>. <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> ufed all poffible arguments to have feparated him from her, but he would never be induced, infomuch that having ſequeſtred his Sacerdotal Dignity, his Wives Dower, and his Paternal Eſtate, no wonder if he ſuſpected his adherence to his Enemies.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      And indeed to evade the indignation of ſo puiſſanta perſon, <persName rend="italic">Cæfar</persName> was conftrained to abfcond, to change his Quarters every night (though under the violence of a Quartan Ague) and to bribe himſelf out of their hands who had Orders to arreſt him: At length by the interceffion of the Vestal Virgins, <persName rend="italic">Mamercus Emilius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Aurelius Cotta</persName>, his near Kinfmen, he obtained indemnity;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      But certain it is, that when <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> had for a long time reſiſted the importunities of his intimate Friends, and ſuch perſons of quality as had interpoſed in his behalf, being at laſt overcome, he cry'd out, as infpired, or by way of Prediction, <q rend="italic">Take him then, if you must have him but know, the person for whom you have been ſo zealous, will be the destruction of the Nobility and Common Interest we have ſo ardently defended for I affure you, in <persName rend="italic">Cæfar</persName> there are many <persName rend="italic">Marii</persName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. His firſt bearing Arms was in <placeName rend="italic">$A/ia$</placeName>, as a Voluntier, or Reformade, under <persName rend="italic">M. Thermus</persName> the Præ- tor, by whom being ſent into <placeName rend="italic">Bithynia</placeName> to expedite the Fleet, he protracted the time of his ſtay with <persName rend="italic">Nicomedes</persName>, and was ſuſpected to be his proſtitute, which jealouſie was much confirmed, when he returried fuddenly to him again, upon no greater pretence, than the folliciting for Monies duetoa Libertine his Client; but his fucceeding gallantries remo ved thoſe afperfions and preſented him with a Civick Crown at the taking of <placeName rend="italic">Milyene</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. He ferved alfo in <placeName rend="italic">Cilicia</placeName> under <persName rend="italic">Servilius Ifau ricus</persName>, but that was not long, for hearing of <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName>'s death, and hoping for new troubles from the difcontents of <persName rend="italic">M. Lepidus</persName>, he returned immediately to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, yet not daring to put any confidence in his Conduct, when he came there; and finding things leſs probable than he expected, he could not be wrought to his Party, though <persName rend="italic">Lepidus</persName> made him fair proffers, and uſed all means pollible to ingage him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4.. When thoſe diſcords were over he accuſed <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Dolabella</persName> (a Conſular man, and one that had triumph'd) of Extortion; but being unable to make good his Charge, and <persName rend="italic">Dolabella</persName> acquit, he thought fit to withdraw to <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName>, as well to decline the envy he had contracted, as to ſtudy with more leifure under <persName rend="italic">Apollonius Molon</persName>, one of the moſt celebrated Orators of thoſe times; Having embark'd himself in Winter with this deſign, he was taken by Pyrats off the Ifle of <placeName rend="italic">Pharmacusa</placeName>, in whoſe clutches he continued near forty days, with great perturbation; during the moſt part of his reftraint he had only with him, a Phyſitian, and two Valets de Chambre,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      the rest of his Companions and Servants being fent in the beginning of his Captivity to raiſe Money for his Ransom; fifty Talents being paid, they fet him on ſhoar: to recompence their kindnefs, he puts immediately to Sea, purfues, overtakes, takes, and executes them, as he had often threatned <foreign rend="italic">en raillerie</foreign>, when he was their prifoner. <persName rend="italic">Mithridates</persName> in the mean time making great devaftation in the Neighbouring Countries, and he thinking it diſhonourable to lie ſtill, whilft the Allies were in diſtreſs, paſt from <placeName rend="italic">Rhodes</placeName> into <placeName rend="italic">$A/ia$</placeName>, and leavying what Forces he could, he beat his Governour out of thoſe Provinces, and confirmed ſeveral Cities in their allegiance, which before were inclining to a Revolt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. The firſt dignity conferred upon him by the fuffrage of the People after his return to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, was, the Military Tribune ſhip; as long as he enjoy'd it, he was a ftrenuous ſupporter of that Party which ſtood for the reſtitution of the Authority of the Tribunes, which had been much weakned by <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName>: By an Act of the Commons, paſs'd at the motion of <persName rend="italic">Plofius</persName>, he obtained that <persName rend="italic">Lu. Cinna</persName>, his Wives Brother, and ſeveral others (which had followed him in his confederacy with <persName rend="italic">Lepidus</persName>, and fled with him to <persName rend="italic">Sertorius</persName>, after he was killed) ſhould be recalled; in order to which, he made an Oration to the People himſelf.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. Being Quastor, he made Funeral Orations (as the cuſtome was in the praise of <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>, (his Aunt by the Fathers ſide) and <persName rend="italic">Cornelia</persName> his Wife. In his commendation of his Aunt, ſpeaking of the Extraction of her felf and Father, he has theſe Words; <q rend="italic">My Aunt <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> by the Mother-fide was defcended from Kings, and by the Fathers, She was allied to the Gods; for from <persName rend="italic">Ancus Marcius</persName>, the <persName rend="italic">Marcii</persName> (Surnamed REGES) are derived, and the <persName rend="italic">Julii</persName> (which is our Family) from VENUS. In our Houſe therefore, we have the Majesty of Kings, (who are the most Potent amongst Men) and the Veneration of the Gods, (who are more powerful than they.)</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      7. His Wife <persName rend="italic">Cornelia</persName> being dead, he Married <persName rend="italic">Pompeia</persName> the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Q. Pompeius</persName>, and GrandDaughter to <persName rend="italic">L.Sylla</persName>, but she was repudiate in a ſhort time, upon fufpicion of Adultery with <persName rend="italic">Clodius</persName>, and a confident report, that he had acceſs to her in the habit of a Woman, whilft they were upon Publick and Divine Ceremonies; and ſo ſtrongly had this rumour obtained, that by expreſs order of the Senate, he was to be indited of Sacrilege.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Being Quastor, the Government of the farther part of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> fell to his Lot, where by Order from the Pra- 1tor, as he was making his Circuit, and keeping the Courts of Juſtice in that Province, he arrived at <placeName rend="italic">Cadez</placeName>; where, obferving the Image of <persName rend="italic">Alexander the Great</persName> in the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Hercules</persName>, he fetch'd a deep figh, as confcious of his own floth, for having - done nothing Remarkable, at the Age wherein he had conquered the World; upon which contemplation, he beg'd immediately to be diſmiſt, that he might attend fome greater enterprize at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having dream'd alſo the night before that he had raviſh'd his Mother, it exalted him exceedingly, when the Interpreters told him, it was a preſage of his Dominion over the whole Earth, feeing the Mother, which seemed to have been violated, could be nothing but the Earth, which was the common Parent of all.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. Departing therefore from thence before his Commiſſion was expired, he went amongst the <placeName rend="italic">Latin</placeName> Colonies, who at that time were preſſing their infranchiſements, and he had queſtionleſs excited them to fedition, had not the Confuls fruſtrated his deſigns, by retaining the Legions for fome time in thoſe parts, which were appointed for <placeName rend="italic">Cilicia</placeName>, which yet could not hinder him from greater praCtiſes in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. For not many days before he entred upon the Ædileship, he was ſuſpected of conſpiracy with <persName rend="italic">M. Craffus</persName> (a Confular Man) <persName rend="italic">Pu. Sylla</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Antronins</persName>, who (after they had been deſigned Confuls) were convict of ambition, and corrupt procuring of Voices. Their deſign was to have fet upon the Senate in the beginning of the year, and having cut ſuch throats as they thought convenient, <persName rend="italic">Craffius</persName> was to have made himself Dictator, <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> General of the Horſe, the Republick to have been fettled according to their contrivance, and <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Antronius</persName> to be reftored to the Confulſhip:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Tanufius Geminus</persName> makes mention of this Conſpiracy in his Hiftory, <persName rend="italic">M. Bibulus</persName> in his Edicts, and <persName rend="italic">C. Curio</persName> the Elder, in his Orations. <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> alfo (in one of his Epiſtles to <persName rend="italic">Axins</persName>) ſeems to allude to it in theſe words, <q rend="italic"><persName rend="italic">Cæfar</persName> in his Confulship Establish'd that Monarchy which he had contrived when he was Ædile.</q> <persName rend="italic">Tanufins</persName> adds, that <persName rend="italic">Craffis</persName>, (toucht either with fear or remorſe) abfenting himſelf the day on which their Plot was to be Executed, <persName rend="italic">Cæfar</persName> gave not the fignal as was agreed, which, as <persName rend="italic">Curio</persName> reports, was to have been given by throwing his Gown from his Shoulders.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The ſaid <persName rend="italic">Curio</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">M. Actorius Nafo</persName>, affirm he was in another confpiracy with <persName rend="italic">Cn. Pifo</persName>, (a young Nobleman to whom the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> was irregularly given, to fruſtrate ſome deſigns he was fufpected of at home) it was agreed betwixt them, that he should make what Party he could abroad, and <persName rend="italic">Cæfar</persName> in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; but <persName rend="italic">Piso</persName> dying, that project dyed with him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. In his Ædileſhip he not only beautified the Comitium (where their Magiſtrates were chofen) the Market-places, and their Halls of Justice, but he adorned the Capitol with Galleries erected for the preſent ſolemnity, wherein part of the preparation might upon occafion be expoſed, Baiting of Wild Beafts, Stage-Plays, and fuch other infinuations with the people, he exhibited by himself, and with his Collegue, but with fuch artifice, and cunning, that he appropriated the credit of a common expence, and gave <persName rend="italic">Bibulus</persName> good reason to complain that his forturne and <persName rend="italic">Pollax</persName>'s were the ſame; for (fays he) <q rend="italic">as the Temple Erected in the Market-place, and dedicated to both the Brothers was called the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Castor</persName> alone: fo our joint Munificence is imputed only to <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName>.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But to all theſe paſtimes, and recreations for the People, <persName rend="italic">$Ce\int ar$</persName> added his Gladiators, yet not in fuch numbers as he propos'd, for having fent for them in Multitudes from all parts, his Enemies took the Alarm, and publiſh'd an Edict - reſtraining him to a certain number, which was not to be exceeded in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. Having foftned and cajoled the people in this manner, his next deſign was (by the intereſt of fome of the Tribunes) to get the Province of <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName> conferred upon him by their Act; That which gave him encouragentent in founusual an attempt was, that the People of <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName> had driven out their King, who was at that time look'd upon by the Senate, as their Friend and Allie; but this propoſition being oppos'd by the Nobility, that plot fell to the ground: To be reveng'd of their unkindnefs, he endeavoured all ways to leflen theip. Authority; he repaired the Trophies and-Monumonts Erected in memory of <persName rend="italic">Ca. Marius</persName> bis Victories over <persName rend="italic">Fugurtha</persName>, the <persName rend="italic">Cimbrians</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Teutons</persName>, which <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> had thrown down: being alſo by commiſſion to try fuch perfons as ſhould be accuſed of Murder, he refkon'd them into the number, who had receiv'd Mony out of the Treasury for the heads of fuch perfons as were profcrib'd though they were indemnify'd, and particularly excepted by the Cornelian Laws.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. Hefuborned witneſſes, which accuſed <persName rend="italic">C. Rabirim</persName> of Treason, for that not many years before, the Senate, by his particular aſſiſtance, fuppreft the feditious endeavours of <persName rend="italic">L. Saturninus</persName> the Tribune, being deputed his Judge, he condemn'd him with ſo much animoſity, that he appeal'd to the people, and nothing so much inclin'd them to his favour, as the vehemence of the Judge.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. Having given over all hopes of his Government in <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, his next deſign was to make himfelf High Prieft, which he manag'd with ſo much extravagant profuſeneſs, that revolving with himſelf the vaſt ſums he had borrowed, 'tis reported he ſhould ſay to his Mother when he took his leave of her that Morninghe went to the Election, that if he were not chofen, he would never return; and he was as good as his word, for fo far did his liberality prevail above the age and authority of his Competitors, that he had more Voices, in each of their Tribes, than they had in all.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. The Confpiracy of <persName rend="italic">Catiline</persName> being discover'd in his Prætorſhip, and the Senate generally condemning him and his accomplices to death, he was the only man that moderated the ſentence, and preſt their imprisonment and confiſcation, and no more; which he performed with ſo much ardour and zeal, inculcating the displeaſure of the people, and the confequences thereof, that he terrified his adverſaries, and made <persName rend="italic">D. Silanus</persName> (Conful deſign'd) becauſe he could not with honour intirely recant, to apologize and mollifie his advice, as if it had been taken with more feverity than he intended.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Nay fo far had he fucceeded, that he had drawn the greatest part of the Senate to his ſide, and the Conful, <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName>'s Brother amongst the reft: and doubtless, had not <persName rend="italic">Cato</persName>'s Oration recollected them, the whole Senate had complied. Nevertheless he oppos'd himself againſt the Execution of the Decree, with that obſtinacy, that he was threatned to be kill'd by the Guards which attended the Houſe; who coming, in and ſeting their ſwords to his throat, menac'd him ſo, that She was deferted by thoſe which fate next him, and with great difficulty protected by the interpofition of his Friends. Then he was frighted indeed, and not - only fubmitted unto the plurality of Voices, but forbare to come to the Senate all the rest of that year.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. The first day of his Prætorſhip, he convented <persName rend="italic">2. Catulus</persName> before the People, about the reparation of the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>; and publiſhed an Ordinance, by which he transferr'd that Office upon another. But not able to refift the Combination of the Nobility, who had forſaken their attendance upon the Confuls, and came thronging into the Court, in oppoſition to him, He gave over that alſo.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. <persName rend="italic">Cecilius Metellus</persName>, a Tribune of the People, having made and exhibited pernitious Laws, contrary to the judgments and approbation of his Colleagues, he eſpouſed his Quarrel, afferted his Laws, and defended with fuch violence, that at length they were both of them interdicted by Decree of the Senate; [cite: 8] Nevertheless <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> continued in the execution of his Magiſtracy, contumaciouſly adminiſtring juſtice, till he understood there were Souldiers appointed to interrupt him: Then he diſmiſt his Lictors, deveſted himſelf of his purple Robe, and retired privately to his own house, as fubmitting to the iniquity of that time: [cite: 9]
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Two days after, the People came to him in great throngs of themselves, and in a tumultuous way, proffer'd him their aſſiſtance, but he appeas'd them beyond all expectation: And ſo well was it interpreted by the Senate (which was then hastily aſſembled about that very Commotion) that he had the [cite: 9] thanks of the Houſe by the principal perſons amongſt [cite: 10] them, was re-invited into the Senate, commended, reſtored, and the Decree for his fufpenfion revok'd. [cite: 12]
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. He fell again into troubles afterwards, and was accufed as a Confpirator with <persName rend="italic">Catiline</persName>, by <persName rend="italic">L. Vetius</persName> before <persName rend="italic">Novius Niger</persName> the Quæſtor, and before the Senate by <persName rend="italic">Q. Curius</persName>, to whom they had ordered a publick reward, for that he had firſt diſcovered their deſigns. [cite: 13] <persName rend="italic">Curius</persName> pretended, <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> was the firſt imparted the plot to him; [cite: 14] <persName rend="italic">Vetius</persName> promis'd to produce a Letter of his to <persName rend="italic">Catiline</persName> under his own hand; [cite: 15]
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName>, looking upon that ſcandal as infupportable, appeal'd to the teftimony of <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName>, to whom he had made fome voluntary detection; [cite: 16] by which means, he not only brought himself off, but hindred <persName rend="italic">Curius</persName> of the recompence decreed him. [cite: 17] Nor did <persName rend="italic">Vetins</persName> eſcape ſo well, for having caused him to be fined, his goods to be ſeizéd, and himself torn almoſt in pieces before the <placeName rend="italic">Roftra</placeName>, he at laſt clapt him in Prifon, and the Queſtor <persName rend="italic">Novius</persName> with him, for his preſumption in calling a Magiſtrate before him, which was of greater authority than himself. [cite: 18]
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      18. Having finiſhed his Prætorſhip, the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Hispania Ulterior</placeName> fell to his Lot. [cite: 19] His Creditors endeavoured to have ſtayed him, but he gave them ſecurity to their fatisfaction. [cite: 20] Nevertheless, contrary to all Law and Cuſtom, he departed before his fucceſſor was chofen, or the Provinces ſupplyed, either that he might haften the relief which the allies had implored, or avoid fome proceſs which was privately contriving against him. [cite: 21] Having quieted his Province, he returned with the fame expedition, not fo much as attending the arrival of a Succeſſor, as if he had been impatent of delay, either as to his Triumph or Confulſhip: But Proclamation being [cite: 22]
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      out for the Election of the Confuls, he could not be admitted into the Town but as a private perfon; [cite: 24] he preft very earnestly to be difpenced with in that Cafe, but he found fo great oppofition, he was glad to wave his triumph, for fear of lofing the Confulſhip. [cite: 25]
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      19. <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Bibulus</persName>, being his Competitors he fided with <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName>, upon condition, that he, being richer (though having a leſs intereſt) ſhould diftribute his Money among the Centuries for them both: [cite: 26] But the Nobility having notice of the Compact, and apprehending, left <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> advanced to ſo abſolute an authority, and fortified with a Collegue of his own making, ſhould abuse the truſt repoſed in him, they prevailed with <persName rend="italic">Bibulus</persName> to promiſe the fame largeſs, to which (upon <persName rend="italic">Cato</persName>'s declaring that it was for the ſervice of the Common-wealth) moſt of them contributed. [cite: 27]
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Whereupon he was made Conful with <persName rend="italic">Bibulus</persName>; and to leſſen their authority, the Care of the Forrests, High-ways, and matters of ſmaller importance were obtruded upon them: <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> reſenting the affront, infinuated himſelf with all poſſible artifice into the friendſhip of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, who at that time was in defiance with the Senate, becauſe after his Victory over <persName rend="italic">Mithridates</persName>, they had delayed the ratification of his Acts: He made a reconciliation alſo betwixt <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Craffus</persName>, compofing the animoſity and mif-intelligence which had been betwixt them ever since their Confulſhips, he joyn'd himself ſo firmly to them [cite: 28] both that nothing could be tranſacted in the State, but by confent of all three. [cite: 29]
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      20. After his promotion to the Confulſhip, he was the firſt that ordained a Journal of all Tranfactions both of the Senate and People, to be kept, and [cite: 30] divulg'd; He revived alſo the antient Cuſtome, that in thoſe Months the Rods and Axes were not carried before him, the <foreign rend="italic">Accenfus</foreign> ſhould uſher him, and the Lictors or Sergeants follow behind. The <foreign rend="italic">Lex Agraria</foreign> being promulg'd, and his Colleague proteſting against it, he drave him out of the place by violence, who, upon his complaint in the Senate next day, finding not any one that would move in the Houſe to have a fray of that high Nature taken into conſideration, nor give his vote for Reparation to be made, as they had done formerly upon fmaller occafion; in utter deſpair, he retired immediately, and kept himself in his houſe all the reſt of his Confulſhip, not daring to oppoſe him after that, but only by his Edicts.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      From this time <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> had the fole adminiſtration and manag'd all things with that uncontroulable arbitrarineſs, that fome of the pleasantly diſpoſed Citizens, when they ſubſcribed any will, or record, they dated it in Merriment, not when <persName rend="italic">Cæfar</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Bibulus</persName>, but when <persName rend="italic">Julius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Cæfar</persName> were Confuls, putting the name and furnante of one Conful, for the names of them both, and fuddenly after theſe Verſes were diſperſed,
      <q rend="italic">Non Bibulo quidquam nuper, fed Cæfare factum:
      Nam Bibulo fieri Conſule nil memini.</q>
      <q rend="italic">All things of late great Cafar acts alone;
      Poor Bibulus is out of fashion grown.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      As an inſtance of his power, (not obſerving the antient way of Lots) he divided the <placeName rend="italic">Stellat-Field</placeName>, (dedicated by their Ancestors to Religious uſes) and the <placeName rend="italic">Campane</placeName> Territory (left to the Common-wealth in the nature of a Subſidy) amongst twenty thousand fuch Citizens as ſhould have three Children or more. The Farmers of the Revenues, petitioning for defalcation, in refpect of the hardness of their bargain, he abated them a third part of their Rent, with this admonition, that they ſhould bid more warily for the future: Other things he granted alfo, and without Contradiction; if any were fo audacious as to oppoſe him, he frighted them into a Concurrence.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Cato</persName> he caused to be halled violently out of the Senate, and committed, for interrupting him only, and <persName rend="italic">Lucullus</persName> expoftulating too freely, was made fo ſenſible of the dangerous effects, that he fubmitted, and caft himſelf at his feet. <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName>, for but deploring the Miserable State of affairs, (as he called it) faw the fame day and that at three a Clock, his principal Enemy <persName rend="italic">P. Clodius</persName> tranſlated from the rank of the Senators, to that of the People, a thing he had long folicited from the Senate, but in vain;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      he fuborned <persName rend="italic">Vetins</persName> to give falſe witneſs againſt certain of his adverſaries, and to charge them with offering him Money to kill <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, but one or two being named, and the practice ſuſpitious, deſpairing of ſo inconfiderate a project, and to prevent any further discovery, he poisoned his Knight of the Poft.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      21. About the fame time, he Married <persName rend="italic">Calpurnia</persName>, the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Piso</persName> (who was to fucceed him in the Confulat) and his own Daughter <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> to <persName rend="italic">Cn. Pompey</persName> having rejected her firſt Husband <persName rend="italic">Servins Capio</persName>, (though of all his Friends, he was the only perfon by whoſe aſſiſtance he had overpowered <persName rend="italic">Bibulus</persName>.) After this new Alliance, he began to ask <persName rend="italic">Pompeys</persName> Vote, the first of all the Senators, whereas formerly he was wont to begin with <persName rend="italic">Craffus</persName>, for it was the Cuſtome to obſerve the fame Order all the year thorough, with which the Conful began on New-years day.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      22. Being aſſiſted in this manner by the intereſts of his Wives Father, and his Son in Law, amongſt all the Provinces he made choice of <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName> as the moſt profitable, and moſt probable for his triumph : His firſt Province was only <placeName rend="italic">Gallia Cifalpina</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName>, (added to it by the Act of the Popular Affembly at the procurement of <persName rend="italic">Valerius</persName>) But afterwards they gave him <placeName rend="italic">Tranſalpina</placeName> alſo, as apprehending, if they did not, the People would give it him themſelves;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      with which advancement he was ſo elated, that he could not contain from boafting in a full Affembly a while after, that he had laid his enemies upon their backs, and would keep them under for the future, to which one (alluding to his Sodomy with <persName rend="italic">Nichomede</persName>) anſwering, That it would be no eafie matter for a Woman, he reply'd without any notice of the Sarcasm, That <persName rend="italic">Semiramis</persName> had done it in <placeName rend="italic">Affifia</placeName>, and the <persName rend="italic">Amazones</persName> had fubjelted a great part of <placeName rend="italic">Afia</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      23. Having ended his Confulſhip, and <persName rend="italic">C. Memmius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Lu. Domitius</persName> the Prætors, having made Report of what Acts had paſt the year before, he referred the diſquiſition to the Senate, but obſerving them delatory, and to have confumed three whole days in impertinent difputes, he departed to his Province. After which, it was not long before his Quastor was accus'd of certain delinquencies, and a while after, himself, by <persName rend="italic">Lu. Antiftius</persName> a Tribune of the People; But appealing to the Colledge at last, he obtain'd, that in refpect he was abſent upon the Publick ſervice, he ſhould not be impleaded.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For his ſecurity therefore for the future, he made it his buſineſs to oblige, and ingratiate with the annual Magiſtrates, and in all Competitions to ſide with, and aſſiſt only fuch as would efpouſe his intereſt in his abſence, of which he was then ſo careful and follicitous, that he gave fome of them an Oath, and exacted it from others, under their hands and Seals.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      24. <persName rend="italic">L. Domitius</persName> being a Candidate, or Pretender to the Confulſhip, having ſwaggered openly that he would do when he was Conful, what he could not when he was Prætor; and that he would take away the Command of his Army from him: <persName rend="italic">Cefar</persName> having confulted with <persName rend="italic">Craffus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> at <placeName rend="italic">Luca</placeName>, (a City in his Province) prevailed with them to ſtand again for the Confulſhip in oppofition to <persName rend="italic">Domitins</persName>, and to renew his Commiflion for five years longer, and he fucceeded in both: Upon which, he took the confidence to add fome certain Legions of his own private raiſing, to what he had received of the State.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      One of them raiſed in the Countries beyond the <placeName rend="italic">Alps</placeName> he called by a French word, <foreign rend="italic">Alauda</foreign>, which he bred up and inſtituted in the <persName rend="italic">Roman</persName> Cuſtomes and Diſcipline, and made them all afterwards free of the City.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      With theſe Troops he fought all occafions of making of War, infefting his Confederates as well as Enemies, infomuch that the Senate had once decreed, to fend Commiflioners into <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName>, to examine the State of affairs there, and fome propounded to have him delivered up to the Enemy. But he was fo fortunate in all his enterprizes, that he had more thankſgiving days than any of his Predeceffors.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      25. His atchievements during the 9 years in which he had the principal Command of the Army, were generally theſe; He reduc'd into a Province all that part of <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName> which lies betwixt the <placeName rend="italic">Pyrenaan</placeName> Mountains, the <placeName rend="italic">Alps</placeName>, the Mountains <placeName rend="italic">Gerbenna</placeName>, the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, and the <placeName rend="italic">Rhofne</placeName>, which contains 3200. miles in circumference (besides ſuch Towns as had merited well, and allied themselves to him before.) Не impos'd 40000000 of Seſterces upon them in the nature of a Tribute.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was the first of all the <persName rend="italic">Romans</persName> who built a Bridge over the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>, affail'd the <persName rend="italic">Germans</persName> on the other ſide the River, and gave them ſeveral conſiderable defeats. He invaded the <persName rend="italic">Britains</persName> alſo, which were till then unknown, and having over-run them in a short time, he forced them to give him Hoſtages and Contribution: Amongſt all the variety and greatness of his Enterprizes, he never had ill fortune but thrice; The firſt upon the Coafts of <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName>, where his whole Fleet had like to have miſcarried by ſtorm; the ſecond in <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName>, where one of his Legions was intirely cut off; and the third on the Frontiers of <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, when <persName rend="italic">Titurius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Aurunculeius</persName> his Lieutenants, were circumvented by an Ambuſcade, and defeated.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      26. About the fame time, he lost his Mother, his Daughter, and Grand-Daughter by the faid Daughter, and not long after <persName rend="italic">Clodius</persName> was killed, and the Common-wealth in great conſternation; infomuch that the Senate having reſolved to Create but one Conful, and that <persName rend="italic">Cn. Pompey</persName> ſhould be the Man, <persName rend="italic">Cefar</persName> prevail'd with the Tribunes of the People, (who were endeavouring to make him his Colleague) that they ſhould rather propofe to the People, that in reſpect of his abfence upon the Publick affairs, they would grant him a capacity of being created again, when his Government was expired, leſt otherwise he ſhould be conſtrained to leave the Wars (he had ſo profperoufly begun) immature and unfinished;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      having fucceeded in his desires, and his hopes enlarged with his deſigns, there was no kind of bounty or munificence which he omitted to all people, either in publick or private: He began the ſtructure of his Forum or Town-Hall, which he built with the ſpoils of his Enemies, and paid above a hundred Millions of Seſterces for the Area, or ground on which it ſtood: having pronounced a folemn Sword-play, and feaft, to the people, in memory of his Daughter, (which no man ever had done before) to make it the more acceptable to them, he not only imployed all the Cooks and Victualers of the City to provide what they could get, but he made preparations alſo as much as poſſible at home:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      if any of the moſt eminent Gladiators were in extraordinary danger of their lives, when on any occafion the Spectators were incens'd againſt them, he ordered them to be taken away by force, and referved for another time: ſuch as were to be trained up to that faculty, he fuffered not to be taught in any publick Schools, or by any Maſters of defence, but in private houſes, by <persName rend="italic">Roman</persName> Knights, and fuch of the Senators as were moſt dexterous and skillful at their Arms, beſeeching them(as is ſtill evident in his Epiſtles) that they would undertake them, and give them their Rudiments themſelves. He doubled the pay of his Legions in perpetuum. When his Magazines were well ſtored, he gave them proviſions without meaſure, and once he gave each Souldier a ſlave, and a Farme.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      27. To continue his friendſhip and affinity with <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, he promis'd him <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName> (his Sifters grand-Daughter, though ſhe was married to <persName rend="italic">C. Marcellus</persName>) and made an overture to marry his Daughter, who was contracted alſo before to <persName rend="italic">Faustus Sylla</persName>. Having in order to this obliged all people about <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, and most part of the Senators, either by giving or lending them Monies, upón very reaſonable terms; he ingratiated likewife with the reſt by frequent invitations, or noble preſents, when they came of themſelves, not forgetting to let their fervants and relatives to participate of his bounty, according as they stood fair in the favour of their Maſters.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      All Criminals, all Debtors and Prodigals, had their Sanctuary in him, provided their Crimes, their Debts, and Neceflities, were not beyond the latitude of his Relief: In that cafe he was wont to tell them whoſe condition was ſo deſperate, in plain terms, They had nothing to pray for but a Civil War.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      28. Nor was he leſs ſtudious of infinuating with forreign Princes and Provinces. To fome he would make preſents of Prisoners by the thousands; to others he would fend ſupplies, as many and asoften as they defired, without the conſent or authority either of Senate or People: Besides this, he beautified and adorned the moſt eminent Cities in <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Asia</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Greece</placeName>, with their moſt confiderable buildings.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Till at length all people being in amazement whither these things did tend, <persName rend="italic">M. Claudius Marcellus</persName> the Conful, having by preface to his Edict desired to confer about the great affairs of the Common-wealth, he proposed to them at their meeting, that they would name a Succeſſor to <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName>, before his time was expired, becauſe the War being finiſhed, and Peace eſtabliſhed, it would be convenient that Army ſhould be disbanded.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      That the Senate was not obliged to have any regard to the abfence of <persName rend="italic">$Ce\int ar$</persName>, feeing <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> had not abrogated that act of the People by their confent, for ſo it happened, in the Law he made for the Regulation of Magiſtrates, in an Article in which all fuch as were abſent were excluded from thoſe dignities, he forgot to except <persName rend="italic">$Ce\int dr$</persName>, which error afterwards when the law was ingraven and inrolled, he would have corrected, but too late. Nor was <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName> contented to deprive him of his Provinces, and the priviledge of his abſence, but he moved alſo that the Colonies with <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> had fent to <placeName rend="italic">Novum Comum</placeName> by virtue of the Law <foreign rend="italic">Vatinia</foreign>, ſhould be dif-infranchiſed again, and their freedom of the City be taken from them, as obtained contrary to form.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      29. <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> being nettled at this, and judging (as he was often heard to ſay) it leſs eaſie for him, being the firſt man in the City, to be depreſt to the ſecond, than from the ſecond to the laft, he applyed all the reſiſtance he was able; partly by the interceſſions of the Tribunes, and partly by the intereſt of <persName rend="italic">Sulpitius</persName> the other Conful: The next year <persName rend="italic">C. Marcellus</persName>, fucceeding his Coufin German by the Fathers fide <persName rend="italic">Marcus Marcellus</persName> in the Confulſhip; and promoting the fame deſigns against <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName>, by vaſt Bribes and Gratuities he wrought oft <persName rend="italic">Amilius Paulus</persName>, (his Collegue) and <persName rend="italic">Caius Curio</persName> (a moſt turbulent Tribune) to his ſide.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Yet all things being ſtill carried on with great obſtinacy, and the Confuls deſigned, ingaging fiercely against him, by addreſſes to the Senate, he did humbly requeſt, that either that favour and priviledge from the people, might be made good to him; or that all other Generals might lay down their Commands. Suppofing (as was imagined) he ſhould with more eaſe (upon occafion) recollect his Veterane Troops, than <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> his new. He propoſed alſo to his Adverſaries, by way of Capitulation, that he would difmiſs eight of his Legions, and reſign all that part of <placeName rend="italic">Gaule</placeName> which lies beyond the <placeName rend="italic">Alps</placeName>, upon condition to that he might retain the Province of <placeName rend="italic">Cifalpina</placeName> and two Legions, or one Legion and the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName>, till he was created Conful.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      30. But neither the Senate interpoſing, nor his Adverſaries complying with his defires, as not thinking it fit to capitulate with a Subject in matters of State: he paſt into the nether part of <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName>, where, having executed his Provincial Jurisdictions, he remained at <placeName rend="italic">Ravenna</placeName>, with full reſolution to oppoſe with his Sword, whatever Decree the Senate ſhould make against the interceſſions of the Tribunes of the People who were of his party.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      And this was his pretence for his Civil wars, though others were of another opinion. <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> was us'd to fay, that not being able to finiſh thoſe publick buildings, which with ſo much magnificence he had begun, nor to fatisfie the expectations of the people at his return with his private Eſtate, he reſolved to put all things into confufion.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Others ſay he was jealous of being queſtioned for what he had done illegally in his firſt Confulſhip, contrary to the <foreign rend="italic">Auſpices</foreign>, Laws, and Remonſtrances of the Tribunes; and the rather becauſe <persName rend="italic">Cato</persName> had folemnly ſworn to impeach him, as foon as he had parted with his Army; and it was the general talk, that if he returned as a private perfon, they would handle him as they did <persName rend="italic">Milo</persName>, and make him anſwer before the Judges with ſtrong guards about him:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      which ſeems the more probable by theſe words which <persName rend="italic">Afinius Pollio</persName> affirms he ſpake at the Battel of <placeName rend="italic">Pharfalia</placeName> when he saw his Adverſaries run: <q rend="italic">This is their own doings, I my self must have been condemned, after so many noble exploits, had I not begg'd the aſſiſtance of my Army.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      Some there are which believe that having been ſo long accuſtom'd to Command, and cunningly computing his own Forces, and his Enemics, he laid hold of that occafion to ufurp, which he had attended from the beginning: and of this opinion <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> ſeemed to be, when in the third book of his Offices he ſays, that <persName rend="italic">Cefar</persName> had frequently two verſes of <persName rend="italic">Euripides</persName> in his mouth, which he rendred thus in <foreign rend="italic">Latin</foreign>:
      <q rend="italic">Nam fi violandum est jus, regnandi gratia
      Violandum est: aliis rebus pietatem colas.</q>
      <q rend="italic">Ne're ſtand on justice when the ſtake's a Crown;
      In leſſer things pretend Religion.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      31. When word was brought him that the interceflion of the Tribunes was ineffectual, and that they themselves were departed out of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he gave private orders to his Troops to march immediately, &amp; that no fufpicion of his deſigns might arife, he was preſent that day at a publick ſpectacle, he furvey'd and adviſed about the Model of a new Theatre he had deſigned for his Sword-plays, and was preſent at a publick entertainment as before.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But after Sun ſet having made bold with a Bakers Mules, which were then at hand, and clapt them fuddainly into his Chariot, he began his journey with as much fecrefie, and as fimall attendance as was poſſible: his Torches going out he lost his way, and wandred up and down a great part of the night, but towards break of day he got a guide, and leaving his Chariot, was glad to march on foot through by Lanes and fuch places, to recover his Road, which at length he did, and coming up to his Troops at the banks of <placeName rend="italic">Rubicon</placeName>, he stood ſtill a while ruminating upon the Enterpriſe he was undertaking, at laſt turning to thoſe which were next to him, he said, <q rend="italic">Thus far we are safe, and may return if we please; if we pass but this bridge, we shall have nothing to trust to but our Arms.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      32. Whilst he stood in this hæſitation and fufpence there appeared to him a perſon of a remarkable ſtature, and beauty, fitting hard by him, and playing upon a Reed: not only the Shepheards, but feveral of the Souldiers ran to hear him, and fome of the Trumpeters amongst the reſt, which being obſerv'd by this Piper, he took his opportunity, ſnatcht a Trumpet out of one of their hands, and leaping ſuddainly into the Water, he founded a Charge, and continued it to the other fide of the River: Upon which, <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> cryed out, <q rend="italic">Come then, it is decreed, let us go on whither the Prodigies of the Gods, and the Iniquity of our Enemies invite us.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      33. Having paſs'd his Army over the River, and joyned himself with the Tribunes of the people, who upon their expulfion out of the City were rezired to him: he made an Oration to the Souldiers, and with tears in his eyes, he implor'd their fidelity and afſiſtance. It was reported alſo, that he promi. fed each of them a Knights Fee, but that was a miſtake; for ſhewing them often his Ring finger upon his left hand, as he was ſpeaking, and affirming that he would willingly ſtrip himself even to his Ring, rather than they ſhould go unsatisfied who aſſerted his honour; thoſe who were remote, and could fee better than hear, imagining from their eye, that he had spoke what they defired, gaye out he had promised them the dignity of the Ring, (which was worn only by the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knights) and 400000. Sefterces into the bargain.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      34. The order and fum of his ſubſequent atchievements is this: he poſſeſt himself of <placeName rend="italic">Picenum</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Umbria</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Etruria</placeName>; <persName rend="italic">Lu. Domitius</persName> who was tumultuoufly nominated his fucceflor, having a Garifon in <placeName rend="italic">Corfinium</placeName>, hereduc'd, and diſmiſt; marching from thence along the <placeName rend="italic">Adriatick</placeName> Coafts towards <placeName rend="italic">Brundusium</placeName>, whither <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> and the Confuls were fled for more convenient and ſpeedy tranſportation: He imployed all his induſtry to prevent or retard them, but finding it in vain, he returned to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having called the Senate together, and advis'd about the moſt weighty matters of State, he marched into <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, against the moſt conſiderable of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>'s forces, under the Command of <persName rend="italic">M. Petreius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">L. Afranius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">M. Varro</persName>; and faid publickly amongst his friends at his going away, <q rend="italic">He was going against an Army without a General, But at his return, his next Expedition would be against a General without an Army.</q> The ſhutting of the Gates againſt him at <placeName rend="italic">Marseilles</placeName>, and the incommodities of that Leaguer, was no ſmall impediment to his March, yet he overcame all, reduc'd that Town, and fettled <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> in a short time.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      35. Having thence return'd to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and put things in good Order there, he fets out for <placeName rend="italic">Macedon</placeName> against <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> himself, beſieges and blocks him up in his own Camp for four months together, with incredible labour, and at laſt defeated him utterly at the battel of <placeName rend="italic">Pharfalia</placeName>: he pursued him into <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, finds him flain by <persName rend="italic">Ptolomey</persName>, who was conſpiring the fame Entertainment for him: whereupon he was ingaged in a moſt deſperate war there, as neither having time nor place to defend himself; Yet though it was Winter, and his fupplies (by conſequence) uncertain, though he was ſhut up within the fame walls, with a numerous and fubtile Enemy, and unprovided of all kind of neceſſaries, he overcame them at laſt, made himſelf Master of all <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, and gave the Command of it to <persName rend="italic">Cleopatra</persName>, and her youngest Brother, when he had done: not daring to make it a Province, left falling afterwards into the hands of a violent or pragmatical Governour it might yield new cauſe of Commotion:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      From <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName> he went into <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, and from thence into <placeName rend="italic">Pontus</placeName>, upon news that <persName rend="italic">Pharwates</persName> the Son of <persName rend="italic">Mithridates</persName>, elated with ſeveral victories, had taken that opportunity to make war upon the <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName>: The fifth day after his arrival, he engaged him, and in four hours after he appear'd in fight, he beat him quite out of the field. The caſineſs of this Victory made him often commemorate the felicity of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, who had acquired fo great Glory upon ſo pitiful and puſillanimous an Enemy. After theſe, he reduced <persName rend="italic">Scipio</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Juba</persName>, (who had rallied fome of the remaining Troops in <placeName rend="italic">Africa</placeName>) and <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>'s fons in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      36. In all his Civil Wars he never received any defeat, but in his Lieutenants, of which number <persName rend="italic">C. Curio</persName> miſcarried in <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName>, <persName rend="italic">C. Antonius</persName> was taken Prisoner, <persName rend="italic">P. Dolabella</persName> loſt his Fleet in <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName>, and <persName rend="italic">Cn. Domitius</persName> his Army in <placeName rend="italic">Pontus</placeName>: In all his own Encounters he was fortunate, and never in any hazard but twice; once at <placeName rend="italic">Dyrrachium</placeName>, where <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> repuls'd him, but not profecuting his advan tage, <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> declared he knew not how to make the beſt uſe of a Victory: his next Exigence was in his last battel in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> in which his affairs were fo defperate, he had once thoughts of diſpatching himself.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      37. His wars being ended he triumpht five times; after he had defeated <persName rend="italic">Scipio</persName>, four times in a month, but with ſome intermiſſion of days; and once more after his victory over the Sons of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>: his first, and moſt magnificent triumph was that of the <placeName rend="italic">Gaules</placeName>, the next of <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, the third of <placeName rend="italic">Pontus</placeName>, the fourth of <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName>, and the laſt of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>; the Pomp and preparation of each of them, was different and various.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      On the day of his Gallick Triumph, the Axle-tree of his Chariot breaking, he had like to have been caſt upon the ground: He afcended to the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> with lights, having forty Elephants attending him on both hands, with carriers of Torches: In his Pontick Triumph, upon his ſeveral Pageants, this Motto was inſcribed, <q rend="italic">VENI, VIDI, VICI</q>, importing not fo much the Acts, as the expedition of his Conqueſts.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      38. In lieu of their Plunder, he gave every footfoldier of the Veterane-Legions, besides the two thousand Seftertü, at the beginning of the troubles four thousand more, and to each of the horse 24000. He aſſigned Lands to them alſo, but not contiguous, leſt any of the poſſeſſors ſhould be diſleiſed; He gave the people beſides X Modii of Corn, and as many Pints of Oyl, 300 Sestertii apiece which he had promised them of old, and 100 more in confideration of their forbearance: he remitted alſo a years rent to fuch as were in arrear for their habitations in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, if it exceeded not 2000 Seftertii, but to the rest of <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> but 500.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      To theſe Liberalities he added a publick Feast, a general diſtribution of raw fleſh, and two dinners after his Victory in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, for fuppofing the firſt not fuitable to his Grandeur, five dayes after, he made another far more magnificent.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      39. He exhibited alſo ſeveral forts of Shews and divertiſements to the people, as Prizes, and Stage-Plays acted in all Languages, and all quarters of the Town: he preſented them with the paftimes of the Grous, Wrestlings, and fights at Sea. <persName rend="italic">Furius Leptinus</persName> of the Prætorian Race, and <persName rend="italic">Q. Calpenus</persName>, fometime a Senator and Pleader at the Bar, play'd a Prize in the Market-place: The Pyrric or warlike Dance, was danced by the Sons of the Princes of <placeName rend="italic">$A/ia$</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Bythinia</placeName>:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      During theſe Playes <persName rend="italic">Decimus Laberius</persName>, a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Gentleman, acted a Farce of his own ſo well, that <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> gave him 500000 Sefterces, a Ring of Gold, and place amongst the Knights, to whoſe Seats he paſt immediately from the Stage. To make the Circenſian Games more acceptable and great, he inlarged the Circus on both fides, and deſigned in it a winding Euripus. Here it was the young Cavaliers of the beſt famiJies in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> ſhewed their dexterity and addreſs in vaulting from one Horſe to another, and managing their Chariots ſome with four Horfes, and others with two: The Trojan Game was performed by two Troops, one of greater, the other of leſſer boyes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      For five dayes together there were feveral wild Beafts baited, and laſt of all a kind of a pitch'd Battel, betwixt 500 Foot, 300 Horſe, an 20 Elephants of a ſide, the Goals being taken away for their greater liberty, and two Camps (or Tents) confronting one another ſet up in their ſtead. The Wrestlers having a place prepared for them in the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martins</placeName>, continued that exerciſe three dayes together.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The Naumachia, or Sea-fight, was repreſented (in a Lake cut on purpofe near the leſſer <placeName rend="italic">Codeta</placeName>) by the Gallies of <placeName rend="italic">Tyre</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, with two, three, and four ranks of Oars, all very well mann'd: for the feeing of which fights, there was fo great a confluence of people, moſt part of the ſtrangers were glad to make use of Tents and Booths fet up in the ſtreets and high wayes inſtead of houſes; many perſons were killed in the Crowds, and amongst them two Senators.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      40. Applying himself after this to the ſettlement of the State, he reformed the Kalender, which, by the ignorance, or corruption of the Priefts, or the liberty they took of interlacing (their months and dayes) was become ſo confused, that neither the Harvest Holy-dayes fell out in Summer, nor the Vintage in Autumn. He accommodated the whole year to the courſe of the Sun, made it to confift of 365 dayes, and having taken away the leap month, he fuperinferted only one day in every fourth year.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But to the end that the Computations of time might be more exact for the future, by commencing the account from the Kalends of January; he inter-- poſed two Months betwixt November and Decem ber, ſo that in the year this reformation was made, there were fifteen Months with the ordinary Leap Month which fell in that year on courſe.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      41. He filled up the Senate, choſe new Patritii, increas'd the number of the Prators, Ædiles, Queſtors, and other inferiour Magiſtrates. Such as were degraded by the Cenfors, or condemned of Bribery, or corrupt acquisition of their places, he restored.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The power of Election of Magiftrates, he parted with the people; (Except in the competition for the Confulſhip) one half of the Candidates were declared by them, the other by himself, which he ſignified by little Billets fent to the Tribes in theſe words, <q rend="italic"><persName rend="italic">Cesar</persName> Dictator; To this or that Tribe, &amp;c. I recommend ſuch or Such a person to you, that by your fuffrage he may be admitted into fuch or fuck an Office.</q> He preferr'd the Children of fuch as had been profcrib'd, unto places of honour. He reſtrained all Judgments to two forts of Judges, one of them of the Order of Knights, the other of Senators, ſuppreſſing the third, which was the Tribunes of the Treasury.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He took the number of the poorer fort of people, by the Land-Lords, neither in the uſual manner, nor place, but Street by Steet: The 2300000 People which had their proviſion out of the publick Magazines of the Town, he reduc'd to 150000. And that no new meetings might at any time arife upon occaſion of this Survey, the ordained, that every Prætor ſhould chooſe a certain number by Lots, of ſuch as were not comprehended in the former Survey, to ſucceed in the places of ſuch as ſhould die.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      42. Having diſtributed 80000 Citizens of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> amongſt his forreign Colonies, that he might fupply or prevent any want of men in the City, he made a Law, tha that no Citizen being above twenty, or under forty years of age, fhould be abſent out of <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> above three years; unless he was under a Military Oath to the State. That no Senators Son ſhould be permitted to travel into other Countries, but in the Train and Company of ſome Magiſtrate or other. That thofe which fed Cattel, ſhould have at leaſt a third part of their Keepers free-born young men: He made the Profeſſors of Phyſick, and Teachers of the Liberal Arts, free of the City, to encourage them which lived there to continue, and to invite others thither.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      As for ſuch as were in debt, and hop'd by their frequent follicitations to have obtain'd their difcharges, he decreed at laſt they ſhould fatisfie their Creditors, and an Eftimate being made of all Lands according to the value they were purchased at before the Civil Wars, whatever had been pay'd, or was put down for intereſt upon the account, ſhould by the Debtors be deducted out of the principal, ſo that the Creditor by this means loft above a third part of his Debt:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He diſſolv'd all the New Companies and Societies, confirming only fuch as were of antient Conſtitution: He enlarged the penalties againſt Criminals; and becauſe the rich and wealthier fort being only baniſh'd, without loss of their Eſtates, were become more licentious, and prone to any kind of wickedness he made Murther loss of all, (as <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> reports) and Man-ſlaughter of half.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      43. In the adminiſtration of Justice he was very diligent, and ſevere; fuch as were convicted of Extortion, he removed out of the Senate. He brake the Marriage of a person which had been formerly Prator, for marrying a woman within two days after ſhe had been feparated from her former husband, though there was no ſcandal, or fufpicion of adultery. He laid impoſts upon forein Commodities: He prohibited the uſe of Litters, the wearing of Purple Robes and Jewels, to all but perfons of fuch a quality and age, and that only upon certain days alſo.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But in nothing was he more vigoroufly intent, than in the Execution of the Sumptuary Laws; to repreſs Extravagance in Diet, he not only placed Guards in the Shambles and Butcher-rows, to ſeize ſuch meat as ſhould be fold contrary to Law, but he ſent his Sergeants and Officers to particular houſes, with Command to take away (though upon their very Tables) fuch diſhes as might poſſibly bave eſcap'd the vigilance of his Guards.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="44">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      44. For the Embellishment of the City, the Government and augmentation of the Empire, his contrivances were every day greater than other: His chief defign was to have built a Temple to <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName> (the moſt magnificent in the whole world) by filling up, and levelling that Lake in which his Naval Battle was exhibited. His next was, to have erected a ſtately Theatre near the Mount <placeName rend="italic">Tarpeins</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      To reduce the body of the Civil Law, to a certain mean and mediocrity, and from ſo vaſt and confuſed number of Statutes, to ſelect ſuch as were moſt useful and neceſſary, and to expoſe them in abridgments. To build as large Libraries (both for <placeName rend="italic">Greek</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Latin</placeName> Authors) as he could poſſibly, and to commit their Ordering and digesting to <persName rend="italic">M. Varro</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      To drain the Fenns of <placeName rend="italic">Pomptina</placeName>, to let out the Lake <placeName rend="italic">Fucinus</placeName>, to make a Cawfey from the <placeName rend="italic">Adriatick</placeName> Sea, along the <placeName rend="italic">Apennine</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>: to cut through the <placeName rend="italic">Isthmus</placeName> at <placeName rend="italic">Corinth</placeName>. To repell the <persName rend="italic">Daci</persName>, who had invaded <placeName rend="italic">Pontus</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Thrace</placeName>. To make war upon the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName> in the leſler <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName>, but not to engage them, till he had made a perfect diſcovery of their force.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      But death came and nipt all theſe projects in the Bud; of which before I make any particular relation, it will not be impertinent if I deſcribe him in his perſon, habit, manners, and actions both Civil and Military.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="45">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      45. His ſtature is reported to be tall, his complexion white, his limbs ſtrong and compact, his viſage full, his eyes black and lively, his temper found and healthy, only in his latter days he was ſubject to founding fits, and to be affrighted in his dreams; Twice alſo he was ſurpriſed with fits of the falling-fickneſs as he was fitting in judgment.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      About his body he was ſo ſuperſtitioufly curious, he was not only clipt and ſhaved conſtantly, but had the down or fofter part of his hair pluck'd out by the roots, of which he was many times reproach'd: His baldness was a great trouble to him, and had often expoſed him (to his great dif-fatisfaction) to the flouts of his Enemies: To conceal it as much as he could, he had a Cuſtome of wearing his hair comb'd backward over his Crown, from his forehead; and among all the honours conferr'd upon him by the Senate and People, he received none with more pleaſure and delight, than the priviledge of wearing a Laurel Garland perpetually.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In his cloaths alſo he was fingularly remarkable, wearing his long Senators Robe, ſtudded with Gold, fringed at the hands, and Girt about, but always looſly, which gave occafion to that expreffion of <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> who oftentimes admonish'd the Nobility, <q rend="italic">To beware of that boy who went girded fo flightly.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="46">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      46. His firſt habitation was in a ſmall houſe in the <placeName rend="italic">Suburra</placeName>; But after he was made High Prieft he removed into one of the publick houſes belonging to the City in the <placeName rend="italic">Via Sacra</placeName>. Many have writ that he was exceedingly addicted to neatness, and fumptuous hofpitality at his Table. Having began, and finiſhed at a vaſt expence, a noble houſe in the Territory of <placeName rend="italic">Nemorenfis</placeName>, becauſe it did not exactly anſwer to his mind, he pull'd it down again to the Ground, though his Eſtate at that time was but ſmall, and he very much in debt. He had a Cuſtome alſo, in all his expeditions, to carry ſquare Tiles of chequer'd Marble to pave the place where he took up his own Quarters.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="47">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      47. It is reported, he undertook his Voyage into <placeName rend="italic">Great Britain</placeName>, in expectation of Pearls, whose value he could judge by poising them in his hands, he was a great Lover, and a most curious Collector of Jewels, Engraveries, Statues, Seals, Pictures, and such kind of Antiquities as were the Originals of the prime Masters of old, at any rate: He spared no cost for his Slaves, if they were young and handsome, buying them sometimes at such rates, as he was ashamed should be known; and therefore would not suffer them to be entred in his accounts.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="48">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      48. In all his Provinces he kept two Constant Tables, one where his Officers and Commanders, the other where the men of his long Robe, and the most Eminent persons of the Province did usually dine. The discipline of his House he kept up so exactly in little things, as well as great, that he clap'd one of his Cutlers into Irons, for having given some of his Guests worse bread than what he had himself, and punish'd another of his Gentlemen (which he loved otherwise very well) with death, for having committed adultery with a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knights Wife, though there was no Complaint brought against him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="49">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      49. Nothing reflected upon his Continence so much as his intimacy with <persName rend="italic">Nicomedes</persName>, and that was so lasting and bitter, it expos'd him to every mans invectives, I omit the Common Verses of <persName rend="italic">Calvus Licinius</persName>. <foreign rend="italic">Bithynia quicquid, Et Pædicator Cæsaris unquam habuit.</foreign> I pass by the Libels of <persName rend="italic">Dolabella</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Curio</persName> the Father, with the Edicts of <persName rend="italic">Bibulus</persName>, in which he called him <q rend="italic">Queen of Bithynia</q>, and published, <q rend="italic">That he loved a King formerly so well, he had now set his heart upon a Kingdom.</q> <persName rend="italic">M. Brutus</persName> reports, that about the same time that there was one <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> about the Court (whose folly and weakness gave him the liberty of his tongue) who having saluted <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> in a great Assembly by the name of King, he addrest himself to <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> with the title of Queen.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Cains Memmius</persName> goes farther and charges him to have waited upon <persName rend="italic">Nicomedes</persName> amongst his old Catamites, and filled Wine at the Table, in the presence of several <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Merchants, which he names.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      But <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> not content with this, affirms in some of his Epistles, that he was conducted into the Kings Chamber by his Pensioners, That having put on a Purple Robe, he lay down upon a gilt Bed; and so the flower of his age who was descended from <persName rend="italic">Venus</persName> (as he had boasted) was contaminated in <placeName rend="italic">Bithynia</placeName>. Besides these <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> being earnest in the defence of <persName rend="italic">Nisa</persName> (the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Nicomedes</persName>) before the Senate, and amongst the rest of his arguments, enumerating his favours to him, <q rend="italic">Let that pass I beseech you,</q> (says <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName>) <q rend="italic">we know very well how things have stood betwixt you.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      In his <placeName rend="italic">Gallick</placeName> Triumph, the Souldiers which followed his Chariot, amongst other Songs and Lampons (which were used merrily to be sung) did frequently repeat these, 
      <foreign rend="italic">Gallias Cæfar subegit, Nicomedes Cæfarem. Ecce Cæfar nunc triumphat, qui subegit Gallias: Nicomedes non triumphat, qui subegit Cæfarem,</foreign> 
      <q rend="italic">Cæsar subdued the Gauls, Bithynia's King Subdu'd great Cæsar, why then here's the thing, Must not he triumph too, that o'recame him?</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="50">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      50. The general report is, he was much given to Women, and being very liberal and profuse, he debaucht several Ladies of Quality, amongst the rest <persName rend="italic">Posthumia</persName> the wife of <persName rend="italic">Servius Sulpitius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Lollia</persName> the wife of <persName rend="italic">Aulus Gabinius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Tertulla</persName> of <persName rend="italic">M. Crassus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Mutia</persName> the wife of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>; for not only the <persName rend="italic">Curio's</persName> both Father and Son, but many others upbraided <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, <q rend="italic">That out of an extravagant ambition of greatness, he had married the daughter of him, for whose sake he had put away his own wife after he had had three children by her, and was wont in his passion to call him <persName rend="italic">Ægisthus</persName>, or Adulterer.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      But above all, his greatest affection was for <persName rend="italic">Servilia</persName> the Mother of <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName>, to whom in his last Consulship he presented a Pearl which cost him 60000 Sesterces, besides other considerable Gifts during the Civil Wars, and several Lands and Farms publickly exposed, he suffered her to purchase at a very small rate; which most people admiring, <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> very pleasantly satisfied in these words, <q rend="italic">That you may know</q> (faith he) <q rend="italic">she has the better bargain, <foreign rend="italic">TERTIA DEDUCTA EST</foreign>,</q> alluding to her Daughter <persName rend="italic">Tertia</persName>, which it was supposed <persName rend="italic">Servilia</persName> had prostituted to <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="51">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      Nor did he abstain from the Ladies in the Provinces where he Commanded, if we may believe the Song the Souldiers sung at his <placeName rend="italic">Gallick</placeName> Triumph. 
      <foreign rend="italic">Urbani servate Uxores, mœchum calvum adducimus, Aurum in Gallia effutuisti, hic sumpsisti mutuum.</foreign> 
      <q rend="italic">Friend look t'your wife, our baldspate fornicator Do's both your businesses, if he gets at her subdue Thou st squandred all in France and now comest home, At thy old Rate, to borrow more in Rome.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="52">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      51. He wassinamour'd also of several Queens, as of <persName rend="italic">Eunoe</persName> the wife of <persName rend="italic">Bogudis</persName> King of <placeName rend="italic">Mauritania</placeName> to whom, (as <persName rend="italic">Naso</persName> says) and to her husband, he made many great Presents; But his chiefest passion was for <persName rend="italic">Cleopatra</persName>, with whom he would many times spin out his Entertainments till next morning, he past in the same Barge, or pleasure Boat with her into <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, almost as far as <placeName rend="italic">Ethiopia</placeName>, and had doubtless gone thorow, had not his Army mutiny'd, and refus'd to follow; He invited her afterwards to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and sent her back with many honours, and rewards.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He permitted her likewise to call a Son of hers by his name, which some of the <placeName rend="italic">Greek</placeName> Authors affirmed to resemble <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> both in feature and Mine. <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName> asserted in the Senate, that he owned him, and that <persName rend="italic">C. Matius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">C. Oppius</persName>, and several other of <persName rend="italic">Cæsars</persName> intimates knew it very well. But <persName rend="italic">C. Oppius</persName> (looking upon it as a scandal, and thing worthy of an Apology) put forth a Book, proving, <q rend="italic">It was not the Son of <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName>, which <persName rend="italic">Cleopatra</persName> would have father'd upon him.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Helvius Cinna</persName>, a Tribune of the People, confest to several of his friends, that he had a Law by him, ready prepared and ingrost, which <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> commanded him to publish in his absence, and it was to this purpose, <q rend="italic">That he might have as many, and what wives he pleased, to propagate upon:</q> And that no man may doubt of his Sodomy, <persName rend="italic">Curio</persName> the Elder in one of his Orations stiles him, <q rend="italic">A Man for all Women, and a Woman for all Men.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="53">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      52. That he was temperate in drinking, his very enemies have not deny'd: <persName rend="italic">Cato's</persName> saying was, <q rend="italic">That he was the only sober man ever went about to Subvert the Government of the State.</q> In his diet also he was so indifferent, that <persName rend="italic">Oppius</persName> tells us, being at an Entertainment amongst other company, where ill Oyl was brought up, instead of good, the rest refusing to touch it, he eat very heartily lest otherwise he should seem to have upbraided his Host, either of Poverty, or Neglect.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="54">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      53. He abstained from no way of getting Money, either in his Civil or Military Commands: Some have left it upon Record, that in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> he exacted great sums both of the Pro-Consul, and Allies, towards the payment of his Debts. Certain Towns in <placeName rend="italic">Portugal</placeName> which embrac'd his Commands, and opened their Gates to receive him, he plundered, and sack'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName> he took great store of Jewels and riches out of their Temples, which had been dedicated to their Gods. He demolished several Towns more for their wealth than delinquency, by which means he had got such plenty of Gold, that he sold it in <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, and the Provinces by the pound, for 3000 Sesterces, and no more.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In his first Consulship he made bold with 3000 weight of Gold out of the Capitol, and believed afterwards he had made it good when he gave as much gilt brass in the place. The Honourable Titles of Kings, or Allies, he sold many times for money: <persName rend="italic">Ptolomey</persName> alone paid him 6000 Talents for himself and <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>: After which he maintained the rest of his Civil Wars, Triumphs, and Spectacles, by most evident Rapine and Sacriledge.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="55">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      54. In Eloquence and Martial Conduct, he equalled, if not excelled the best of his Predecessours. After the impeachment of <persName rend="italic">Dolabella</persName> he was ever reckoned amongst the principal Advocates of the City. <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> in his Catalogue of Orators directed to <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName>, affirms, <q rend="italic">He knew not to what person <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> ought to subscribe:</q> and in his Epistle to <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Nepos</persName>, <q rend="italic">That his Stile was Elegant, Brisk, Majestick, and like a Gentleman;</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and in another place; <q rend="italic">Which is it</q> (says he) <q rend="italic">among all your Orators brought up to nothing else, that you can prefer before <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName>? Who is there more pungent, and frequent in his sentences, or more neat and elegant in his words?</q> 55. Whilst he was young, he seemed to affect the stile of <persName rend="italic">Strabo Cæsar</persName> so much, that in his Oration, call'd <foreign rend="italic">Divinatio</foreign>, he transferr'd some of his sentences word for word out of his Oration <foreign rend="italic">Pro Sardis</foreign>. He gave great life to his Harangues, by the clearness of his voice, and the comeliness of his gesture;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      some Orations he left behind him, to which others are inconsiderably added, as that <foreign rend="italic">pro C. Metello</foreign>, which <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> with good reason believes to be put forth rather by some Clerk, or Short-hand writer (who was not able to keep pace with his words as he spoke them) than by himself, for in some Copies I find that it is not inscrib'd, <foreign rend="italic">pro Metello</foreign>, but <foreign rend="italic">quam scripsit Metello</foreign>, being indeed a speech which <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> made to vindicate himself and <persName rend="italic">Metellus</persName> from certain scandals and aspersions laid upon them by their common Enemies.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Nor has <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> any better opinion of his Orations <foreign rend="italic">ad milites</foreign> in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, the first made before his first battel, and the other before his last, and <persName rend="italic">Asinius Pollio</persName> confirms it when he says that the incursion of the Enemy was so sudden, he had no time for any such thing.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="56">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      56. He left also Memoires or Commentaries of his own actions in his Wars with the Gauls and <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>. The rest as of <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, are supposed to be spurious, some people imputing them to <persName rend="italic">Oppius</persName>, others to <persName rend="italic">Hirtius</persName>, who finish'd the last book of his Gallick Wars, which <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> left imperfect.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Of these Commentaries of <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> in the same Epistle to <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName> gives this Character, <q rend="italic">His Commentaries</q> (faith he) <q rend="italic">are exceedingly to be approved, they are plain, neat, and beautiful, without any Rhetorical ornament or disguise: his design was only to prepare matter for such as would write his History, and happily he may have done a pleasure to some light impertinent people who think they can beautifie it perhaps with their miserable Art, but all sober men he has discourag'd from medling.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Of the same Book <persName rend="italic">Hirtius</persName> gives this Testimony; <q rend="italic">His Commentaries are so universally admired, he has rather deterred, than invited others to write: But my wonder is by so much greater than the rest, by how much they only know the Excellency and Generosity, but I the Expedition and Easiness of his Pen.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Pollio Asinius</persName> is of Opinion, they were not carefully done, nor matters of fact so truly represented as they should have been; that <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> took up many things done by other persons, lightly, and upon trust, and that touching his own Exploits, either for want of Memory, or on purpose he set them down wrong.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      He left also two books <foreign rend="italic">de Analogia</foreign>, two <foreign rend="italic">Anticatones</foreign>, and a Poem called <foreign rend="italic">Iter</foreign>. The former two he composed in his passage over the <placeName rend="italic">Alps</placeName>, as he was returning out of <placeName rend="italic">Gallia Cisalpina</placeName> to his Army; the other two about the time of the battel at <placeName rend="italic">Munda</placeName>, and the last in his four and twenty dayes journey betwixt <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> and the furthest part of <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      There are also Extant some Epistles of his to the Senate, which were the first joyned together by leaves, and made into the fashion of a Book, for before the Consuls and Generals writ cross the Paper, and no otherwise: he has some also to <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName>, and to his friends about his private affairs, in which when he had any thing of secret, he imparted it by a certain transposition of Letters so dispos'd, as they seemed nothing to other people, and yet by commuting the fourth Letter for the first, (as D. for A.) &amp;c. his meaning was easily discovered.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
    <p>
      It is reported also, he writ some things when he was a Boy, as the <foreign rend="italic">Phrases of Hercules</foreign>, the Tragedy of <foreign rend="italic">Oedipus</foreign>, and a Collection of Apothegmes; But <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> in a short Epistle to <persName rend="italic">Pompeius Macrus</persName>, who had the charge of his Library, commands him to stop their Publication.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="57">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      57. At his Weapon, and at riding the great Horse, he was excellently expert, most indefatigable in labour: he march'd constantly at the head of his Army; sometimes on Horse-back, sometimes on foot, but always (in spight either of heat or rain) with his Head bare: His diligence was so incredibly great in most of his Expeditions, that he would go fifty Leagues a day in a Hackney Chariot, swimming over the Rivers, if there were any in his way, or else passing by the help of blown bladders, so as many times he out-run all intelligence of him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="58">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      58. In his Martial undertakings, it is doubtful whether he used more Caution or Courage: he never march'd his Army by any dangerous wayes, till he had thorowly discover'd them. Before his Expedition into <placeName rend="italic">England</placeName>, he himself survey'd the Ports and accesses into that Island. Having intelligence that his Camp was beleaguer'd in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, he pass'd their Guards in the disguise of a French-man, and came safe to their relief.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He pass'd from <placeName rend="italic">Brundusium</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Dyrrachium</placeName>, thorow two of the Enemies Fleets in the midd'st of winter and seeing his Troops which he had commanded to follow him, neglected his orders, though he had sent several to hasten them, he muffled himself in his Robe, put himself alone into a Skiff, neither discovering who he was to the Pilot, nor permitting him to yield to the impetuosity of the weather till he was near buried in the waves,
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="59">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      59. No Religious scruple could ever divert, or retard him in his Enterprises. Before his Expedition against <persName rend="italic">Juba</persName>, the Victim ran away as it was about to be sacrificed, which was esteemed a dangerous Omen, yet it was not able to discourage him from his designs. As he was getting out of the Ship, he fell upon the ground, but perverting the presage, he cryed out, <q rend="italic">I take possession of thee O <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName>.</q> To elude the predictions whereby the name of <persName rend="italic">Scipio</persName> was esteemed fatally happy and invincible in that Province, he carried along with him in his Camp an idle inconsiderable fellow of that name of the <persName rend="italic">Cornelian</persName> Race, who in reproach of his life was called <persName rend="italic">Salvito</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="60">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      60. He fought not only by design, but upon occasion, as he thought he had advantage; many times immediately after March, sometimes in stormy weather, when he was least expected: He was alwayes forward to engage, till in his latter dayes: for making reflexion upon the number of his Victories, he thought it indiscretion to hazard so often; and that one Victory more, would not add half so much to his Honour, as one defeat would substract: he never routed an Enemy, but he beat him out of his Camp by the hotness of his pursuit, leaving them no time to rally. When he observed the issue of any battel to be doubtful, he dismounted his Cavalry, and sent their Horses away, and his own first, that by taking away the possibility of escaping, he might put them upon a necessity of fighting it to the last.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="61">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      61. Herid upon a moſtremarkable horse, with feet almoſt like a Mans, and hoofs cloven into Toes: he bred him up from a Colt, and that with no little care, the South-ſayers having preſaged his Maſter ſhould have the Empire of the whole World: He would fuffer no body upon him, but <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> who back'd him himself, and afterwards dedicated his Statue before the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Venus Genitrix</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="62">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      62. Several times he reſtored the Battel when it was almoſt in diſorder by oppofing himself against them that fled, taking them by the Throats, and forcing their faces towards the Enemy. Once they were in fuch diforder, <persName rend="italic">$Ce\int ar$</persName> endeavouring to have ſtaid one of his Standard-bearers, he was threatned with the point of it which is ſtuck into the ground, and another ran away and left his Colours in his hand.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="63">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      63. Nor were theſe the greatest inſtances of his courage; after the battel of <placeName rend="italic">Pharfalia</placeName>, having ſent his forces before into <placeName rend="italic">$A/ia$</placeName>, he followed in a Bark himself through the ſtreights of the <placeName rend="italic">Helefpont</placeName>, where meeting <persName rend="italic">L. Caffius</persName> of the Enemies party, with ten Men of War, he was ſo far from declining him, that he made up to him, commanded him to yield, and upon his fubmiflion, receiv'd him aboard.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="64">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      64. At the ſiege of <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, as he was attempting the Bridge, the Enemy made a defperate fally, and forc'd him into a Boat, into which others precipitating as well as he, he leapt into the Sea, and ſwam two hundred paces to the next Ship, though he carried his left-hand above water, to preferve fome Papers he had in it, and trailed his <foreign rend="italic">Paludamentum</foreign> or Generals Robe after him in his teeth, leſtit ſhould fall into their hands.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="65">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      65. He confidered his Souldiers neither by their Qualities, nor Wealth, but by their courage and Strength; he us'd them all alike with the ſame ſeverity and indulgence; his Diſcipline was ſtricteſt when the Armies were near, then was he ſo ſevere an Exactor of Duty, that without acquainting them, either with their March or the time they were to fight, he kept them cloſe to their Arms, that they might be ready every moment to be drawn out as he pleaſed; fometimes he would give them falſe Alarms, eſpecially in ill weather, and upon Feſtival days: and having commanded every one to have an-Eye over him, he would ſteal ſuddenly from them, fometimes by day, and ſometimes by night, making longer Marches than he intended, to tire them which lagg'd.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="66">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      66. If the report of the number of the Enemy, had at any time diſcouraged his Men, he confirmed them; not by denying or leſſening, but by encreaſing their number above what was true: In this manner when the Alarm of <persName rend="italic">Juba</persName>'s approach was become terrible to his Souldiers, he called them together, and made this Speech: <q rend="italic">Know</q> (Says he) <q rend="italic">in a few days the King will be here with ten Legions, thirty thousand men at Arms, a hundred thousand horse, and three hundred Elephants; Therefore let every one forbear to inquire or concern himself farther, for I am Sufficiently inform'd otherwise I will put the offenders into the oldest Ship I can get, and expose them to the mercy of the winds and the floods.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="67">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      67. He neither took notice of all faults, nor puniſh'd them alike: Thoſe that were feditious or deſerted their colours, he ſtrictly inquired after and puniſh'd always feverely; after a Battle, and Victory, fometimes he would abate of his Diſcipline, and bear with them in all their Riot and Luxury: Boasting often, <q rend="italic">That his Souldiers could fight in their very perfumes</q>:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He call'd them not Souldiers in his Speeches: but by a more obliging Compellation, Commiſſioners, or Fellow-Souldiers: he kept them alwayes neat and brave, he fet them out in Arms ſhining with Gold and Silver, and that not so much for Oftentation and ſhow, as that the apprehenfion of lofing them might give them more courage to defend them, he loved them ſo well, that hearing of <persName rend="italic">Titurius</persName> his defeat, and the deſtruction of his Army, he let his hair and beard grow in indignation, refuſing to cut them till he was thorowly revenged.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="68">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      68. When he firſt undertook his Civil wars, there was not a Captain in any of his Legions, but proffered to find him a horſe out of his own pay: &amp; generally all the Souldiers tendred him their fervice freely without amunition, bread, or pay, and the rather becauſe the wealthier of their Comerades had undertaken for the fupport of the poorer:and which is moft admirable, during the whole ſeries of the Wars, there was none of them forſook him: and most of thoſe which were taken by the Enemy, and offered their lives if they would take up arms against him, choſe rather to die.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      They indured hunger and other extremities of War with that conſtancy and patience, (not only when they were beleaguer'd themſelves, but when they block'd up their Enemy) That at the Siege of <placeName rend="italic">Dyrrachium</placeName>, when <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> was ſhown a fort of Bread made of Herbs, upon which they ſubſiſted; He cryed out <foreign rend="italic">cum feris fibirem eſſe</foreign>, <q rend="italic">That he had to do with Beasts</q>, Commanding it to be taken away and concealed, left the Patience, and Pertinacity of the Enemy, ſhould be any discouragement to his Men.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      With what valour and Magnanimity they fought, is evident in their ill fucceſs at <placeName rend="italic">Dyrrachium</placeName> where having been repuls'd, they came and offered themselves to be punish'd, in ſo much that <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName>s trouble was more to comfort, than correct them. In all his other ingagements, they eaſily overcame much greater armies than themselves; in ſhort one Company of his fixth Legion being ordered for the defence of a ſmall Caſtle; they maintained it ſeveral hours, against four of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> Legions, till they were all wounded with their arrows, of which 36000 were found afterwards in their Trenches:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Nor is this ſtrange if we conſider the actions of particular Men, <persName rend="italic">Caffius Scava</persName> their Captain in defending the Gate of the faid Fort, not only loſt an Eye, was wounded in the ſhouldier and thigh, but had his Buckler ſhot thorow in an hundred and twenty places; and yet left not his Poſt. <persName rend="italic">Acilius</persName> in a Sea-fight not far from <placeName rend="italic">Maffilia</placeName>, having his right hand cut off wherewith he had laid hold of one of the Enemies Ships; (according to the memorable example of <persName rend="italic">Cynagins</persName> among the <placeName rend="italic">Greeks</placeName>) he leapt into the Ship, thruſting his Shield into their faces who ſtood in his way.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="69">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      69. During his ten years Wars in <placeName rend="italic">Gaul</placeName>, his Army never mutined; in his Civil Wars, but ſeldom; and then they returned preſently to their Duty, not fo much by the indulgence, as authority of their General. He never flattered or complyed with them at all, but always oppos'd himself. His ninth Legion mutining at <placeName rend="italic">Placentia</placeName>, he cashier'd it with great ignominy (though <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> was then in Arms) and hardly reſtored them after frequent and earneft fupplication, till he had made ſome of them Exemplary.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="70">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      70. His tenth Legion demanding their reward and diſmiſſion with great eagerness, and danger, to the City; He went immediately to them himself, and diſcharged them, contrary to the advice of his Friends, the War in <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName> being hot at that time. But calling them Citizens, and not Soldiers, as he was wont; they were ſo nettled with it, they cryed out they were Souldiersand no Citizens, and followed him into <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName> whether he would or no: Nor could that reconcile them till he had taken away a third part of the pillage, and Lands, (which were fet out for them) from the moſt eminently ſeditious.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="71">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      71. His kindness and conſtancy to his Clients appeared from his very youth. When he had defended the cause of <persName rend="italic">Masintha</persName> (a young Gentleman) againſt <persName rend="italic">Hiempſal</persName> the King, with fuch zeal, that in the heat of the argument he took <persName rend="italic">Juba</persName> the Kings Son by the beard, <persName rend="italic">Mafintha</persName> being declared a Stipendarie, he forc'd him out of the hands of the Officers, conceal'd him in his own house, and a while after when his Prætorſhip was expir'd, and he went into <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, he took him along with him in hisown Litter, amongst the best of his Officers and Friends.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="72">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      72. He carried himself alwaies with ſo much Courtefie and Reſpect towards his Friends, that <persName rend="italic">C. Oppius</persName>, accompanying him in his March thorow a large Forreft, and being fuddenly taken ill, he gave him his Lodging, and lay himself upon the Ground. After he had made himſelf Emperour, he advanc'd perſons of the meaneſt condition to the highest honours; and being blamed for it by his friends, he replyed; <q rend="italic">If they were Thieves, and Murtherers, and had stuck to me in the defence of my Hanour, I would do the same.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="73">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      73. He never had fo great an animoſity against any man, but he could lay ít afide upon the leaft occafion given. <persName rend="italic">C. Memmius</persName> had publiſh'd bitter invectives against him, to which he answered as fmartly; yet he gave him his aſſiſtance in his petition for the Confulſhip. <persName rend="italic">C. Calvus</persName> having blaſted him with his defamatory Epigrams, defiring afterwards to be reconciled, <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> was ſo generous as to write tohim firſt. The fame Clemency he uſed towards <persName rend="italic">Valerius Catullus</persName>, who having branded his reputation with eternal infamy, (as he faid himſelf) nevertheless the fame day he did but fay he was forry, he took him with him to Supper, and lay afterwards in his Fathers houſe as he had formerly done.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="74">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      74. He was not naturally vindicative. He reveng'd himself upon the Pirats which had taken him Prifoner, becauſe he had fworn to crucifie them if they came under his Power, yet he did it with fuch moderation, that he commanded them firſt to be ſtrangled before they were faſtned to the Croſs. He would never fuffer any miſchief to be done to <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Phagita</persName>, though he had much ado to efcape the Traps he laid for him in the night, and (as fick as he was) from being carried to <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> by his means. <persName rend="italic">Philemon</persName> a fervant or Secretary of his, having engaged to the Enemies to poifon him, was put only to an ordinary death, and not permitted to be tortured.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being cited as a witness against, <persName rend="italic">Publius Clodius</persName>, accused of Adultery with his Wife <persName rend="italic">Pompea</persName>, and for the fame caufes of polluting the holy Ceremonies, he denied that he knew any thing of it, though his Mother <persName rend="italic">Aurelia</persName>, and his Siſter <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> had fworn it; Being ask'd by the Judges, why then he had turned her away, <q rend="italic">Because</q> (Jaid he) <q rend="italic">I would have niy family as free from Sufpicion as Guilt.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="75">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      75. His Clemency and Moderation was admireable, not only in his adminiſtration and management of his Civil Wars, but in his Victories and Triumphs. <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> by Proclamation declared them Enemies of the State, who but fuſpended their afſiſtance at that time: he declared he would look upon all Neuters as Friends. Those who by <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>'s recommendations he had preferr'd to any Commands, he permitted to paſs to his party.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      There being propoſitions made, and a Treaty actually on foot at <placeName rend="italic">Ilerda</placeName> in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>, during which Treaty the Souldiers trading and converfing promifcuoufly both one fide and the other, <persName rend="italic">Afranius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Petreins</persName> took their advantage, and put all <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName>s Souldiers to death, upon the diſſolution of the Treaty; yer could not <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> be provok'd to imitate their perfidy, but fent them all home which were in his Camp. At the Battle of <placeName rend="italic">Pharfalia</placeName> he made proclamation, That all Citizens ſhould be spared, and afterwards gave every one of his Souldiers liberty to ſave one of the adverſe party, if they pleaſed, fo that there was none killed but in the heat of the fight;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Except <persName rend="italic">Afranius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Faustus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">L. Caeſar</persName> the younger, and it is thought they were flain againft his will; Though the two firſt had revolted after pardon once obtain'd, and <persName rend="italic">L. $Ce\int ar$</persName>, not contented to have killed and perfecuted his fervants with fire and ſword, moſt malitiously flew the very Beaſts he had prepared for his publick ſhows.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      To conclude, in his latter days, thoſe whom as yet he had not pardon'd, he fuffer'd to return into <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, to Govern as Magiſtrates in the City, and as Officers in the Field. He re-erected the Statues of <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, which the people had pull'd down: Andat any time if any thing extraordinary was fpoken or contrived against him, he choſe rather to prevent, than puniſh, to amoniſh than correct them;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      And accordingly having information of ſeveral Confpiracies, and meetings in the night; he troubled them no further than by Edict, to let them know they were discovered; To fuch as ſpoke ill of him, he thought it ſufficient to admoniſh them before the people, that for the future they ſhould deſiſt. <persName rend="italic">Aulus Cicinna</persName> having ſeverely aſperſt him with his Libells, and <persName rend="italic">Pitholaus</persName> with his Satyrs, he took all patiently without any revenge.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="76">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      76. However, the reſt of his words, and actions do preponderate, and make him appear not only to have abuſed his authority, but to have been worthy of death. For beſides the extravagant Honors which he affumed, as the perpetual Dictatorſhip, the continual Confulſhip, the Cenſorſhip, the title of Emperour, and Father of his Country, a Statue amongst the Kings, a Chair, or Box upon the Stage, a Chair of Gold in the Senate, and another in the Courts of Justice; He Ufurp'd greater Dignities than conſiſted with humane condition, as to have his Effigies carried folemnly in the Pageantry of the Cercenfian Games. He had his Temples, Altars, Images, by the Gods, his Confecrated Beds, his Priefts, his Luperci, and the denomination of one Month in the Year. In short, there were no Honours whatever, but he took, or gave as he pleaſed.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He did not execute his third nor his fourth Confulſhip, for retaining only the Title, he contented himself with the authority of his Dictatorſhip, decreed to him with his Conſular's at the fame time; in the three last months of each year, he ſubſtituted two Confuls, ſo as within that time there was no aſſembly for Elections, but for Tribunes and Ædiles Plebis. He created Provoſts instead of Prætors, gave the vacancy to a perſon which deſired and injoy'd it but a few hours, that Office of courſe expiring the next day.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      With the fame liberty, contrary to all Cuſtome he ordained Magiftrates for feveral years. He gave ten Prætors power to wear the Conſulary Ornaments. He receiv'd private Citizens into the Senate, and fome of the half Barbarous <placeName rend="italic">Gauls</placeName>. He appointed his own Servants and Officers to ſuperviſe his Mint, and Revenue. He Committed the three Legions he left in <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, to the Command of the Son of <persName rend="italic">Rufinus</persName>, his Freeman, and Catamite of old.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="77">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      77. Nor did his publick expreſſions ſpeak him leſs infolent: <persName rend="italic">T. Ampius</persName> reports, he ſaid, <q rend="italic">That the Common wealth was now but a word, without either bodyor Soul.</q> <q rend="italic">That <persName rend="italic">Sylla</persName> was no good Grammarian that could part with his Dictatorship so easily;</q> <q rend="italic">That hereafter he was to be spoke to with more Reverence, and every word that he spoke was to be lookt upon as a Law.</q> Nay to that height of arrogance was he he arrived, that a Prieſt having found no heart in a Beaſt, which was to be Sacrificed, and bringing him word of the badnefs of the Omen; <q rend="italic">Trouble not your $\int elf$</q> <foreign rend="italic">($\int ays~be$)</foreign> <q rend="italic">they Shall be better when I please, nor is it to be thought a prodigie, if a beast wants a heart.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="78">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      78. But the greatest and moſt inextinguiſhable hatred he drew upon himself, was from hence: when the Senators came to him in a Body with moſt honourable decrees, he received them fitting before the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Venus Genitrix</persName>. Some fay, he would have riſen but <persName rend="italic">Cornelins Balbus</persName> held him down; 0- thers ſay, he was ſo far from offering it at all, that <persName rend="italic">C. Trebatius</persName> intimating it was expected, received a ſevere frown for his pains.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      And that which made this action of his more remarkable, was, That in one of his Triumphs, pafſfing by the Seats of the Tribunes, and obſerving all the Company rofe up and faluted him but <persName rend="italic">Pontius Aquilla</persName>, he could not contain, but in great indignation cryed out, <q rend="italic">Well done Tribune <persName rend="italic">Aquilla</persName>, you had best try if you can wrest the Govern ment of the Common-wealth out of my hands, with your Tribuneſhip,</q> and by way of mockery and contempt, he promis'd nothing to any one for ſeveral daies af ter, but with this exception; <q rend="italic">If <persName rend="italic">Pontius Aquilla</persName> confents.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="79">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      79. To this contumely and flight of the Senate, he added a greater picce of arrogance; for return ing from the Sacrifice of the <placeName rend="italic">Latine</placeName> Feſtivals, amongst the freſh and immoderate acclamations of the people, one of them had put a Crown of Lawrel (tyed about with a white band) upon the head of his Statue; which being obſerved, <persName rend="italic">Epidius Marul lms</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Cafetius Flave</persName>, Tribunes of the Commons, Commanded the band to be taken off, and the fel low to be laid by the heels; This he took ſo hainour $ly_{p_{i}}$ (whether the Omen of his Coronation fucceeded no better, or that (as he pretended) they had ta ken from him the Honor of doing it himself) that he ſharply rebuk'd them, and turned them out of their Commands.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Nor could he clear himself from the fufpicion of affecting the Name of a King, though the People faluting him with that Title, he replied <foreign rend="italic">Caeſarem se, non Regem effe</foreign>, <q rend="italic">He was <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> indeed, but no King</q>, and in the Lupercalia when the Conful <persName rend="italic">An tonius</persName> offered feveral times to put the Crown upon his head, he refuſed it, and fent it to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> into the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      There was a ſtrong report likewiſe, as if he meant to retire to <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, or <placeName rend="italic">Troy</placeName>, to drain <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> of the choice of its Soldiers, and (having left the Government of the City to his friends) to carry the wealth of the whole Empire along with him. There was a Rumour alſo in the next meeting of the Senate, that <persName rend="italic">Lacius Cotta</persName>, one of the Quindecim-viri, was to declare his opinion that <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> ſhould be called King, becauſe he had found in the Books of the Sibylls, that the <persName rend="italic">Parthians</persName> were not to be conquered but by a King.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="80">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      80. This was a great occaſion of haſtning the Execution of their Conſpiracies, otherwise the Conſpirators would have been forc'd to confent: Their Councils therefore which before were man aged, by the meeting of two or three at a place, were united now, and carried on by a common con vention of all together;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      the people growing fenfi ble of their condition, upbraiding the Government, and wiſhing for fome Body or other to af fert their Liberties, and rescue them from the ſlavery they were under, by reaſon that ſtrangers were admitted into the Senate; there was a PafQuin fet up with this Preface, <foreign rend="italic">Bonum Factum, &amp;c.</foreign> <q rend="italic">Let no Man ſhow the Senate House to our New Sena tors, &amp;c.</q> and theſe Verſes ſang publickly about the Streets. <foreign rend="italic">Gallos Caeſar in triumphum ducit, idem in Curia Galli bracas depoſuerunt, latum clavum ſumferunt.</foreign> <q rend="italic">The Gauls in triumph led from Cæfars Wars, Shifting their Pantaloons, turn Senators.</q> <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> having ſubſtituted <persName rend="italic">Q. Maximus</persName> Conful for three Months, as he entred the Theatre, the people were admoniſh'd by the Officers (of the Court) to pay him their reſpects, but they cryed out univerſally, <q rend="italic">He was no Conful.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      After <persName rend="italic">Cafetins</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Ma rullus</persName> were removed (as aforesaid) from the Tribuneſhip, they had many voices (at the next Ef lections) to make them Confuls. Some there were who writ theſe words under the Statue of <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName>, <foreign rend="italic">Utinam viveres</foreign>, <q rend="italic">would to God thou wert alive again;</q> others under <persName rend="italic">Caeſars</persName>, <q rend="italic"><persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName> was created the first Conful for expelling the Kings, and this man the last of Kings, for fuppreffing the Confuls.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The Confpiracy was mannaged by above fixty perſons. The chief of them were <persName rend="italic">C. Caffius, Marcus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Decimus Brutus</persName>, they were a long time in deliberation about the place of Execution, fome were for throwing him over the Bridge, as he call'd over the Tribes at the Election in the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martius</placeName>, and (having divided themselves before) to kill him when he was down. Others were for Murdering him in the <placeName rend="italic">Via Sacra</placeName>, and others at his entrance into the Theatre. But after the Senate had Orders to meet in <persName rend="italic">Pompeys</persName> Court upon the Ides of March, they preferr'd that time and place before all the reft.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="81">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      81. <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> had warning of his death by manifeſt preſages: fome few Months before, thoſe of the Colonie, which were fent to <placeName rend="italic">Capua</placeName> according to the Law <foreign rend="italic">Julia</foreign>, as they were pulling down the old Sepulchers to build them up houſes, (and that with the more induſtry and diligence, becauſe they found feveral Veſſels and antiquities amongst the Rubbish) In the Monument of <persName rend="italic">Capys</persName> the founder of <placeName rend="italic">Capua</placeName>, they found a braſs Table with this inſcription in Greek, <q rend="italic">When the bones of <persName rend="italic">Capys</persName> shall be discovered, it shall come to paſs, that a person descended from <persName rend="italic">Iulus</persName>, shall be murdered by his Kindred, and his death revenged a while after by the ruine of all <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>;</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and (that this report might not be thought fa- -fabulous) know that <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Balbus</persName>, an intimate friend of <persName rend="italic">Caeſars</persName> is the Author of it. Not many dayes likewife before this diſaſter, the Horſes (which he had confecrated, (according to cuſtome) at his paſſage over the <placeName rend="italic">Rubicon</placeName>, and were let loofe in the wide fields without any keeper, (he had certain intelligence) forbare their meat, by common conſent (as it were) and wept abundantly. As he was at Sacrifice,. the Augur <persName rend="italic">Spurinna</persName> admoniſh'd him to beware of a danger hanging over his head, which would ſcarce be deferr'd beyond the Ides of March.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The very day before the Ides, a little Bird call'd the Regaliolus flying into <persName rend="italic">Pompey's</persName> Court with a branch of Lawrel in, her Beak, was pursued by ſeveral Birds out of the next Grove, and pull'd in pieces there. That night he dreamt alſo that he was flying above the Clouds, and fometimes ſhaking <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> by the hand. <persName rend="italic">Calphurnia</persName> his Wife dreamt likewise, that the top of the houſe was fallen down, that her Husband was ſtabb'd in her arms, and immediately the doors flew open of themselves:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Upon theſe conſiderations, and an indiſpoſition which was then upon him beſides, he had thoughts of ſtaying at home, and deferring the affairs he had propos'd to the Senate: But <persName rend="italic">D. Brutus</persName> perſwading not to difappoint the Senate which was now full, and had attended him a long time, he went to them about eleven a Clock. By the way he was preſented (by a perfon he met) with a Paper diſcovering the whole Plot, but he put it amongst other Papers in his left hand, as if if he would read it anon. In short, having made many Sacrifices to the Gods, and ſucceeding in none; in defiance of all Religion he entred the Senate, laughing at <persName rend="italic">Spu rinna</persName> as a falſe Prophet, ſeeing the Ides of March were come without any diſaſter: to which he re ply'd, <q rend="italic">They are come indeed, but not past.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="82">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      82. As foon as he was fet, the Conſpirators plac'd themſelves about him, pretending to do him honour, and immediately <persName rend="italic">Cimber Tullius</persName>, who had undertaken the firſt part, addreſs'd himself to him, as if he had fomething to demand; but <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> refu fing him, and making ſigns to him to put it off to fome other time; <persName rend="italic">Cimber</persName> catch'd hold of his Gown on both ſhoulders, and <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> crying out that <q rend="italic">this was violence</q>, one of the <persName rend="italic">Caffii</persName> came in and ſtabb'd him under the throat;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      then <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName> laying hold of <persName rend="italic">Caffius</persName> his arm, ſtruck it thorow with his Stile, and endeavouring to get up, was ſtopt with another wound: but feeing ſeveral ſwords preſented to his breaft, he cover'd his head with his Gown, and with his left hand ſpread it over his thighs, that by covering thoſe parts, he might fall with the more modeſty. In this manner he receiv'd 23 wounds, and died without ſpeaking a word, or fetching fo much as a figh; but at the firſt ſtroke though ſome have reported, that when <persName rend="italic">M. Brutus</persName> aſſaulted him, he cryed out, <q rend="italic">And art thou, art thou amongst them my Son?</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Being dead, and all the Conſpirators fled, he lay there for a while, till at length three of his ſervants put him into a Litter, and carried him home with one hand dangling out. <persName rend="italic">Antiftius</persName> his Phyfitian was of opinion, amongst all his wounds the ſecond only (upon his breaft) was mortal.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The Confpirators were refolv'd to have drawn his body into the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>, to have confiſcated his Eſtate, and refcinded his Acts, but they were afraid of <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName> the Conful, with <persName rend="italic">Lepidus</persName> the General of the Horſe, and durſt not proceed.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="83">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      83. At the request therefore of <persName rend="italic">L. Piso</persName> (his Father in Law) his Will was opened and read in the houſe of <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>: it was made at his Country houſe at <placeName rend="italic">Lavicum</placeName> upon the Ides of September, and given in keeping to the chief of the veſtal Virgins. <persName rend="italic">2. Tubero</persName> writes, that from his firſt Confulſhip, to the beginning of his Civil Wars, he had named <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> his heir, and that his Will was many times read to his Souldiers;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      but in his laſt he made three of His Grand-Nephewes (being his Sifters GrandSons) his Heirs, viz. to <persName rend="italic">C. Octavius</persName>, he gave three fourths, to <persName rend="italic">L. Pinarius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">$Q_{u}$. Pedius</persName>, the fourth part remaining. In the bottom of his Will, he adopted <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> both into his Family and Name. He had nominated feveral of his Murderers as Guardians to his Son, if he ſhould be fo happy as to have any: He left alfo <persName rend="italic">D. Brutus</persName> amongst his fecond Heirs, (that is, upon default of the firſt) and gave his Gardens upon the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName> to the people in common, and 300 Sefterces a Man.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="84">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      84. His Funeral being proclaimed, his funeral Pile was erected in the field of <placeName rend="italic">Mars</placeName>, near the Monument of <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>, and a Gilt Chappel after the Model of the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Venus Genetrix</persName>, fet up before the <placeName rend="italic">Roftra</placeName>: within this Chappel was placed a bed of Ivory cover'd over with Purple, imbroider'd with Gold, and at the head of it a Trophy fupporting the Robe in which he was killed; and that the multitude of thoſe which carried offerings might be no impediment to the folemnity, (the day not being long enough for all) it was commanded, that they ſhould carry them into the field of <placeName rend="italic">Mars</placeName> without any order, thorough what Steets of the City they pleas'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Amongst their Games and Playes, there were ſeveral Verſes exhibited to move the people to pity, and indignation; ſuch as thoſe taken out of the Tragedy of <persName rend="italic">Pacuvius</persName>, intituled, <foreign rend="italic">The Judgment of Arms.</foreign> <foreign rend="italic">Men ſervaſſe, ut eſſent qui me perderent?</foreign> <q rend="italic">Unhappy I who let these men go free, That there might those be left, durst murder me.</q> And others to the like purpoſe out of <persName rend="italic">Accins</persName> his <foreign rend="italic">Electra</foreign>. Instead of a Funeral Oration, <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> the Conful publiſh'd an Act of the Senate by the publick Cryer, (by which they decreed him all honour, both humane and divine) as alſo he caus'd the Oath to be read, by which they had oblig'd themſelves in the defence of a ſingle Perſon, to which he added fome few words of his own.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The Magiſtrates and perſons which had been of Authority in the City, removed the Bed of State from before the <placeName rend="italic">Roftrum</placeName>, into the <placeName rend="italic">Forum</placeName>, and whilft they were divided in their reſolutions where it ſhould be burnt, whether in the Cell of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>, or in the Court of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> (where he was flain) on a sudden two men with Swords by their ſides, and two Javelins in their hands, fet it on fire with Torches, and immediately the multitude threw in their dry Wood, the Benches and Seats of the Tribunal, and what ever they had brought as an offering:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      then the Minſtrils and Stage-Players pulling off the Garments which they had receiv'd out of the proviſion for the Triumph, they tore them in pieces, and threw them into the Flames. The old Legionaries did the fame with their Arms, which they wore on purpoſe that day in honour to the Funeral. The Ladies threw in (many of them) their Jewels, and Ornaments, and the very Purple embroidered Robes of their Children.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      In this general Mourning, there were ſeveral from foreign Nations, which were preſent, and contributed their lamentation according to the modes of the ſeveral Countreys, but eſpecially the Jews, who ſpent whole nights in their Ceremonies at the place where he was burnt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="85">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      85. No fooner were the Ceremonies of the Funeral over, but the people with Fire-brands in their hands, ran in great multitudes to fet the houſes of <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Caffius</persName> on fire: being with ſome difficulty repell'd, they met with <persName rend="italic">Helvius Cinna</persName> by accident as they came back, and miſtaking him for <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Cinna</persName> (who had made a bitter ſpeech against <persName rend="italic">$Ca\int ar$</persName> the day before) they flew him, cut off his head, and fixing it upon a Spear, carried it about with them up and down the City; after this, they fet up a folid Pillar of <placeName rend="italic">Numidian</placeName> Marble, near twenty foot high, with this infcription, <foreign rend="italic">Parenti Patria</foreign>, <q rend="italic">To the Father of his Country</q>, At which place for a long time afterwards they did uſe to facrifice, to make Vows, and to de cide their Controverfies by ſwearing by the name of <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="86">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      86. Some of his friends were of opinion, that in reſpect of his fickness and indiſpoſitions, he had no defire to live any longer, and for that reaſon he neglected the Prodigies, and the advertisements of his friends: fome imagined he relied fo much upon their Oath, and the laſt Act of the Senate, that in confidence of that he fent back his <placeName rend="italic">Spanish</placeName> Guards, which alwayes attended him with their Swords by their fides:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Others report, he had often declar'd, that he had rather die once, than live in perpetual fear: Others affirm, he was wont to fay, that his fafety was more for the intereſt of the Common-wealth, than for his own; that he had acquir'd Honour and Power enough already; but that if any miſchief happen'd to him, the Republick would fall into new troubles, the effects whereof would be more calamitous than ever they had been under him.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="87">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      87. In ſhort all agree in this, that he died according to his own defire; for having read in <persName rend="italic">Xenophon</persName> upon a time, how <persName rend="italic">Cyrus</persName> being under the extremity of his diſeaſe, and at the point ofdeath, gave fome directions for his Funeral, abhorring fo tedious a death, he wiſh'd when he died, it might be of a fudden; and the day before he died, being at Supper in <persName rend="italic">M. Lepidus</persName> his houſe, upon a queſtion occafionally offered, Which was the beſt death? he declared, in his judgement, a ſudden, and unexpected.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="88">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      88. He died in the 56 year of his age, and was Canonized amongst the Gods, not only by the mouth of them which pronounc'd the Decree, but by the perſwaſion of the people; For at the firſt Games <persName rend="italic">Auguftus</persName> exhibited to the people, and dedicated to him, as being his Heir, there appear'd a Star which ſhin'd afterwards ſeven dayes together, aroſe about the eleventh hour, and by them was confidently believed to be <persName rend="italic">Caeſar's</persName> Soul, for which cauſe there was a Star ſet afterwards upon the Crown of his Statue. Order was given alſo, that Court ſhould be ſtop'd up where he was killed: that the Ides of March ſhould be call'd <foreign rend="italic">Parricidium</foreign>, and that the Senate ſhould never ſit more upon that day.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="89">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      89. Of his Murderers there was ſcarce any outlived him three years, or died a natural death: All of them ſtood condemned, and fell by ſeveral accidents, ſome wreck'd at Sea, others kill'd in fight, and fome flew themselves with the fame dagger with which they had murder'd <persName rend="italic">Caeſar</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

      

</div></body></text></TEI>