<tei>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>


            <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      T
      HAT the Family of the <persName rend="italic">Octavii</persName> were of principal rank in <placeName rend="italic">Velitre</placeName>, we have many Arguments to perſwade us; for besides that there is a Street in the moſt conſiderable part of the Town, call'd <placeName rend="italic">Octavian</placeName> to this day, and an Altar confecrated to one <persName rend="italic">Oftavius</persName>, their General against the Borderers, who as he was facrificing to <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>, having intelligence that the Enemy had made a ſudden Inroad into his Territories, ſnatch'd up the Intrailes from the Altar halfraw as they were, and offer'd them: after which he march'd out immediately, fought, and defeated them; upon that Victory a Decree was made, (which is ſtill extant upon record) That for the future the Intrails ſhould be offer'd to <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName> in that manner, and no other; and the reliques, or remainder of the Victime, be carried back to the <persName rend="italic">Octavii</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. This family was admitted (amongst the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Families) into the Senate by <persName rend="italic">Tarquinius Prifcus</persName>, amongst the Patricians by <persName rend="italic">Servius Tullins</persName>, and in proceſs of time ranking it felf amongſt the people, after a long interval, it was readvanc'd amongst the Patricii by <persName rend="italic">Julius Cafar</persName>. <persName rend="italic">C. Rufus</persName> was the firſt of this Race, who was elected to the Magiftracy by the fuffrage of the people.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having paſt his Quæſtorſhip, he had two Sons, <persName rend="italic">Cneius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, from whom ſprang the two branches of the <persName rend="italic">Octavii</persName>, of different quality, and condition, for <persName rend="italic">Cneius</persName> and all his Progeny, were imploy'd in the greateft and moſt honourable charges. But <persName rend="italic">Cains</persName>, and his, (either through the Malignity of their Fortunes, or the humility of their minds) continued in the rank only of Gentlemen, till the time of <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> his Father. In the ſecond Punick war, <persName rend="italic">Angustus</persName> his great Grand-father was a Military Tribune in <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, under <persName rend="italic">Emilius Pappus</persName>, who commanded the Army. His Grand-father contenting himself with the plenty of his own Patrimony, and the Civil authorities of the City, lived in great eaſe and tranquillity till he was an old Man, and this is that which others report;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> himself fays onely this, that he was deſcended from an ancient family of the Equestrian Order, and that his Father was the firſt of it, which fate in the Senate. <persName rend="italic">M. Anthony</persName> upbraideth him by his Great-Grand-Father, as if he were a Libertine by Birth, a Roper by Trade, ſprang out of a little Village in the Countrey of the <placeName rend="italic">Thurines</placeName>, and that his Grand-Father was a Caſhier or Banker, and this is all I can meet with concerning the Pedegree of <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName>, by the Fathers fide.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. His Father <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> being a perſon of Eſtate, and eſteem from the beginning of his age, I cannot but wonder he ſhould be reproach'd by fome people with the name of a Banker, or diſtributer of Money in the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martins</placeName> upon Election of Officers, for having been brought up from his Cradle in great affluence and plenty, he arrived easily at great honours, and as worthily adminiſtred them. His Prætorſhip being expired, the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Macedon</placeName> fell to his Lot; he reduc'd the remainder of <persName rend="italic">Spartacus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Catiline</persName>'s Forces, (which were rallied and in Arms about <placeName rend="italic">Thurin</placeName>) by the way, having an extraordinary Commiſſion from the Senate to that purpoſe.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He govern'd his Province with as much Valour as Juſtice, for after he had overthrown the <persName rend="italic">Beffi</persName> and the <persName rend="italic">Thracians</persName> in a great Battle, he comported himself ſo handſomly towards his Allies, that there are certain Epiſtles of <persName rend="italic">M. Tullius Cicero</persName> ſtill extant, in which he adviſes his Brother <persName rend="italic">Quintus</persName> (who was Proconful of <placeName rend="italic">$A/ia$</placeName> at that time, and had mannaged it not without fome ſcandal and infamy) that if he had a mind to oblige his Allies, he ſhould need to do no more, than toimitate the example of his Neighbour <persName rend="italic">Oftavius</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      4. Departing from <placeName rend="italic">Macedon</placeName>, he died fuddenly, before he could ſtand for the Confulſhip, leaving behind him <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName> the elder (which he had by <persName rend="italic">Ancharia</persName>) <persName rend="italic">Oitavia</persName> the younger, and <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> by <persName rend="italic">Atia</persName>, which <persName rend="italic">Atia</persName> was the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Atius Balbus</persName> by <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> the Siſter of <persName rend="italic">Ca. Cafar</persName>. <persName rend="italic">Balbus</persName> was an <persName rend="italic">Aricine</persName> by the Fathers ſide, and had had many Senators in his Family; and by the Mothers fide he was nearly related to <persName rend="italic">Pompey the Great</persName>. After his Prætorſhip was paſt, he was one of the twenty deputed by Commiſſion to divide the Lands in the Territory of <placeName rend="italic">Capua</placeName> amongst the People according to the Law <foreign rend="italic">Julia</foreign>;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Yet <persName rend="italic">M. Anthonie</persName> deſpiſes <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> his deſcent by the Mothers fide alſo, and reproaches him as if his great Grand-father on her ſide was an African born, ſometimes that he kept a Perfumers ſhop, and ſometimes a Bakers in <placeName rend="italic">Aricia</placeName>. <persName rend="italic">Caffius Parmenfis</persName> goes further, and in one of his Epiſtles aſperſes him with being the Grand-child of a Banker, as well as a Baker, in theſe terms; <q rend="italic">Thou art of a Dough by the Mothers fide, which a CaShier of <placeName rend="italic">Nerulon</placeName> ſtole out of an <placeName rend="italic">Arician</placeName> Bake-house, moulding and kneading it into a Consistence with his duxty fingers, discoloured with telling of Money.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      5. <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> was born in the Confulſhips of <persName rend="italic">M. Tullius Cicero</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Anthony</persName>, the ninth of the Calends of <date rend="italic">October</date>, a little before the rising of the Sun in the <placeName rend="italic">Palatine</placeName> quarter, at a place called the <placeName rend="italic">Oxe-heads</placeName>, where there is a Temple to be ſeen at this day, which was erected and dedicated to him a while after his death; and upon this occaſion, as appears by the Journal and Regiſters of the Senate. <persName rend="italic">C. Lectorius</persName> (a young man of a Patrician Family) being accuſed of Adultery, (to obviate, or mollifie the ſentence) befides his age, and extraction, pleaded that he was the Poffeffor and Guardian of that ground which <persName rend="italic">$A_{H}g_{H}ft_{HS}$</persName> firſt touch'd after he was born, and beg'd that he might be forgiven for his fake, as he being his Domeſtick and peculiar Lar: whereupon it was immediately decreed that that part of the houſe ſhould be confecrated.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. His Nurſery is to be ſeen to this day, in a little Country houſe belonging to his Ancestors near <placeName rend="italic">Velitre</placeName>, which is no bigger than a Cabine; and yet ſome are of opinion it was the place of his birth alſo. To enter into it without great neceſſlity and devotion, was look'd upon as prophane, the people being perſwaded of old, that they which entred inconfiderately, were immediately furpriſed with a certain trembling and horror, and this fancy was much confirmed by this ſtory. A new Landlord, or Poffeffor of this Village, either with deſign to make experiment, or by chance taking up his lodging one night in that place, it happen'd after few hours repofe, he was not only diſturb'd with a fudden and violent noiſe, but himself and Bed taken up and carried out of doors, where he was found ſpeechless and half dead the next morning.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. Being but an infant he was called <persName rend="italic">Thurinus</persName>, either in memory of the Origine of his Ançeſtors, or becauſe his Father had about the time of his nativity fought a Battle against the Fugitives upon the Borders of the <placeName rend="italic">Thurines</placeName>. But that <persName rend="italic">Thurinus</persName> was his furname, I think I may affert, for I had a little Copper Medal in which he was répreſented in his infancy, and that name inſcribed in old Iron Characters, almoſt worn out; which I gave to the Emperour, and he received it ſo kindly, he keeps it to this day in his Cloſet amongſt his moſt venerable curiofities. <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName> in his Epiſtles, calls him often <persName rend="italic">Thurinus</persName> by way of contumely and ſcorn, to which he made no other reply, but that He wondred his first Name ſhould be objected to him as a reproach:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      After that he aſſum'd the Sirname of <persName rend="italic">Ca. Cafar</persName>, and then of <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName>; one by the laft Will and Teftament of his great Uncle, the other by the Vote of <persName rend="italic">Munatius Plancus</persName>; for whilſt ſome gave their Voices he ſhould be call'd <persName rend="italic">Romulus</persName>, as if he also had been a fecond founder of the City, <persName rend="italic">Plancus</persName> prevail'd to have him rather call'd <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName>, not only as a newer, but more honourable Title, becauſe Religious and holy places, in which any thing is confecrated with the Ceremonies of the <foreign rend="italic">Angures</foreign>, are called <placeName rend="italic">Augusta</placeName>, taking its Etymology either <foreign rend="italic">ab auctu</foreign>, or elfe <foreign rend="italic">ab avium gestu gustuve</foreign>, from growing, or from the geſture, or feeding of Birds; as <persName rend="italic">Ennius</persName> intimates in theſe words; <q rend="italic">Augusto angurio postquam inclyta condita Roma eft.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. When he was four years old his Father died, and at twelve he made a Funeral Oration for his Grand-Mother <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> before the people: four years afterwards he was preſented with the Military Gifts at the African triumph of <persName rend="italic">$Ce\int ar$</persName>, though by reaſon of his age he had never had experience in the Wars. A while after, his Uncle going into <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName> against <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>'s children, he followed him with a fmall Train, though he was ſcarce recover'd of a fit of fickness, the wayes infeſted by the Enemy, and he not only ran the hazard, but was actually Shipwreckt by the way; by which diligence in his journey, and the ſweetness of his deportment when he came there, he indeared himfelf to his Uncle exceedingly.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having reduc'd the Spaniards to their obedience, and deſigning a new War upon the <persName rend="italic">Daci</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Parthians</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> fent <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> before to <placeName rend="italic">Apollonia</placeName> to follow his ſtudies for Tome time: As foon as he had intelligence that <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> was dead, and had left him his Heir, deliberating with himself a good while, whether he ſhould implore the aſſiſtance of the neighbouring Legions; at laſt he laid by thoſe thoughts as precipitous and unſeaſonable. Being return'd to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he immediately made claim to his Inheritance, though his Mother knew not what to refolve in the Cafe, and his Father in Law <persName rend="italic">Mortius Philippus</persName> (who had formerly been Conful) was poſitively againft it, and diſſwaded him what he could.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      From which time, having levied fuch Forces as were neceſſary, he govern'd the Commonwealth firſt with <persName rend="italic">M. Anthonie</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">M. Lepidus</persName>, then with <persName rend="italic">Mark Anthony</persName> alone almoſt twelve years, and afterwards four and forty by himself.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. Having propos'd to my ſelf to write a ſummary of his life, I shall deduce the particulars not according to the order of time, but according to the nature and quality of his actions, which I conceive will render them more comprehenſible and distinct. He had five Civil Wars in his time, viz. at <placeName rend="italic">Mutina</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Philippi</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Perufium</placeName> in <placeName rend="italic">Sicilia</placeName>, and at <placeName rend="italic">Affium</placeName>: The firſt and laſt were against <persName rend="italic">Marc. Anthonie</persName>, the ſecond against <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Caffius</persName>, the third against <persName rend="italic">L. Antonius</persName> the brother of the Triumvir, and the fourth against <persName rend="italic">Sextus Pompeius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Cn. Pompeius</persName> his Son.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. The pretence and foundation of allhis Wars, was the revenging his Uncles death, as judging nothing more plaufible &amp; convenient for his ends, than to profecute that vigouroufly, and to juſtifie his decrees! As soon as he was return'd from <placeName rend="italic">Apollonia</placeName>, his firſt deſign was either ſo ſurprize <persName rend="italic">Caffius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName>, by fome artifice, or to ſuppress them otherwise by force; but they having taken the alarm, fled for their ſecurity, and ſpoil'd that deſign: Being gone, he defſiſted not from his Revenge, but betaking himself to the Law, he accus'd them of Treaſon, and the Murther of <persName rend="italic">$Ce\int ar$</persName>, (though they were abfent.) Obſerving that thoſe who had the charge of Exhibiting the Playes publickly deſign'd for <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName>s Victory, were afraid to undertake them, he affum'd their offices, and exhibited them himself;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and that he might the better go thorow with what ever he should afterwards attempt, he endeavour'd to be fubrogated in the place of a Tribune of the people, (who was by accident dead at that time) though he was a Patrician, and no Senator: But <persName rend="italic">M. Anthony</persName> oppoſing him with all his force, from whom he expected his greateſt aſſiſtance, and perceiving nothing was to be done by him without contract and promife of great reward, he apply'd himfelf to the Nobility and Senators of the Town, which he knew at that time had no great inclinations to <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> for ſeveral reaſons, and amongst the reſt, that he had befieg'd <persName rend="italic">D. Brutus</persName> in <placeName rend="italic">Modena</placeName>, and would have driven him out of a Province which was given him by <persName rend="italic">$Ce\int ar$</persName>, and confirm'd to him by the Senate:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      But this not being fufficient, he was perſwaded by fome perſons to afſlaſſinate <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>; but that Plot being difcover'd, and he himself apprehenſive of the fame practices, he infinuated with the Veteran Army by all the bounty and indulgence imaginable, and prevail'd with them to undertake the defence of the Publick intereſt, and his own. Being made General of this Army, inſtead of the Prator, and with <persName rend="italic">Hirtins</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Panfa</persName>, the Confuls commanded to the relief of <persName rend="italic">D. Brutus</persName>; in two Battels, and three months time he ended that War,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> reports, he ran away in the firſt fight, and two dayes afterwards appear'd indeed, but without his <foreign rend="italic">Paludamentum</foreign> his Robe of Command, or his Horſe; But howsoever he behaved himself there, in the next battel he ſhew'd himself not only a Captain, but a Souldier; for the Standard bearer of his Legion being defperately wounded, he took the Standard from him, and carried it upon his own ſhoulders a long time.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. <persName rend="italic">Hirtius</persName> being flain in this War, and <persName rend="italic">Panfa</persName> dying a while after of his wounds, it was commonly reported he had made them away, to the end that <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> being routed, and the Common-wealth without Confuls, he might have fole poffeflion of the Conquering Army; and indeed <persName rend="italic">Panfa</persName>'s death was ſo ſuſpicious, that <persName rend="italic">Glyco</persName> his Phyſitian was clapt into Priſon for putting poiſon into his wound: And <persName rend="italic">Aquilius Niger</persName> affirms, that <persName rend="italic">Hirtius</persName> the other Conful was killed by <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> his own hands in the throng and confufion of the fight.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. Underſtanding that <persName rend="italic">M. Anthony</persName> after his flight was receiv'd by <persName rend="italic">Lepidus</persName>, and that the reſt of the Captains and Commanders of his Army had declared for the Senate, he abandon'd that party immediately upon pretence of a diſguſt they had given him by words ſpoken in his contempt; fome of them having call'd him Boy, and others faid he deferv'd to be dress'd, and taken up, (or off) that by that means both himself and his Veterans might be paid their arrears; and that his defertion of that party might appear more fincere, he not only laid a greater Fine upon the <placeName rend="italic">Nurfines</placeName> than they were able to bear, but baniſh'd them the Town for non-payment of it, becauſe they had erected a Monument at the publick charge for fuchas were flain at the battel of <placeName rend="italic">Modena</placeName>, with an inſcription, importing, <q rend="italic">That they died for the liberty of the City.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. Having made a League with <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lepidus</persName>, in two battels he compleated the Philippin Wars, though he was indiſpos'd, and ſcarce recover'd of a late fit of fickness. In the firſt ingagement he was beaten out of his Camp, and with much ado eſcap'd to <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> his wing; however he got the Victory, and managed it with great ſeverity, for he fent <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName> his head to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> to be plaod at the foot of <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName>s Statue, and treated the reſt of his Priſoners of the highest condition with as much cruelty as contempt:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      To one that begg'd only that he might be buried, he reply'd, <q rend="italic">That that was now in the power of the Birds:</q> And the Father and the Son begging mutually for one anothers lives, he order'd them either to draw lots, or commanded them by fighting to determine the doubt, ſtanding by himself whilft both of them died; the Father (who offer'd himself) being killed, and the Son (with indignation of the Spectacle) diſpatching himself: Infomuch that ſeveral others, and <persName rend="italic">M. Favonius</persName>, the great imitator of <persName rend="italic">Cato</persName>, amongst the reſt, being brought out in Chains to Execution, They faluted <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> with great reſpect, giving him the Title of Emperour, but upbraided <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> with his inhumanity to his face.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      After this Victory they divided their Commands, <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> undertook the Government of the East, and <persName rend="italic">Auguftus</persName> to reconduct the old Souldiers into <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, and to diſpoſe them into the Municipal Territories afſigned to them; but he managed his buſineſs ſo, that he fatisfied neither Inhabitants nor Souldiers, one party complaining they were diſpoſſeſt, the other that they were not rewarded proportionably, either to their expectation or deferts.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. About this time <persName rend="italic">L. Antonius</persName> prefuming upon the authority of the Confulſhip, and the power of his Brother, was contriving new troubles in the State; but <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> interpoſed, beat him into <placeName rend="italic">Perufia</placeName>, and forc'd him to furrender for want of Proviſions; Yet not without great dangers to himself both before and in the War; for obſerving a Common Souldier fitting in the Gentlemens ſeats at a Stage-Play, he commanded him to be pull'd down by an Officer, and a report being ſpread by his Enemies that he had tortur'd him thereupon; the reft of the Souldiers in great tumult and indignation demanded their Camerade, and doubtleſs he had run great hazard in the Tumult, had not the Souldier been immediately produc'd without any injury at all. He eſcap'd very narrowly alſo as he was facrificing before the walls of <placeName rend="italic">Perufia</placeName>; for a Sally being made on a fudden, he miſs'd narrowly of being either taken or killed.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. At the taking of <placeName rend="italic">Perufia</placeName>, he exerciſed great cruelty; ſuch as would have excus'd themselves, or fubmitted, he cut ſhort with theſe words, <q rend="italic">You must die.</q> Some have writ, that he ſelected three hundred of both Orders from the rest of his Prifoners, and facrificed them upon the Ides of March before the Altar dedicated to <persName rend="italic">D. Julius</persName>; Others affirm he took up Arms on purpoſe for the detection of his Enemies, as conceiving that fuch as had been reſtrain'd rather by fear than allegiance, and opportunity given by their Captain <persName rend="italic">Antoniu</persName>, would probably declare for him, which he not doubting to overcome, refolv'd to confiſcate their Eſtates, and inable himſelf that way to recompence his Veterans as he had faithfully ingag'd.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. The <placeName rend="italic">Sicilian</placeName> War he began betimes, but it proved very tedious, by ſeveral intermiſſions, ſometimes to repair his Navy, which was twice wreckt in one Summer, ſometimes being forc'd to a Truce by the importunities of the people, who being in great want of proviſions (all paſſages ſtop'd) they became deſperate of ſupplies, grew impatient of the War, and compell'd him to a Treaty. At last, having rigg'd out a new Fleet, and manumitted twenty thousand Slaves to be brought up at his Oares, he made the haven at <placeName rend="italic">Bayes</placeName> by letting in the Sea into the Lakes <placeName rend="italic">Lucrinus</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Avernus</placeName>. In which place, after he had exercis'd his Seamen a whole winter together, advancing against <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, he overcame him betwixt <placeName rend="italic">Mylas</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Naulochum</placeName>; as they were juſt ready to ingage, he was ſurpris'd with ſo ſound a fleep, his friends were forc'd to wake him to give the fignal, which gave occaſion to <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> to upbraid him, <q rend="italic">That he was not able with his own eyes to see how his Fleet was drawn up, but lying tumbling upon his back, and gazing upon the Skies, he neither rose, nor shew'd himself to his Souldiers, till <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> had broken and diſpers'd the Enemies Fleet.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Others condemn him both in his actions, and words, particularly for ſaying in publick, after his Fleet was ruin'd by ſtorm, <q rend="italic">That he would have the Victory in despight of <persName rend="italic">Neptune</persName>;</q> and in the next folemn Circenſian Games, he would not fuffer the Image of the ſaid God to be ſeen in the Ceremony.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Never did his imprudence expoſe him to more dangers than in this War, for having landed one part of his Army in <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, and returning to the Continent for the tranſportation of the reſt, he was ſo ſurpris'd and overlaid by <persName rend="italic">Demochares</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Apollophanes</persName> (two of <persName rend="italic">Pompey's</persName> Lieutenants) he had much ado to get off with one ſingle Veſſel. Another time, paſſing by <placeName rend="italic">Locris</placeName> towards <placeName rend="italic">Rhegium</placeName> on foot, and perceiving <persName rend="italic">Pompey's</persName> Galleys ſtanding to the ſhore, he ſuppos'd them to be his own, made towards them as faſt as he could, and was in a fair way of being taken Priſoner. Having made his eſcape from then, and preſerv'd himself thorow Lanes, and by-wayes, he was met by a Slave belonging to <persName rend="italic">Emilius Paulus</persName> (his Companion) who reſenting that he had formerly proſcribed his Maſters Father, and judging that a convenient opportunity to revenge it, he attempted to kill him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      After he had routed <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName>, <persName rend="italic">M. Lepidus</persName> one of his Colleagues (whom he had invited out of <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName> to his relief) growing ſo infolent upon confidence in his twenty Legions, that with threats he demanded the foveraignty of the reſt: He turn'd him out of the Army, and having with great difficulty granted him his life, he baniſh'd him perpetually into the Iſland <placeName rend="italic">Circei</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. His Leagues with <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> being doubtful and uncertain, and patch'd up upon occaſion by ſeveral reconcilements, he brake with him quite, at laſt; and that he might render him the more obnoxious to the people, and his actions demonſtrate how much he was degenerated from the integrity of a Citizen, he caus'd his will, (which he had left behind him at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>) to be publickly read, in which he had nominated <persName rend="italic">Cleopatra's</persName> Children, among the reſt of his Heirs.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Nevertheless, though he had declared him an Enemy to the State, He diſmiſt his relations and friends and ſent them to him, and amongſt the reſt <persName rend="italic">C. Sofius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Tr. Domitinus</persName>, both Confuls at that time. The <placeName rend="italic">Bolonians</placeName> being antient dependants and followers of the <persName rend="italic">Antonii</persName>, he excus'd and difpenc'd with, for not Confederating with the rest of <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> in his behalf: a while after he overcame <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> in a Sea-fight near <placeName rend="italic">Actium</placeName>, which laſting till the Evening, he was forc'd to lie all night (Conqueror as he was) on Shipboard.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      From <placeName rend="italic">Actium</placeName> he paſt into <placeName rend="italic">Samos</placeName> for winter Quarters, but underſtanding that the Souldiers he had drawn out of his whole Army after the Victory, and fent before to <placeName rend="italic">Brunduſium</placeName>, had mutinouſly demanded diſmiſſion and pay; he returned into <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> again, but not without danger of being twice caſt away by the violence of the weather, once betwixt the Promontories of <placeName rend="italic">Peloponneſus</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Ætolia</placeName>, the other about the Mountains <placeName rend="italic">Ceraunii</placeName>; Both in one and the other ſome part of his Fleet was caſt away, the Tackling of his own Ship rent, and his rudder broken; He ſtay'd but twenty ſeven dayes at <placeName rend="italic">Brunduſium</placeName>, then having appeas'd the Mutiny, and fatisfied his Souldiers, Coaſting by <placeName rend="italic">Aſia</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Syria</placeName>, he fail'd into <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, beſieg'd <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName> (whither <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Cleopatra</persName> were fled) reduc'd it in a ſhort time,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      and becauſe <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> had neglected his opportunity of making his peace, he not only compell'd him to kill himself, but took delight to behold him when he was dead. He had a great defire to have preſerved <persName rend="italic">Cleopatra</persName> for his Triumph, and imploy'd feveral of the <persName rend="italic">Pfilli</persName> to fuck out the poiſon out of her Breaſt, which her <foreign rend="italic">Aſps</foreign> had infuſed, but in vain: However he buried them honourably together, and commanded the Tomb which they had began themſelves to be ſpeedily finiſh'd.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> the younger (the eldeſt of his two Sons by <persName rend="italic">Fulvia</persName>) not being able with all his prayers and obſecrations to mitigate the anger of <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName>, he fled to the Image of <persName rend="italic">D. Julius</persName>, as to a Sanctuary, but <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> commanded him to be pull'd violently from thence and diſpatch'd. <persName rend="italic">Cæſario</persName> alſo (whom <persName rend="italic">Cleopatra</persName> declared ſhe had had by <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>) he fetch'd out of the place whither he was fled, and put him to death, the rest of their Children, he preſerved as if they had been his own relations, advancing them afterwards according as they were qualified.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      18. At the ſame time the Coffin of <persName rend="italic">Alexander the great</persName> being brought to him out of its Sepulcher, he ſurvey'd the embalmed Body as it lay, and having viewed it a while, he put a Crown of Gold upon its head, and ſtrew'd flowers about it, with great Veneration; and being ask'd if he would ſee <persName rend="italic">Ptolomies</persName> alſo, he replyed, <q rend="italic">His curioſity was to ſee a King, not a dead Man:</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having reduced <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName> into a Province, that he might render it more fertile, and commodious for the ſupplying of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, by the incredible labour of his Souldiers, he cleanſed all the Ditches into which the <placeName rend="italic">Nile</placeName> overflowed, which for a long time before had been choak'd up with mud. That the memory of his <placeName rend="italic">Actiack</placeName> Victories might be more famous to poſterity, he built the City of <placeName rend="italic">Nicopolis</placeName> not far from <placeName rend="italic">Actium</placeName>, and conſtituted certain Plays and Games there every five years. He enlarged the old Temple of <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName> likewiſe, and having adorned the place where he incamped, with the ſpoils and prizes he had taken at Sea, he conſecrated it to <persName rend="italic">Neptune</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      19. After this there were ſeveral tumults in the City, and many plots and conſpiracies laid againſt him which he diſcovered in time, and ſuppreſt before they came to maturity; as firſt the conſpiracy of <persName rend="italic">Lepidus Junior</persName>, then that of <persName rend="italic">Varro</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Muræna</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Fannius Cæpio</persName>, a while after that of <persName rend="italic">M. Egnatius</persName>, next <persName rend="italic">Plautius Rufus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">L. Paulus</persName> who married his Grand-daughter. That of <persName rend="italic">L. Audafius</persName> an old and infirm man, who had been formerly accuſed of forging of Wils; after that <persName rend="italic">Aſinius Epicadus</persName>, deſcended from the <persName rend="italic">Parthines</persName>, of a Mungril extraction: and laſt of all of <persName rend="italic">Telephus</persName>, a pittiful Nomenclator, and ſervant to a woman; Nay ſo ingrateful was he become, he was in danger of his life, even by the meaneſt and moſt abject of the people.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Audafius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Epicadus</persName>, had laid their plots to have ſurpriſed his Daughter <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> and his Grand-ſon <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>, in the Iſlands in which he had diſpoſed them, and to have carried them to the Army. <persName rend="italic">Telephus</persName> being perſwaded he was deſigned to the Empire by his deſtiny and fate, reſolv'd to have attempted both the Senate and <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> too. There was taken one night a Servant or Pedee, belonging to the <placeName rend="italic">Illyrian</placeName> Army, who had ſtoln into the Chamber with a Hunts-mans Skeane by his ſide, having ſlipt by his Guards; but whether he was really diſtracted, or did only pretend ſo, is not certainly known, for they could extort nothing from him with all the torments they could inflict.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      20. He commanded the Army in perſon but twice againſt foreign Enemies, firſt in the Wars in <placeName rend="italic">Dalmatia</placeName> (at which time he was but young) and having overthrown <persName rend="italic">Anthonius</persName>, his ſecond was in the expedition againſt the <persName rend="italic">Cantabrians</persName>. In his <placeName rend="italic">Dalmatick</placeName> wars he receiv'd ſeveral hurts, in one Battle, he got a blow on his right knee with a ſtone, and in another he hurt one of his legs, and both his Arms, by the fall of a bridge. The reſt of his Wars he managed by his Lieutenants, but ſo as in his <placeName rend="italic">Pannonian</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">German</placeName> wars, he was many times preſent in perſon, or elſe at hand upon occaſion, having removed from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, to <placeName rend="italic">Ravenna</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Milan</placeName>, or <placeName rend="italic">Aquileia</placeName> on purpoſe.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      21. By his own Conduct ſometimes, and ſometimes by his Lieutenants, he ſubdued the <persName rend="italic">Cantabrians</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Aquitans</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Pannonians</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Dalmatians</persName>, and all <placeName rend="italic">Illyrium</placeName>, beſides the <persName rend="italic">Rhætians</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Vindelicians</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Salaſſians</persName> inhabiting the <placeName rend="italic">Alps</placeName>. He repell'd alſo the Incurſions of the <persName rend="italic">Dacians</persName>, having ſlain three of their Generals, and cut off a vaſt number of their Men. He forc'd the <persName rend="italic">Germans</persName> beyond the River <placeName rend="italic">Elbe</placeName>, but the <persName rend="italic">Ubii</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Sicambrians</persName>, ſubmitting to his Terms, he tranſplanted into <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName>, and diſpoſed them upon the banks of the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He reduc'd other Nations to obedience likewiſe, but never invaded any without juſt, and unavoidable occaſion: and ſo little Teſtimonies did he give of his ambition, either of dominion or honour by unlawful waies, that he contented himſelf with the Oaths only of ſeveral Barbarian Princes, who ſwore to him in the houſe of <persName rend="italic">Mars the revenger</persName>, that they would keep their Faith moſt religiouſly, and preſerve that Peace which ſo graciouſly he had granted them; but from ſome of them he requir'd Hoſtages, and that of a new kind, for obſerving they were not ſo careful of their men, he exacted Women at that time; yet he never dealt ſo ſtrictly with them, but that they might have their pledges again when they themſelves pleaſed. The moſt frequent, and moſt perfidious of his Rebels, he never puniſh'd worſe than by ſelling them as Captives, with condition, that they ſhould not ſerve in any Neighbouring Countrey, nor be manumitted and made free within thirty years ſpace.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The reputation of his Virtue and moderation was ſo great, that the <persName rend="italic">Indians</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Scythians</persName>, known only by name, were induc'd to ſend Embaſſadors to deſire his friendſhip; No ſooner had he ſignified to the <persName rend="italic">Parthians</persName>, the title and pretence the Commonwealth had to <placeName rend="italic">Armenia</placeName>, but they immediately reſigned, reſtored the Enſigns they had taken from <persName rend="italic">M. Craſſus</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName>, upon his demand, and gave him hoſtages alſo; laſtly, ſeveral Princes being in competition at the ſame time for a certain Kingdom, They referr'd it to his Arbitrament, and would not admit of any other determination.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      22. Having made an univerſal peace both by land and Sea, he ſhut up the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Janus Quirinus</persName> thrice, (which had been ſhut up but twice before from the building of the City, and in a much ſhorter ſpace than it was ſhut up the two times before.) Twice he entred the City by way of Ovation, once after the <placeName rend="italic">Philippick</placeName>, and again after his <placeName rend="italic">Sicilian</placeName> war; three times he triumph'd, for three dayes together, after his <placeName rend="italic">Dalmatick</placeName>, his <placeName rend="italic">Actiack</placeName> and his <placeName rend="italic">Alexandrian</placeName> Victories.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      23. He ſuſtain'd but two conſiderable loſſes in all his wars, and both of them in <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>; <persName rend="italic">Lollius</persName> his defeat was more diſhonourable than prejudicial, But <persName rend="italic">Varius</persName> his was almoſt irrecoverable. Three Legions with their General, Lieutenants and all their Auxiliaries being utterly cut off. Upon the news of this diſaſter, he ſet watches night and day in the City to prevent any tumult, or uprore; prolonging the Governments of his Provinces, that the Allies might the better be kept in their allegiance by experienc'd Captains, and ſuch as were accuſtomed to them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He vowed alſo great Games to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, <q rend="italic">If he would vouchsafe to restore the Common-wealth to a better condition,</q> which had been formerly done in the time of the <placeName rend="italic">Cimbrian</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Marſian</placeName> Wars. In ſhort, it is reported he was ſo much diſcompos'd at this misfortune, that he let his beard and his hair grow for ſeveral months together, knocking his head many times againſt the doors, crying out aloud, <q rend="italic">Give me my Legions again <persName rend="italic">Quintilius Varus</persName>;</q> and kept the day of his defeat as a mourning and faſting day every year after.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      24. In his Military Diſcipline many things he alter'd, and many he inſtituted, and ſome he reduc'd to the primitive Order, he was very ſevere in keeping his Soldiers to their duty, not ſuffering (but with great difficulty) his Lieutenants to make a viſit to their Wives, and that only when their Armies were in their Winter Quarters. A <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight cutting off the Thumbs of two of his Sons thereby to diſenable them for the Wars, he commanded him to be ſold and Confiſcated his Eſtate; But ſeeing Money bid liberally for him, by the Publicans of the City, he ordered him to be delivered to one of his Libertines, to be ſent down into the Countrey and live there at his freedom.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His tenth Legion obeying Orders unwillingly, he disbanded with diſgrace, and others which demanded inſolently to be diſmiſt, he Caſhier'd without any reward: if in his Engagements, any of his Cohorts gave ground, or were diſordered, he executed every tenth man, and allowed the reſt nothing but Barly. The Captains or Officers of his Cohorts abandoning their Poſts, were puniſh'd likewiſe with death. If their offences were but ſmall, his ſentence was proportionable, contenting himſelf with making them ſtand all day long upright before his Pretorium: ſometimes ungirt in their Tunicks only, ſometimes with long poles in their hands, ſometimes with turffs of Earth.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      25. After his Civil wars were ended he never called his Soldiers Fellow-Soldiers, but Soldiers, both in his Orations and Edicts. Nor would he ſuffer his own or his wives children who had the Command of Armies at that time, to call them any other wiſe; conceiving it undecent, and unſutable either with his Military Diſcipline, the Tranquillity of thoſe times, or the Grandeur of himſelf and Family.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Unleſs it were in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> upon occaſion of Fires, or when any Commotion of the people was apprehended from the ſcarcity of Proviſions, he never put the Servants into Arms but twice, The firſt time for defence of the Colonies upon the Frontiers of <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName>, the other to make good the Banks of the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName>. He exacted them then from the richer ſort both Men and Women, and being manumitted forth-with, he put them under his firſt colours, diſtinguiſhing them from his free-born men as well by their places, as arms.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He more readily and frequently beſtowed Military gifts, (as Trappings, Chains, and whatever was made of Silver and Gold,) than Vallar, or Mural Crowns, which (being more honour) he conferr'd but ſeldom, and then without any partiality, to the meaneſt of his Souldiers if his actions deſerv'd it. He preſented <persName rend="italic">M. Agrippa</persName> with a blew Standard upon his Naval Victory in <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>; ſuch as had triumpht though they had been his aſſociates, and born part in his Expeditions and Victories, were the only perſons he never judg'd fit to be preſented with thoſe Military rewards, and for this Reaſon, becauſe they had the ſame right to give them to every body themſelves:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He held this as an infallible Maxime, that raſhneſs, and precipitancy in a General, were the greateſt defects; and therefore he had this ſaying frequently in his Mouth, <q rend="italic">No more haste than good speed, slow and sure, whatever is well done, is done time enough.</q> He maintain'd, that War was never to be undertaken, nor a Battel never to be given; but where the advantage hoped for was apparently greater than the loſs fear'd; <q rend="italic">for,</q> ſaid he, <q rend="italic">Those who hazard much to gain but little, are like them who fish with hooks of Gold, whose loss is never to be repaired by any prize they can take.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      26. He arrived at the Magiſtracy, and other honours before he was at age, ſome of them were of new conſtitution, and ſome perpetual. He Uſurped the Conſulſhip at twenty three years of age, by drawing up his Army about the Town, and deputing perſons to demand his Election in the name of the whole Army; and the Senate appearing ſcrupulous, and unwilling to come to a Reſolution, <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Centurio</persName> (the chief perſon that was ſent) laying his hand upon the hilt of his Sword, and throwing off his Coat, had the confidence to tell them, <q rend="italic">This shall do the business, if you will not.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Nine years after his firſt Conſulſhip, he bore his ſecond, the third a year after that, and ſo his others ſucceſſively till they came to eleven, afterwards he refuſed ſeveral which were offer'd him for ſeventeen years together, but at laſt he deſired his twelfth Conſulſhip himſelf, and two years after, his thirteenth, to the end that being in that Grandeur, he might bring his Sons <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> (who were then Students at Law) with the more oſtentation, and authority to the Bar.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      His five intermediat Conſulſhips betwixt his ſixth and eleventh he adminiſtred the whole year thorow, the reſt only for nine or ſix, or four, or three Months; but the ſecond for ſome hours only, for upon the Calends of January in the morning, having plac'd himſelf before the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>, and ſat there for ſome time in his Curule Chair he reſigned that Office and ſubſtituted another: Nor did he enter upon his Conſulſhips always at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, but the fourth he began in <placeName rend="italic">Aſia</placeName>, the fifth in the Iſle of <placeName rend="italic">Samos</placeName>, and his eighth and ninth in <placeName rend="italic">Tarragan</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      27. For the better Regiment of the Commonwealth, he bore the Triumvirat for ten years together, in which he reſiſted his Colleagues for a while, and oppos'd the Proſcription, but when it was commenc'd, he executed it with more ſeverity than his Comerades, who yielding many times to the prayers and importunities of ſeveral perſons, he endeavoured with all eagerneſs alone that none might be ſpared, proſcribing <persName rend="italic">C. Toranius</persName> who had been his Tutor, and his Father <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> his Colleague in his Ædileſhip.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Junius Saturnius</persName> goes farther and tells us that when the time for the Proſcription was expir'd, and <persName rend="italic">M. Lepidus</persName> had excuſed what was paſt in the Senate, and promis'd more Clemency for the future, ſeeing juſtice had been ſatisfied abundantly; <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> ſtood up and declared to the contrary, telling them boldly, <q rend="italic">That he had set no limits to the proscription, but his own will, and would proceed therein still as he pleased himself.</q> Nevertheleſs repenting afterward of his obſtinacy, he honor'd <persName rend="italic">T. Vinius Philopæmen</persName> with the order of Knighthood, for having conceal'd his Patron formerly, in the time he was proſcrib'd:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      During his Triumviracy he contracted much envy by his comportment; for upon a time as he was making a Speech to the Souldiers, <persName rend="italic">Pinarius</persName> a <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight coming in with ſeveral Citizens to hear his Harangue, and writing down ſuch paſſages of his Oration as he lik'd, concluding him pragmatical and a ſpy, he commanded him to be killed before his face. <persName rend="italic">Tedius Afer</persName> (being Conſul Elect) having reflected too ſharply upon ſome of his actions, he terrified ſo deſperately with his threats, that in a melancholly fit, he threw himſelf down a precipice, and brake his own neck.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Q. Gallius</persName> the Prætor, coming to ſalute him and pay him his devoirs, with a pair of double writing Tables under his robe, he imagined it a poinard, but not daring to inquire into the truth at that time, leſt ſomething elſe might be found, he ſuſpended his anger for a while, but not long after he caus'd him to be torn from the Tribunal by his Guards, and tortur'd like a ſlave, (and confeſſing nothing) he pull'd out his Eyes with his own hands, and then commanded him to be killed. But he writes himſelf that <persName rend="italic">Gallius</persName> deſigned to have ſtabb'd him as they were in diſcourſe, that he clapt him in priſon, at length baniſh'd him the City, and that afterwards he periſh'd either by Shipwrack or Thieves.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      He made himſelf perpetual Tribune, in which he admitted no Colleagues, but twice he aſſum'd the perpetual regulation of Manners and Laws, and though never dignify'd with the Office of Cenſor, yet he muſter'd the people three times; the firſt and laſt with a Colleague, the ſecond by himſelf alone.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      28. Twice he had thoughts of aſſigning the Government into the hands of the Senate; the firſt time was preſently after he had defeated <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>, and upon this ſcore, becauſe he had often pretended <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> was the only impediment which hinder'd him: the other was upon a long fit of ſickneſs, in which he call'd the Senators and Magiſtrates of the City to his houſe, and deliver'd them all the Rolls and Records of the Empire. But upon ſecond thoughts, conſidering that he could not live as a private perſon, without great danger, and that it would be imprudence to commit the Government of the Commonwealth to the management of ſo many, he perſiſted in his reſolution to hold it himſelf, and 'tis a doubt to this day whether his ſucceſs or his deſign was more happy:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      This deſire he declar'd often times in his diſcourſe, but more remarkably in one of his Edicts in theſe words; <q rend="italic">Would to God I might so fix and establish this Commonwealth upon its proper Basis, and reap such fruits of my labour as I desire, that I may hereafter be reputed the founder of so excellent a Fabrick, and carry this hope along with me when I die, that the Commonwealth will continue and flourish upon the foundations which I have laid:</q> and certainly by his own Conduct he compaſt his deſires, endeavouring by all means that no man might have juſt cauſe to complain of the alteration of the Government.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      29. The City being neither beautified according to the Majeſty of the Empire, nor free from Inundations and Fires, he repair'd and imbelliſh'd it to that degree, as he was wont to boaſt, (and not without reaſon) <q rend="italic">Though he found it but Loam, he should leave it Marble:</q> He provided alſo as far as humane induſtry or invention was capable for its future ſecurity;
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He rais'd many publick Buildings, amongſt which the chief were, the Forum or Court of Juſtice, the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Mars the Avenger</persName>, the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName> in <placeName rend="italic">Palatia</placeName>, and the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Jove the Thunderer</persName> in the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>. That which moſt powerfully excited him to the building of the Forum, was the multitude of Clients and Cauſes, which being too numerous for the two old Courts, ſeem'd to call for a third: Whereupon it was erected with all poſſible ſpeed, before his Temple of <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName> was finiſh'd, and Proclamation put forth, that all publick Trials, and all Elections of Judges by lot, ſhould be held ſeparately in that place.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He devoted the Temple to <persName rend="italic">Mars</persName> in his <placeName rend="italic">Philippick</placeName> Wars, which he undertook in revenge of the death of his Father: He decreed therefore that the Senate ſhould meet for the future in that place, to conſult about all matters of War, or Triumphs: that the Governors of Provinces, and Generals of Armies, ſhould be attended from hence when they went away to their Commands, and that ſuch as returned with ſucceſs, ſhould hang up the Enſigns and Trophies of their Triumphs in this place.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He built the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName> in that part of the <placeName rend="italic">Palatium</placeName>, which (according to the interpretation of the Southſayers) being ſtruck down with thunder, that God had deſired, he adorned it with a fair Gallery, and Library both of <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> and <foreign rend="italic">Latine</foreign> Books: In his old age he ſat oftentimes in Council with the Senate, and ſurvey'd the Decuries of the Judges: The Temple of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter the Thunderer</persName>, he built upon a dangerous eſcape he had had in <placeName rend="italic">Cantabria</placeName>, for travelling in thoſe parts by night, a flaſh of Lightning glanced upon his Litter, and ſtruck a Servant of his dead, which was lighting him along.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Other things he did under other peoples names, as of his Wife, his Siſter, and his Nephews; he built the Gallery and Portico of <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, and alſo the Palaces of <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, and the Theater of <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName>,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      and as if all this had been too little, he often exhorted the principal and moſt wealthy perſons of the City, that they would each of them according to their faculties erect or repair ſome Monument or other that might remain an honour and ornament thereunto, and upon his perſwaſion, many did build: <persName rend="italic">Marcius Philippus</persName> built the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Hercules Muſarum</persName>, <persName rend="italic">L. Cornificius</persName> the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Diana</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Aſinius Pollio</persName> the Court of Liberty, <persName rend="italic">Munatius Plancus</persName> the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Saturn</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Balbus</persName> a Theatre, <persName rend="italic">Statilius Taurus</persName> an Amphitheatre, and <persName rend="italic">Marcus Agrippa</persName> ſeveral, and thoſe magnificent Structures.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      30. Having divided the City into Wards, and Streets, he order'd the firſt to be govern'd by Aldermen or Magiſtrates annually choſen, and the Streets by the moſt conſiderable of the people. He was the firſt which appointed Watches and Guards to go about on nights to prevent any miſchief that ſhould happen by Fire: againſt Inundations or overflowings of the River he enlarged and cleans'd the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>, which for a long time had been choak'd up with rubbiſh, and the ruines of houſes; and that the City might be the more acceſſible on all ſides, he took upon himſelf the reparation of the <placeName rend="italic">Via Fluminia</placeName> as far as <placeName rend="italic">Ariminum</placeName>, leaving the reſt of the Cawſeys to be mended by certain perſons which had triumpht, and the charges to be defray'd out of the Spoils of the Enemy.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Such Churches alſo as had been deſtroy'd by time, or any accident by fire, he reedified himſelf, and inrich'd both them and the reſt with moſt magnificent Preſents. To the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitólinus</persName> he gave at once 16000 pound weight of Gold, beſides Jewels and precious Stones, to the value of 50 millions of Seſterces.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      31. <persName rend="italic">Lepidus</persName> being dead, he took the High Priest hood upon himself, which during his life he would never take from him: Having got together all the Prophecies and Books of Predictions written by unknow or unapproved Authors, either in <placeName rend="italic">Greek</placeName> or in <placeName rend="italic">Latine</placeName>, he caus'd them to be burnt, to the number of 2000, and upward, referving only fome ſelect pieces of the <persName rend="italic">Sybils</persName>, which he diſpoſed into two gilt Desks under the Piedeſtal of <persName rend="italic">Apollo Palatinus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He reduc'd the Year to <persName rend="italic">D. Julius's</persName> Calculations which by the negligence of that age was become diforder'd and confus'd; in the regulation of which he choſe to call the Month <foreign rend="italic">Sextilis</foreign> by his own name, rather than <foreign rend="italic">September</foreign> in which he was born, becauſe in that month he obtain'd not only his firſt Confulſhip, but many remarkable Victorics.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He augmented the Number, the Dignity, and the Revenue of the Priests, but eſpecially of the Vestal Virgins: The Eſteem he had of that Order appear'd by this, that there being one of thoſe Virgins dead, and another of neceffity to be chofen in her place, obſerving many applications made to keep their Daughters from the danger of that Lottery, he proteſted publickly, <q rend="italic">That if any of his Grand-daughters were of competent years he would preſent her to the place.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He restored fome of the ancient Ceremonies likewife, which time had aboliſh'd by degrees; as the Augury of <persName rend="italic">Salus</persName>: the Flamenſhip of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>: the <foreign rend="italic">Lupercal</foreign> Games: the Secular, and the Compitalitial Playes. In the <foreign rend="italic">Lupercal</foreign> Solemnities, he forbad all fuch Youths as had no beards to bear a ſhare; In the Secular Playes, he prohibited the young people of both fexes to be preſent at any of the Revels, unlefs in the company of fome graver perfon of their relations. He decreed the Lares Compitales, or Houſhold-Gods, ſhould be adorn'd twice a year with Flowers, that is, both in the Spring and the Summer:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      After the honour and reverence he gave to the Gods, there was nothing in that veneration with him, as the memory of thoſe Captains who had contributed to the advancement of the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Empire from ſo inconſiderable a beginning: for which reafon he repair'd all their Monuments, referving their old Titles and Inſcriptions, and dedicating their Statues and triumphal Effigies in both the Galleries or Porticos of his Forum, or Court of Justice, having declar'd in an Edict, <q rend="italic">That his design was to propose them as a pattern and example, by which himſelf while he lived, and the Princes that should succeed, might order and frame themselves, and the people exait their conformity.</q> He removed the Statue of <persName rend="italic">Pompey</persName> from the Court where <persName rend="italic">Cæsar</persName> was murder'd, and difpoſed it upon a Triumphal Arch of Marble over against the Court of his Theatre.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      32. He corrected ſeveral things of evil Example, which had been introduc'd by the liberty of the Wars, or the ſecurity of Peace, and would in time have contributed much to the deſtruction of the State. For there were great numbers of Highway-Men or Banditi, which walkt publickly with their Swords by their fides, pretending their own defence, who notwithstanding ſeized upon all Travellers without distinction, either of fervants or freemen, and carrying them away, made them work hard in their Store-houſes in the Countrey: There were alſo ſeveral parties or factions which had form'd themſelves into a ſociety calling themſelves the new Colledge, and obliging themſelves to one another in all manner of iniquity whatsoever: whereupon diſpoſing his Guards in convenient places, he fuppreft thoſe robbers, he viſited their Workhouſes, and abolish'd all Fraternities but ſuch as were antient and legal.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He burnt all the old Bonds and Accounts which were due to the publick Treasury, as the chief occafion of all vexatious Suing: If the Title of any publick place in the City was doubtful and litigious, he awarded it to him that was in poſſeſſion. Old Prisoners, both Criminals, and fuch as were kept under reſtraint, only to delight their Creditors or Informers with their fquallour and wants, he releaſt, with this caution, that ifany one moleſted them again, they ſhould run the fame Risque, and be punish'd like them: Nevertheless that no enormity or cauſe might eſcape unpuniſht, or be delay'd, he took thirty dayes from the honorary Playes, and adding them to the old terms, he appointed them to be imploy'd in hearing and determinating of pleas and actions.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      To the three decuries of Judges he added a fourth, which was inferior to the relt, and called the Court of the <foreign rend="italic">Ducenary</foreign>, as having cognizance of actions to the value of two hundred Sefterces and under. He admitted Judges at 25 years of age, five years fooner than anciently they did. But many of them declining that office as tedious and troubleſome, he granted at laſt, but with much difficulty, that each Court or Decury ſnould alternately have its annual vacation, and that fuch Cauſes as were wont to be heard in <foreign rend="italic">November</foreign> and <foreign rend="italic">December</foreign>, ſhould be omitted and laid by.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      33. He was very affiduous in hearing of Caufes in his own perſon, and would fit fome time with patience a good part of the night; if he had any indifpofition upon him he was brought into the Court in his Litter, or else would hear them in his own Palace, lying along upon a Couch. He adminiſtred juſtice with as much clemency as ſtrictneſs if the cauſe would bear it, for a perfon being accuſed before him as a Parricide, and by the law (if he confeft) to be ſown into a fack, and thrown into the Sea, to refcue him from that punishment, and as it were dictate to him what he was to anſwer, he interrogated him thus, <q rend="italic">Sure it was not you killed your Father.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Again there being a buſineſs before him about forging a Will, and all the witneſſes which ſet their hands to it, ipso fatto guilty by the Law <foreign rend="italic">Cornelia</foreign>, he gave to the Judges not only the two Tables of Condemnation, and Abſolution, but a third and intermediate Table, by which they were to be pardon'd, who were deluded, and had been perfwaded to fign either by fraud or furprize.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The appeals of the Citizens heappointed to be determined before the Prætor of the City: but all actions or pleas in his Provinces, he order'd to be judg'd by Confulary perfons, ſuch as he had deputed on purpoſe in every Province.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      34. He reviſed and corrected ſeveral obſolete Laws, and others he made perfectly new, as namely his Sunıptuary Laws, his Laws againſt Adultery, Sodomy, and all kind of incontinence, his Laws againſt Bribery and corrupt acquiſition of offices; as alfo about Marriages: but having been more ſtrict and preciſe in reformation of this Law than the reft, he could not paſs it into an Act for the multitude of oppofers, till he had moderated it &amp; cut off a part of the penalty, granted an indulgence for three years, &amp; befides augmented the rewards.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Yet not contented with that, when a certain <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Knight ſtood up at a Publick Spectacle, and preſt very peremptorily that that Law might be abolish'd, he cauſed <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> his Children to be called, who being come and ſome of them got into his lap, and ſome into their Fathers, with his hand and his head he made ſigns to him that he ſhould follow the example of that young Gentleman, and marry: and obſerving by the immaturity of contracts, and frequent changing of Marriages, the force and feverity of the Law was eluded, he limited the time of their Contracts, and regulated the extravagancies of divorces.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      35. The Number of Senators growing exorbitantly great, confifting of more than a thousand, and fome of them mean and unworthy perfons (having after <persName rend="italic">Cæsars</persName> death by favour and bribery wrought themſelves into the Senate and were called <foreign rend="italic">Orcini</foreign> by the people) he reduc'd them to their primitive number and glory, and that by two manner of E- lections, in the firſt as they pleas'd themſelves every one might chooſe his man; in the ſecond as he and <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> thought fit;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      only it is reported, that as he preſided at this Election, he was arm'd with a coat of Male under his Cloathes, a Sword by his fide, and ten of the moſt valiant of the Senators his friends ſtanding about his Chair. <persName rend="italic">Cordus Cremutius</persName> writes, that even then none of the Senators were admitted to come into the Houſe, but alone, and after they had been ſearcht: He forc'd fome of them to that point of modeſty as to excuſe themſelves from fitting in the Senate, yet he preferv'd to them the priviledge of their habit, the honour of fitting in the <foreign rend="italic">Orchestra</foreign> amongst the Senators at Playes, and their right of precedence at Publick Feafts:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      And that fuch as were elected and approved might perform the functions of Senators with more religion than trouble, he decreed that before they took their ſeats in the Senate, each of them ſhould pay their devotions with Frankincense and Wine before the Altar of that God in whoſe Temple they were afſembled; and that for the future, the Senate ſhould fit (unless upon extraordinary occafion) but twice a month, viz. on the Calends and Ides, and in <foreign rend="italic">September</foreign> and <foreign rend="italic">October</foreign>, that it should not be neceſſary that any more ſhould meet than a certain preciſe number to be choſen by lot, which ſhould be ſuſhcient to paſs any Ordinance or Decree:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He inſtituted a Counſellour himself to be choſen by lots alſo every fix months, to debate and prepare fuch Bills as were to be prefer'd afterwards to the Senate in matters of great importance; he ask'd not the judgments of the Senators according to Order, or the method of old, but every mans as he pleas'd himſelf, to the end that every one might be oblig'd to as much intention, as if he were to advise, as well as to confent.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      36. Besides theſe, he was Author of ſeveral other Acts, as that the transactions in the Senate ſhould not be made publick. That the Magiftrates which had honourably acquitted themſelves of their charges fhould not be immediately hurried away into the Provinces. That a certain fum of Money ſhould be allowed to the Proconfuls for their accomodation with Mules and Tents, which formerly were hired for them by the Publick. That the charge of the Treasury ſhould be tranſlated from the Quastors of the City, to the Prators, or fuch as had been Prators before. That the Centumvir al Court which in former times was called together by the Quastors, ſhould after that time be aſſembled by the Decemviri.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      37. And that there might be more ſharers in the adminiſtration of the Commonwealth he invented new places, as the Overseer of the Publick works, the Highways, the Waters, the Channel of <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>, and the distributions of Corn amongst the people: The Provoſtſhip of the City: Two Triumvirats, one for the Election of Senators, and the other for muſtering and reviewing the Horſe as oft as there was occafion. The Censorship which for a long time had been laid afide, he revived again, and increaſt the number of the Prators, and having demanded two Colleagues, as often as he ſhould be chofen Conful, he could not obtain it, the people replying, it was already too much diminution to his honour to have one.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      38. He was ſo great an honourer of Military Virtue, that he granted compleat Triumphs to above thirty Captains, and Triumphal Ornaments to ſeveral more.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      To the end that the Sons of the Senators might be the more early accuſtomed to the management of publick affairs, he permitted them all at one time to put on the <foreign rend="italic">Toga virilis</foreign>, the Senators Gown, and to be preſent in the Senate houſe when buſineſs was in transaction: at their firſt entrance alſo into the Wars, he not only made them Tribunes, or Colonels of Regiments, but he gave them the Commands of whole Wings, and Brigades, and that none of them might be ignorant in the Art of Encamping, he most commonly gave the Command of both Wings to two of the Senators Sons.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He fre quently called over his Cavalry, which for a long time had been diſcontinued, and revived the Cuſtom of Tranfvection, yet ſo as that he fuffer'd not the accufers, to arreft or take any of them away as they were Muſtring, (which in times paſt was usual:) if any were old, or maimed in the Wars, he permitted them to fend their horſes before in their ranks, and to follow themselves on foot to answer as often as they were called, and at laſt he granted this favour to fuch as were paſt thirty five years of age, that they might deliver up their horfes, if they had no farther inclination to the wars.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      39. The Senate having appointed him ten Adjutants, or Aſſiſtants, he compelled all the <placeName rend="italic">Roman</placeName> Horſemento give an account of their lives, punishing fome and diſgracing others according to the quality of their offences; but admonishing moſt, and that ſeveral ways: His mildeſt way of admonition was, by giving them publickly a pair of writing Tables, and requiring them to read immediately, and to themselves. Others he reprehended, and diſgrac'd for having taken up Money at ſmall intereſt, and put it out again at great.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      40. In the Aſſemblies for the Election of Tribunes, if there were no Candidates out of the Senate, he created them out of the Gentlemen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> with liberty of continuing for the future in which Order they would chooſe. And becauſe during the Civil Wars, feveral Gentlemen had ruined, or at leaft waſted and leflen'd their Patrimonies, fo as they durſt not appear at any publick plays or ſpectacles in the fourteen benches amongst the rest of their quality, for fear of the Theatral penalty; He pronounc'd them exempt, and not lyable to that Law, if either they themselves or their Ancestors had ever had a Gentlemans Eſtate.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He call'd over the People by Streets, and that they might not be diverted too often from their affairs by the frequent diſtributions of Corn, he order'd that tickets ſhould be given them, by virtue of which they might receive it three times in a year, but they begging and importuning to have their old Cuſtome preſerved, he alter'd his refolutión, and continued their doles monthly as before. He reſtored likewise the antient priviledges and circumſtances in Aflemblies; He order'd feveral &amp; severe punishments againft bribes and corrupt acquiſition of Offices, and to prevent any expectation in that nature from the Competitors, on the day of his Election he diftributed out of his own Purse, among the <persName rend="italic">Fabians</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Scaptiens</persName> (who were of his own Tribe) a thousand Sefterces a-piece.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Conceiving it of importance to con. ſerve the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> intire, from any degenerate mixture with foreign or ſervile blood, he grant ed the freedome of the City with great difficulty, and but rarely, and ſet new limits to the manumif ſion of flaves. <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, defiring that freedom for a <placeName rend="italic">Grecian</placeName> which was one of his Clients, he writ him this anſwer, <q rend="italic">That he would do nothing in the Cafe, unless he could come himself, and satisfie him of the juſtice of his request:</q> <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> interceding in like manner for a Tributary <placeName rend="italic">Frenchmen</placeName>, he pereniptorily deni'd to make him free, yet granted him immunity. and exemption from his Tribute, with this profeffion, <q rend="italic">that he would fooner condeſcend to a diminution of the publick Revenue, than to proſtitute or deprive the Honour of the Citizens.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      And as if it were not fufficient that he had by ſeveral difficulties interpoſed, made it no eaſie matter for a flave to get his liberty at all, but much more a juſt and compleat infranchiſement, having by certain pre-. ciſe Rules determin'd both of the Number, Condition, and difference of ſuch as ſhould be ſet free, he added this Article, <q rend="italic">That no ſlave which had ever been under any torture, or in chains, ſhould obtain the freedome of the City in any kind whatsoever.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      He endeavoured alfo to restore the ancient Modes and Faſhions in apparel, and having obſerv'd a great number of <placeName rend="italic">Romans</placeName> attending at an Aſſembly in their old dirty Cloaks, he cried out in great indignation: <q rend="italic">do you fee, <q rend="italic">Romanos rerum dominos, Gentemq, togatam: The Lords of the world, and the Nation of the long Robe.</q></q> And gave the Ædiles Orders that for the future nо one ſhould be permitted to ſit either in the Courts of Justice, or Circus, but in their Gowns, without any Cloak or Mantle whatever.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      41. He expreſs'd his liberality very frequently, and to all Orders of perfons as occafion was offer'd. In his <placeName rend="italic">Alexandrine</placeName> Triumph he brought <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> fo great a proportion of riches which he had taken from the Kings of <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, that thereby he made money very common, he leſſen'd the value of Intereſt, and advanc'd the prices of Land: and as often (afterwards) as there was any thing redundant of confiſcated goods, he was ſo bountiful as to Iend it gratis for a time, to ſuch perſons as were able to fecure him his principal by double the value: he augmented the Eſtates of the Senators, and whereas before they were requir'd to have to the value of 800000 Seſterces, he exacted now they ſhould have 1200000, and made up their fums which were defective with his own Moneys:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He gave many Largeſſes and Congiaries to the people, and of different fums; ſometimes four hundred, ſometimes three, ſometimes two hundred and fifty Sefterces a man: nor did he bawk the very Children themselves, though the custome before was they were to receive nothing till they were eleven years old. Upon any ſcarcity of Victuals, he diſtributed Corn by the Poll amongst the people, ſometimes at a ſmall rate, ſometimes for none at all, and fome times he doubled their Tickets for moneys.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      42. But that he may appear a Prince more folicitous of the good difcipline of his people, than to have them live in Luxury and Profuſeneſs, when complaint was made to him of the dearness and ſcarcity of Wine, he reproved them very ſharply, and told them, <q rend="italic">That his Son in Law <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>, had by his Aqua-duits provided, that no body need die with Thirst;</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and being prefs'd by them another time for a Dole he had promis'd them; he reply'd, <q rend="italic">His credit was not yet lost, he was still able to perform:</q> But when they demanded a benevolence which he never had promis'd at all, he was ſo far incens'd, that he publiſh'd an Edict, reproaching them by their impu dence, and declaring he would then give them nothing though he had deſigned it before. Nor with lefs Gravity and Conſtancy did he proceed, when upon publication of a Congiary, he understood that feveral perſons which had been manumitted, had crowded themselves into the number of the Citizens, he deny'd that he had promis'd them any thing, and for that reaſon gave Order they ſhould have nothing at all: retrenching alſo what he had promis'd to the reſt, that the fum he had appointed might be fufficient to go round.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Upon a great fcarcity of Corn, there being no viſible remedy, he was conſtrained to turn all Slaves, Gladiators and their Families, all Foreigners (except Phyſitians, or Schoolmaſters) and ſome of the ordinary Domeſticks out of the City: At length, the prices of Victuals returning to its old Standard, It was in his mind, to abolish those publick Purveyings for Corn, upon the Confidence of which the people neglected the im provement of their Lands: However he perſiſted not long in that opinion, being affured the ambition of his ſucceſſors would restore them fome time or other: And therefore after this, he carried himself with that mediocrity to both parties, that he ſeem'd to have no leſs care and kindness for the Farmers in the Country, than for the Citizens of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      43. In the frequency, variety and magnificence of his Shows and Playes, he exceeded all his Predeceſſors; he exhibited to the people in his own name (as he affirms himself) four and twenty; and for other Magiftrates which were either abſent or unable, three and twenty more: ſometimes he appointed them to be acted in the ſtreets in all languages, and by Actors of all Nations; not only in the Forum, and the Amphitheatre, but in the Circus and Septa; yet ſometimes he repreſented only the baiting of wild Beasts. He built Scaffolds and Seats in the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martius</placeName>, that the people might with more convenience behold the Wrestlers and Fencers: He exhibited in like manner a natural Combate in a Lake digged on purpoſe near the Ti ber, where <persName rend="italic">Cæsar's</persName> Grove grows now; upon which dayes he plac'd Guards about the City, left the people running in multitudes to the Shews, and leaving their houſes but flenderly provided at home, Thieves ſhould take advantage of their abſence, and rob them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Hebrought fuch perſons into the Circus as were moſt experienc'd and dextrous at running, managing of Chariots, and killing of wild Beasts, amongſt which he produc'd fometimes the Sons of the best Families in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>. He took great delight in the Tournament, or Warlike paftime called <foreign rend="italic">Troy</foreign>, and making choice of his boys of greater and leſſer ſtature, he exhibited it oftner than any of his Predeceſſors, as judging it an antient and honourable exerciſe, and becoming the education of the beſt of the Nobility. At the folemnity of this Game <persName rend="italic">C. Nonius Afprenas</persName> having hurt himſelf with a fall from his Horſe, he preſented him with a chain of Gold, and permitted him and his pofterity to bear the name of <persName rend="italic">Torquatus</persName> for ever. But not long after he diſcontinued that Game, <persName rend="italic">Afinius Pollio</persName> having made a bitter complaint against it in the Senate, upon occafion of his Grandchild <persName rend="italic">Æferminus</persName> his breaking his thigh in the ſame recreation.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In his Comedies and the combats of Gladiators, he ſometimes made uſe of his Knights of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, but it was before there was a decree of the Senate to the contrary; after that, he exhibited only one Noble Youth who was called <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName>, and him only becauſe he was ſcarce two foot high, and weighed but feventeen pounds, and yet had a voyce extraordinary.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Upon one of the dayes of this folemnity, the <placeName rend="italic">Parthian</placeName> Hoſtages being newly arrived, he carried them to be ſpectators thorough the midſt of the Stage, and placed them in the ſecond rank above himself. He was wont alſo if any ſtrange thing worthy the fight of the pople was brought to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, to expoſe it to their view, without obferving the uſual dayes or places for ſuch Spectacles: He cauſed a Rhinoceros to be ſhown in the Park, a Tigre upon the Stage, and a Serpent 50 Cubits long, in the Court of Elections.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      Being folemnizing his Circenſian Games, according to his Vow, he was taken ill of a sudden, yet he followed the <foreign rend="italic">Thenfa</foreign> or facred Chariots with great devotion, lying along in his Litter. Another time whilft he was celebrating the ſports at the dedication of the Theatre of <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName>, it happen'd that his Curule Chair open'd by an unexpected flipping of the joynts, and laid him on his back. Again in one of the Playes exhibited by his Grand-Children, obſerving the people ſo much diſcompoſed by an apprehenfion of the falling of the Theatre, that they could not be recollected, he removed from his own feat, and plac'd himself where the danger was greateſt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="44">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      44. He corrected the confufions and diſorders which did frequently happen at theſe plays in former times, excited thereunto by an affront offered to a Senator at <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName>, where at onc of the greatest and moſt popular Affemblies no man would give him place. Whereupon it was decreed by the Senate that at all publick repreſentations, the firſt rank of seats ſhould be referved for the Senators for the future. He forbad alſo, That the Embaſſadors to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, (though from free Nations, and their Allies) ſhould have any place in the <foreign rend="italic">Orchestra</foreign>, becauſe he had taken notice there were ſome of them but Libertines in degree.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He diftinguiſhed likewife betwixt the Souldiers and the People: He afligned peculiar places to fuch as were married, though of the number of the Commons. To the young Gentry he appropriated a place by themſelves, and appoint ed the next to them to be kept for their Tutors. He made an Order that none of the inferior fort ſhould fit in the pit of the Theatre in their black Gowns, and forbad the Womens feeing fo much as the Gladiators promiscuoufly amongst the Men as they had formerly done) afſigning the upper Gallery for their place, only the Veſtal Virgins were by peculiar favour permitted to fit in the Theatre apart by themſelves, juſt over againft the Præ- tors Tribunal.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      But at the Spectacle of the Wreftlers he was fo far from admitting any Woman at all, that in the Pontifical Plays the people defiring to fee a couple of them, he put them off till the next morning, and declared, <q rend="italic">He would have no Woman appear in the Theatre the next day, before eleven of the Clock.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="45">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      45. For the moſt part he beheld the Circean Games himself, out of the Chambers of his friends, or fuch perfons as he had infranchiſed; fometimes he fat upon the Bed (upon which the Images of the Gods were plac'd) with his Wife and Children. He would be abſent from theſe Spectacles ſeveral hours, fometimes whole days together, but never without an Apology to the people, and till he had recommended fome other perfon, to preſide in his place. When he was preſent, he was alwayes intent, not doing any thing elſe, either to avoid the reproaches which were caft upon his Father by the people, for reading and anſwering of Letters and Petitions, during the time of thoſe ſolemnities, or out of a real delight he took in them, which he ingenuoufly profeft without any diffimulation;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For which reaſon at the Prizes and Plays of other people he gave Coronets and rewards of great value; and at all the <placeName rend="italic">Grecian</placeName> Exerciſes he ever was at, he beſtowed ſome honour or other upon the Actors according to their deferts. But of all his recreations, he was moft affected with the Pugiles or engagements at fifty-cuffs; eſpecially if they fought after the Mode of the <placeName rend="italic">Latines</placeName>: not fuch as were Champions by profeſſion ſo much (which he uſed notwithstanding to match against the <placeName rend="italic">Greeks</placeName>) as the robuſt and doggeder fort of the Citizens when they fell together by the Ears among themſelves in the ſtrects, and belaboured one another without confideration or art.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      In ſhort he had a particular regard to all perſons relating any way to thoſe publick ſpectacles and ſhows. He continued and enlarged the Priviledges of his Wrestlers; He would not fuffer the Gladiators to fight, till diſmiſſion was promis'd to the Conqueror. The Coercive power which the Magiſtrates had exercis'd in all places and ages over the Players by virtue of an old Law, he reſtrain'd, and would not permit them to exerciſe it but upon the Stage only, and that during the time of the Plays.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Nevertheless he was a fevere exacter of order amongſt his Champions, and ſo juſt a reprehender of Licentiouſneſs amongſt his Stage-players, that having certain information that <persName rend="italic">Stephano</persName> a Comedian was attended by a Woman, with her hair cut, and in the habit of a Boy, he ordered him to be whipt through the three Theatres, and baniſh'd him when they had done. Upon the complaint of the Prætor against <persName rend="italic">Hylas</persName> a Mimick or Buffon, he cauſed him to be whipt in his own Court-yard, and that the Gates ſhould not be ſhut against any that had a mind to be a ſpectator of his Correction. <persName rend="italic">Pylades</persName> alſo he baniſh'd out of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> both, becauſe he had pointed his fing er at an Auditor which had hiſt him, and by that means expoſed him to the People.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="46">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      46. Having by this manner provided for the Policy, and Regiment of the City, he repeopled <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> (which had been much exhaufted by the Civil wars) with eight and twenty Colonies which he brought thither, and planted, and embelliſhing them with ſeveral magnificent Structures, and publick Revenues he equall'd them in ſome fort with the City of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> in priviledges &amp; eſteem, by inventing new kind of fuffrages, which the Decuriones or Aldermen of Colonies, were to take in their ſeveral Liberties, and to ſend up fealed to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> against the day of Election of the Magiftrates there. And that there might be no defect of perfons of honour in any part of his Dominions, he advanced all fuch into the order of Gentlemen, who at the publick folicitation of any Town whatfoever had deſired to be lifted into the number of the Cavalerie: To the Commons in his Viſitations through all the Regions of <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, if they made it appear to him they had Sons and Daughters, he ordered a thousand Sefterces a-piece, both to them and their Children.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="47">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      47. The most confiderable Provinces which were neither eafie nor fafe to be governed by Annual Magiftrates, he took upon himself; the reft he committed to Proconfuls by lot, ſometimes he changed them, but most commonly of what kind foever they were, he visited them himself. Some of the Confederate Cities which by their too much licentioufneſs were running headlong to deſtruction, he deprived of their libertie: others oppreft with their Debts, or fubverted by Earthquakes, he relieved, and repaired; and if they were able to alledge any ſervice they had done for the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he gave them the priviledges of the <placeName rend="italic">Latines</placeName>, or made them free of the City. There is ſcarce a Province belonging to the whole Empire, unless it be <placeName rend="italic">Africk</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, but he visited in perfon, into which having chaſed <persName rend="italic">Sextus Pompeius</persName>, and being defirous to have purfued him out of <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, and all things prepared in order to his Tranſportation, there aroſe fuch violent and continual Storms, as obſtructed it that time, and afterwards he had no occafion.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="48">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      48. The Kingdoms which he had conquered (excepting fome few) he either reſtored them to the fame Princes from whom he had taken them, or elfe beſtowed them upon ſome ſtrangers: Thoſe Kings which were in aſſociation with him, he joyned alſo in mutual obligations amongst themſelves, as being alwayes a moſt industrious promoter, and favourer of Amity; and one, that looking upon all of them as parts and members of the Empire, had an equal care and concernment for them all. He was wont alſo to appoint Governours to fuch Princes as were young, or any way diſtemper'd in their minds, till they came to a competency of Age, or intelligence; and many times had them brought up and inftructed amongſt his own Children.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="49">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      49. Out of his Military force, he diſtributed his Legions, and Auxiliaries by Provinces. He kept one Fleet at <placeName rend="italic">Misinam</placeName> for the ſecurity of the <placeName rend="italic">Tuskan Sea</placeName>, and another at <placeName rend="italic">Ravenna</placeName>, for defence of the <placeName rend="italic">A- driatick</placeName>: He had his Guards alſo, being a certain number of Souldiers ſelected for the ſafeguard of the City, and his Perſon: He having disbanded his <persName rend="italic">Calagurritans</persName>, which he conſtantly kept in Arms about him till he had overcome <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>, and his <persName rend="italic">Germans</persName> likewise, who had the Guard of his Body to the time that <persName rend="italic">Varius</persName> was defeated. Nevertheless he never fuffer'd more than three Cohorts at once in the City, and they without any intrenchments; the reft he usually difpofed upon the Frontiers both in Winter and Summer:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      And left his Soldiers after they ſhould be disbanded or diſcharged, might be excited to fedition by their age, or neceffity, he aſſigned to every one of them a preciſe allowance as a reward according to the ſeveral times and qualities of their ſervices; and that the proviſion for them might be eaſie and perpetual, he eſtabliſhed a Treasury for the Army, and impofed new Tributes for their maintenance:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      For his more ſpeedy advertiſement of occurrences in his Provinces, he first of all laid certain young men of his Army upon all great Roads, who being on foot, and at no great diſtance, ran to one another like fo many foot Poſts with the News. Afterwards he fet up a fort of flying Chariots, as judging them more Commodious in this refpect, becauſe befides that the Expedition, and arrival of Letters was greater this way, he had the advantage alſo of interrogating, and diſcourfing more particularly with the Meſſengers, if occaſion required.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="50">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      50. In his Patents, Letters, Writs, and all his diſpatches, he made uſe at firſt of a Seal with the impreflion of a Sphinx, afterwards he had the image of <persName rend="italic">Alexander the Great</persName>, and laſt of his own ingraven by the hand of <persName rend="italic">Diafcorides</persName>, with which his fucceſſors figned alfo for a conſiderable time: he was ſo punctual in the dating of his Letters, that he fet down uſually the very minute not of the day only, but the night wherein they were figned.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="51">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      51. Of his Clemency and Moderation, there are many inſtances: He not only pardon'd and indemnifi'd ſeveral of his Adverſaries, but fuffer'd them to continue in the principal offices of the City: And though <persName rend="italic">Junius Novatus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Caffius Patavinus</persName> (perfons of the meaner fort of people) had greatly offended him; the firſt having publiſh'd a moſt defamatory Epiſtle against him in the name of young <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>, and the other declar'd boldly at a publick entertainment, <q rend="italic">That he neither wanted will, nor courage to destroy him</q>; he contented himſelfto lay a moderate Fine upon the one, and a gentle Baniſhment upon the other:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      On a particular day of hearings <persName rend="italic">Emilie Ælianus</persName> of <placeName rend="italic">Corduba</placeName> being accus'd amongst other things, of ſpeaking irreverently of <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName>, He in a pretended fury turn'd to the informer, and faid, <q rend="italic">I wish you could prove it with all my heart, if you did, I would make <persName rend="italic">Elianus</persName> know I have a tongue as well as he, and could say twice as much of him</q>, and reſenting it no further, he never inquired into it afterwards.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> alſo aggravating the faid infolence in a Letter to him, and preffing him with more violence to the vindication of his honour, he return'd him this anſwer, <q rend="italic">Do not (my <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>) indulge the paſſion of your years, too much in this Cafe, nor be too much concern'd; if there be a man found which speaks ill of me, we are happy enough if our Condition be ſuch that he can do us no harm.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="52">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      52. Heunderstood very well that Temples had been confecrated even to Proconfuls, yet in none of his Provinces could he be brought to accept that honour, unless in the Common Name of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> and himself, and in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> he abſolutely refuſed it. Nay his modeſty went yet farther, and thoſe Statues of Silver which had been fet up for him, he cauſed to be melted down, and fold, and Tables of Gold bought with the Money, and dedicated to <persName rend="italic">Apollo Palatinus</persName>. When the people not only offer'd, but preſs'd and importuned him to take the Dictatorſhip upon him, he fell down upon his knees, caft his Gown from his ſhoulders, uncover'd his Breaft, and with all poſſible deprecation, deſired to be excused.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="53">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      53. He had alwayes ſo great an averſion to the Title of Lord, that he look'd upon it as a reproach. As he was at a Comedy one day, theſe words were pronounc'd; <q rend="italic">O most Gentle and most Gracious Lord!</q> which the people taking with an allufion as applicable to him applauded exceedingly: but he rebuk'd their flatteries forthwith by the ſigns of his hand and forehead, and the next day reproved them more particularly in a fevere Edict exhibited on purpoſe, forbidding himself to be called Dominus either in jeſt or earneſt, even by his own Children and Grandchildren, amongſt whomalſo he prohibited thoſe appellations.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      So great was his modeſty and goodneſs to his Subjects, that he very rarely entred, or departed from any City or Town, but in the Evening or in the night, on purpoſe to excuſe their formalities and attendance. In his Confulſhip he went commonly on foot, out of his Confulſhip, in a cloſe Chair or Sedan. He was ſo affable, that he admitted the falutations of the meanest of the people, and received their Petitions with fuch alacrity and pleafantneſs, that 'tis reported he merrily reprehended one that preſented him his requeſt ſomething timoroufly, by faying, <q rend="italic">That he had delivered his Petition to him, as he had been presenting something to an Elephant.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      On the dayes the Senate fate, he never faluted any of them but in the Senate, and then, as they were fitting he ſpake to them all by their ſeveral Names without the aſſiſtance of a Prompter, and at his departure he took his leave in the ſame order. He performed mutual offices of Friendſhip and Kindneſs with ſeveral perfons, aſſiſting at all their Solemnities till he began to be in years, and was unable to endure the incommodities of a Crowd, as he found by experience upon one of the Sponfal dayes. <persName rend="italic">Gallus Terrinius</persName> a Senator, being taken ſuddainly blind, and refolving to ſtarve himself to death becauſe he had no hopes of recovery, though his familiarity with him was but ſmall, yet he went to him himself, and by the kindness and efficacy of his perſwafions diverted him from thoſe thoughts.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="54">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      54. As he was ſpeaking one day in the Senate, he was interrupted by one who told him, <q rend="italic">He understood him not</q>, and another that said <q rend="italic">He would contradict him if he were his Equal.</q> As he was going out of the Council being offended with their tedious and impertinent altercations, he was ſtayed by ſome perſons who told him; <q rend="italic">That the Senators ought to have their liberty whilst they were Speaking of the Common Wealth.</q> <persName rend="italic">Antiftius Labeo</persName>, at an Election (in which every Senator named his man) having elected <persName rend="italic">M. Lepidus</persName> an Enemy to <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> of old, and at that time in banishment, being ask'd by <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> <q rend="italic">If he could find no better a man than he?</q> he replyed; <q rend="italic">every man had hioown judgment</q>, nor was this boldneſs, and contumacy revenged upon any of them.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="55">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      55. He was so much unconcern'd with Libels and Lampons which were thrown about the Court, and took fo little care to refute them, that he did not fo much as enquire into the Authors; only this order he made, That for the future, Cognizance fhould be taken of all fuch as under pretended names, exhibited Libels or Verſes to the infamie and difparagement of any man; and having been himfelf provok'd by the ſawcy and reflexive jeſts of fome, he anſwer'd them by publiſhing a Remonſtrance to the contrary; nevertheless when the Senate were about reſtraining the great liberty which was taken by Perſons in their Wills, he oppofed himself against it.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="56">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      56. As often as he was preſent at any aſſembly for the Election of Magiſtrates, he went about through his Tribes with the Candidates in his Company, recommending them to their choiſe in the uſual manner. He gave his own fuffrage likewife in his Tribes, as he had been one of the people. When he appeared as a Witneſs in any Judicial Court, he fuffer'd Himſelf not only to be interrogated, but croft and contradicted in his depoſitions:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was ſo great an E- nemy to violence, that he choſe rather to build his Hall of Justice too narrow and ſtrait, than to difpoſſeſs his refractory Neighbours of their Proprieties. He never recommended his own Sons to the people, but with this condition; <q rend="italic">If they shall deserve.</q> When they were Children, and in their Robes border'd with Purple, coming into a Play, the whole houſe roſe up, and clapt their hands in demonftration of their refpect, but <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> took it ſo ill, he complained of it as an offence. How great and potent foever his Favourites were in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, he would not allow them more priviledge than the reft, nor by any means exempt them from the Judiciary Laws.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Afprenas Nonius</persName>, his intimate Friend being accuſed for poyſoning a Man, by <persName rend="italic">Caffius Severus</persName>, and to make his defence, <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> confulted the Senate how he was to comport himself in the Cafe; <q rend="italic">For</q> faid he, <q rend="italic">if I appear for him, I shall perhaps wrest a Malefaltor out of the hands of the Law, if I do not, I maybe thought to have abandon'd my Friend, and Condemn'd him before his Judges.</q> Upon the which he plac'd himself by advice of them all, in the lower Seats, where he fat ſtill for ſeveral hours filently, without ſo much as one word in his Commendation, though it was uſual in fuch Cafes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He appeared alfo as an Advocate for his Clients, amongst the reſt he defended one of his old Souldiers in an action of the Cafe brought against him. Of all the Criminals and accufed perfons in his time, he reſfcued but one, whoſe name was <persName rend="italic">Caftricius</persName>, by whoſe means he had diſcover'd the Conſpiracy of <persName rend="italic">Murena</persName>, nor did he preſerve him by any other way, than by his entreaties, with which he ſo mollified the heart of his Aс- cufer in the preſence of the Judges, that he withdrew his Proceſs, and deſiſted.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="57">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      57. How grateful, and Amiable theſe qualities made him to the people, it is no hard matter to imagine. I omit the honours decreed him by the Senate, as things which may be ſuppoſed the effects either of force, or flattery; it is ſufficient to ſay, that the Knights and Gentlemen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, of their own proper motions, and by common confent, did annually Celebrate his Birth, with two whole dayes folemnity: And all the Orders of the City beſides, caft little pieces of Money into <persName rend="italic">Curtius</persName> his Lake, paying their Vows thereby for the profperity of <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName>. On the Calends of January alſo, (though he was abſent himself) they offered their New-years-gifts to him in the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, with which moneys he bought his moſt ſtately Images of the Gods, and dedicated them in every quarter of the Town, as particularly the Statues of <persName rend="italic">Apollo Sandaliarius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Tragœdus</persName>, and others,
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His Palace on Mount <placeName rend="italic">Palatine</placeName> being burnt to the ground, the Souldiers, the Lawyers, the Tribes, and all forts of people whatever, contributed perſonally and voluntarily according to their abilities, to the building it again: But <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> would not make use of half that they brought in. When he return'd out of any Province, he was receiv'd not only with acclamations and good wiſhes, but with Mulick and Songs; and one thing more was conftantly obſerv'd, there was never any Execution on the day he entred into <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="58">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      58. By an univerfal and unexpected concurrence of all people, he had the Title given him of Father of his Countrey. The Commons gave it him firſt in an Embaſlie to <placeName rend="italic">Antium</placeName>, but having refus'd it there, the multitude got together in great numbers, with Crowns of Laurel upon their heads, and faluted him with it again in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> as he was going into the Theatre; after this the Senate did the fame in their Court, not by decree, or acclamation, but by the mouth of <persName rend="italic">Valerius Meſſala</persName>, who was commanded in the name of the whole Senate, to deliver himself to <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> in theſe words:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">The Senate by unanimous confent, and the concurrence of the People of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, falutes you (<persName rend="italic">Cæfar Auguſtus</persName>) with the Title of PATER PATRIÆ, wishing all fort of felicity both to you and your Family, and in doing so, they wish perpetual felicity to the Commonwealth.</q> To which he replyed, with tears in his eyes, in theſe words, (for I have fet down both <persName rend="italic">Meffala's</persName> meſſage, and his anſwer in terminis) <q rend="italic">Gentlemen I am now master of my wishes what remains for me to implore of the Gods, but that I may continue in your affection and good will to the end of my dayes?</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="59">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      59. As a further inſtance of their tenderneſs to his Perſon, by a voluntary contribution they erected a Statue of Braſs, and plac'd it by the Image of <persName rend="italic">Afculapius</persName>, in honour to <persName rend="italic">Antonius Mufa</persName> a Phyſician, by whole means he had recover'd of a moſt dangerous fit of fickneſs. Some Citizens there were who left it asa charge upon their Heirs in their Wills, that they ſhould carry Victims into the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, and Sacrifice them there, with a writing before them, declaring thoſe Vows to be perform'd in gratitude to the Gods, for having gracioufly permitted them to leave <persName rend="italic">Cæfar Auguſtus</persName> behind them. Some Cities in <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName> began their years on the day he came firſt amongst them: But most of the Provinces, beſides Altars and Temples erected to his memory, almoſt in every Town inftituted Games and Playes, which they celebrated every five years to his honour.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="60">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      60. The Kings his Friends and Confederates, every one in his own Kingdom, built a City and called it <placeName rend="italic">Cafaria</placeName>; besides which, by common confent, and at the common charge, they agreed to finiſh the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Olympicus</persName>, begun of old at <placeName rend="italic">Athens</placeName>, and to dedicate it to his Genius. Nay fo great was their Reverence for him, that they left their Kingdoms many times to do him honour, and attended him as Clients in their long Robes, without any of their Enſigns of Regality, not only in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, but in his Viſitations thorow his Provinces.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="61">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      61. Having repreſented him in his Magiſtracies, and publick Adminiſtrations both in Peace and War, I shall now relate his more familiar and private Converſation, his manners, conduct and fortune at home, from his minority to his death.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He loft his Mother in his firſt Confulſhip; his Siſter <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName> in the 54. year of his age; and having perform'd to them all the good offices of a Son, and Brother, whilft they were living, he did them all poflible honours when they were dead.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="62">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      62. When he was but a Youth he was contracted to the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Servilius Ifauricus</persName>, afterwards the firſt differences being compos'd betwixt him and <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>, both Armies preſſing them to an Union by fome nearer Alliance, he took <persName rend="italic">Claudia</persName> (the Daughter-in-law of <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>, which his Wife <persName rend="italic">Fulvia</persName> had had formerly by <persName rend="italic">P. Clodins</persName>) to his Wife, though he was ſcarce Marriageable at that time; but new controverfies ariſing betwixt him and his Mother-in-law <persName rend="italic">Fulvia</persName>, he fent home her Daughter untouch'd and a Virgin as ſhe came:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Then he married <persName rend="italic">Scribonia</persName>, the Widdow of two perſons both of them of Confular dignity, and by one of them a Mother; but being tired out (as he writes himself) with the perverſeneſs of her humour, he turn'd her away, and being enamoured of <persName rend="italic">Livia Drufilla</persName>, the Wife of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius Nero</persName>, then with child, he took her from him by force, married her, and loved her entirely to the laſt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="63">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      63. By <persName rend="italic">Scribonia</persName> he had <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>, by <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> nothing, though he did earnestly defire it; true it is, ſhe was once with child, but miſcarried. He married his Daughter <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> firſt to <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName> the Son of his Sifter <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, when he was ſcarce got out of his Child-hood. When he died, he married her again to <persName rend="italic">M. Agrippa</persName>, by the conſent of his Siſter, with whom he had prevailed to give him her Son-in-law, for <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> was at that time married to one of the <persName rend="italic">Marcella</persName> Daughter to <persName rend="italic">Octavia</persName>, and had children by her.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He being dead alſo, he was a long time finding out a new Husband for his Daughter, amongſt all the Knights and Gentlemen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>; at laſt having pitch'd upon <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> his Wifes Son, he forc'd him to leave his old Wife (though he had had feveral children by her, and ſhe was then with child.) <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName> writes, That <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> promis'd his Daughter <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> first to his Son <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>, next to <persName rend="italic">Cotis</persName> King of the <placeName rend="italic">Getæ</placeName>, at which time he also was in Treaty for the Kings Daughter.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="64">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      64. By <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> he had three Grand-Sons, <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>, and two Grand-Daughters, <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>: <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> he married to <persName rend="italic">L. Paulus</persName> the Cenfors Son, and <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName> to <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> his Sifters Grand-fon. Having bought them of their Father <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>, he adopted <persName rend="italic">Cains</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> into his own Family, and (though as then they were but young) he imploy'd them in pub-lick affairs, deſigned them Confuls, and gave them the Command of Provinces and Armies.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His daughter and her Children he brought up with that ſeverity, they were taught to Spin, and forbidden either to ſpeak or do any thing but in publick, and what might be afterwards recorded in their memories. He prohibited all Strangers from having acceſs to them alſo, whereupon he writ a Letter to <persName rend="italic">L. Tucinius</persName>, a comely young Gentleman, to this purpoſe, <q rend="italic">That he had not done handſomely in going to <placeName rend="italic">Bayas</placeName> to give his daughter a visit.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He was his Grandſons Tutor himself, and taught them not only to fwim, but all the Rudiments of Learning; but his greateſt endeavour was to make them write his Character, and imitate his hand. He never eat but his Grandchildren were fitting at the lower end of the Bed; nor took a journey, but he had them either before him in a Chariot, or about him on Horſe-back:
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="65">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      65. But though he promis'd himself much happineſs from his Iſſue, and the gravity of their Education, his fortune deceiv'd him in all; For his Daughter <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>, and her Daughter, (having abandon'd themſelves to all forts of infamy and wickedness) he was conftrain'd to baniſh; in eighteen months time he loft <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> dying in <placeName rend="italic">Lycia</placeName>, <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> at <placeName rend="italic">Marfelles</placeName>: After which he adopted <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>, his third Grand-ſon, and <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, his Wives Son, in a Publick Aſſembly of the people, by an Act of the Curie: But <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> proving of a fordid and furious diſpoſition, he turned him off again in a short time, and confin'd him to <placeName rend="italic">Surrentum</placeName>;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      taking the deaths of his Grandchildren with much more patience, than their debaucheries. The misfortunes of <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName> he endur'd with fome moderation; but his Daughters diſhonour went ſo near his heart, he could not forbear complaining of it to the Senate, though he were out of Town, in a Letter, which was read publickly by the Quastor or Chancellour. In this melancholy, he not only retir'd himself a long time from all converſation, but he had thoughts alſo ſometimes of putting her to death; and underſtanding that <persName rend="italic">Phœbe</persName> (one of his Daughters Confidents) had hang'd her felf, he proteſted openly, <q rend="italic">That he had rather have been <persName rend="italic">Phœbe</persName>'s Father, than <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>'s.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Having baniſh'd her, he forbad her the uſe of Wine, and all forts of delicacy whatsoever, either in diet or cloths: He permitted no perſon of what condition foever to come near her, without his knowledge both of their age, ſtature, complexion, and the very private marks or fcars of their bodies. At length, after he had kept her five years confin'd in an Iſland, he removed her into the Continent, where ſhe was treated with ſomewhat leſs ſeverity than before; but he could never be perfwaded to bring her back to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, as often and as carneſtly as the people interceded, he ſtopping their mouths with this imprecation, <q rend="italic">I wish you had all fuch Daughters and Wives.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The child which was born of his Grandchild <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> after she was condemned, he would neither own, nor bring up: <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> in ſtead of becoming more tractable, growing every day wilder than other, he tranſported him alfo into an Iſland, clapt Guards upon him, and by a Decree of the Senate prevail'd to have him kept there for ever. As often as any mention was made of him, or the <persName rend="italic">Juliaes</persName>, he was wont with a moft profound figh to break out into this expreffion, <q rend="italic">Would to God I had lived without a Wife, or dyed without Children!</q> Nor did he call them ordinarily by any other name, than his three biles or imposthumes.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="66">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      66. His friendſhip was not easily acquired, but when once contracted, it was conftant and firm : He was not only an honourer of the deferts and virtues of his friends, but a patient endurer of their infirmities, if they did not exceed. For of all the number of his friends, there is ſcarce any to be found ill treated by him, unless it be <persName rend="italic">Salvidienus Rufus</persName>, whom he had rais'd to the very Confulſhip, and <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Gallus</persName> to the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName>, and both of them from mean and inconſiderable fortunes:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Having diſcover'd <persName rend="italic">Rufus</persName> deſigning new troubles, and endeavouring once more to involve the Commonwealth, he deliver'd him up to the Senate, to be condemned; and the other for his contumacy and ingratitude, he turn'd out of his Province, and forbad him his Houſe; who being by the depoſitions of his accufers, and the decrees of the Senate, reduc'd into ſo defperate condition that he made himself away, <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> was ſo ſenſible of their zeal, that he gave them thanks for the piety of their indignation, but complain'd of his misfortune withal, <q rend="italic">That he was the only person, which had not liberty to be angry with his friends to what degree he pleas'd himself.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The rest of his Favourites, every one in his ſeveral order and degree, flourish'd in honour and riches to the end of their lives, yet not without fome fits and intermiſſions of his difpleaſure. He was much troubled at the want of patience in <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>, and the want of refervedneſs and taciturnity in <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName> <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> having forfaken all, and retir'd in great melancholy to <placeName rend="italic">Mitilyne</placeName>, upon a bare fufpicion that <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> look'd fowr upon him, and had more kindness for <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName>; and <persName rend="italic">Marcellus</persName> having discover'd the detection of <persName rend="italic">Murena</persName>'s Conſpiracy to his Wife <persName rend="italic">Terentia</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He required Teſtimonies of the affection and benevolence of his friends, not only whilſt they were living, but dead: For though he was not infected with Covetouſneſs at all, nor was ever known to make advantage of the Legacies of a friend, yet he had a ſtrict and moroſe regard alwayes to their laſt Wills and Testaments, conceiving much joy or difpleafure, according as they had expreſs'd their eſteem of him therein. If any Parents (which had Children alive) did at any time leave him a Legacy, or part of their Inheritance, he either return'd it immediately to their Children, or if they were too young to receive it, he kept it till they were of competent age, till the day they put on their virile Robes, or were married, and then deliver'd it with a confiderable addition of his own.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="67">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      67. As to his Domeſticks he was no leſs a ſevere than a gentle Maſter; he conferr'd very honourable imployments upon ſeveral of his Freemen, as upon <persName rend="italic">Licinius Enceladus</persName>, and others: <persName rend="italic">Cofmus</persName> a Servant of his having ſpoken very ill of him, he contented himself with having him clapt into Irons: He choſe rather to jest and make fport with the timidity of <persName rend="italic">Diomedes</persName> his Steward, than to impute it to any malicious deſign, when walking with him alone, a Wild-Boar coming fuddenly upon them, <persName rend="italic">Diomedes</persName> to ſecure himself, made bold to thruſt his Maſter to the Boar; a buſineſs of no ſmall danger and prefumption, yet being <foreign rend="italic">ex tempore</foreign> and undefigned, he imputed it to his fear, and turned all into mirth: But <persName rend="italic">Proculus</persName> (a freed perfon, and one of his Favourites) eſcap'd not fo well, for having been accus'd and convict of Adultery with Ladies of Quality, he caus'd him to be put to death.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Thallus</persName> (his Amanuensis) discovering one of his Letters for 500 denarii, had his legs broke by his order. The Governour and other attendants of his Son <persName rend="italic">Cains</persName>, having behaved themſelves infolently upon the report of his ficknefs and death, and committed many outrages in his Province, he caus'd them to have weights put about their necks, and to be thrown headlong into a River.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="68">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      68. In his youth he had variety of ſcandals which lay heavy upon him: <persName rend="italic">Sex. Pompeius</persName> upbraided him with effeminacy; <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName> affirm'd publickly, that he had never been in that favour, nor adopted by his Uncle, had he not been his proſtitute; And <persName rend="italic">Lucius</persName>, the Brother of <persName rend="italic">Marcus</persName>, ſpared not to divulge, that <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> having deflowr'd him firſt, he fold the remainder of his modeſty for three hundred thousand Seſterces, to <persName rend="italic">A. Hirtius</persName> in <placeName rend="italic">Spain</placeName>; and that he was wont to ſcorch his legs with hot nuts, to make the hair come the ſofter, and more delicate. The people alſo being aſſembled together at a Comedy or Stage-Play, not only interpreted to his diſhonour, but by unanimous confent applauded an expreſſion ſpoken of a Priest of (<persName rend="italic">Cibele</persName>) the Mother of the Gods, playing upon his Timberel, as if it had been ſpoken of him: The words were theſe, and most of them ambiguous; <q rend="italic">Videfne ut Cinœdus orbem digito temperet ? See how this Catamite governs the Orb with one finger.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="69">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      69. That he was given to Adultery, is a thing fo clear, his very friends could not deny; all they could do was to mollifie and excuſe it, by pretending that what he did was not out of Luft, but for certan reaſons of State, his deſign being in infinuating with the Wives, to discover the plots and practices of their Husbands. <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName> (befides his precipitate marriage with <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>) reproach'd him for having taken the Wife of a perfon which had been Conful, out of the Dining-room before his face, and carrying her into his Bed-Chamber, from whence after ſome time he brought her back again to the Banquet, with her ears all red, and her hair in disorder. For having put away <persName rend="italic">Scribonia</persName>, becauſe ſhe reſented the authority and reputation of one of his Concubines too much. For having imploy'd his friends to make bargains for him, to enquire him out Virgins, and Matrons, who were to be be ſtript, and expos'd naked to their view, as if <persName rend="italic">Thoranius</persName> had fold them, who made it his Trade.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Moreover, before he had declar'd himself his enemy, he writ to him merrily and familiarly in this manner: <q rend="italic">What is it hath alter'd you? is it that I lye with a Queen? she is my Wife, and that can be no news, for I have been married this nine years: Let me ask you one Question Do you lye with no body but <persName rend="italic">Drufilla</persName>? May you be happy as certainly when you have read this Letter, as you have. kiss d <persName rend="italic">Tertulla</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Terentilla</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Rufilla</persName>, or <persName rend="italic">Salvia Titiſcenia</persName>, or all of them; for what matter where, or who is your Mistress?</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="70">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      70. There was a ſtory alſo of a Supper he made privately for twelve of his friends, which was called the Supper of the Twelve Gods; in which the perfons invited appear'd in the habits of Gods and Goddeſſes, himself reprefenting <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName>: And with this he is charg'd not only by the Epiftles of <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>, in which the very names of the Gueſts are moſt invectively enumerated, but by theſe Verſes alſo, better known than their Author.
      <q rend="italic">Cum primum iftorum conduxit menſa choragum,
      Sexque dros vidit Mallia, Sexque deas:
      Impia dum Phœbi Cefar mendacia ludit,
      Dum nova divorum cœnat adulteria:
      Omnia fe à terris tunc Numina declinarunt,
      Fugit &amp; auratos Jupiter ipfe Thronos.</q>
      <q rend="italic">When first the Habits'gainst this feast were hired,
      And Mallia faw twice told fix Deities,
      Whilft Cæfar to Apollo's Part afpir'd
      Andto Re-act their old Adulteries:
      The Gods deteſting ſuch profane deſignes
      Forfook the Earth, and Jove the Gilded Shrines.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The noiſe of this Supper was much augmented by an accidental ſcarcity of proviſions in the City at that time, in ſo much that the next morning it was cryed publickly up and down the Streets, That the Gods had devour'd all the Corn, That <persName rend="italic">Cæfar</persName> was turn'd <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName> indeed, but it was <persName rend="italic">Apollo Tortor</persName>, by which Title he was then worſhip'd in a certain place of the City. He was famous alſo for his immoderate defire of rich houſhold-stuff, <placeName rend="italic">Corinthian</placeName> Veſſels, and being immoderately given to play: and in the time of his proſcription, this farcaſine was writ under his Statue,
      <q rend="italic">Pater Argentarius, ego Corinthiarius,</q>
      <q rend="italic">To deal in money was my Fathers Fate,
      And mine as much in rich Corinthian Plate.</q>
      Because it is ſuppoſed ſeveral perſons were foiſted into the number of the profcrib'd, for their Plate only. Afterwards during the Wars in <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName> this Epigram was made of him, and diſpers'd,
      <q rend="italic">Poftquam bis claſſe victus naves perdidit,
      Aliquando ut vincat, ludit affiduè aleam.</q>
      <q rend="italic">After his Fleet at Sea, twice loft had been,
      He fell to play, that he might sometimes win.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="71">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      71. But theſe Crimes, or Afperfions (as you pleaſe) he cafily refuted, The ſcandal of Proftitution, by the continued chastity of his life; The malitious flander of coveting rich houſhold-ſtuff, by his comportment at the taking of <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>, where of all the Queens furniture, he detained only one Porcelan Cup, and melted down all the Golden Veſſels, though never ſo uſeful. To Women indeed he was fomething addicted, and afterwards as is reported, to deflowring of Virgins, to which humour his Wife was ſo indulgent, ſhe fought him oût Maids her felf where ever she could find them. The report of his playing at dice, concerned him not at all, he continued that cuſtome till he was an old man, playing openly, and fairly, for his recreation, and no otherwise, not only in <foreign rend="italic">December</foreign>, but upon other holy days, and working days as he pleaſed.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      This appears by a letter under his own hand. <q rend="italic">My <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, (Says he) I Supp'd amongst the persons you wot off, to which <persName rend="italic">Vinicius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Silvius</persName> the Father, added themselves; Betwixt the Courses we play'd, like old Gameſters both yesterday and to slay. The Dice being thrown, as every man threw the chances Canis,or Senio, he deposited as many deniers as there were fpots, all which he that threw Venus carry'd away.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      And in another he writes; <q rend="italic">My dear <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, we have past the Feast of <persName rend="italic">Minerva</persName>, with pleaſure enough, We play'd at Dice every day to some tune, Your Brother kept a mighty ſtir, and was very obstreperous, but at last he came off pretty well, having recovered himself strangely, and beyond expectation; Iloft 20000 Sefterces out of my Purse, but my liberality augmented it, as it usually does: had I not remitted what was lost to me, and kept what I gave away, I had been winner above 50000. But 'tis better as it is, For my bounty will exalt me to the Heavens themselves.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      And in a Letter to his Daughter thus, <q rend="italic">I have fent you two hundred and fifty Deniers, the ſame ſum I have given to the rest of my guests, That they may play during the Collation at Dice, or any other game as they please.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="72">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      72. The rest of his life was very continent, and virtuous, without the leaft fufpicion of any wickedneſs at all. His firſt habitation was near the <placeName rend="italic">Forum Romanum</placeName> above the Anulary stairs, in a houſe which formerly belonged to <persName rend="italic">Calvus</persName> the Orator. Afterwards he lay indeed in the <placeName rend="italic">Palatium</placeName>, but it was in a little houſe of <persName rend="italic">Hortenfius</persName> his, confiderable neither in its capacity nor furniture; the Galleries being very ſhort, the Pillars of a ſoft <placeName rend="italic">Albane</placeName> stone, and the Rooms of State quite without any Marble, or extraordinary pavement: For forty years together and more, he lay in one Chamber both Winter and Summer, though he found the air of the City did not agree with him in the Winter, yet he continued in the City all the Winter.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      When he had any thing to do in private, and no mind to be interrupted, he retired to a private place a top on his houfe (which he called <placeName rend="italic">Syracuse</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Technophyon</placeName>,) or elfe to fome of the Houses of his Liberty a little way out of Town. But if he was ſick, he lay conſtantly in the house of <persName rend="italic">Macenas</persName>. Of all his houfes of pleafure, he had moſt inclination to thoſe which ſtood upon the Sea, as in the Ifles of <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, or elſe the Towns near <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, as <placeName rend="italic">Lanuvium</placeName>, <placeName rend="italic">Praneſte</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Tibur</placeName>, when he adminiſtred juſtice very often in the Portico of the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Hercules</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Large and Magnificent Palaces he affected not at all. That which his Grand-child <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> had built at a prodigious expence, he pull'd down to the ground. His own were but moderate, and not fo much beautified with Statues or Pictures, as accommodated with Cloiſters and Groves, and fometimes with antiquities, and rarities, as the vaſt members of certain wild Beaſts and Fishes found in the ifles of <placeName rend="italic">Capra</placeName>, which were of fo exceeding a dimenſion, they are reported to be the bones of Gyants, and the arms of the old Horoes in antient times.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="73">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      73. His parfimony in the goods and furniture of his houſe is evident at this day by the Beds and Tables he left behind him, which for the moſt part are not rich enough for a private perſon of any virtue or curioſity. His own bed is reported to be low and mean, and but indifferently furnished. His cloaths were commonly home-ſpun, and made either by his Wife, his Daughter or Grand-daughter. His Robes were of an indifferent fize, neither too fcanty nor large, and the ſtuds neither too broad, nor too narrow. His ſhooes were ſomething higher than ordinary, that he might appear taller than he was. In ſhort his cloths and his shoes both lay alwaies ready in his Chamber, for him to put on upon any fudden and unexpected occafion.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="74">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      74. He treated very often, always with fet feafts, to which none were invited but perfons of Eminence either for their virtue or quality. <persName rend="italic">Valerius Meſſala</persName> reports that never any of his Libertines were admitted to his Table, but <persName rend="italic">Mena</persName> only, and that after he had given him his freedom for betraying <persName rend="italic">Sextus Pompeius</persName> his Fleet. Yet he ſays himself he invited a perſon in whoſe house he had lain formerly in the Country, who had been once of his Guards: He came to the Table himself ſometimes very late, and left it ſometimes as early; the Gueſts falling to many times before he came, and continuing at it after he was gone. His ordinary proviſion was but three diſhes commonly, upon extraordinary occafion he exceeded to fix: but the coſtlineſs of the diſhes recommended not the Feaſt, ſo much as the familiarity and pleaſantneſs of the Maſter. Being facctious himself, and a great lover of mirth, he would defire ſuch as he ſaw whiſper, to fpeak out, and let him participate of their converſe. He had always Players, and Buffons, or elſe Aftrologers, or fuch kind of people, out of the Circus, who fat at his Table, and many times Pedants and Paradoxical Philofophers, to make him ſport.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="75">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      75. His Feſtivals and Solemn days he celebrated moſt commonly with great profuſeneſs, but ſometimes with mirth only. At the <foreign rend="italic">Saturnalia</foreign>, and when elſe he pleas'd, he diſtributed gifts amongſt the people, fometimes Apparel, Gold, or Silver, otherwhiles Money of all impreſſions, as the Coins of antient Kings, and foreign pieces; at other times nothing but hair-Cloath, Sponges, Oven-poles, Pincers, and fuch kind of Trifles, with obſcure and ambiguous infcriptions. He took delight alſo in making a kind of a Lottery (at his Entertainments) of ſeveral things of different value, and to fell Pictures by the backſide, that ſo by the uncertainty of their fortune, he might make himſelf merry at the felicity or disappointment of the buyer; and that every one might have his part either of good luck or bad, he order'd the Lottery to be carried from one Bed to another, and every body to take his fortune,
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="76">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      76. I must not forget his Diet, which was ufually but ſmall, and very coarse: He loved Houfhold Bread, little Fiſhes, new Cheeſe, green Figgs, and eſpecially ſuch as bear twice a year; and fed betwixt meals, where and at what time foever his ſtomach required. In one of his Epiſtles he writes thus; <q rend="italic">Whilst we were in our Chariot, we eat Bread and Dates.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Again; <q rend="italic">In my Litter as I was paffing from the Court to myown house, I made bold with about an ounce of Bread, and a few Sharp Grapes.</q> And in another; <q rend="italic">The <persName rend="italic">few</persName> himself, my <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, keeps not the Sabbath ſo ſtrictly, as I have done this day, having eat only two mouthfulls of Bread in the Bath, and that at ſeven a clock at night, whilst they were preparing their Sweet Oyntments for me.</q> In this indifferency of Diet he fupp'd alone many times, before or after the Feast, at which he was preſent ſtill, though he eat nothing at the Table.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="77">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      77. He was naturally no great friend to Wine; if we may believe <persName rend="italic">Cornelins Nepos</persName>, he drank but three times at one Supper during the whole Leaguer before <placeName rend="italic">Modena</placeName>: in his greateſt exceedings he drank not above fix fextants; if he ventur'd farther, it was fure to come up again. He delighted moſt in the <placeName rend="italic">Rhatian</placeName> Wine, but feldom drank any of it in the day time. To quench his thirſt he took commonly a piece of bread foak'd in cold water, a piece of a Cucumber, the top of a Lettice, or elſe a freſh Pearmain.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="78">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      78. After dinner he took his repoſe for a while, in his Cloths and Shooes as he was, with his feet well cover'd, and his hand before his eyes. After Supper he withdrew into a little Cloſſet or Study, where he remain'd till he had finiſh'd the remainder of that days journal, or at least the greatest part of it, which ſometimes took him up a good part of the night. From thence he went to Bed, where at moſt he ſlept but ſeven hours, and that not continually, but with three or four interrupti ons;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      if he could not fleep again, as it happened ſometimes, he call'd for people to read by him, or entertain him with difcourſe till he fell into a ſlumber, which laſted perhaps till after break of day. He never lay awake in the dark, but he had one fitting by him, and was much diſcompos'd if he had not his fleep in the morning. If his affairs or devotions obliged him to wake fooner than ordinary, to avoid that inconvenience, he would re poſe himself in the next Chamber which belong'd to any of his Domefticks; and fometimes being ſleepy in earneſt, he would cauſe his Litter to be fet down, and take a nap in the ſtreets.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="79">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      79. He was of an excellent proportion, and continued handſome to the laft; but ſo negligent and incurious in his dress, that he made ufe of ſeveral Barbers at once in a huddle, having his Beard ſometimes clipt, ſometimes ſhav'd, and he either reading or writing all the time: Whilft he was either ſpeaking, or filent, he had fuch a quietneſs and ferenity in his countenance, that one of the great Lords of the <placeName rend="italic">Gauls</placeName> confess'd amongst his friends, that that alone had mollified and diverted him from a reſolution he had taken, to have thrown him down a precipice headlong, as he was pafling the <placeName rend="italic">Alpes</placeName>, being admitted to come near him upon pretence of private diſcourſe.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His eyes were clear and ſparkling, and he had a mind it ſhould be thought their vivacity had fomething divine in it, for he took much delight if in looking ſteadily upon any body, they put down their faces, as they would do at the brightness of the Son: But towards his latter dayes he ſaw but little with his left eye. His teeth were thin, ſmall, and rugged; his hair curled a little, and was fomewhat yellow; his eye-brows met upon his forehead; his ears ſmall, his noſe high and long, his complexion between white and brown; his ſtature was but ſmall, (yet <persName rend="italic">Julius Marathus</persName> his freed-man writes, that he was five foot and nine inches high) but let his height be what it will, he was fo well proportioned in all his limbs, that unless one ftood by him that was very tall, he could not be difcern'd to be low.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="80">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      80. It is reported he had freckles on his body, diſpoſed naturally upon his breaſt and his belly, into the figure, order and number of the Stars in the Celestial Bear; as alſo certain Calloſities upon him, proceeding from the itching of his body, or from the violent and frequent uſe of the Strigil (or Curry-comb) which appear'd in his skin in the ſnape of a Tetter. His hip, and his thigh, and his left leg were not fo well, but he halted ſometimes on that fide; but he recovered his ſtrength ágain, by a fomentation of Sand and Reeds. He found ſuch a weakness in the fore-finger of his right hand, that being crampt and contracted with cold, he could ſcarce make use of it to write, with the help of a Cramp-ring: He complain'd alfo of the Strangury, but the Gravel coming at length away with his Urine, he was eas'd of that torture.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="81">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      81. He had feveral, and thoſe very dangerous fits of fickness in his time, but eſpecially after his Conquests in <placeName rend="italic">Cantabria</placeName>, at which time his Liver being vitiated with defluxions, he was reduc'd into fo defperate a condition, that he was fore'd to enter into a doubtful and contrary courſe of Phyfick, to leave off the warm fomentations which he had uſed before, and (by the advice of <persName rend="italic">Antonius Musa</persName>) to betake himself to cold which method, how contrary foever to the practice of thoſe times, ſtopt his defluxion, and compleated the Cure.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was fubject alfo to certain annual, and periodical diſtempers, which afflicted him at conſtant ſeaſons: About his Birth-day he was taken always with a weakness; at the beginning of the Spring, with the Spleen; and with a stuffing cold, when the wind was in the South: by which means his body being weaken'd and ſhatter'd, he could ſcarce endure extremity either of heat or cold.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="82">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      82. To defend himself against the ſharpness of the Winter, he wore ordinarily a good thick Gown, four Coats, a Waftcoat, a Flannel Stomacher, with rollers about his legs and his thighs. In the Summer time he lay with his Chamber doors open, ſome times in a <placeName rend="italic">Peristylium</placeName>, or Grotto, with his Waterworks about him, and one ſtanding by on purpoſe to fan him. He could not endure ſo much as the Winter Sun, and never walk'd out when he was at home, but with a Bont-grace, or broad-brimm'd Hat hanging over his face. When he travell'd, he went generally in his Litter, in the night for the moſt part and that gently, and but ſmall journeys, as making it two dayes ſometimes to <placeName rend="italic">Praneſte</placeName> or <placeName rend="italic">Tibur</placeName>: Nevertheless when he could go any whi ther by Sea, he feldom or never went by Land;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      but if his infirmity was great, his care and regard of himself was not ſmall. Baths being not only improper, but hurtful for him, he refrain'd as much as poſſible; he was frequently anointed with ſweet Oyls, ſweated before the fire, and then waſh'd with warm water, or water heated in the Sun. When for the ſtrengthening of his Nerves he ufed either Sea-water, or the waters of <placeName rend="italic">Albula</placeName> heated, he fat upon a wooden chair, which he call'd by a Spanish word <foreign rend="italic">Dureta</foreign>, and contented himself only with ſtirring his hands and feet up and down the water by turns.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="83">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      83. As foon as his Civil Wars were over, he gave over the exerciſes of riding the great Horſe, or managing his Arms in the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martius</placeName>, and betook himself to Tennis, or Hand-ball, in their ſtead. After that, it was not long before he gave over all exerciſe, but taking the air in a Litter, walking and skipping a little' at the end of his Career, wrapt up in a Muffler, or linen Mantle. For the recreation of his mind, he would fish fometimes with an angle, ſometimes play at Dice, Cockal, or with Nuts amongst the moſt amiable and witty children he could find, eſpecially if they were Moors, or Syrians; but for fuch as were Dwarfs, or any way crooked or distorted, he look'd upon them as ominous, and the mockery of nature.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="84">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      84. From his minority he apply'd himself with great induſtry to the learning of Eloquence, and other Liberal Arts. During the War of <placeName rend="italic">Modena</placeName>, he is reported not to have paſs'd one day in the midst of his most important affairs, without reading, writing, and declaiming: After that Expedition, he never made a Speech either to the People, the Senate, or Souldiers, but what was premeditated, and precompos'd, though he wanted not the faculty of ſpeaking <foreign rend="italic">ex tempore</foreign>;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      and left his memory ſhould fail, and he ſpend too much time in getting them by heart, he read to them whatever he had to ſay: His private diſcourſes with his friends, nay even with <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> his wife, if about any ſerious matter, he put down in writing, left he ſhould ſpeak more or less than was convenient on a fudden. His accent was ſweet, and whatever he pronounc'd was with a very good grace, of which he was ſo curious, he kept a Maſter on purpoſe to teach him the management of his voice: But when he was troubled with a hoarſeneſs, or fore throat, the publick Cryer read his ſpeech to the people in his ſtead.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="85">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      85. He compos'd ſeveral things in Profe, upon ſeveral fubjects, of which he read fome in a meeting of his familiar friends, as it had been in an Auditory; amongst the reſt, his answer to <persName rend="italic">Brutus</persName> upon <persName rend="italic">Cato</persName>: Having read a good part of thoſe Volums himself, being old and weary, he gave them to <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> to recite the remainder. He writ alſo Certain Exhortations to Philosophy, and a ſhort History of his Life in thirteen Books, as far as his <placeName rend="italic">Cantabrian</placeName> War, and no farther.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Poetry he medled with but fuperficially; yet that he was not altogether ignorant in that alſo, appears by a Book written by him in Hexameter Verſe, whoſe Title is <placeName rend="italic">Sicilia</placeName>, and is yet extant; and another little Collection of Epigrams, which for the greatest part he compos'd in his Baths. Having begun a Tragedy with great ardour, and finding his ſtile not like to hold out at that rate, he expung'd what he had written already; and being ask'd by his friends what was become of <persName rend="italic">Ajax</persName>, (who was the ſubject of that Play) he reply'd, <q rend="italic">That <persName rend="italic">Ajax</persName> had made himself away with a Sponge.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="86">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      86. He obſerv'd always a very elegant and temperate way in his ſpeeches, ſhunning impertinence and inconcinnity in his fentences, and as he call'd it himself, the fœtor or noifomneſs of hard and obſolete words: his principal care being only to expreſs himself intelligibly and fuccinctly; and that he might not detain or confound the intention of his reader or hearer, he added Prepoſitions to his Verbs, and reiterated his Conjunctions many times, which being taken away do indeed contribute grace and ornament to a diſcourſe, but with some kind of obſcurity.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Thoſe which delighted in new words, and thoſe which affected old, being contemptible in both kinds, he equally deſpiſed. He derided ſeveral, and eſpecially his friend <persName rend="italic">Macenas</persName>, for his <foreign rend="italic">Murobrecheis Cincinnos</foreign>, or perfum'd Curles, as he calls them, perfecuting him continually for the affectation of his language, and imitating him fometimes to make himself ſport. <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> alſo had his reprehenfion for his obſcure and antiquated phrases, and <persName rend="italic">M. Antonius</persName> he eſteem'd as a mad man, for writing what men might admire, but hardly under- Stand. Afterwards drolling upon the irreſolute and indifcreet election of his ſtile, he adds theſe words;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <q rend="italic">And are you still to refolve whether <persName rend="italic">Cimber Annius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Veranius Flaccus</persName> are to be imitated by you, that so you may make use of the words which <persName rend="italic">Crifpus Saluftius</persName> selected out of <persName rend="italic">Cato's Origines</persName>? or rather the <placeName rend="italic">Afiatick</placeName> Orators, transferring their affectation and verbofity into our language and difcourse.</q> And in one of his Epiſtles, commending the parts and ingenie of his Grandchild <persName rend="italic">Agrippina</persName>, <q rend="italic">But be fure</q> (fayes he) <q rend="italic">you neither write nor Speak any thing that may be in a troublesome and ingrateful Stile.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="87">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      87. It is remarkable by letters under his own hand, that in his ordinary Converſation, he had particular ways of expreſſing himself, which he fre quently used, as when he would fignifie that fuch a man would never pay his debts, he would fay, he would pay them, <q rend="italic">ad Gracas Kalendas.</q> When he exhorted any one to be content, and acquiefce in his preſent condition, whatever it was, he cry'd <q rend="italic">Come let us be content with this <persName rend="italic">Cato</persName>.</q> To intimate the dexterity and expedition wherewith a thing was done, he would fay, <q rend="italic">It was done before Asparagus could be boyled.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was us'd alſo continually to put one word for another, as <foreign rend="italic">Baceolus</foreign> for <foreign rend="italic">Stultus</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Pul leiaceius</foreign> for <foreign rend="italic">Pullux</foreign>, for <foreign rend="italic">Ceritus</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Vacerrofus</foreign>, for <foreign rend="italic">male Se habere</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Vappide se habere</foreign>, for <foreign rend="italic">Languere</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Betizare</foreign>, which is commonly expreſt by <foreign rend="italic">Lachaniſſare</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Simus</foreign> alfo for <foreign rend="italic">Sumus</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Domos</foreign> in the Genitive Caſe ſingular, for <foreign rend="italic">Domus</foreign>. Nor did he ever use these two words otherwise, left it ſhould be interpreted by any one a fault rather than a cuſtome.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      One thing I find in his Manufcripts very often, that he parted not his words, and if one line was too short for a whole word, he brought not the redundant Letters to the next, but fet them down underneath in a kind of a Parenthesis.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="88">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      88. Orthography, that is the form and Method of writing which was taught by the Grammarians, he did not obſerve exactly, but ſeemed rather of their judgment who were of opinion, <q rend="italic">That they were to write as they spoke:</q> For as to the frequent tranſpofition, and omiffion, not only of Letters and Sylla bles, it is not his fault alone, but a common Error among men: Neither ſhould I have taken notice of it, had I not been aftoniſh'd at what is reported by fome people, That a Confuls Lieutenant for but failing in his Orthography, and writing <foreign rend="italic">ixi</foreign> for <foreign rend="italic">ipfi</foreign>, was look'd upon by him as an ignorant and illiterate fellow, and another put in his place. When he had a mind to write any thing privately and in Ciphers, his way was to put B. for A. C. for B. and fo forward thorough the whole Alphabet, till he came to Z. for which he put a double a a.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="89">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      89. Nor was he leſs ſtudious and delighted in the <placeName rend="italic">Grecian</placeName> learning, in which he arrived at no ſmall perfection by the induſtry of <persName rend="italic">Apollodorus</persName> of <placeName rend="italic">Pergamus</placeName>, whom he carried along with him from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Apollonia</placeName>, though he was but a youth, and <persName rend="italic">Apollodo- Yus</persName> an old man. Afterwards being repleat with humanity, and the various erudition of <persName rend="italic">Spharus</persName>, he entred into an intimate familiarity with <persName rend="italic">Arews</persName> the Philoſopher, and his two Sons <persName rend="italic">Dionyfius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Nicanor</persName>; though fo as he neither ſpake <foreign rend="italic">Greek</foreign> very readily, nor durſt venture to compoſe any thing in it. If occaſion required at any time, he writ down what he had a mind to in <foreign rend="italic">Latin</foreign>, and then gave it to another to convert into that language: As he was not unskilful in Poetry, fo he took great delight in the old way of Comedies, which he frequently exhibited in the publick Aſſemblies.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In all the Authorswhich he read in both languages, his principal obfervation was what precepts and Examples he might collect for the publick, or private inſtruction of his ſubjects and friends; when he thought any of them proper, he took them out word by word, and would fend them either to his Domesticks, the Governours of his Provinces, or Armies, or the Magiſtrates of the City, very commonly, as any of them wanted admoniſhment. Sometimes he went further, and read whole books to the Senate, and recommended them afterwards to his people by Proclamation, as the Orations of <persName rend="italic">Q. Metellus</persName>, <foreign rend="italic">de prole angenda</foreign>, and <persName rend="italic">Rutilius de modo adificiorum</persName>, in which, his deſign was to convince them that he was not the firſt that propos'd either of them, but that their Forefathers had the fame inclinations.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      To the Wits, and Virtuoſi of his time, he gave great encouragement, attending with great courtefie and patience at ſeveral of their Recitations, not only of Poetry, and Hiſtory, but of Orations and Dialogues. But if any thing were written of himself, (though in his praiſe) unleſs ſerioufly, and by a Maſter, he would be very much offended; and gave the Prætors in particular charge, that they ſhould not fuffer his Name to be made common in their ordinary Recitations.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="90">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      90. He is reported to have been full of Religious ſuperſtition and ſcruple; he was ſo pufillanimoufly afraid of Thunder and Lightning, that he carried a Seals-skin always about him to ſecure him: and having been frighted with that flaſh he eſcap'd fo narrowly upon the road, (as we have mentioned before) upon the leaft forefight or apprehenfion of any Tempeft extraordinary, he run immediately into a Cellar of Vault under ground for protection.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="91">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      91. He was a great obſerver of Dreams, whether his own, or other peoples, referring to himself: At the Battle of <placeName rend="italic">Philippi</placeName>, he refolv'd once not to go out of his Tent, by reaſon of an indiſpoſition upon him at that time: nevertheless being advertis'd of the Dream of one of his friends, he went forth, and (as it prov'd) very luckily; For his Camp being taken by the Enemy, they fell upon his Litter by accident, and imagining him in it, they run their Swords into it, and mangled it to pieces.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      times of the year he was troubled with them too, but they were neither ſo many, nor fo impertinent.. Being very frequently at a Temple in the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> which was dedicated to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter the Thunderer</persName>, he dreamt that <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName> made complaint to him, that his Worſhippers were taken away, and that he had anſwer'd him, <q rend="italic">That he had plac'd <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Tonans</persName> in that place as his Porter</q>, and afterwards caus'd Bells to be hung about the top of the houſe, that it might the more naturally reſemble a Porters-lodge. Inſtigated another time by a nocturnal apparition, he begg'd upon a certain day every year, ſome benevolence or other from the people, and would put forth his own hand to receive their fingle money.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="92">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      92. He took great notice of the flight or chattering of Birds, and look'd upon them as infallible preſages. If in the morning his Shooes were given him wrong, or the right foot Shooe was preſented to him for the left, he counted it ominous. If it rain'd or mizled as he was taking a journey either by Land or by Sea, he was pleas'd, and reckon'd it a sign of a ſpeedy and profperous return: But nothing affected him fo much as Prodigies. Obſerving a Date-tree to ſpring up betwixt the ſtones before his door, he tranſplanted it into the place where his Houſhold-gods ſtood, and took great care to have it grow there.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Being in the Itland <placeName rend="italic">Caprea</placeName>, he was ſo tranſported to fee an old Elm, whoſe branches hung down to the ground, and were almoſt dead, revive at his arrival, that he made an exchange with the Republick of <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>, and gave them <placeName rend="italic">Anaria</placeName> for that Iſland. Besides this, he held fome days for unfortunate; he would never begin a journey the next day after the <foreign rend="italic">Nundina</foreign>, nor undertake any buſineſs of conſequence upon the Nones of a month; for no other reaſon, (as he writ to <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>) but to avoid the unluckiness or ill omen of the name.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="93">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      93. As to the Religious Ceremonies of Foreign Countries, he had a great veneration for fuch as were antient and of authority, and as much contempt for the reſt; for having been initiated at <placeName rend="italic">Athens</placeName>, (in the mysteries of <persName rend="italic">Ceres</persName>) and fitting afterwards in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> upon his Tribunal, to hear ſome things argued relating to the Priviledges of the Priests of that Goddess, obſerving fecret and nice points to be ſtarted, he diſmiſs'd the Aſſembly, and heard the buſineſs diſcuſs'd before himself in private. But in his Voyage into <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName> he was not ſo precife, for he would not go out of his way, though but a little, to make a visit to the God <persName rend="italic">Apis</persName>; and commended his Son <persName rend="italic">Caius</persName> another time, for that he had paſs'd through <placeName rend="italic">Judea</placeName>, and not paid his devotions in the Temple at <placeName rend="italic">Ferufalem</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="94">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      94. And because we have proceeded thus far, it will not be impertinent if we add in this place fuch remarkable accidents as followed or preceded his Birth, and fuch as fell out upon the very day he came into the World, which were as fo many preſages of his future Grandeur, and felicity.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      At <placeName rend="italic">Velitris</placeName> part of the Town-wall having been beaten down by Lightning, it was anſwered by the Oracle, <q rend="italic">That a Citizen of that Town ſhould one day have the Empire of the whole World;</q> upon confidence of which Prophecie, the <persName rend="italic">Velitrines</persName> made War immediately upon the <persName rend="italic">Romans</persName>, and renew'd it ſeveral times afterwards, but with ſo much misfortune, they were almoſt deſtroy'd: At laſt they were convinc'd, (but well near too late) that it portended nothing but the Dominion of <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Julius Marathus</persName> reporteth, that a few months before <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> was born, there happen'd a Prodigy at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, by which the <persName rend="italic">Romans</persName> were publickly advertiſed, <q rend="italic">That nature was producing a King for the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>;</q> with which the Senate was ſo alarm'd, they made a Decree, <q rend="italic">That no Man-child ſhould be brought up that year.</q> But those who had their Wives big at that time, (that they might every one appropriate the hopes to himſelf) took fuch order that that Act was never recorded in the <foreign rend="italic">Ærarium</foreign>, or City Chamber.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      It is related alſo in the Books of <persName rend="italic">Afclepiades the Mendeſian</persName>, entituled <foreign rend="italic">Theologoumenon</foreign>, That <persName rend="italic">Atia</persName> the Mother of <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> being come at Midnight to the folemn ſervice of <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName>, and having plac'd her Litter in the Temple, ſhe fell afleep amongst the rest of the Ladies, when on a fudden a Serpent came crawling to her, and in a ſhort time went away again, without doing her any harm; wherewith ſhe awak'd, and purified her ſelf, as if she had lain with her Husband: But that which is moſt admirable is, that at the fame inſtant ſhe found a mark upon her body, in the figure of a Serpent, which ſhe could never get off; upon which ſcore ſhe never appear'd afterwards in any publick Bath. The fame Author affirms alſo, That <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> being born the tenth month after, he was generally reputed the Son of <persName rend="italic">Apollo</persName>. The faid <persName rend="italic">Atid</persName> dreamt alſo before she was brought to bed, that her Entrails were elevated to the Stars, and extended over the whole Circumference, both of the Heaven, and Earth. His Father <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> dreamt likewife, that a beam of the Sun came out of his Wives belly, when it aroſe in the morning.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      The day he was born, the Senate being aſſembled to deliberate about <persName rend="italic">Catilines</persName> Conſpiracy, and <persName rend="italic">Octavias</persName> coming in late by reaſon that his Wife was deliver'd, it is well known. <persName rend="italic">P. Nigidius</persName> being told the cauſe of his abſence, and inform'd himself of the hour of his birth, he cry'd out openly, <q rend="italic">That the Lord of the whole World was then born.</q> A while afterwards, <persName rend="italic">Octavius</persName> conducting an Army through <placeName rend="italic">Thrace</placeName>, and having the curiosity to confult the Priefts, (in the Grove confecrated to <persName rend="italic">Liber Pater</persName>) according to their barbarous Ceremonies, about the deſtiny of his Son, he receiv'd the fame anſwer again; for having ſprinkled their Wine upon the Altar, there brake forth ſuch a flame, as not only furmounted the top of the Temple, but feem'd to run up even to the Heaven it felf: A prodigy that never happen'd to any but <persName rend="italic">Alexander the Great</persName>, as he was Sacrificing once at the fame Altars.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
    <p>
      The next night he fancied he saw his Son, of a greater ſtatue and proportion than was uſual amongſt men, with a Thunderbolt, a Scepter, all the Ornaments of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, in a Chariot adorned with Laurel, drawn by twelve horſes of extraordinary whiteness, and a wreath of rayes about his head in the fashion of a Crown. <persName rend="italic">Caius Drufus</persName> writes, that his Nurſe having left him one night below in the Cradle, he was not to be found the next morning; and that after long fearch, ſhe found him at length upon a very high Tower, with his face towards the East.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
    <p>
      He ſcarce began to ſpeak, when being at a Countrey-houfe of his Fathers, and offended with the noiſe of the Frogs, he commanded them to be filent; and from that time, as it is reported, they never croak'd more. Another day as he was at Dinner in a Wood in the road to <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, about four miles from <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, an Eagle made a ſtoop on a sudden, and took the bread out of his hand; which having carried up almoſt as high as the Clouds, ſhe came down again gently by degrees, and moſt reverently reſtored it.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
    <p>
      After the dedication of the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, <persName rend="italic">Q. Catulus</persName> dream'd two nights together; The firſt night he imagined he faw ſeveral young Children of the beſt families in <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> playing about the Altar, and that <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> took one of them apart, and put the Signet of the Republick (which he had then in his hand) in-to his boſome; The next night he dream'd he faw the fame child in <persName rend="italic">Jupiters</persName> arms, and having commanded him to be taken away, he was rebuk'd by the faid God, and given to underſtand, that that child ſhould be brought up for the defence of the Common-wealth; and meeting with <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> next day, though he had never feen him before, he beheld him with admiration, and proteſted that nothing could be more like the Lad he had dream'd on: Some there are which report his firſt dream after another manner; as if feveral of the Noble-mens fons having petitioned him for a Tutor, <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> ſhew'd them one amongst themselves, to whom they ſhould direct all their defires, and that having ſtroaked the Boy gently over the mouth with his hand, he kifs'd it himself when he had done:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Cicero</persName> alſo had his Dream which he told to his Friends as he was following <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> into the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>; it was, That he faw a little Boy of a moſt incomparable feature, let down from Heaven by a Golden Chain, and ſtanding before the doors of the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> put a whip into his hands: Suddenly after having ſeen <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> (unknown at that time to moft people) whom his Unkle <persName rend="italic">Cefar</persName> had called to the Sacrifice, he declared that was the Boy whoſe Image he had feen in his Dream.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
    <p>
      As he was putting on his Virile Robe, his purple Gown being unbuttoned on both ſides, it fell down to his feet, which was look'd upon as a preſage, That the order of the Senators of which that was a badge, ſhould oneday be in ſubjection to him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Julius Cafar</persName> as he was cutting down a Wood near <placeName rend="italic">Munda</placeName> (where he then was incamp'd) found a Date-Tree by accident amongst the reſt, which he ordered to be kept carefully, as a preſage of fucceſs. Not long after there put fortha young ſhoot, which in few days increas'd ſo much that it not only outgrew, but overgrew its ſtock, ſpreading abroad its branches in fuch manner, that the Pigeons built frequently upon them, though that fort of Bird avoids fuch kind of leaves as are hard and ſharp; by that prodigy (as is reported) <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> was induc'd to make his Sifters Grand-fon his Succeſſor, and no other.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
    <p>
      In his retirement to <placeName rend="italic">Apollo-nia</placeName>, going with <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> upon a time to give a viſit to <persName rend="italic">Theogenes</persName> an Aftrologer, <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName> having asked the firſt queſtions about his fortune, and received great and incredible predictions, <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> was a long time before he would tell him his Nativity, for ſhame, or fear left his Horoscope ſhould not afford him as good tidings: But after much importunity, having diſcovered it at last, <persName rend="italic">Theogenes</persName> leapt up with joy, and then falling down at his feet, gave him all poſſible adoration. Upon which <persName rend="italic">Angustus</persName> conceived fo great an opinion of his Deftiny, that he publish'd the Configuration, and ſtamp'd Money with the mark of <persName rend="italic">Capricorn</persName>, under which conſtellation he was born.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="95">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      95. After <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName> was murdred, and <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> returned from <placeName rend="italic">Apollonia</placeName>, as he was making his entry into the City, on a sudden the sky being clear and ferene, there appeared a Circle in the faſhion of a Rain-bow which encompass'd the Sun; and preſently after the Tomb of <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Cafars</persName> Daughter, was demoliſh'd by lightning. After this as he was attending his Augurie in his firit Confulſhip, twelve Vultures appear'd to him, as they did formerly to <persName rend="italic">Romulus</persName>; and the livers of all the Sacrifices were found to be replicate, and doubled inward, which all perfons experienc'd in that Art, interpreted a token of extraordinary Grandeur and Profperity.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="96">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      96. He commenc'd no War, nor fought any Battle, but he foresaw the event by fome Omen or other. The Troops of the Triumviri having their Rendezvouz at <placeName rend="italic">Bolonia</placeName>, an Eagle came and fat upon his Tent, which being infeſted on both fides with two Ravens, ſhe was too hard for them both, and beat them down to the Ground: This being taken notice of by the whole Army, was look''d upon as a preſage of the diſſention which enſued betwixt him and his Colleagues, and the advantage that accrued to him thereby. At <placeName rend="italic">Philippi</placeName> a certain Theffalian gave him afſurance of his Victory, from <persName rend="italic">D. Cafar</persName> who had appeared to him in his own image as he was travelling in a by-way.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      As he was facrificing at <placeName rend="italic">Perufia</placeName> another time, but without any favourable or propitious ſign, and thererefore demanded more Victimes to pacifie the Gods, the Enemy made a fally and carry'd away the whole preparation for the Sacrifice: whereupon the Divines being confulted, it was concluded, that all the miſchiefs denounc'd and threatned by that Sacrifice, would inevitably fall upon them that had the entrails, and it hapned accordingly. The day before his Sea-fight near <placeName rend="italic">Sicily</placeName>, as he was walking upon the ſhore, a fiſh leapt out of the Sea, and threw it felf at his feet. At <placeName rend="italic">Altium</placeName> as he was preparing to fight, he met an Afs-Keeper called <persName rend="italic">Entichus</persName>, driving an Afs called <persName rend="italic">Nicon</persName>: After the Victory he commanded the Statues both of the Man and the Aſs to be made of braſs, and fet up in a Temple he built upon the ground where his Army was incamp'd.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="97">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      97. Neither was his death (of which I ſhall fpeak hereafter) or Apotheosis foretold with fewer Prodigies. As he was muſtring in the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martins</placeName> according as they were accustomed every five Years, in the fight of a vast multitude of People, an Eagle flew ſeveral times about him, and at laſt flying to a ſtone hard by, ſhe took ſtand upon the firſt Letter of <persName rend="italic">Agrippa</persName>; which when he perceived, he commanded his Colleague <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> to make thoſe vows, which according to cuſtome were made, till the next Lu-ftrum; For though the Tables and writings were all ready, yet he declared he would not undertake any thing which he could not perform.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      About the fame time a flash of lightning falling upon one of his Statues, carried away the firſt letter of his name; upon which having interrogated his Southfayers, he was told he ſhould live but a hundred days, which was imply'd in the Letter C. and that afterwards he ſhould be tranſlated amongst the Gods, becauſe <foreign rend="italic">Afar</foreign>, which was the remainder of <persName rend="italic">Cafar</persName>, in the <foreign rend="italic">Tufcane</foreign> language fignified a God.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Upon which he fent <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> into <placeName rend="italic">Illyricum</placeName>, and was about to have accompanyed him as far as <placeName rend="italic">Beneventum</placeName>, but being detained and interrupted by the importunities of ſeveral perfons, impatient to have their Caufes fuf-pended, he cryed out (and it was afterwards reckon'd as an Omen) <q rend="italic">That if every thing ſtop'd him, he would be no more at <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.</q> Having begun his journey, he came to <placeName rend="italic">Afturia</placeName>, from whence in the night (which was contrary to his cuſtome) he took the opportunity of a gentle wind, and was tranſported in a ſhort time.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="98">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      98. The diſtemper that kill'd him was cauſed by a Flux; during his indiſpoſition, he coafted about <placeName rend="italic">Campania</placeName>, and the neighbouring Ifles: after which he pafs'd four whole dayes at <placeName rend="italic">Capree</placeName>, in great affability and quiet.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      A while afterwards, as he was pafling the Gulf of <placeName rend="italic">Puteoli</placeName>, a Veſſel from <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName> being newly arriv'd, the Seamen and Paſſengers being all in white, and crown'd with Garlands, offer'd incenſe to him with great Elogies, and wish'd him all profperity, as the perfon <q rend="italic">To whom they ow'd their Lives, their Trade, their Liberties, and the enjoyment of whatever they had.</q> Theſe acclamations were fo grateful to him, that he diſtributed forty pieces of Gold amongst his Companions, obliging each of them to imploy the faid fum, in buying the Merchandizes which came from <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The rest of his time he ſpent in giving ſmall preſents, as Robes, and Mantles, with this condition, that the <persName rend="italic">Romans</persName> ſhould habit themselves <foreign rend="italic">a la Greque</foreign>, and the Grecians like the <persName rend="italic">Romans</persName>; and that the <persName rend="italic">Romans</persName> ſhould ſpeak Greek. He took great delight likewise to fee the young men (of which there were fome yet remaining in <placeName rend="italic">Caprea</placeName>) do their Exerciſes according to the diſcipline of the Antients. He gave them a Treat likewife, and was preſent at it himself, not only permitting, but commanding them to be merry and free, and according to their old liberty to ſnatch away the meat and fruit from one another, and to behave themselves as they pleas'd: In short, he deny'd himself no manner of divertiſement.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      And whereas a confiderable part of his Retinue were retired into a pleaſant Iſland adjacent to <placeName rend="italic">Caprea</placeName>, he called it <placeName rend="italic">Aprago polis</placeName>, or Lubber-land, from the idleneſs of thoſe which were gone thither. As likewife he called <persName rend="italic">Mafgabas</persName>, one of his Favourites,  ; as much as to ſay, the Founder of that Iſland. This <persName rend="italic">Mafgabas</persName> being dead a year before, as he was looking out of his Dining-room he obſerv'd his Sepulchre frequented with great numbers of people, and many lights in their hands, and pronounc'd a verſe in Greek which he made <foreign rend="italic">ex tempore</foreign>, to this purpoſe; <q rend="italic">Methinks I see the Founders Tomb on fire.</q> Then turning to <persName rend="italic">Thrafyllus</persName> a Companion of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, who was then at the Table over against him, and knew nothing of the matter, he ask'd him if he knew who was the Author of that verſe; to which he giving no ready anſwer, he added another, <q rend="italic">Seeft thon <persName rend="italic">Maſgabas</persName> honoured with lights</q>, and de-manded his opinion thereupon; and the other replying, that the Verfes were good whoever compos'd them, he fell a laughing, and was in a good humour all the day after.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      A while after he croſs'd over to <placeName rend="italic">Naples</placeName>, and though his diſeaſe was upon him at that time, yet he was a diligent Spectator of the Quinquennial Games, which were inſtituted in his honour; from whence he departed with his Companion <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> to the place he deſigned: But as he was returning, his diſtemper increaſing, he was forc'd to ſtay at <placeName rend="italic">Nola</placeName>, where calling back <persName rend="italic">Tiberins</persName> from his voyage, he fpent a long time in private with him, and never after that concern'd himself in any State affair.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="99">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      99. The last day of his life, he enquired ſeveral times if there was as yet no tumult about him; and having called for a Glaſs, he commanded them to put his hair in order, and to correct the ſinking of his cheeks; then calling his Friends into the Chamber to him, he demanded of them, <q rend="italic">What they thought of him, and whether he had not acted his part well, in the Farce of his life</q>: Adding this expreſſion thereto, <q rend="italic">Then if all be well, when I am dead and gone, clap your hands, and give me your applause with joy.</q> After this he took his leave of all the people, and diſmiſs'd them: Then demanding what news of a Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Drusus's</persName> which was fick at that time, he turn'd himself about to <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName>, and kiſſing her, he expir'd with these words in his mouth; <q rend="italic"><persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> adien, re-member our Marriage whilst thou livest, and farewell.</q> And in this manner he died, as he had alwayes defired;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      for as often as it was told him, that any one died ſuddenly, and without any torment, he wiſh'd the fame <foreign rend="italic">Euthanasian</foreign> (for that was his uſual word) to himself, and his friends. There was one fign of a delirium and diſtractedness of mind, and that was a little before his death, when upon a sudden ſtart as in a fright, he complain'd, <q rend="italic">He was carrying away by forty young men;</q> and that was rather a preſage, than any weakness of brain, for ſo many were there of the Pretorian band which carried him publickly before the people when he was dead.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="100">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      100. He died in the fame Chamber where his Father <persName rend="italic">Octavins</persName> died, when the two <persName rend="italic">Sextuses</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Pompeius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Apuleius</persName>, were Confuls, on the 17th. of August, about nine a clock in the morning, 76 years of age wanting but 35 dayes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      The Decuriones of the Municipal Towns and Colonies, convey'd his body from <placeName rend="italic">Nola</placeName> to <placeName rend="italic">Boville</placeName>, marching folemnly by night, (by reaſon of the heat of the weather) repofing it in the day time in the chief Palace or Temple of every Town they went through. From <placeName rend="italic">Boville</placeName> it was conducted by the Equestrian Order to <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>, and plac'd in the Portico of his own house. The expreffions of the Senate were ſo great both in honouring his memory, and adorning his Funeral, that amongst other tokens of their zeal, fome advis'd that his Funeral Pomp might paſs through the Triumphal Gate, with the image of <persName rend="italic">Victoria</persName> (which is in the Council-Chamber) carried before it, the principal Noblemens children of both ſexes ſinging his Dirges as they went along. Others were of opinion, they ſhould leave off their Gold, and put on rings of Iron on that day. Others, that his bones ſhould be gather'd together by the Priests of the highest Societies.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      One there was propos'd to have the name of the month August, to be chang'd into September, becauſe <persName rend="italic">Auguſtus</persName> was born in one, and died in the other. Another moved, that the the ſpace of time betwixt his Birth and his Funeral, might be called <foreign rend="italic">Seculum Auguftum</foreign>, and ſo entred in the Kalendar. But it being thought beſt to moderate his honours, <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> and his Son <persName rend="italic">Drusus</persName> gave him each of them a Funeral Oration; <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, before the Temple of <persName rend="italic">D. Julius</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Drufius</persName> before the <placeName rend="italic">Roftra</placeName>: after which his body was carried upon Senators ſhoulders into the <placeName rend="italic">Campus Martius</placeName>, and burnt.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      Nor wanted there a perſon of Quality, who had been a Pretorian, to ſwear that he saw his Image afcend into the Heavens. The Reliques of his bones and aſhes, were gather'd together by the chief of the Equestrian Order, in their Tunicks ungirt, and barefoot, which they buried afterwards in a ſtately Monument or Mausoleum, which he had built betwixt the <placeName rend="italic">Via Flaminia</placeName> and the banks of <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName> in his fixth Confulſhip, and given the adjacent Walks and Woods to the people.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="101">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      101. The third day before the Nones of April, a year and four months before his deceaſe, in the Confulſhip of <persName rend="italic">L. Plancus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">C. Silius</persName>, he had made his Will in two parts, written partly with his own hand, and partly under the hands of <persName rend="italic">Polybius</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Hilarion</persName>, two of his Freemen; and having depoſited it in the cuftody of the Vestal Virgins, they produc'd it with three other Volumes feal'd up in the fame manner, which were all open'd and publickly read in the Senate.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      His firſt Heirs were <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> of two thirds, and <persName rend="italic">Livia</persName> of the other, with authority to bear his Name. His fecond Heirs were <persName rend="italic">Drusus</persName> the Son of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName> of one third, and <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> with his three Sons of the reſt. In the third degree he nominated his Kindred, and ſeveral of his Friends. To the people of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> he left a Legacy of 40000000 Sefterces, to the Tribes about three millions and a half of Seſterces, to every Souldier of his Guard a thousand Sefterces, to the Companies of the City 500, to the Legionarie Cohorts 300 apiece, which fum he commanded ſhould be paid down, for he had so much in Bank by him, repoſited for that purpoſe.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He gave ſeveral Legacies beſides theſe, the greatest of them not exceeding 500 Crowns, for the payment of which he allowed a years time, excuſing it from the ſmalneſs of his Eſtate, and proteſting that there would remain to his Heirs not above 150 millions, though within the last twenty years he had receiv'd by way of Legacy from his friends 1400000000: All which vaſt ſum, with the Patrimonies of two Fathers, and other Inheritances beſides, he had imploy'd about the publick affairs of the Commonwealth. The two <persName rend="italic">Julie</persName> (when they ſhould deceaſe) he left an expreſs Caveat they ſhould not be buried in his Sepulchre.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The three Volumes contain'd, firſt his directions as to his Funeral; the ſecond, an Index of all his actions, (which he defir'd might be engraven in Braſs, and ſet up before the Mausoleum ;) the third was, a true Breviate or State of the Empire, representing the eſtabliſhment of his Souldiers in pay, the precife fums of money in the City Chamber, and his own Exchequer, with the arrears of the Tributes and Taxes, and a Catalogue of the Freemen and Slaves from whom they were to require an accompt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


        </div>
    </body>
    </text>
</tei>