<TEI>
<text>
    <body>
        <div>
            <pb n="475"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      THE EIGHTH BOOK, Being the LIFE OF <persName rend="italic">Titus Flavius Domitianus</persName>, THE TWELFTH Emperour of <placeName rend="italic">ROME</placeName>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">DOmitian</persName> was born the 24th of October, (his Father being Conſul Elect, and to enter into that honourable Charge the Month following) in the ſixth quarter of the City, in the Street called the Pomegranate, at a houſe which he converted afterwards into a Temple, and dedicated to the
      <pb n="476"/>
      Family of the <persName rend="italic">Flavii</persName>. It is reported, he paſſed his youth and minority in that infamous poverty, he had not one piece of Plate to make uſe of in his whole houſe. This is moſt certain, <persName rend="italic">Clodius Pollio</persName> (of Prætorian degree) againſt whom <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> compos'd his Poem called <foreign rend="italic">Luscio</foreign>, which is yet extant, kept a Note he had under <persName rend="italic">Domitian's</persName> own hand, (and he ſhew'd it upon occaſion) by which he promis'd him a nights Lodging when he pleas'd. Some affirm, he proſtituted himſelf to <persName rend="italic">Nerva</persName>, who ſucceeded him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      During the Wars of <persName rend="italic">Vitellius</persName>, he fled into the Capitol with his Unkle by the Fathers ſide <persName rend="italic">Sabinus</persName>, and part of ſuch Forces as they had about them; but the Enemy being entred by force, and the Temple on fire, he conceal'd himſelf that night with the Sexton; and in the morning, habited like one of <persName rend="italic">Iſis</persName> Prieſts, amongſt the Votaries of that vain Superſtition, being fled over the <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName> only with one Companion, to the houſe where the Mother of one of his Schoolfellows lived, he hid himſelf ſo, that though he was follow'd by his footſteps, he could never be diſcovered.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      At laſt after the Victory, he appear'd again in publick, was ſaluted by the name of <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>, took upon him the dignity of the City Prætor, with the Conſular authority; but that was only in Title, for he transferred the Power to his next Colleague. Nevertheleſs he forbore not to exerciſe that authority he had, with ſo much licentiouſneſs and violence, that it was eaſie to gueſs what was to be expected from him hereafter. I do not propoſe to give an exact and particular relation of his deportment; After he had debauched the Wives of ſeveral other perſons, he married <persName rend="italic">Domitia Longina</persName>, whom he had taken away by force from <persName rend="italic">Ælius Lamia</persName> her Husband. And in
      <pb n="477"/>
      one day he diſpoſed of above twenty Offices in the City and Provinces; wherewith <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> being ſurprized, was heard to ſay, <q rend="italic">He wondered he did not ſend one to ſucceed him alſo.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      2. Though his Fathers friends diſſwaded him what they could from a deſign he had into <placeName rend="italic">France</placeName>, and <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, as an Expedition altogether unneceſſary; yet they could not beat him off it, he would go, only to equal the Exploits and Glory of his Brother. Being rebuked ſeverely for theſe whimſeys, that he might have the more conſideration of his age and condition, he was taken home and lodg'd in his Fathers houſe; and when he and his Brother <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName> went forth in their Chair, he followed them for the moſt part in his Litter; and when both of them Triumphed over the <persName rend="italic">Jews</persName>, he accompanied them mounted upon a white Horſe. Of ſix Conſulſhips, he executed but one, according to the ordinary form, and that was by the ceſſion and interpoſition of his Brother.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He was a great pretender to Modeſty, but eſpecially to Poetry, in ſo much that he recited his Compoſitions in publick; but it being a ſtudy in which he had not been much vers'd before, he deſpiſed it by degrees, and gave it quite over. Not long after, <persName rend="italic">Vologesus</persName> King of the <placeName rend="italic">Parthians</placeName> having demanded ſome Succours againſt the <placeName rend="italic">Alani</placeName>, and deſired one of the Sons of <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName> to Command them, he uſed all art and means he could invent, to procure that imployment for himſelf; and when he found thoſe differences compoſed, he ſollicited other Princes of the Eaſt, (by his promiſes and preſents) to deſire Supplies.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      After the death of his Father, having a long time deliberated with himſelf, whether he ſhould offer the Souldiers a double Donative, to what his Bro-
      <pb n="478"/>
      ther <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName> had given them, at laſt he declar'd boldly, <q rend="italic">That he was left Partner in the Empire by his Father, but that his Will had been abus'd.</q> Nor from that time did he forbear contriving the deſtruction of his Brother, both in publick and private, till ſeeing him deſperately ill, before he was quite dead, he commanded the room to be clear'd, and all people to leave him, as he had been already in his Grave. Nay even after he was deceas'd, he vouchſafed him no other honour, but a bare Conſecration, carping at, and reviling his memory, both in reflective ſpeeches, and in his Edicts or Declarations.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      3. In the beginning of his Empire, he had a cuſtom of retiring into his Chamber an hour every day, where his imployment was nothing but catching of Flies, and pricking them thorow with a Pen-knife: whereupon one enquiring, <q rend="italic">Who was in the Cloſet with <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName>?</q> it was wittily anſwer'd by <persName rend="italic">Vibius Crispus</persName>, <q rend="italic">Not ſo much as a Fly.</q> After this, though in the time of his ſecond Conſulſhip he had had a Son by his Wife <persName rend="italic">Domitia</persName>, and the next year had ſaluted her with the Title of <persName rend="italic">Augusta</persName>, yet he divorc'd her notwithſtanding, and all for an immoderate affection ſhe had for a Stage-player called <persName rend="italic">Paris</persName>. But in a ſhort time he repented of what he had done ſo raſhly, and being impatient of their ſeparation, he took her again, pretending great importunity and ſollicitation from the people.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      In the adminiſtration of the Empire, (for ſometime) he was very various, by reaſon of the equality, and proportion of his Vices and Virtues, till at length his Vices prevail'd above his natural inclination, (as far as we may conjecture) making him covetous becauſe of his wants, and cruel by reaſon of his fears.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <pb n="479"/>
    <p>
      4. All the Shews and Spectacles which he exhibited, not only in the Amphitheatre, but in the Cirque, were noble and magnificent: In the Cirque beſides the Courſes of the Chariots with two horſes and four, he preſented them with two Combates, one of Horſe, and the other of Foot, and a Sea-fight in the Amphitheatre. His Baitings, and Gladiators he repreſented by Torch-light in the night, as alſo not only his Mens Combates, but his Womens. The Quæſtorian Shows having been diſcontinued for a long time, he brought up again into uſe, and was not only always preſent himſelf, but ſtill gave the people liberty to demand two couple of his Gladiators, which were always brought in at laſt, habited according to the dignity of the Court.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Whenever he was preſent at any of theſe Sword-plays, he had a kind of a Dwarf ſtanding continually at his feet, cloathed in Scarlet, whoſe head was ſo little, it was almoſt a miracle: with this young Lad he diſcours'd very much, and ſometimes gravely, and of matters of importance: For he was once heard to ask him, <q rend="italic">What he thought of his deſign to give the Government of <placeName rend="italic">Egypt</placeName> to <persName rend="italic">Metius Rufus</persName>, the next Ordination.</q> Having digg'd a vaſt Lake near the River of <placeName rend="italic">Tiber</placeName>, built his Walls, and ſet up his Scaffolds againſt them, he repreſented his Sea-fights, by great numbers of Ships, well nigh amounting to compleat Fleets; and the greateſt ſhowers that fell, could not hinder him from being there, and ſtaying out to the end of the fight.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He gave them likewiſe their Secular Plays, computing the time not from the year in which <persName rend="italic">Claudius</persName> began them of late, but from that in which <persName rend="italic">Augustus</persName> expos'd them of old. In the Circenſian Games, that the hundred ordinary Courſes might be the more
      <pb n="480"/>
      eaſily diſpatch'd, he reduced every Match from ſeven Stages to five.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      In the honour of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>, he inſtituted three ſorts of Conteſts, to be obſerv'd every five years, of Muſick, Horſmanſhip, and Wreſtling, in which he diſtributed his Coronets in greater numbers than they do at this day. Beſides theſe, he had his Diſputations and Controverſies both in Latine and Greek Proſe, as alſo his Singers with the Harp, Dancers, and plain Harpers, and his Virgins for running of races: At all theſe ſolemnities he ſat Preſident himſelf in his Pantofles, with a Purple Robe upon him, after the faſhion of the <persName rend="italic">Germans</persName>, and a Crown upon his head, with the Images of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, <persName rend="italic">Juno</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Minerva</persName>. The Prieſt of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName>, and the Colledge of the Flavian Prieſts, ſat by him in the ſame habit, only to their Coronets his Image was added. He uſed alſo yearly to celebrate the Feaſts of <persName rend="italic">Minerva</persName>, upon the <placeName rend="italic">Albane</placeName> Mount; and in honour to her, he erected a Colledge, out of which ſuch as were to be Maſters and Governours by Lot, were oblig'd to give the people the diverſion of magnificent Baitings, Stage-plays, and Contentions both in Poetry and Rhetorick.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      Three ſeveral times he gave a benevolence to the people, of three hundred Seſterces apiece; and a great Feaſt during the Combate of the Gladiators. At the ſolemnity of the Seven Mountains, having preſented the Senators and Gentlemen with larger Paniers, he caus'd little Baskets of meat to be diſtributed among the common people, and gave them an example to fall on. The next day he threw amongſt them a maſs of all things, to be ſcrambled for, and becauſe the greateſt part of it fell amongſt the common people, he commanded fifty Tickets to be given to every Bench of the Senators and Gentlemen.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <pb n="481"/>
    <p>
      5. He re-built ſeveral ſtately and Noble Fabricks, which had been deſtroyed by the Fire; amongſt the reſt, the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> which had been burnt the ſecond time: But the Glory he was reſolved to ingroſs to himſelf, for he would not ſuffer any name in the inſcriptions but his own, nor allow the leaſt mention of the primitive Founder. In the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName> he built a New Chappel, which he dedicated to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Cuſtos</persName>: as alſo the <placeName rend="italic">Forum</placeName>, or Hall of Juſtice, which is called at this time <placeName rend="italic">Forum Nervæ</placeName>: He built likewiſe another Temple for the Flavian Family, a Courſe, or Liſts, for Running or Wreſtling, a Muſick-houſe, and a place for a Sea-fight; the Stones of which were imploy'd afterwards for the repairing of the Circus, which on two ſides had been lamentably burnt.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      6. His Military Expeditions, he undertook voluntarily partly, as that againſt the <placeName rend="italic">Catti</placeName>, and partly of neceſſity, as that againſt the <placeName rend="italic">Sarmatians</placeName>, upon the cutting to pieces a whole Legion, and the General which Commanded them; and two more againſt the <placeName rend="italic">Daci</placeName>, in the firſt of which <persName rend="italic">Oppius Sabinus</persName> (who had been Conſul) was ſlain; and in the ſecond, <persName rend="italic">Cornelius Fuſcus</persName>, Colonel of the Prætorian Cohorts, to whoſe Conduct he had committed the chief management of that War. After ſeveral Engagements, and variety of fortune, having conquer'd the <placeName rend="italic">Catti</placeName>, and the <placeName rend="italic">Daci</placeName>, he Triumphed twice: But for his Victory over the <placeName rend="italic">Sarmatians</placeName>, he had only the honour to preſent his Laurel Garland to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">L. Antonius</persName> Governour of the Upper <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, having revolted and put himſelf at the head of a Mutinous Army, by moſt admirable fortune he reduced, though he was abſent himſelf: For as they were ready to joyn Battle, the <placeName rend="italic">Rhine</placeName> overflowing on a ſudden, ſtopt the Barbarian Force from paſſing over to the aſſiſtance of <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName>. Of which Victory his firſt news was rather by preſage than intelligence; for the very day on which that Battle was fought, an Eagle having covered his Statue with her wings, made a noiſe expreſſing a kind of joy, and not long after the news was ſo hot that <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> was killed, that many people affirmed his head was brought to Town, and that they had ſeen it themſelves.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      7. In many things he altered the ordinary Cuſtoms; particularly, he took away the publick Diſtributions to Clients in Little Baskets, and brought them to the old method of magni-
      <pb n="482"/>
      ficent Suppers: To the four antient Factions at the Circenſian Games, he added two more, one in a Livery of Gold, the other in Purple. He forbad the Comedians acting publickly upon the Stage, but allowed them their liberty in particular houſes. He prohibited the Caſtration of Children; and ſuch as were Eunuchs already, and in the poſſeſſion of the Merchant, he moderated their prices, and brought them down to a more reaſonable rate.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Obſerving a vaſt plenty of Wine, and as great a ſcarcity of Corn in the ſame year, he concluded, that by their too much care of cultivating their Vines, they had neglected their Tillage; to prevent the ſame inconvenience for the future, he put forth an Edict, commanding no more Vines ſhould be planted in <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, and that they ſhould be cut down in the Provinces, or at leaſt reduc'd to a moiety of what they were at that time; but he perſiſted not in this reſolution. Some of the greateſt and moſt conſiderable Offices, he communicated indifferently between his Libertines and Souldiers.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He would not ſuffer the Legions to double their Camps, nor any of the Souldiers to depoſite above a thouſand Seſterces about their Colours. Foraſmuch as <persName rend="italic">Antonius</persName> deſigning a Mutiny in the Winter Quarters of the two Legions, ſeemed to have founded his confidence upon the money in depoſito, he added alſo to the pay of the Souldiers, which conſiſted of three pieces of Gold by the month, a fourth piece.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      8. In the adminiſtration of Juſtice, he was very diligent and induſtrious; He many times ſate himſelf in an extraordinary manner in Court, and ſuperſeded the partial ſentences of the <foreign rend="italic">Centumviri</foreign>; He admoniſh'd the Commiſſioners and Delegated Judges likewiſe, not to incline too much to the Rhetorical perſwaſions of ſuch as interpos'd in the behalf of the Slaves, and Servants which demanded their liberty, taking particular notice of ſuch Judges and Counſellors as were corrupt, and acted by bribes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He encouraged the Tribunes of the people to accuſe an Ædile of Extortion, and to demand Juſtice againſt him of the Senate. He was ſo careful againſt the enormities of the City Magiſtrates, and the Governours of Provinces, that there was never known more equity and modeſty amongſt the great Officers than in his time, though after his death moſt of the ſame perſons were convict of all manner of crimes.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Having taken
      <pb n="483"/>
      upon himſelf the Cenſorſhip, and regulation of manners, he reformed the liberty which was taken in the Theatres, of ſitting promiſcuouſly amongſt the Nobleſs. He ſuppreſſed ſuch Libels, and defamatory writings, as any wayes reflected upon perſons of Quality of either ſex, and caus'd them to be aboliſhed, with diſgrace and infamy to the Authors. He turned a Gentleman out of the Senate, for no other reaſon but that he took an immoderate delight in Buffonry and Dancing. From ſuch women as were ſcandalous in their lives, he took away the priviledge of Litters, and their capacity of Legacies, and inheritance. He blotted a <persName rend="italic">Roman</persName> Knight out of the Liſt of the Judges, for taking his Wife again after ſhe had been repudiate for Adultery. He condemned ſome particular perſons of both degrees, (as well Senators as Gentlemen) by the Law <foreign rend="italic">Scatinia</foreign>. The inceſts of the Veſtal Virgins, which his Father and Brother had negligently paſſed over, he puniſh'd ſeverely ſundry wayes: Such as were convicted but once, were only put to death;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      but others, according to the antient Cuſtom: For having permitted two Siſters of the Family of the <persName rend="italic">Ocellæ</persName>, to make choice in what manner they would dye, and expreſs'd the ſame favour afterwards to <persName rend="italic">Varonilla</persName>, he baniſh'd the perſons which had debauched them: But when <persName rend="italic">Cornelia</persName> their Principal was brought before him, who had been pardoned before, and was a long time after proſecuted and convict for the like offence again, he commanded her to be buried alive, and the perſons which had vitiated her, to be whipt to death in the midſt of the <placeName rend="italic">Comitium</placeName>. One perſon only which had been Prætor, whom (the Evidence being not clear) they had conſtrained to a Confeſſion by torture, he favour'd ſo far as only to baniſh him;
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      and that no man might violate the Religion and Reverence which was due to the Gods, with impunity, he caus'd the Souldiers to demoliſh a Monument which one of his Freemen had erected for his Son, with the Stones which were deſigned for the Temple of <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>, and the bones and aſhes which were in it, to be thrown into the Sea.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      9. At the beginning of his reign he ſhewed himſelf ſo gentle, and abhorring all manner of Cruelty, that in the abſence of his Father, upon the Memory of this Verſe in <persName rend="italic">Virgil</persName>,
    </p>
    <p>
      <quote rend="italic"><l>Impia quam cæſis Gens eſt epulata Juvencis.</l></quote>
    </p>
    <p>
      <pb n="484"/>
      <quote><l>E're the prophaner world ſet out their feaſts</l>
        <l>with innocent, and yet with ſlaughter'd Beaſts.</l></quote>
    </p>
    <p>
      He reſolved by an Expreſs Edict to forbid the ſacrificing of Oxen. Whilſt he was a private perſon, he gave not the leaſt Umbrage, or ſuſpicion of covetouſneſs, or parſimony, nor for a long time after he was Emperour; on the other ſide, he gave frequent teſtimonies, not only of his moderation, but liberality, behaving himſelf very bountifully to all that were about him, inculcating nothing to them ſo much as to avoid baſeneſs and ſordidneſs.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Such inheritances as were left him by perſons which had Children, he would never accept; <persName rend="italic">Ruſcius Cepio</persName> having by his Will obliged his heir, <q rend="italic">To pay a certain ſum every year to every Senator which entred into the Senate</q>: He made the Will void, and would not ſuffer it to be executed. Such as had been ſued in the Treaſury five years before, and had their ſuits ſtill depending, he diſcharged, not allowing any new proceſs to be made upon that account, but within a years time, and that with this Caution, that if the Informer made not his charge good, he ſhould be baniſhed for his pains.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      The Clerks, and Notaries belonging to the Quæſtors, having been accuſtomed to Negotiate contrary to the Law <foreign rend="italic">Clodia</foreign>, he pardoned for the time paſt, but not otherwiſe. The diviſion of lands having been made for the Veteran Souldiers, he confirm'd the remainders which were left, to the old poſſeſſors, as held of the Crown in Fee; ſuch falſe informations as fell under the Cognizance of the Exchequer, he repreſt, and not without ſevere chaſtiſement to the Informers, this by report being his uſual ſaying, <q rend="italic">That Prince which does not puniſh Informers, does but incourage and increaſe them.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      10. But this mercy and moderation was not long lived, and yet he fell away ſooner to cruelty than avarice. A Scholar of <persName rend="italic">Paris</persName> the Mimick, being at that time but a Youth, and very ſick, he caus'd him to be ſlain, for nothing, but becauſe he reſembled his Maſter both in his action and feature. <persName rend="italic">Hermogenes</persName> of <placeName rend="italic">Tarſus</placeName> was ſerved in the ſame
      <pb n="485"/>
      kind, for certain figurative reflections upon him, in a Hiſtory which he compoſed, and the Clerks which tranſcribed it were hanged. A ſubſtantial Houſe-keeper being a Spectator at that time, and but ſaying of one of the Gladiators, <q rend="italic">The Thracian is hard enough for the other againſt whom he fights, but not for him who exhibits the Shew,</q> was pulled down immediately from his Seat, and thrown upon the ſtage to be expoſed to the dogs, with this inſcription, <q rend="italic">The Thracians part-taker for having ſpoken irreverent words.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Many Senators he cauſed to be put to death, ſome of which had been formerly Conſuls, as particularly <persName rend="italic">Civicus Cerealis</persName> in his Proconſulſhip of <placeName rend="italic">Aſia</placeName>, <persName rend="italic">Salvidenus Orfitus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Acilius Glabrio</persName> in their baniſhment, pretending practiſes againſt the State; Multitudes of others alſo he puniſh'd upon every ſlight occaſion: <persName rend="italic">Ælius Lamia</persName> amongſt the reſt was executed for his jeſts, though they were old and innocent; <persName rend="italic">Domitian</persName> being in diſcourſe with him one day after he had taken away his Wife, he took occaſion to commend his voice, to which <persName rend="italic">Ælius</persName> replyed, <q rend="italic">Yet alas I muſt hold my peace.</q> <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName> adviſing him likewiſe to another Wife, he anſwered;
    </p>

    
    <quote rend="italic"><l>μὴ καὶ σὺ γαμῆσαι θέλεις;</l></quote>
    <quote rend="italic"><l>And would you, Sir, be married too?</l></quote>
 
    
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Salvius Cocceanus</persName>, for that he celebrated the Nativity of <persName rend="italic">Otho</persName> the Emperour, who was his Unkle by the Fathers ſide. <persName rend="italic">Metius Pompoſianus</persName> becauſe he was reported to have had an Imperial Horoſcope, and that the poſition of the Heavens at his birth, portended he ſhould be Emperour; as alſo becauſe he carried about him a Map of the World in Parchment, the Speeches of all the Kings and Captains mentioned in <persName rend="italic">Livy</persName>, and had preſumed to give the names of <persName rend="italic">Mago</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Hannibal</persName> to certain of his Slaves. <persName rend="italic">Saluſtius Lucullus</persName> Lieutenant General in <placeName rend="italic">Britain</placeName>, for ſuffering a new ſort of Lances to be called <foreign rend="italic">Lucullia's</foreign> after his own name. <persName rend="italic">Junius Ruſticus</persName> for publiſhing a writing in commendation of <persName rend="italic">Pætus Thraſea</persName>, and <persName rend="italic">Helvidius Priſcus</persName>, and affirming them to be very honeſt men, upon which occaſion likewiſe he baniſhed all the
      <pb n="486"/>
      Philoſophers as well out of <placeName rend="italic">Italy</placeName>, as <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      He cauſed <persName rend="italic">Helvidius</persName> Junior, to be ſlain in like manner, for that he had made a certain Farce which he cauſed to be recited upon the Stage, in which under the names of <persName rend="italic">Paris</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Oenone</persName>, he had made ſome reflections upon the Divorce betwixt his Wife and him. <persName rend="italic">Flavius Sabinus</persName> one of his Couſin Germans, for that upon the day of the Aſſembly for the creation of Conſuls, the Publick Crier by miſtake pronounced him Emperour to the people, inſtead of Conſul.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
    <p>
      Nevertheleſs his cruelty increaſed after his Victory in the Civil War, in ſo much that to revenge himſelf of thoſe who had been of the adverſe party, and to diſcover their Complices, he invented a new kind of torture, by putting fire into their privy parts and ſometimes cutting off their hands. This is moſt clear, he never pardoned but two perſons that were of any eminence, (one a Tribune, of Senators degree, and the other a Centurion) who to make their innocence the more conſpicuous, made it appear they had been Catamites, and effeminate perſons, and by conſequence uncapable of any intereſt either with the General or Army.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      11. Nor was he only fierce and poſitive in his Cruelty, but ſubtil alſo and artificial in ſurprizing. The day before he crucified the Comptroller of his Houſhold, he called him up into his Chamber, conſtrained him to ſit down by him, diſmiſſed him merry and ſecure, and ſent him a diſh of meat from his own Table that night. <persName rend="italic">Aretinus Clemens</persName>, a man of Conſular dignity, and one of his principal Favourites and Emiſſaries, when he had concluded upon his death, he ſent for him, cajol'd him, ſhewed him the ſame or greater favour than before, till at laſt (being in the ſame Litter with him, as they were taking the air one day) perceiving his Accuſer, he demanded of <persName rend="italic">Clemens</persName>, <q rend="italic">whether he ſhould hear the next day what that Raſcal could ſay?</q>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      And that he might abuſe the patience of men with the more ſcorn, and contempt, he never pronounced any diſmal ſentence, but with a Preamble full of clemency and mercy: ſo that whenever he appear'd gentle in the Prologue, it was a ſure ſign the Epilogue would be bloody. Having brought ſome perſons (who were accuſed of Treaſon) before the Senate, to prepare them for his deſign, he declared publickly, that <q rend="italic">That day he ſhould be able to diſcern how dear he was to the Se-</q>
      <pb n="487"/>
      <q rend="italic">nate;</q> by which means he fore-ſpoke their judgments, and eaſily prevailed to have them condemned to dye <foreign rend="italic">more majorum</foreign>:
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      Which when he had obtained, as if he had been terrified with the atrocity of the puniſhment, to take off the envy from himſelf, theſe words, for it will not be amiſs to ſet them down expreſly; <q rend="italic">P. C. permit I beſeech you that I may obtain of your piety, (which notwithſtanding I know muſt be obtained with great difficulty) that theſe poor people condemned, may be allowed to make choice of what deaths they will dye; By ſo doing you will reſcue your own eyes from a ſpectacle of horror, and all the world will take notice I was preſent in the Senate.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<pb n="487"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      12. Having exhauſted his Treaſure by his extraordinary Buildings, by his Exhibitions to the people, and augmenting the pay of his Souldiers; to eaſe his Military expences, he attempted to reform his Troops, and reduce them to a leſſer number: But conſidering with himſelf, that would but leave him open to the Invaſions of the Barbarians, and beſides that, the other Charges of the Empire were too great for him to contend with, he gave himſelf over to all kind of Rapine and Extortion. Upon the leaſt accuſation, by the firſt Informer, he ſeiz'd upon the Eſtates of all people, whether living or dead: The leaſt action or word againſt the Majeſty of their Prince, was ſufficient to undo them.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      He confiſcated Inheritances though never ſo remote, if there were but one witneſs found to depoſe, that he heard the deceaſed party ſay when he was living, <q rend="italic">That <persName rend="italic">Cæſar</persName> was his Heir:</q> But above all, the Tribute of the <persName rend="italic">Jews</persName> was exacted with moſt ſeverity; not only from ſuch as by profeſſion were <persName rend="italic">Jews</persName>, and practiſed their Religion in the City, but from ſuch alſo as had diſſembled their Original, and by that means, evaded the Impoſitions. I remember when I was but a Boy, I was preſent at an Aſſembly in which the Emperours Procurator cauſed an antient man of fourſcore and ten years of age, to be ſearched, that he might know whether he was circumciſed or not.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      From his very youth he was rude, and unſociable, preſumptuous and immoderate, both in his words and his actions. <persName rend="italic">Cenis</persName> one of his Fathers Concubines (returned newly out of <placeName rend="italic">Iſtria</placeName>) preſenting her ſelf to him to kiſs him as ſhe had uſed to do, he gave her his hand. Taking it ill his Brothers Son-in-law had his Servants in white Liveries like his, he cryed out,
      <pb n="488"/>
      
      
      <quote rend="italic" xml:lang="grc"><l>Οὐκ ἀγαθὸν πολυκοιρανίη.</l></quote>
      <quote rend="italic"><l>No pleaſant proſpect it affords,</l>
<l>To ſee at once two Soveraign Lords.</l></quote>
    </p>
    <p>
      <q rend="italic"></q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      13. When he was arrived at the Empire, he had the confidence to boaſt in the Senate, <q rend="italic">That it was he had given it both to his Father, and Brother, and that they had but reſtored it to him again.</q> After his Divorce, when he took his Wife again, he declared, <q rend="italic">That he had re-taken her to his Sacred Bed:</q> And when he made a great Feaſt one day, he took great delight to hear their acclamations and wiſhes of all health and happineſs to <q rend="italic">our Lord and Lady.</q> His obſtinacy and perverſeneſs appear'd at the repreſentation of the Plays inſtituted in honour to <persName rend="italic">Jupiter Capitolinus</persName>; where the whole Aſſembly by common conſent making it their petition, that he would reſtore <persName rend="italic">Palfurius Sura</persName>, (who had been formerly turned out of the Senate, but had at that time gained the Prize amongſt the Orators) he gave them no anſwer, more than by the common Cryer to command their ſilence.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      With the ſame arrogance dictating a Letter for one of his Officers, he began, <q rend="italic">Our Lord and our God requires it ſhall be ſo:</q> whereupon it was ordered, that no man ſhould preſume to call him otherwiſe, either in writing or diſcourſe. He would not permit any Statues to be ſet up for him in the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, but what were of Gold or Silver, and a preciſe weight. He erected ſo many Gates, and Triumphal Arches (upon which were repreſented his Chariot and four Horſes, with all his Enſigns of Triumph) that upon one of the ſaid Arches <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἌΡΚΕΙ</foreign> was inſcribed, which in Greek ſignifies enough.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He was the firſt man which was ever known to be Conſul ſeventeen times; the middle ſeven ſucceſſively, but almoſt all of them he held only in Title, none beyond the Calends of May, and ſeveral to the Ides of January, and no longer. After his two Triumphs, (over the <placeName rend="italic">Catti</placeName> and <placeName rend="italic">Daci</placeName>) when he had aſſumed the Surname of <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName>, he altered the names of the two months September and October, and cauſed them to be called <persName rend="italic">Germanicus</persName> and <persName rend="italic">Domitianus</persName>, becauſe in one of
      <pb n="489"/>
      them he was made Emperour, and in the other he was born.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      14. His deportment having made him terrible, and by conſequence odious to all people, he periſhed at length by the Conſpiracy of his Friends and Freemen of greateſt intimacy with him, with the privity and co-operation of his Wife. A long time before, he had an apprehenſion not onely of the year and day, but of the hour and manner of his death.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For the <placeName rend="italic">Chaldeans</placeName> had given him their Predictions when he was but a child. One night as he was at Supper, he was obſerved to forbear Muſhromes, which his Father taking notice of, fell a laughing at him, as one that was ignorant of his own Deſtiny, for that he did not fear the ſword rather than them: upon this ſcore he lived in perpetual diſquiet, the leaſt apprehenſion throwing him down into the greateſt anxiety. It is ſaid he repealed the Edict he had exhibited for the deſtroying of Vines for no other reaſon, but becauſe theſe Verſes in Greek were ſcattered about <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName>.
      <quote rend="italic"><l>Pluck up my roots, try all can be devis'd,</l>
<l>Yet I'le find wine when <persName rend="italic">Cæſars</persName> ſacrific'd.</l></quote>
   

    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      By the ſame diffidence and fear (though he was otherwiſe very vain and ambitious) he refuſed the new honour which they had contrived for him, which was, that as oft as he ſhould exerciſe the Conſulſhip, the Gentlemen of <placeName rend="italic">Rome</placeName> choſen by lot, habited in their robes, with Military Lances in their hands, ſhould march before him amongſt his Lictors, and Serjeants.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
    <p>
      The time of his ſuſpected danger drawing near, he grew every day more jealous than other, inſomuch, that he cauſed a Gallery in which he uſually walked, to be ſet about with a certain ſtone called <foreign rend="italic">Phengitas</foreign>, by the brightneſs of which, the Images were reflected in that ſort, he could ſee whatever was done behind him, as well as in a Glaſs. He would not admit any Priſoner or Criminal to be brought before him, but in private; nor would he hear what any of them could ſay for themſelves, till he had firſt gotten their chains in his hands;
      <pb n="490"/>
      that his Domeſticks might ſee how unſafe it was for any one to attempt the life of his Patron, though to never ſo good an end, he commanded <persName rend="italic">Epaphroditus</persName> (Secretary to <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName>) to be put to death, becauſe it was reported that when <persName rend="italic">Nero</persName> was deſerted by every body elſe, he gave his helping hand to the making him away.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      15. Though <persName rend="italic">Flavius Clemens</persName> was his Couſin German, and no way to be feared in reſpect of the inactivity and contemptibleneſs of his life; though he had declared his Sons (which were very young) his Succeſſors, and having alter'd their old names, cauſed one of them to be called <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſian</persName>, and the other <persName rend="italic">Domitian</persName>: Yet on a ſudden, upon a ſlight and groundleſs ſuſpicion, he commanded him to be cut off, before he was well out of his Conſulſhip: Which piece of cruelty gave no ſmall expedition to his own ruine.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      For eight months together, there was ſo much thunder and lightning in all parts, that when the news was brought him, he cryed out, <q rend="italic">Let him ſtrike now whom he pleaſes.</q> The <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, the Temple of the Family of the <persName rend="italic">Flavii</persName>, his Palace, and his very Chamber were all ſmitten; The Inſcription upon a Triumphal Statue, was taken off the Baſis by the violence of a Tempeſt, and fell down into a Monument hard by. The Tree which had been thrown down in <persName rend="italic">Veſpaſians</persName> time, and roſe up again of it ſelf, fell down the ſecond time on a ſudden. The Oracle at <placeName rend="italic">Preneſte</placeName>, which was accuſtomed to favour him conſtantly, and to promiſe him good fortune at the beginning of every year; contrary to its former kindneſs, preſaged nothing but ſorrow now, and that not without mention of blood.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He dreamed that <persName rend="italic">Minerva</persName>, (whom he adored even to ſuperſtition) had withdrawn her ſelf from the Chappel he had conſecrated to her, and that ſhe told him, <q rend="italic">That <persName rend="italic">Jupiter</persName> had diſarmed her, and ſhe could protect him no longer.</q> But nothing went ſo near him, as the anſwer of <persName rend="italic">Aſcletarion</persName> the Aſtrologer, and the accident which enſued thereupon. For he being accuſed of having publiſhed his Predictions according to the Rules of Art, and not denying it at all, he asked him if he knew his own fortune, and could tell what would become of himſelf; the Aſtrologer replyed, <q rend="italic">That in a ſhort time he ſhould be devoured by Dogs.</q> To convince the World, as he thought of his error, he cauſed him immediately to be killed, and burned with as much care as was poſſible; whilſt they were obeying his Commands, a fu-
      <pb n="491"/>
      rious tempeſt aroſe on a ſudden, threw down the Funeral Pile, and blew off the body; and the Dogs by accident caught it up, and eat it before it was half burnt; Which the Mimick <persName rend="italic">Latinus</persName> having ſeen as he paſt by, he told <persName rend="italic">Domi-tian</persName> as he ſate at ſupper that night, amongſt the reſt of his ſto-ries of that day.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      16. The day before he was killed, having commanded that ſome Nectarines which were brought him then, ſhould be ſet up againſt the morrow, he added theſe words, <q rend="italic">if it be my fortune to uſe them;</q> and turning about to ſuch as were near him, he told them, <q rend="italic">That the next day the Moon would appear bloody in <placeName rend="italic">Aquarius</placeName>, and that ſomething would be done, which ſhould be the diſcourſe of all the world.</q> A-bout midnight he was ſo affrighted, he leaped out of his bed. The next morning he ſent for an Aſtrologer which was come out of <placeName rend="italic">Germany</placeName>, and condemned him to death, becauſe having conſulted him about the Conſequences of thoſe lightnings, he made anſwer that they portended a revolution in the State.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      It happened alſo that ſcratching a Bile he had upon his forehead, till the Blood ran down upon his face, he uttered theſe words with a ſigh, <q rend="italic">And would to God this were all!</q> Then he inquired what a Clock it was, and they told him by deſign it was twelve, inſtead of eleven, which was the hour he apprehended. At which being over joyed, as if the danger was paſt, he haſted with all ſpeed to his Bath, for the refreſhment of his Body; but <persName rend="italic">Parthenius</persName> his principal Chamberlain carried him another way, pretending he had got a perſon in his Chamber, who had matter of great importance to diſcover to him, and ſuch as was not to be deferred, up-on which he commanded all people to withdraw, and re-tiring into his Chamber, was murdered as ſoon as he came in.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      17. The Order of the Conſpiracy, and the manner of its execution, are related as follow. Whilſt the Conſpi-rators were in diſpute amongſt themſelves, what courſe they ſhould take, and whether they ſhould aſſail him in his Bath, or at Supper; <persName rend="italic">Stephanus</persName> the Procurator of <persName rend="italic">Domi-tella</persName> (who at that time ſtood accuſed for embezeling certain Moneys) tendred them his aſſiſtance. To take off all ſuſpicion he pretended ſomething was amiſs in his left arm, and for ſome days kept it wrapt up in Wool, and
      <pb n="492"/>
      ſwath'd, into which having conveyed a dagger, he entred into the Chamber, and under pretence of diſcovering a Plot, he preſented the Emperour with a Liſt, and whilſt he was reading it with great horror and aſtoniſhment, <persName rend="italic">Ste-phanus</persName> ſtruck his dagger into his privities.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      <persName rend="italic">Domitian</persName> finding himſelf wounded, endeavoured to defend himſelf, but <persName rend="italic">Clodianus</persName> (who had the command of a wing of the Army) <persName rend="italic">Maximus Parthenius</persName>, (one of his Freemen) <persName rend="italic">Saturius</persName> (a principal officer belonging to his Chamber) with one of the Gladiators, fell all upon him, gave him ſeven deſperate wounds, and killed him. A young lad who had the keep-ing of the Chamber where the <persName rend="italic">Lares</persName> or Houſhold Gods were kept, had the fortune to be by, and he added this to what we have ſaid before, that upon the firſt wound <persName rend="italic">Do-mitian</persName> receiv'd, he called to him to reach him a dagger which was under his pillow, and to call the Servants, but that there was nothing of the Dagger to be found, but the Hilt, and the doors all locked faſt, and ſecure. That the Emperour ha-ving ſtruggled for ſome time with <persName rend="italic">Stephanus</persName> at laſt got him down, ſometimes ſtriving to wreſt the Dagger out of his hand, and ſometimes, (though they were all mangled and cut) to thruſt his eyes out with his his fingers.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
    <p>
      He was ſlain the eighteenth of September, in the five and fortieth year of his age, and the fifteenth of his Empire. His body being carried out upon a Bier, as a perſon of the meaneſt condition, by common Bearers; <persName rend="italic">Phillis</persName>, his Nurſe, burned it at a Country houſe ſhe had, not far from the Town, in the Highway, called <placeName rend="italic">Latina</placeName>. But his aſhes ſhe carried private-ly into the Temple of the <persName rend="italic">Flavians</persName>, and mingled them with the aſhes of <persName rend="italic">Julia</persName> the Daughter of <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName>, which ſhe had nurſt alſo.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      18. His ſtature was Tall, his Countenance modeſt, though ſanguine, his eyes large, but dull and dim, he was handſome, and well proportioned in all his limbs, except his feet, for his toes were of the ſhorteſt, but his youth and his beauty went away together, for afterwards he grew bald, his belly great, and his leggs very ſmall and lean, by a long fit of ſickneſs: He was ſo affected with the o-pinion the World had of his comlineſs, that he boaſted of it one day before the Senate in theſe words; <q rend="italic">Hither-to you have not diſapproved either of my heart, or proportion.</q> However he was ſo much diſſatisfied with his baldneſs,
      <pb n="493"/>
      that if any other perſon was reflected upon by ir, either in jeſt or in earneſt, he took it to himſelf, aad interpreted it as ſpoken in contempt of him.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Yet in a Book which he dedicated to one of his Friends, about the preſervation of the Hair, he uſed theſe words both for his, and his own conſolation; <q rend="italic">Seeſt thou not how proper and handſome I am? yet my hair has the ſame deſtiny with yours, and I take it patiently that it grows old whilſt I am in my youth: But you muſt know, as nothing is more graceful, ſo nothing is more tranſitory than beauty.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      19. Living as he did in delicacy and eaſe, no wonder if he was impatient of labour, and ſeldom made uſe of his feet: In his Military Expeditions, ſometimes he went on Horſe-back, but moſt commonly in his Litter. Of all the Exerciſes of Arms, he delighted eſpecially in ſhooting with an Arrow, in which he was ſo excellent, that many have ſeen him kill hundreds of ſeveral ſorts of Beaſts in his Park near <placeName rend="italic">Alba</placeName>, with ſuch incomparable art, he would fix two Arrows in their heads at two ſhoots, as if they had been two horns: Sometimes he would ſet a Boy at a good diſtance, to expand the palm of his right hand for a mark, and would ſhoot his Arrows ſo skilfully, they ſhould all paſs betwixt his fingers without doing him any harm.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      20. At the beginning of his Empire, he neglected all kind of Literature, though he was at great expence in re-pairing the Libraries which had been burnt, and recover-ing Copies of ſuch Books as were loſt, ſending on purpoſe as far as <placeName rend="italic">Alexandria</placeName> to tranſcribe and correct them, Never-theleſs he never applied himſelf either to Hiſtory, or Poetry, or even to ſuch Compoſitions as neceſſity requir'd. Beſides the Acts and Commentaries of <persName rend="italic">Tiberius</persName>, he never read any thing, and was beholding to the invention of other people, for all his Letters, Orations, and Edicts. However his diſ-courſe was not unelegant, and ſometimes things came from him very remakable; <q rend="italic">I wiſh</q> (ſaid he) <q rend="italic">I was but as hand-ſome, as <persName rend="italic">Metius</persName> thinks himſelf:</q> Seeing ones head mingled with yellowiſh and white hair, he cry'd, <q rend="italic">It was nothing but Snow and Mead mix'd together.</q>
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      He pronounced alſo, <q rend="italic">That the moſt miſerable condition in the whole world, was the con-dition of a Prince, for that no body would believe he had diſ-covered a Conſpiracy, unleſs he was killed.</q> As often as his
      <pb n="494"/>
      affairs would give him leave, he diverted himſelf at Dice, even on Working-dayes and in the Mornings. He bathed himſelf likewiſe in the day time, and eat plentifully at Din-ner; but at Supper he ſeldom took any thing but a Mati-an Apple, and one ſingle draught out of a narrow mouth'd Vial: He Feaſted often, and magnificently, but was ſeldom long at the Table, never after Sun-ſetting, nor permitted any Collations; for till he went to bed, he did nothing but walk privately by himſelf.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      21. He was ſo much addicted to wantonneſs, he made it his recreation, and called it his <q rend="italic">Bed wreſtling</q>. 'Tis report-ed he pulled the hair off of his Concubines with Pincers, and that he ſwum amongſt the moſt ordinary Proſtitutes. Being obliged by his Marriage with <persName rend="italic">Domitia</persName>, he conſtant-ly refuſed his Brothers Daughter which was offered him likewiſe; yet not long after, when ſhe was married to another man, he debauched her of his own accord, though his Bro-ther <persName rend="italic">Titus</persName> was alive: At length both her Father and Huſ-band being dead, he loved her very ardently, and owned it to the World; yet when he had got her with Child, he forced her to miſcarry, which was the cauſe of her death.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>
      22. His death was indifferent to the people, but the Soul-diers bewailed it exceedingly, who immediately upon the news endeavoured to Canonize him for a God; and had they had any body to head them, had doubtleſly revenged it, as they did not long afterwards, when they demanded the Authors of that Murder, to be executed. But on the contrary, the joy of the Senate was ſo great, that being aſ-ſembled in haſte, they could not forbear inveighing and re-viling him in the moſt contumelious manner imaginable, commanding Ladders immediately to be brought, his Scut-cheons and Images to be taken down, and broke to pieces be-fore their faces; and at laſt decreed, that all Inſcriptions ſhould be razed, and all Memorials of him aboliſhed.
    </p>
  </div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
    <p>
      Not many months before he was murdered, a Crow ſpake theſe words in the <placeName rend="italic">Capitol</placeName>, <foreign rend="italic">ἔται πάντα καλῶς</foreign>, <q rend="italic">All ſhall be well</q>; which was interpreted by ſome body in this manner.
      <pb n="495"/>
      <foreign rend="italic"></foreign>

      <quote rend="italic" xml:lang="lat"><l>Nuper Tarpeio quæ ſedit culmine Cornix,</l>
<l>Eſt bene, non potuit dicere: dixit, erit.</l></quote>
<quote><l>On the <placeName rend="italic">Terpeian</placeName> Mount the Crow did tell,</l>
<l>Though all yet is not, all yet will be well.</l></quote>


      Some report alſo, that <persName rend="italic">Domitian</persName> himſelf having dreamt that he had a certain Bunch or Excreſcence of Gold growing out behind his neck, he concluded it was a certain preſage, that the Commonwealth would be more happy and flouriſhing after his death; and indeed it fell out accordingly not long after, by the prudence and moderation of the Princes which ſucceeded him. FINIS.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>
    
        </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>