<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Libation Bearers</title>
        <title>The tragedies of Aeschylus</title>
        <author>Aeschylus</author>
        <editor role="translator">Theodore Alois Buckley</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Translator credited as</resp>
          <name>Theodore Alois Buckley (1825–1856)</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Gregory Crane</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder>Volunteer</funder>
      </titleStmt>

      <!-- Added series -->
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">Bohn’s classical library</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Series publisher</resp>
          <name>Henry G. Bohn</name>
        </respStmt>
      </seriesStmt>

      <extent>About 90Kb</extent>

      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence target="https://www.hathitrust.org/rights/public-domain">Public domain (U.S.)</licence>
          <p>Digitized copy served via HathiTrust.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Aeschylus</author>
            <title>The tragedies of Aeschylus</title>
            <title type="sub">Literally translated, with critical and illustrative notes, and an introduction</title>
            <editor role="translator">Theodore Alois Buckley</editor>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Bohn</publisher>
              <date when="1849">1849</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="series">Bohn’s classical library</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="extent">xx, 234 p.; front.; 19 cm</biblScope>
          </monogr>
          <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/hvd.32044005046321">HathiTrust handle</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation marks="none"/>
      </editorialDecl>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="l"
                     matchPattern="(\w+)"
                     replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div//tei:l[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts lines</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-23" who="GRC">New file created drawing metadata from the HathiTrust record for Buckley (1849); series noted as Bohn’s classical library.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <pb n="95"/>
       <div type="translation"
              xml:lang="eng"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg006.perseus-eng2">
      <pb n="146"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="146"/>
      <ab>
        <title type="sub">THE CHOEPHORI</title>
      </ab>
      <ab>
        <title type="sub">ARGUMENT.</title>
      </ab>
      <p>ORESTES, returning from Phocis, recognizes his sister offering libations at the tomb of Agamemnon, and with her concerts a plan for revenging their father's death. Encouraged by the ill-omened dream of Clytemnestra, he resolves to enter the palace with his companion Pylades, and having deceived Clytemnestra with a pretended account of his death, he wreaks vengeance upon her and Ægisthus. The play concludes with his horror at the deed, and determination to go to Delphi to receive purification.</p>
      <ab>
        <title type="sub">PERSONS REPRESENTED.</title>
      </ab>
      <castList>
        <castItem>
          <role>ORESTES</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>ELECTRA</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>CLYTEMNESTRA</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>ÆGISTHUS</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>A NURSE</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>A DOMESTIC</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>CHORUS OF CAPTIVE TROJAN WOMEN</role>
        </castItem>
      </castList>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="1" end-line="21">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>MERCURY of the shades! presiding over the power delegated from the sire <ref n="146.1">1</ref>, be thou a saviour and ally to me beseeching it; for I am come into this land, and I return from exile <ref n="146.2">2</ref>. And over this mound of his sepulchre too I call upon my father to listen, to give ear <ref n="146.3">3</ref>. * * * * * * * * * * * * * a ringlet cherished in honour of
          <note type="footnote" n="146.1">1 <bibl><bibl>Aristophanes, <title>Ran. 1141</title></bibl></bibl>, makes <bibl>Euripides</bibl> quibble at the meaning of <quote xml:lang="grc">πατρω̃α κράη,</quote> which might mean Agamemnon's realm.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="146.2">2 On this <bibl><bibl>Euripides</bibl></bibl> observes, <quote xml:lang="grc">δὶς ταυτὸν ἡμῖν εἶπεν ὁ σοφὸς Αἰσχύλος.</quote> But Æsehylus, defends this on the grounds— <quote xml:lang="grc">φεύγων ἀνὴρ ἥκει τε καὶ κατέρχεται.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="146.3">3 <bibl>Bacchus, ibid</bibl>., gives this facetious reason: <quote xml:lang="grc">τεθνηκόσιν γὰρ ἔλεγεν, ὦ μοχθηρὲ σὺ, οἷς οὐδὲ τρὶς λέγοντες ἐξικνόυμεθα.</quote>
          </note>

      <pb n="147"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="147"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="9-51"/>
    Inachus <ref n="147.1">1</ref> and this, the second, expressive of my sorrow. * * * * * * * * * * * * * What is it that I see? what is this concourse of women [coming] hither conspicuous in sable weeds? To what calamity shall I refer it? Is it that a new death <ref n="147.2">2</ref> hath happened in the palace? or am I right in guessing that these maidens are conveying libations to my father-a propitiation for the departed <ref n="147.3">3</ref>? It is nothing else; for I think I see my sister Electra advancing, distinguished by grievous sorrow. O Jupiter! grant me to avenge the fate of my father, and be thou a willing ally to me! Pylades, stand we apart, that I may clearly learn what means this suppliant procession of women.</p>
   </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="22" end-line="83">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>I am come forth from the palace, sent as an escort to the drink-offering with the noise of sharp clapping of hands. Marked is my cheek with bloody gashes, the furrow newly cut by my nail: for ever is my heart fed on wailings; and the rendings of tissues ruining the vesture, make a noise through my sorrows, the breast-protecting robes being torn through smileless woes. For a thrilling, hair-stiffening panic, the dream-prophet of the house, breathing wrath in the midst of slumbers, echoed an outcry full fearfully at dead of night from the inmost apartments, falling heavy on the chambers of the women. Interpreters too of these dreams, bound to veracity, declared on the part of the gods, that those beneath the earth are complaining full angerly and are wroth against their murderers. Such an unkind kindness devising as an averter of ills, O Earth, mother! does the godless woman send me. But I dread to utter this word: for what atonement is there for blood that has fallen on the ground? Alas for the all-unhappy hearth! Alas for the ruin of the dwelling! A gloom uncheered by the sun, abhorred of
          <note type="footnote" n="147.1">1 Perhaps we may supply <quote xml:lang="grc">φέρωδὲ,</quote> with Erfurdt. The custom of consecrating the hair to a deity, or to the river gods (for rivers are spoken of as personified), is learnedly illustrated by <bibl>Stanley</bibl> and <bibl>Blomfield</bibl>. Cf. <bibl><bibl>Censorinus de die nat. § I</bibl></bibl>. "<cit><quote xml:lang="lat">Quidam etiam pro cætera bona corporis valetudine crinem deo sacrum pascebant</quote></cit>," where Lindenbroge's note deserves consulting. <bibl><bibl>Pausan. VII. 41</bibl></bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">oi Φιγαλέων παῖδες ἀποκερονται τῷ ποταμῳ̃ τὰς κόμας.</quote> For a probable supplement of this passage see Dind.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="147.2">2 <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>, in his notes, however, reads <quote xml:lang="grc">πη̃μα,</quote> calamity.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="147.3">3 The dative <quote xml:lang="grc">μειλίγμασιν</quote> is vainly defended. See <bibl>Blomfield</bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <pb n="148"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="148"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="52-81"/>
      <p>mortals, hides the house through the death of the master. And majesty, which was in the olden time unconquered, invincible, unassailed, making its way through the ears and the mind of the people, is now banished. And somebody <ref n="148.1">1</ref> is terrified. But to be prosperous-this is both a god and more than a god among mortals. And the swift turn of Justice visits some in daylight, and some lingering burst forth with violence in the interval of darkness, and some impracticable night possesses <ref n="148.2">2</ref>. Because of the blood that hath been drunk by the fostering earth, gore that cries for vengeance, is fast clotted so as never to be washed away. A piercing bitter curse destroys <ref n="148.3">3</ref> the author of the all-sufficing malady. But [as] there is no remedy for maidenhood <ref n="148.4">4</ref> to its violater, [so] all the streams, moving in one course, flow in vain <ref n="148.5">5</ref> to purify murder of the foul hand. But 'tis my lot, for the gods have visited me with the hardship of a captured city; for they brought me to a slave's estate afar from the house of my fathers, to acquiesce in the things that seem fit to the lords over my life, just or unjust, [the deeds] of mastering the loathing of my soul, those who are violently borne along <ref n="148.6">6</ref>.
        <note type="footnote" n="148.1">1 i. e. "<quote xml:lang="eng">sunt qui metuant.</quote>" -<bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>.
        </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="148.2">2 I have followed <bibl>Dindorf</bibl>'s text literally. <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl>'s</bibl> explanation hovers strangely between allegory and grammar. <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl> himself would read, partly from the conjecture of Sophianus, <quote xml:lang="grc">τοὺς .... βρύει χρονιζοντ'</quote> axi, throwing out <quote xml:lang="grc">μένει</quote> and <quote xml:lang="grc">ἄκρατος</quote> with <bibl>Schutz</bibl>. <bibl>Paley</bibl>, with much elegance, <quote xml:lang="grc">τοὺς .... μένει χρονίζοθ' άσυχα̃.</quote> I myself am all uncertainty, and have made the version purposely literal, in preference to filling up the meaning with bracketed glosses.
        </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="148.3">3 See <bibl><bibl>Stanley</bibl></bibl>. <quote xml:lang="grc">βρύειν</quote> after <quote xml:lang="grc">νόσου</quote> has been thrown out by <bibl><bibl>Hermann</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>, I think, wrongly. See <bibl>Peile</bibl> and <bibl>Paley</bibl>.
        </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="148.4">4 Cf. <bibl><bibl>Sept. c. Th. 454</bibl></bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">πωλικω̃ν ἑδωλίων.</quote> There is something similar in <bibl><bibl>Suppl. 227</bibl></bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">πω̃ς ἂν γαμω̃ν ἂκονσαν ἂκοντος πάρα</quote> (?) <quote xml:lang="grc">άγνὸς γένιτ' ἄν</quote> ;
        </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="148.5">5 In the absence of better suggestions, 1 follow <bibl>Heath's</bibl> emendation. The sentiment has been so copiously illustrated, especially from Shake-spere, that I will only quote <bibl><bibl>Tasso, Gerus. Lib. XVIII. 8</bibl></bibl>, - <quote xml:lang="lat">Che sei de la caligine del mondo, E de la carne tu di modo asperso ; Che '1 Nilo, o '1 Gange, ò l' Ocean profondo Non ti potrebbe far candido, e terso.</quote>
        </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="148.6">6 This passage is very unsatisfactory, on account of the double hyperbaton (<quote xml:lang="grc">ἀνάγκαν γὰρ</quote> and <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐκ γὰρ οἲκων</quote>), and the words <quote xml:lang="grc">πρέποντ ἀρχαις. ϐίου.</quote> I have followed <bibl>Peile</bibl> in rendering the passage, but, with <bibl>Paley</bibl>, I must confess my doubts as to the possibility of giving a reasonable trans-lation of the words as they now stand.
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb n="149"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="149"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="81-113"/>
      <p>But I weep beneath my robes at the hapless fortunes of my masters, chilled with secret sorrows.</p>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="84" end-line="105">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Ye captive maids, ye garnishers of the palace, since ye are present as my associates in this suppliant procession, be my counsellors in this matter: when I pour these funereal drink-offerings on the tomb, how shall I say what is well-pleasing? how am I to make my prayer to my father? Shall I say that I bring them from a dear wife to a dear husband? from my mother, forsooth <ref n="149.1">1</ref>? I dare not say it; and I know not what to say, as I pour this thick libation on the tomb of my father. Or shall I say this saying, as is the custom of mortals, that he would recompense those who send these chaplets and this gift with a [gift] worthy their misdeeds <ref n="149.2">2</ref> or, in silence, ingloriously, even as my father perished, am I, pouring this out, a draught drunk by the earth, to move backwards <ref n="149.3">3</ref>, like one who casts forth offscourings, as I fling from me the vessel, with eyes never looking back? In this deliberation of mine, my friends, do ye be sharers, for we hold a common object of abhorrence in the house. Hide not your feelings within your heart, through fear of any one. For Destiny awaits alike the free man, and him that is mastered by the hand of another. Tell me if thou knowest aught better than this?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="106" end-line="107">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Reverencing the tomb of thy sire as though an altar, I will speak, for thou biddest me, the sentiment of my soul.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="108" end-line="108">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Speak, even as thou sayest thou reverencest <ref n="149.4">4</ref> the tomb of my father.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="109" end-line="109">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Invoke, as thou pourest the offering, holy things upon the well-wishers.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="110" end-line="110">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>And who are these friends whom I am to speak of?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="111" end-line="111">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>First thyself, and whosoever abhors Ægisthus.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="112" end-line="112">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Shall I then offer this prayer both for myself and for thee?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="113" end-line="113">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Do thou thyself, already informed on these points, take counsel.
          <note type="footnote" n="149.1">1 These words are spoken indignantly, after a slight pause, as <bibl>Butler</bibl> observes.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="149.2">2 I follow <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>, supplying <quote xml:lang="grc">δόσιν</quote> with <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐπαξίαν,</quote> from <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀντιδου̃ναι.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="149.3">3 See <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="149.4">4 Such is the force of <quote xml:lang="grc">ύδέσω.</quote> See <bibl>Paley</bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <pb n="150"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="150"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="114-143"/>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="114" end-line="114">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Whom else then shall I further add to this present company?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="115" end-line="115">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Be mindful of Orestes, albeit he is abroad.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="116" end-line="116">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Well, and in no slight degree hast thou instructed me in this.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="117" end-line="117">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Now to the guilty, mindful of the murder—</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="118" end-line="118">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>What am I to say? teach me unskilful, pointing out the way.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="119" end-line="119">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>That there might come to them some divinity, or some one of mortals.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="120" end-line="120">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Meanest thou a judge, or an avenger?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="121" end-line="121">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Say thou simply, one that shall slay in turn.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="122" end-line="122">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>And are these things such as may religiously befall me from the gods?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="123" end-line="123">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>How not, to requite an enemy with evils?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="124" end-line="151">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Mercury of the realms below * * * * after summoning the divinities beneath the earth to give ear to my prayers, those that watch over the house of my fathers, and Earth herself, that brings forth all things, and, after rearing them, again receives their produce; and I pouring forth these lustral waters do say, calling on my sire: mortals <ref n="150.1">1</ref>, have pity on me, and on the dear Orestes, so that we may restore <ref n="150.2">2</ref> him to the palace. For now, sold as it were by <ref n="150.3">3</ref> her that bare us, we are outcasts, and for a husband she hath taken in exchange Ægisthus, who was accomplice in thy murder. And I, indeed, am as a slave, and from thy substance Orestes is an outcast, while they in mighty haughtiness are wantoning in the fruits of thy labours. But I make my prayer to thee that Orestes may come hither with some success, and do thou. O my sire, give ear to me, and to myself vouchsafe that I may be by far more chaste than my mother, and more pious in hand. For us [I offer] these prayers; but to the adversaries I pray that thou wouldst appear, O my sire, as an avenger, and that those who killed may through justice die in turn. These things I
          <note type="footnote" n="150.1">1 i. e. to Agamemnon. See <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="150.2">2 I have followed <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl>, (and except that they take <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀνάξομεν</quote> closely with '<quote xml:lang="grc">Ορέστην</quote>) <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>. <bibl><bibl>Klausen</bibl></bibl> rightly exploded the notion of <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀνάξομεν</quote> being from <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀνάσσω.</quote> It is from <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀνάγω.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="150.3">3 I strongly suspect that <quote xml:lang="grc">πως</quote> is a repetition from the preceding line, and that we ought to read <quote xml:lang="grc">πεπραμένοι γὰρ νυ̃ν κακω̃ς ἀλώμεθα.</quote>
          </note>


      <pb n="151"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="151"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="145-173"/>
      <p></p>interpose in my good prayer, uttering for them this evil imprecation. And be thou a sender of the blessings we implore to us in this upper world, with the favour of the gods, and of earth, and of triumphant justice. And after such prayers as these I pour forth these drink-offerings; and 'tis meet that you peal forth the dirge of the dead, should make it teem with shrieks.</p>
      <stage>[ELECTRA goes to the tomb.]</stage></sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="152" end-line="162">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Shed ye the pattering death-tear <ref n="151.1">1</ref> for the dead sovereign, now that drink-offerings have been poured out upon this defence against both evil and good by way of averting <ref n="151.2">2</ref> unprayed-for pollution. And do thou, O give ear, give ear, O master, from thy darkling spirit. Woe! woe! woe! woe! alas! what stout Scythian spearman is deliverer of the house, and Mars that in the conflict brandishes with his hands the curved darts, and wields hilted weapons in close combat?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="163" end-line="164">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p><stage>[returning to the Chorus.]</stage> My father now has the earth-drunk libations <ref n="151.3">3</ref>; and do ye share with me in a new discourse.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="165" end-line="165">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Tell it: but my heart is throbbing with terror.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="166" end-line="166">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>I see here a shorn ringlet <ref n="151.4">4</ref> of hair on the sepulchre.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="167" end-line="167">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>From what man or deep-bosomed maid?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="170" end-line="170">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>This is an obvious matter for any one to form an opinion upon.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="171" end-line="171">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>How then may I, aged, learn from thee, my junior?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="172" end-line="172">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>There is no one who could have cut it off except myself.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="173" end-line="173">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>No-for they are enemies to whom it naturally belongs to mourn by offerings of hair.
          <note type="footnote" n="151.1">1 I follow <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl>'s</bibl> version. If the metre will permit it, (and it will, if we follow <bibl>Blomfield</bibl>'s arrangement,) I should prefer reading <quote xml:lang="grc">όλομένω</quote> twice, a repetition elegant in such a passage.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="151.2">2 This whole interpretation is, in substance, <bibl><bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl>'s</bibl></bibl>. Perhaps <quote xml:lang="grc">ἒρυμα κακω̃ν κεδνω̃ν</quote> r' may be said of the tomb of Agamemnon, inasmuch as it was fraught with blessings for Orestes and Electra, but with curses for Clytemnestra. Cf. vss. Ill, 12, 115, 117, 119—21, which seem to confirm the supposition. I do not, however, advance this as a certainty.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="151.3">3 The line which follows, <quote xml:lang="grc">κήρυξ, μέγιστε τω̃ν ἂνω τε</quote> icat <quote xml:lang="grc">κἀτω,</quote> should probably be placed before v. 124, as <bibl><bibl>Hermann</bibl></bibl> has shown. So also <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="151.4">4 On this <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀναγνώρισις,</quote> see <bibl><bibl>Aristot. Poet. § xvi</bibl></bibl>. Compare <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl>'s</bibl> note, and <bibl><bibl>Schlegel, Lect. xi</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <pb n="152"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="152"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="174-211"/>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="174" end-line="174">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>And certainly this is of a very similar hue to behold.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="175" end-line="175">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>To what tresses? for this I fain would know.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="176" end-line="176">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>It is exceedingly like in appearance to my own.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="177" end-line="177">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Is this then a clandestine offering from Orestes?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="178" end-line="178">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>It does very much resemble his ringlets.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="179" end-line="179">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>And how did he venture to come hither?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="180" end-line="180">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>He sent this shorn ringlet as a pleasing offering to his father.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="181" end-line="182">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>No less is this which thou tellest me a subject for tears, if he is never to touch this land with his foot.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="183" end-line="211">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>O'er me too there hath come a heart's surge of bitterness; and I was smitten as with a piercing shaft. And from my eyes there are falling the unrestrained thirsting drops of a sad winter's flood, as I behold this lock: for how can I suppose that any other of the citizens owns this hair? And of a surety she that murdered him did not cut it off—my mother I mean, who has a godless spirit towards her children by no means in accordance with her name. Yet how can I openly yield assent to this conclusion, that this is an offering of honour from Orestes, of all mortals to me most dear? But I am fawned upon by hope. Alas! would to heaven that it had an intelligent voice, like a messenger, that I might not be agitated by distracted thoughts <ref n="152.1">1</ref>; but it were clear for me either to spurn this lock of hair when clearly recognized, if indeed it had been severed from the head of a foe, or that, if it claim kin to me, it might be able to bewail with me an ornament to this tomb and an honour to my father <ref n="152.2">2</ref>. But we invoke the gods, who know in what tempests, like vessels, we are tossed to and fro; and if it is our destiny to attain safety, a great stock might be produced from a tiny seed. And in very truth here are tracks too, a second sign, like to feet, and bearing a resemblance to my own. For there are also here two prints of footsteps, both of himself and of some fellow-traveller. The heels and the impress of the tendons being measured, coincide exactly with my footsteps. But pains (as of a woman in travail) and prostration of mind is upon me.
          <note type="footnote" n="152.1">1 <quote xml:lang="grc">δίφροντις.</quote> Cf. <bibl><bibl>Apul. Met. ix</bibl></bibl>, p. 189, "<cit><quote xml:lang="lat">miroque mentis salo et cogitationum dissensione, misellus in diversas sententias carpebatur, ac distrahebatur</quote></cit>." <bibl><bibl>Q. Curtius III., 6</bibl></bibl>, "<cit><quote xml:lang="lat">diu animo in diversa versato</quote></cit>."
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="152.2">2 On the accusative see <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <pb n="153"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="153"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="212-234"/>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="212" end-line="213">ORESTES</speaker>
        <stage>Orestes coming forward.<ref n="153.1"/></stage>
        <p>Pray thou, uttering to the gods prayers that shall bring their accomplishment, that what remains may turn out well.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="214" end-line="214">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>But what have I now attained as respects the favour of the gods?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="215" end-line="215">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>You have come to the sight of those whom for a long time you used to pray to see.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="216" end-line="216">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>And on whom of mortals is it that thou knowest me to have called?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="217" end-line="217">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>I know that thou hast full oft had sad longings for Orestes.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="218" end-line="218">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>And what, then, do I attain the object of my prayers?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="219" end-line="219">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>I am he: search not for any one more dear to thee than I am.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="220" end-line="220">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>But, stranger, art thou not weaving some trick around me?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="221" end-line="221">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Truly then I am framing schemes against myself.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="222" end-line="222">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>But thou fain wouldst scoff at my calamities?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="223" end-line="223">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Ay, and at my own also, if indeed at thine.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="224" end-line="224">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>As being Orestes, am I then addressing thee with these words?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="225" end-line="234">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Nay, now, when thou seest me in person, thou hardly knowest me, but when thou didst see your brother's shorn ringlet of mourning hair which corresponded with thine own head, and wast tracing thy footsteps in the track of my feet, thou wast all of a flutter, and didst fancy thou sawest me. Consider the ringlet of my hair, after placing it on the part whence I clipped it; and behold this web, the work of thy hand, and the strokes of the shuttle, and on it the delineation of wild beasts <ref n="153.2">2</ref>. Be yourself <ref n="153.3">3</ref>, and be not over-amazed in soul through joy, for I know that the dearest relatives are bitter foes to us twain.
          <note type="footnote" n="153.1">1 i. e. to the <quote xml:lang="grc">θυμέλη,</quote> which represented the tomb of Agamemnon (Genelli apud Müller, Eumenides, p. 256), and also the platform on which it was raised, and on which the chorus were standing. <bibl>Müller, ibid. p. 249, sqq.</bibl>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="153.2">2 See <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl>. I do not, however, agree with him in supposing that <quote xml:lang="grc">εἰς δὲ</quote> can be used adverbially, like <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐν δὲ.</quote> I should prefer reading <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐν δὲ</quote> with <bibl><bibl>Pauw</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl></bibl>, or perhaps <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔτι δὲ.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="153.3">3 See <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <pb n="154"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="154"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="235-274"/>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="235" end-line="245">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>O best-beloved care of thy father's house, thou deplored hope of a preserving seed, trusting in thy prowess, thou shalt recover the house of thy father. O delightful eye that enjoyest four shares [in my affections] <ref n="154.1">1</ref>: and needful it is that I should both address thee as a father, and the endearment of a mother devolves on thee,—(but she is most justly detested)- and of a sister that was barbarously sacrificed: but thou art my faithful brother, bringing dignity to me. Only may both Strength and Justice, with the third, the greatest of all, Jupiter, favour me!</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="246" end-line="263">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>O Jupiter, Jupiter! be thou a spectator of these things; and look upon the orphan brood of an eagle sire, that perished in the folds and coils of a dread serpent. On them bereft is hungry famine pressing, for [the brood] is not of full age to bring their father's prey to the nest. And so thou mayest behold both me and this maiden—I mean Electra—a progeny bereft of their father, both enduring the same banishment from their home. And, wert thou to abandon to destruction these, the offspring of a father that did thee sacrifice and honoured thee greatly, whence wouldst thou have the honour of the solemn festival from a like hand? Neither, wert thou to abandon to destruction the eagle's young, wouldst thou hereafter be able to send tokens well believed by mortals. Nor will this royal stock, if entirely withered, do thine altars service on days when oxen are sacrificed. Take care [of it], and raise from its low estate a mighty house, that now seems to have fallen very low.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="264" end-line="268">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>O children, saviours of your paternal hearth, keep silence, that none may hear you, my children, and, in pleasure for the tongue, report all to the rulers :-whom may I, some time or other, see dead amid the pitchy smoke of the flame!</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="269" end-line="305">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>The oracle of Loxias, great in its might, will not fail me, bidding me pass through this peril, and loudly cheering me on, and muttering out tempestuous curses beneath my fevered breast, should I not pursue the murderers of my father, directing me, maddened like a bull, to slay them in their turn
          <note type="footnote" n="154.1">1 "<quote xml:lang="lat">Affectionem ait suam naturalem in quatuor partes divisam, nempe erga patrem, matrem, sororem Iphigeniam, et fratrem Orestem, in unum jam collatam fuisse Orestem, quippe cum pater et soror mortui essent, mater exosa.</quote>" -<bibl><bibl>Stanley</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>


           <pb n="155"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="155"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="275-302"/>
      <p>with a penalty not paid in money <ref n="155.1">1</ref>; and he declared that [if I failed to do so] I should make this atonement in my soul, enduring many comfortless ills. For the soothing remedies for malignant evils [which arise] to mortals from the earth, these he declared should to us be maladies <ref n="155.2">2</ref>—leprosies that assail the flesh with fierce fangs, and entirely eat away its original nature; and that white hairs should sprout forth in this malady. And he spoke of my seeing clearly, as I guide my brow in the dark, other assaults of the Furies, produced by the blood of my father. For the darkling shaft of those beneath the earth, that comes from suppliants who have fallen by a kindred hand and phrenzy, and groundless terror by night, torments, harasses, and chases from the city the body that has been mangled by the brazen-forged scourge. And of such [he declares] that it is the doom neither to have any share of the festal bowl, nor of the liquor used in libations, and that a father's unseen wrath excludes him from altars, and that no one will receive nor dwell with him <ref n="155.3">3</ref>; but that unhonoured and abhorred of all, he should at length die, horribly wasted away <ref n="155.4">4</ref>, by a doom of utter destruction. To oracles such as these must I not give credence? Nay, if I did not give credence to them, the deed must be done; for many cravings coincide in one-both the commands of the god, and my great sorrow for my father, and the lack of substance moreover presses me—that my fellow-citizens, most highly
        <note type="footnote" n="155.1">1 i. e. by their own death, <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀποχρ. ζημ.</quote> has been taken to mean the loss of property sustained by Orestes (see Linwood), whence <bibl>Peile</bibl> conjectured <quote xml:lang="grc">γαυρουμένους.</quote> <bibl>Paley</bibl> properly denies the correctness of this signification, but refers the words to Orestes' suffering death, if he failed to avenge his father. I have ventured to remove the comma after <quote xml:lang="grc">λέγων,</quote> connecting <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀποχ</quote>· <quote xml:lang="grc">ζημ.</quote> with the notion of punishment that was to befall Clytemnestra and Ægisthus. <quote xml:lang="grc">Ταυρούμενον</quote> I would take by itself, = efferatum.
        </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="155.2">2 We are, for once, indebted to <bibl>Scholefield</bibl>, who is however wrong in limiting the meaning of <quote xml:lang="grc">δυσφρονων,</quote> to diseases, as the anger of the Erinnys and of the dead is clearly meant. I nevertheless incline to <bibl>Paley</bibl>'s view. See his note.
        </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="155.3">3 I follow <bibl><bibl><bibl>Porson</bibl>'s</bibl></bibl> interpretation. See <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>.
        </note>
        <note type="footnote" n="155.4">4 Literally, "pickled." The word is properly used of embalming. Had the commentators considered the shrivelled state produced by the action of salt upon the embalmed body, we might have been spared some absurd explanations of this passage.
        </note>
      </p>
      <pb n="156"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="156"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="303-345"/>
      <p>renowned of men, they that overthrew Troy with gallant spirit, may not thus live in subjection to two women:-for womanish is his mind; or if not, it shall full soon be known <ref n="156.1">1</ref>.</p>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="306" end-line="314">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>But, O ye mighty destinies, vouchsafe ye, by the will of Jove, that it may end in the way which Justice takes. "In return for a hostile speech be a hostile speech paid back"— cries Justice aloud as she exacts the debt,-" and in return for a murderous blow let him suffer a murderous blow." DOER MUST SUFFER; thus saith a thrice-antique saw.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="315" end-line="321">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Father, unhappy father, by saying or by doing what, could I, with a favouring breeze, waft from afar to thee, where thy couch [of death] holds thee, a light equal to darkness <ref n="156.2">2</ref>? But nevertheless <ref n="156.3">3</ref>, a glorious dirge for the patriarchs of Atreus' line, at all events, is deemed a grateful offering.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="322" end-line="331">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>My child, the consuming jaws of fire quell not the spirit of the dead, but afterwards he shows his wrath. But the dead is bewailed with a funeral moan, and he that wronged him is discovered. A righteous grief for fathers and for parents, stirred up on all sides, investigates the whole.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="332" end-line="339">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Give ear now, O my father, in turn, to my griefs of many tears. The lament of thy two children over thy tomb bewails thee. And thy sepulchre hath received us who are alike suppliants and outcasts. What of these things is well? and what is without ills? Is not ours an invincible calamity?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="340" end-line="344">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Yet, hereafter, out of this, God, if he be willing, may grant us sounds more jocund; and, instead of wailings o'er the tomb, a hymn of triumph in the royal halls may usher our newly-arrived <ref n="156.4">4</ref> friend.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="345" end-line="353">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Oh! would that beneath the walls of Ilion, smitten with
          <note type="footnote" n="156.1">1 The passive use of <quote xml:lang="grc">εἴσεται</quote> is sanctioned by <bibl>Erfurdt</bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="156.2">2 So <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>, i. e. "<quote xml:lang="eng">Although I cannot raise up the light of day in thy gloomy tomb, yet will I honour thee with duteous sorrows.</quote>" <quote xml:lang="grc">Φάος ἰσόμοιρον σκότῳ</quote> may be compared with <bibl><title>Soph. Electr. 87</title></bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">γη̃ς ἰσόμοιρ᾽ ἀὴρ,</quote> and more appositely with <bibl><title>Diog. Laert. xix, 26</title></bibl>, quoted by <bibl>Paley</bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">ἰσόμοιρα ειναι ἐν τῳ̃ κόσμῳ φω̃ς και σκότος.</quote> See also <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl>, who however reads <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀντίμοιρον</quote> with <bibl>Erfurdt</bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="156.3">3 See <bibl>Boyes</bibl>, and compare <bibl><title>Hamlet, i. 2</title></bibl>,— <quote xml:lang="eng">———— foul deeds will rise, Though all the earth o'erwbelm them, to men's eyes.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="156.4">4 Literally “newly mixed," i. e. " newly joined to us." <bibl><bibl><bibl>Porson</bibl> on Med. 138</bibl></bibl>, compares <bibl><bibl>Herodot. IV. 152</bibl></bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">φιλίαι συνικρήθησαν,</quote> and <bibl><bibl>VII. 151</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <pb n="157"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="157"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="346-381"/>
      <p>the spear by some of the Lycians, thou hadst been slain, my father! Having bequeathed renown to thy house, after establishing for the ways of thy children [through life] a condition worthy of notice, thou wouldst have occupied a sepulchre with a lofty mound in a land beyond the sea—in a manner that thy family might endure.</p>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="355" end-line="364">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Dear to those dear to thee who there gloriously fell, a prince of august majesty, distinguished beneath the earth, and a minister to the mightiest rulers in the shades below: for thou wast a king so long as thou wast alive, among <ref n="157.1">1</ref> those that fill their destined lot with [deeds of] hands, and the sceptre that wins the obedience of mortals <ref n="157.2">2</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="365" end-line="371">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Nor [would I that you], having fallen beneath the walls of Troy, my father, along with the other <ref n="157.3">3</ref> host, victims of the war, should have been buried beside Scamander's stream <ref n="157.4">4</ref>: but would that his slayers had thus been beaten down previously, so that one, unscathed by these horrors, might have learned their fatal catastrophe.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="372" end-line="379">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>These things of which thou speakest, my child, are more precious than gold, and surpassing e'en Hyperborean happiness, for thou art in anguish <ref n="157.5">5</ref>. But [enough], for the clang of this double scourge comes upon me: the protectors of these [children] are already beneath the earth: but the hands of the odious pair that rule are polluted; on their children too it bath fallen heavier <ref n="157.6">6</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="380" end-line="385">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>This pierced right through my ears, like a dart <ref n="157.7">7</ref>. O
          <note type="footnote" n="157.1">1 As "king of kings." See <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="157.2">2 This is rather a bold zeugma. <bibl><bibl>Jelf, Gk. Gr. § 895, Obs. I</bibl></bibl>. remarks, "<quote xml:lang="eng">in <foreign xml:lang="grc">μόϱιμονλάχοςχεϱο</foreign>ĩ<foreign xml:lang="grc">νπιμπλάντων</foreign>is implied the general notion of governing—this implies the notion of wielding the sceptre, in which sense it is carried on and applied to <foreign xml:lang="grc">βάκτϱον</foreign>.</quote>”
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="157.3">3 Correct <quote xml:lang="grc">ἄλλων</quote> to <quote xml:lang="grc">ἄλλῳ,</quote> with <bibl><bibl>Stanley</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="157.4">4 The prayer should evidently be continued. After reading <bibl><bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl>'s</bibl></bibl> long digression, I am only the more satisfied that <bibl>Abresch, <bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>, and <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl> rightly read <quote xml:lang="grc">τεθάφθαι.</quote>With the following words I have done my best, but they are both corrupt and mutilated.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="157.5">5 <bibl><bibl>Muller</bibl></bibl> would read <quote xml:lang="grc">οὺδύνασαιγάρ.</quote><bibl>Dindorf</bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">δύνσαιγάϱ.</quote>I prefer <quote xml:lang="grc">ὀδύνᾳσᾳ̃,</quote> with <bibl>Lachmann, <bibl>Peile</bibl>, <bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>, = "<quote xml:lang="lat">prisdolore.</quote>"
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="157.6">6 viz. <quote xml:lang="grc">τὸκακὸν,</quote> says <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>. I should prefer understanding <quote xml:lang="grc">ὄνειδος,</quote> partly implied in <quote xml:lang="grc">χέϱεςοὐχὅσιαι.</quote>The <quote xml:lang="grc">ὄνειδος</quote>would arise from Aga-memnon being as yet unrevenged.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="157.7">7 Compare <cit><bibl><title>Hamlet, iii. 3</title></bibl>,— <quote xml:lang="eng">QUEEN.—
                <l>O speak to me no more :</l>
                <l>These words like daggers enter in mine ears ;</l>
                <l>No more, sweet Hamlet.</l></quote></cit> See <bibl><bibl>Boyes, p. 19</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>


       <pb n="158"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="158"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="382-411"/>
      Jupiter, Jupiter, thou that sendest up Atè, the late avenger on the hardy hand of mortals that dares all deeds <ref n="158.1">1</ref>; nevertheless; retribution shall come upon parents.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="386" end-line="392">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Would that it were mine to chant a welcome to the bitter <ref n="158.2">2</ref> outcry of a man when he is smitten, and of a dying woman! for why am I to conceal how unceasingly there hovers [before]my mind, and before my face there sits <ref n="158.3">3</ref> violent passion of heart, wrathful loathing?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="393" end-line="399">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>And would that at length, some day or other, Jupiter, who makes us both to flourish <ref n="158.4">4</ref>, would put to his hand, alas alas! cleaving their heads. May security befall this realm! I ask for justice from the unrighteous. And do ye give ear that are had in honour by those beneath the earth <ref n="158.5">5</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="400" end-line="404">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>But it is a law, that drops of gore shed upon the ground call for other bloodshed in addition, for murder cries aloud to Erinnys <ref n="158.6">6</ref>, who brings on from those that perished before, another woe upon woe.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="405" end-line="409">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Whither, whither have the princedoms of the dead [fled]? Behold, ye potent curses of the departed, behold the relics of the Atreidæ in straits, and dishonoured in their dwellings. Whither should one betake one's self, O Jupiter!</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="410" end-line="417">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Again hath my heart throbbed while I listened to this lament of thine; and sometimes I am in despondency, and my vitals are overcast with gloom at thy speech, as I listen to it;
          <note type="footnote" n="158.1">1 <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl> rightly marks an aposiopesis.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="158.2">2 See <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl>'s</bibl> ingenious note. What “a torch-lit shout" is (see <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl>) I cannot tell.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="158.3">3 <bibl><bibl><bibl>Porson</bibl>'s</bibl></bibl> emendation <quote xml:lang="grc">ἧται</quote> is disputed by <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>, who retains <quote xml:lang="grc">ἄηται.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="158.4">4 More elegantly, <gloss xml:lang="eng">all-flourishing</gloss>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="158.5">5 The common reading will not bear this, nor any other construction. <bibl><bibl>Hermann</bibl></bibl> reads <quote xml:lang="grc">τὰ χθονίων τιτηνά</quote> (<quote xml:lang="eng">ye queens of the shades !</quote>), quoting <bibl><bibl>Hesychius</bibl></bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">τιτη̃ναι: βασιλίδες. τιτήνη: ἡ βασίλισσα. τίταξ,  ἔντιμος,ἢ δυνάστης· οἱ δὲ βασιλεύς.</quote> I have little doubt that this emendation is right, and that Demeter and Cora are meant. On the association of these goddesses with the Erinnys, see the interesting remarks of <bibl><bibl>Mulier, Eumen. § 81 and 86</bibl></bibl>, especially p. 202.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="158.6">6 Read <quote xml:lang="grc">λοιγὸς Ἐϱινὺν.</quote> <bibl>Paley</bibl>'s explanation of the common reading seems rather forced.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>

       <pb n="159"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="159"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="415-440"/>
      <p>and again in turn, having confidence in support, sorrow departs, so that things seem well to me <ref n="159.1">1</ref>.</p>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="418" end-line="422">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>And what should we all chance to be <ref n="159.2">2</ref>? Is it possible to wheedle the wrongs which we endure from those that gave us birth <ref n="159.3">3</ref>? But some things cannot be soothed; for, like a ravening wolf, my mind is from my mother implacable <ref n="159.4">4</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="429" end-line="433">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>She struck a martial strain; then, after the manner of a Cissian heroine <ref n="159.5">5</ref>, with a shower of blows wandering many ways might you see the outstretchings of her hand, dealt without intermission, from above, from afar; and with the stroke my buffeted, and all-wretched head resounds. Woe's me! woe's me! wretched all-daring mother, with wretched obsequies thou hadst the heart to inter a monarch without the attendance of his subjects, a hero unbewailed, without mournings <ref n="159.6">6</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="434" end-line="438">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Every word that thou speakest is to our shame. Ah me! surely then she shall expiate her degradation of my father, as far as the divinities are concerned, and as far as depends upon my hands; then may I perish, after having bereaved her [of life!]</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="439" end-line="443">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Furthermore too-that thou mayest know this he was mangled <ref n="159.7">7</ref>, and as she dealt with him, thus she buries him,
          <note type="footnote" n="159.1">1 As to translating this passage, it is out of the question. <bibl>Dindorf</bibl> has adopted the reading of Turnebus, condemned it in his note, but given us no further information. <bibl>Peile</bibl> and <bibl>Klausen</bibl> have hazarded conjectures, but that is all. I shall follow <bibl>Paley</bibl>, and say nothing.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="159.2">2 This is, of course, nonsense; but I cannot admire <bibl>Dindorf</bibl>'s taste in admitting Bothe's <quote xml:lang="grc">φάντες</quote> for <quote xml:lang="grc">πάντες.</quote>Read with <bibl>Paley</bibl>, <quote xml:lang="grc">τίδ’</quote><quote xml:lang="grc">ἂνεἰπόντεςτύχοιμεν,</quote>"<quote xml:lang="eng">what should we rightly say</quote>?”
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="159.3">3 Alter <bibl>Dindorf</bibl>'s careless punctuation.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="159.4">4 I have followed the suggestion of Linwood, s. v. <quote xml:lang="grc">ἄσαντος.</quote> He renders it, "<quote xml:lang="eng">'tis of no use to soothe me, for, like a ferocious wolf (inheriting the fury of its race), I derive from my mother an implacable spirit.</quote>"
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="159.5">5 But <bibl>Hermann</bibl>'s splendid emendation <quote xml:lang="grc">ἰηλεμιστριας</quote> (Hesych. <quote xml:lang="grc">θϱηνητρίας</quote>) must be followed. See <bibl>Paley</bibl>'s clever note.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="159.6">6 Compare <bibl><title>Hamlet, iv. 3</title></bibl>,— <quote xml:lang="eng">his obscure funeral, No trophy, sword, nor hatchment o'er his bones, No noble rite, nor formal ostentation.</quote> See the exquisite description of the funeral of Pompey in <bibl><title>Lucan VIII 29</title></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="159.7">7 See <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl>, Müller, Eumen</bibl> p. 155, note 8, and p. 231, where he
           remarks : "<quote xml:lang="eng">at Agamemnon's burial no Argive citizen, but only the train of Trojan female slaves was allowed to follow: .... the funeral mourning was conducted by them in the Asiatic style, and in their presence the expiatory right of cutting off the extremities from the corpse was performed by Clytemnestra, whilst Electra, the rightful conductress of the funeral procession, was scandalously debarred and excluded from the privilege.</quote>" Ths last translator utterly mistook the sense, supposing the common mutilation to be meant, as in the case of Deiphobus and Priam Cf. <bibl><title><bibl>Ausonius Epitaph. Her. 13 and 23</bibl></title></bibl>.
          </note>
      <pb n="160"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="160"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="441-473"/>
     eager to consummate for him a doom that should be an intolerable burthen to thy life. Thou hearest thy father's shameful sufferings.</p>
     </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="444" end-line="444">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Thou speakest of my father's doom.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="445" end-line="455">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Ay, and I was thrust forth, dishonoured, nothing worth; and barred out from the innermost apartment, like a too mischievous cur. I gave vent to tear-drops more readily than laughter, blithe if I might conceal my tearful woe. Listening to such things grave them within thy bosom, and make my tale pass through thine ears with the leisure step of thine understanding. For of these matters some are thus, and others seek thou thyself eagerly to learn. But it becomes thee to enter the lists with unflinching spirit.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="456" end-line="456">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>To thee do I make my appeal, lend thine aid, O father, to thy friends.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="458" end-line="460">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>This <ref n="160.1">1</ref> entire company too echoes the prayer: Oh corne into the light and give ear: and be thou present against thy foes.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="461" end-line="461">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Let Mars encounter Mars, DeèDicè <ref n="160.2">2</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="457" end-line="457">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>O gods, give a righteous decision.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="463" end-line="475">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>A shuddering creeps over me as I listen to your prayers. That which is foredoomed abides from the olden time, and to those that pray for it, it may come. Alas! struggle of kindred. and bloody discordant stroke of Atè! Alas for the sad intolerable woes! Alas for the sore hard to stanch! There is in the house a styptic remedy <ref n="160.3">3</ref> for these things, and that not from others from abroad, but from themselves, in that I pursue

          <note type="footnote" n="160.1">1 <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl> reads <quote xml:lang="grc">ἅδ’</quote>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="160.2">2 <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl> well compares the words of Meg Merrilies, <quote xml:lang="eng">Whence Bertram's might and Bertram's right Shall meet on Ellengowan's height.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="160.3">3 Read <quote xml:lang="grc">ἄκος</quote> for <quote xml:lang="grc">ἑκὰς</quote> with <bibl><bibl>Schutz</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <pb n="161"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="161"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="474-501"/>
      <p>the quarrel of blood shedeling <ref n="161.1">1</ref>; this is the song of the powers beneath the earth.</p>
      <p>But oh, ye immortal powers below, give ear to these orisons of ours, and graciously send to the children aid unto victory.</p>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="479" end-line="480">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Father, thou that didst die in no king-like manner, vouchsafe to me entreating <ref n="161.2">2</ref>, the mastery over thy house.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="481" end-line="482">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>I too, father, stand in the like need of thine aid, that I may escape after having brought a signal [doom] upon Ægisthus.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="483" end-line="485">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>For thus should the banquets that are established among mortals be dedicated to thee: but if not, at the funeral feasts <ref n="161.3">3</ref> thou wiit be unhonoured by savoury burnt-offerings from the earth.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="486" end-line="488">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>I too, from my entire substance, will bring to thee my nuptial offerings from the paternal dwelling; for beyond all things I will reverence this thy tomb.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="489" end-line="489">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>O earth, send up my father to overlook the conflict.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="490" end-line="490">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>O Proserpine, vouchsafe to us also victory of beauteous aspect.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="491" end-line="491">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Remember the bath in which thou wast bereaved of life, my father.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="492" end-line="492">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Remember too how strangely they enclosed thee in the net <ref n="161.4">4</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="493" end-line="493">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Thou wast ensnared in fetters not wrought of brass, my father.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="494" end-line="494">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Ay, and in folds of vestments foully planned.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="495" end-line="495">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Art thou not roused by these reproaches, father?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="496" end-line="496">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Dost thou not then rear erect thy dearest head?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="497" end-line="499">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Either despatch justice, an ally to thy friends, or grant [foesj to receive in recompense like injuries, if indeed after having been mastered thou wishest to triumph in thy turn.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="500" end-line="502">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>And give ear, my father, to this final ery of mine to thee. Beholding thy young ones here sitting on thy sepul-
          <note type="footnote" n="161.1">1 This appears to be the sense, taking the words according to their "-rensic usage. See <bibl><bibl>Muller</bibl>, Eum. § 43, p. 124, sqq.</bibl>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="161.2">2 But <quote xml:lang="grc">αἰτούμενος</quote>is probably correct. See <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="161.3">3 <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl> rightly prefers <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐμπύϱοισι,</quote>with <bibl><bibl>Canter</bibl></bibl>, and so <bibl>Dobree</bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>. On these feasts of the dead, See the learned notes of <bibl><bibl>Stanley</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl></bibl>. They formed a part of the lustral rites. See <bibl><bibl>Lomeier de Vet. Lustr. § xxxvii</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="161.4">4 But <quote xml:lang="grc">ώςἐκαίνισαν</quote>is the preferable reading = how they hanselled.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <pb n="162"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="162"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="502-532"/>
      <p>chre, take pity upon thy female, and likewise on thy male offspring; and do not utterly blot out this seed of the Pelopidæ. For thus thou art not dead; not even though thou didst die, for children are to the deceased reputation preserving; and like corks they buoy up the net, upholding the twist of the flaxen cord from the deep. Give ear! 'tis on thy behalf that laments such as these are poured forth, and thou thyself art saved by honouring this our petition.</p>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="510" end-line="513">CHORUS<ref n="162.1"/></speaker>
        <p>And in truth ye have lengthened out this your petition blamelessly, an honour to the tomb and to his unwept fate: for the rest, since thou hast been aroused in spirit to achieve it, do it forthwith, trying thy chance.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="503" end-line="509">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>It shall be so; but it is not out of my way to inquire how it comes that she sent drink-offerings, in consequence of what it is that she pays too late attention to an irreparable wrong? To the dead too, unconscious of it, a sorry offering was sent. I cannot guess the import of these gifts, but they are too small for the trespass. For though one were to make every libation in atonement for a single murder, the labour would be in vain: so runs the saying. But if thou knowest this, tell it to me wishing [to hear it].</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="523" end-line="525">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>I know it, my child, for I was by; for having been agitated by dreams and restless terrors of the night, the godless woman sent these drink-offerings.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="514" end-line="522">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Did ye also hear the dream, so as to tell it correctly?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="527" end-line="527">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>She fancied, as she herself says, that she gave birth to a serpent.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="526" end-line="526">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>And what is the end and issue of the tale<ref n="162.2"/>?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="529" end-line="529">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>that the new-born monster was lying <ref n="162.3">3</ref> in swaddling-clothes like an infant, in want of food <ref n="162.4">4</ref>, and she in her dream gave it her breast.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="528" end-line="528">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>And how was the dug wounded not by the abomination?
          <note type="footnote" n="162.1">1 <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl>'s</bibl> text and notes are, as usual, at variance. I follow the latter, reading <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐτεινάτην,</quote> and assigning these words to the Chorus.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="162.2">2 For <quote xml:lang="grc">καρανου̃ται</quote> compare <bibl>Othello, I. 3</bibl>. <quote xml:lang="eng">The very head and front of my offending Hath this extent, no more.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="162.3">3 <quote xml:lang="grc">όϱμη̃σαι</quote>s is <bibl><bibl><bibl>Porson</bibl>'s</bibl></bibl> emendation. <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl> defend <quote xml:lang="grc">ὁϱμίσαι.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="162.4">4 Read <quote xml:lang="grc">τίνος,</quote> and give this verse to <bibl>Orestes. <bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
        </p>
      </sp>


      <pb n="163"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="163"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="533-571"/>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="533" end-line="533">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>[It did not wound her,] so as to draw clotted blood along with the milk.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="534" end-line="534">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>This vision of a man come not in vain<ref n="163.1">1</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="535" end-line="539">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>And she, fluttering with fear, screamed in her sleep; and many lamps that had been extinguished in darkness sprang into light through the palace on account of our mistress. And then she sends these funereal drink-offerings, hoping for a fitly-shred<ref n="163.2">2</ref> remedy for her sufferings.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="540" end-line="551">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>But I make my prayer to this earth, and to the tomb of my father, that this dream may bring accomplishment to me. And i'faith I interpret it so that it exactly tallies; for if, after quitting the same place with me, the serpent was decked in my swaddling-clothes, and mouthed the breast that gave me nutriment, and mingled with clotted blood the loved milk, and she shrieked in dread at this mischance-it needs must be that she, as she reared a terrific portent, should die a violent death; and I, changed into a serpent, will slay her, as this dream of her's declares. And I choose thee for my expounder of portents as touching this matter.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="552" end-line="552">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>So be it: but explain the rest of thy plan to thy friends, bidding some to do something, and others not to act.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="553" end-line="584">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>The tale is simple: I recommend my sister here to go within and to conceal these plans agreed upon [with her]; that after slaying an august monarch, they too may be entrapped by guile, dying in the very same toils, even as Loxias too predicted, king Apollo, a prophet of unfailing truth heretofore. For like to a stranger, having complete equipment, I will come with my friend Pylades here to the gates of the court-yard, as a guest and friend of the family. And we both will utter the Parnassian dialect, imitating the sound of a Phocian tongue. And suppose that no one of the porters will admit us with gladsome mind, (since the house is possessed with ills,) we will remain thus, so that any one walking past the house may make a guess, and say this: “Why thus with [closed] gates exclude ye the suppliant? if Ægisthus is at home and aware of his presence?" If then I pass the threshold of the gates of the court-yard, and shall

              <note type="footnote" n="163.1">1 I.e., this is not the vision of a mere beast, but of a man under that image. So <bibl><bibl>Scholefield</bibl></bibl>.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="163.2">2 See on <bibl><bibl>Agam. 16</bibl></bibl>. <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐντέμνων ἄκος.</quote>
      </note>
            <pb n="164"/>
            <milestone unit="linechunk" n="572-612"/>

            discover him upon my father's throne, or if he come then and speak to me to my face and cast his eyes upon me, know certainly that before he says, "What countrymen is the stranger?” I will stretch him a corpse, coming round him<ref n="164.1">1</ref> with nimble swordsmanship. And Erinnys, that hath not been stinted of slaughter, shall quaff blood undiluted, a third draught. Now then, do thou watch well what is within the house, that these things may fall out well-combined. But to you I recommend to keep a silent tongue, both to keep silence where it is needful, and to speak what is suited to the moment. For the rest I appeal to this my [friend] to come hither and overlook these matters; to him that has helped<ref n="164.2">2</ref> me to success in this conflict of the wielded sword.</p>
      </sp>
      <ab>
        <stage>[ELECTRA enters the palace: ORESTES and PYLADES retire to disguise themselves.]</stage>
      </ab>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="585" end-line="630">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Full many<ref n="164.3">3</ref> a dread and grievous horror does the earth nurture, and the arms of the deep teem with monsters hostile to mortals! and there spring forth in mid-air lights<ref n="164.4">4</ref> hung aloft. Both the creatures that fly and those that crawl, and the gusty rage of hurricanes, one might be able to describe. But who can tell the mighty daring spirit of man, and of women hardened in their souls, and their loves that venture all, comates with the woes of mortals? Un-lovely love, lording it in woman's heart, overcomes the conjugal societies of brutes and of men. Let whosoever is not flighty in his thoughts know this, when he hath learned what a kindling device the wretched daughter of Thestius, who worked the destruction of her son, sought out, when she committed to the flames the glowing brand that was his coeval, from the time when he uttered his first cry on coming from the womb, and commensurate through his life unto the day foredoomed by


      <note type="footnote" n="164.1">1 See <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="164.2">2 See <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>. Pylades must be meant, not Apollo.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="164.3">3 Compare <bibl>Soph. <title>Antig. 332</title>. sqq.</bibl>.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="164.4">4 <quote xml:lang="grc">λαμπάδες</quote> seems to be a general expression, including meteors, comets, falling stars, and all unusual phenomena of the sky, such as are described by Pseud-Aristotle, de Mundo, § II. 16. ed. Pacti. <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐνδἐΤη̜̃πυρώδεικαι πολλάκις,</quote> translated by <bibl>Apuleius, p. 58. ed. Elm</bibl>.
      </note>
      <pb n="165"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="165"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="613-651"/>
   Fate. Another is there in legends whom we are bound to abhor, the murderess Scylla, who at the foeman's instigation destroyed a man [she should have] loved, having been seduced by Cretan necklaces of wrought gold, the gifts of Minos, what time she, shameless, robbed Nisus of his undying ringlet as he was breathing unsuspectingly in sleep; but Mercury<ref n="165.1">1</ref> overtakes her. And since I have made mention of savage horrors, though unseasonably<ref n="165.2">2</ref>, [one may also mention] the odious match, execrated by the house, and plots laid by a woman's mind against an armed warrior, against a warrior for his majesty bitter to his enemies; and I honour the hearth of a household that knows not audacity, and in women an undaring spirit. Of horrors, indeed, that of Lemnos holds the first place in story; and it is deplored in every clime as an abomination, and a man is wont to compare what is dreadful to Lemnian sufferings<ref n="165.3">3</ref>. And by reason of heaven-detested guilt the race of mortals perishes in infamy; for no one reveres that which is offensive to the gods. Which of these hideous facts do I unreasonably reckon up? But the sword, sharp and bitter, inflicts a wound right through the lungs, driven by the hand of Justice. For the lawless conduct of him<ref n="165.4">4</ref> that hath lawlessly trespassed against every awful attribute of Jupiter, is not trampled under foot on the ground. But the base of Justice is planted firm; and Fate, that forges the sword, prepares it for the deed, and brings into the house a new offering of ancient murders, and time-honoured<ref n="165.5">5</ref> Erinnys avenges the stain.</p></sp>



      <note type="footnote" n="165.1">1 There seems an allusion to Mercury both in his character of the conductor of the dead, and the presider over ill-gotten games. There is a similar conceit in the <bibl>Anthologia, Epigr. Incert, ccxxxvii</bibl>.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="165.2">2 See <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl>. Of <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐπικότω̜σέβας,</quote> I can make nothing satisfactory.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="165.3">3 <bibl><bibl>Hesychius</bibl>, t. II. p. 4G5</bibl>. <quote xml:lang="grc">Κήμνιονκακόν.παϱοιμία,ἣνδιαδοθη̃ναί γυναικω̃ν,</quote> where see comment. On this murder of the Lemnians by the women, from which Thoas alone escaped, being spared by his daughter Hypsipyle, see <bibl>Antig. Caryst. <title>Hist. Mirab. 130</title></bibl>. <bibl><bibl>Valer. Place. II. 113</bibl></bibl>. and the <bibl><bibl>Scholiast on Statius Theb. V. s. 29</bibl></bibl>.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="165.4">4 I have, with the approbation of <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>, adopted <quote xml:lang="grc">παϱεκβάντος,</quote> <bibl>Stanley</bibl>'s emendation, although I am not satisfied even then.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="165.5">5 So <bibl>Donaldson, <title>New Cratylus</title>, p. 390</bibl>. <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl> retains <quote xml:lang="grc">τείνει.</quote>
      </note>
      <pb n="166"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="166"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="652-686"/>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="652" end-line="656">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Boy, boy<ref n="166.1">1</ref>! hear the knocking at the gates of the court-yard. Who is within there in the house? boy, boy, I say again, a third time I call for some one to come out of the house, if Ægisthus forsooth be given to hospitality<ref n="166.2">2</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="657" end-line="657">DOMESTIC</speaker>
        <p>Well, well—I hear you. What countryman is the stranger? whence comes he<ref n="166.3">3</ref>?</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="658" end-line="667">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>Bear word to the masters of the mansion, unto whom I am come and am bringing news; and be quick, since also night's dusky car is speeding on, and 'tis time for wayfarers to let go their anchor in houses that welcome all strangers. Let there come forth some lady-mistress of the house, that hath power: but it were more decorous that a man should [come to us], for that bashfulness does not in the course of conversation make words obscure: man is wont to speak with confidence to man, and expresses his thoughts with certainty.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="668" end-line="673">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
        <p>Guests, say whatsoever is necessary; for there are at hand things such as beseem this dwelling of ours, both warm baths<ref n="166.4">4</ref>, and the couch that soothes fatigues, and the presence of benignant eyes. But if ye are bound to transact any other business that requires somewhat of consultation, this is the concern of men, to whom we will communicate it.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="674" end-line="690">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>I am a stranger of Daulis, come from the Phocians; and as I was journeying to Argos, self freighted with my own baggage, just as I set forth hither on foot, a stranger who met me said to me a stranger, after having particularly inquired and clearly explained to me my road, Strophius the Phocian,—for I ascertain his name in course of conversation:—“Since on other business, stranger, thou art going to Argos, tell his parents that Orestes is dead, strictly remembering it, let it by no means be forgotten; whether the determination of his friends shall prevail to convey him away, or whether to bury him in the land of his sojourn, altogether estranged for ever, bring back with thee their commands on this subject; for now
          <note type="footnote" n="166.1">1 See <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="166.2">2 Read with <bibl><bibl>Elmsley</bibl></bibl>: <quote xml:lang="grc">εἰφιλόξενόςτιςΑἰγίσθουβία.</quote>
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="166.3">3 <bibl><bibl>Eurip. El. 779</bibl></bibl>. <quote xml:lang="grc">χαίϱετ’w ξένοι, τίνες,Πόθενποϱεύεσθ’</quote>,quoted by <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl></bibl>.
          </note>
          <note type="footnote" n="166.4">4 See <bibl><bibl>Blomfield</bibl></bibl>, and for a similar picture of ancient manners, <bibl>Apulcius Met. 1. p. 113. ed. Elm</bibl>..
          </note>

      <pb n="167"/>
      <milestone unit="page" n="167"/>
      <milestone unit="linechunk" n="686-718"/>
    the sides of a brazen urn conceal the ashes of the man who hath been duly bewailed." Thus much I tell thee as I heard it. And whether I am speaking to the heads of the family and to his relations I know not, but it is proper that his parents know it.</p>
    </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="691" end-line="699">ELECTRA</speaker>
        <p>Woe's me! how<ref n="167.1">1</ref> are we utterly ruined. O insuperable curse of this family, how dost thou level at many things that are well placed out of thy way, overcoming them with thy bow, that carries true to the mark even from afar. Thou strippest me thoroughly wretched of my friends. And now Orestes,—for he used to be lucky in his throws, removing his foot from out the slough of destruction,-but now—the hope which was to be medicinal against the goodly revelry in this house, he writes down as present<ref n="167.2">2</ref>.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="700" end-line="706">ORESTES</speaker>
        <p>I could indeed have wished to have become known, and to have been welcomed as a guest by hosts thus opulent through the means of gladsome tidings; for what more kindly feeling is there than that which is entertained by a guest towards hosts? But to my mind it was an act of impiety not to fulfil such an obligation as this to friends, having pledged ray word, and been hospitably welcomed.</p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="707" end-line="718">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
        <p>Be sure thou shalt not meet with unworthy treatment, and not the less shouldest thou be friendly to the household; For some one else would have come all the same to bring us these tidings. But it is the fit time for strangers that spend the whole day in long travel, to obtain the things that are suitable under their circumstances. Conduct him into the hospitable male apartments of the palace, and these his attendants and fellow-travellers, and there let them enjoy treatment such as beseems the house. And I bid thee do this as liable to be called to account. And we will both communicate these things to the heads of the family, and not lacking friends, will deliberate concerning this misfortune.</p>
      </sp>
      <stage>[CLYTEMNESTRA enters the palace.]</stage>

     <note type="footnote" n="167.1">1 <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐνθάδ'</quote> is corrupt. <bibl><bibl>Muller</bibl></bibl> reads <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔμπας,</quote> <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl></bibl> <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐμπέδως.</quote>
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="167.2">2 If these words be correct (of which I have great doubts), we can only explain them by supposing that Electra says <quote xml:lang="grc">καλη̃ς</quote> ironically, and that <quote xml:lang="grc">παϱου̃σαν ἐγγϱάφει</quote> contains an equivoque, meaning either, "he writes down as present, being himself present," or, as Clytæmnestra would understand it: "he reckons as all I see," i. e. as a dead man.
      </note>
      <pb n="168"/>
            <milestone unit="linechunk" n="719-759"/>

      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="719" end-line="733">CHORUS</speaker>
        <p>Well, dear handmaidens of the house, when indeed shall we put forth the strength of our mouths on account of Orestes? O revered earth, and revered pile of the mound, which now dost press upon the remains of the monarch that led the fleet, now give ear, now lend thine aid; for now is it high time for wily plausibility and the nether Mercury to come together, and to guide the mysterious man on his way in conflicts of the destructive sword.</p>
      </sp>
      <p>The stranger seems to be working mischief. But I see the nurse of Orestes coming hither, in tears. On what errand Cilissa, art thou treading the outlet<ref n="168.1">1</ref> of the palace? and no hireling sorrow is it that accompanies thee on thy way.</p>
      <sp>
        <speaker start-line="734" end-line="765">NURSE</speaker>
        <p>My mistress bade me call Ægisthus with all speed for the strangers<ref n="168.2">2</ref>, that having come, man may learn more clearly from man the tidings just reported. Before the domestics, indeed, she suppressed her laughter within her scowling eyes, concealing it over deeds that have been done well for her, but for this house all unhappily, in consequence of the tale which the strangers clearly reported. Verily he, when he hears it, will rejoice in his mind, when he shall have learned the news. Alas, wretch that I am! how did the ancient blended sorrows, hard to be endured, that happened to this mansion of Atreus, afflict with anguish my heart within my bosom! But never yet did I undergo any suffering such as this. For the rest of my calamities I bore through with patience; but my dear Orestes, the care of my soul, whom I reared up, having received him from the moment of his birth<ref n="168.3">3</ref> and from his arousing cries, disturbing me by night many fruitless toils have been endured by me in vain. For [the infant] that has no sense one must needs rear just as if it were an animal, for how can it be otherwise? according to his humour; for a child while yet in swaddling-clothes speaks not, whether hunger, or thirst, or a call of nature beset him; and the belly of an infant works its own relief. I, fore-warned of these things, but in many cases deceived, I ween, was a washer of the baby's



      <note type="footnote" n="168.1">1 <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl>'s</bibl> emendation, <quote xml:lang="grc">πέλας,</quote> seems correct.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="168.2">2 <bibl><bibl>Paley</bibl></bibl> rightly condemns the attempts to explain <quote xml:lang="grc">τοὺς ξένους.</quote> I have followed <bibl><bibl>Pauw</bibl></bibl>, with the apparent approbation of <bibl><bibl>Porson</bibl></bibl> and <bibl><bibl>Dindorf</bibl></bibl>.
      </note>
      <note type="footnote" n="168.3">3 I think the only way of understanding this passage is to mark an abrupta ratio, and read <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐκ νυκτιπλάγτων.</quote>
      </note>
<pb n="169"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="780-782"/>
wrappings; the fuller and the nurse had one and the same
office<ref n="169.1">1</ref>. And I having this twofold manual occupation, I
received Orestes from his father<ref n="169.2">2</ref>. But now I wretched
hear of his having died. And I am going to a man that
hath done foul wrong to this house; and willingly will he
hear these tidings.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="766" end-line="766">CHORUS</speaker><p>With what equipment does she then bid him come?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="767" end-line="767">NURSE</speaker><p>With what equipment? repeat your question, that I
may understand it more clearly.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="768" end-line="768">CHORUS</speaker><p>[I mean] whether with guards, or even unattended?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="769" end-line="769">NURSE</speaker><p>She bids him bring his spear-bearing followers.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="770" end-line="773">CHORUS</speaker><p>Prithee do not thou bear this message to our detested
master<ref n="169.3">3</ref>; but bid him come alone with rejoicing mind, with
the best speed he may, that he may hear without apprehension;
for <quote xml:lang="grc">κυπτός</quote><ref n="169.4">4</ref> tidings are set straight by the bearer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="774" end-line="774">NURSE</speaker><p>What! art thou gladdened by the news that has now
been brought?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="775" end-line="775">CHORUS</speaker><p>No; but [I shall be glad] if Jupiter at some future
time shall work a change in our ills.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="776" end-line="776">NURSE</speaker><p>And how? Orestes, the hope of the house, hath
perished.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="777" end-line="777">CHORUS</speaker><p>Not yet; even a dull diviner might understand this.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="778" end-line="778">NURSE</speaker><p>What sayest thou? knowest thou aught different
from what hath been told us?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="779" end-line="780">CHORUS</speaker><p>Go, tell thy message, execute thine orders. The gods
take care of those things about which they interest themselves.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="781" end-line="782">NURSE</speaker><p>Well, I will go, and in this matter will yield me to
thy bidding. And may the issue be the best it can by the
gift of heaven. <stage>Exit the NURSE.</stage></p></sp>
<note n="169.1">1 This discourse of the nurse has been plentifully abused by many commentators. Without, however, following <bibl>Schutz</bibl>, who admires and praises it most indiscreetly, we shall do well to remember the extraordinary detail of Clytemnestra, <quote xml:lang="lat">Again.</quote> 865. and of Phoenix in Homer, <quote xml:lang="lat">Il.</quote> X. 486, etc., both of which are equally characteristic of the simplicity of the early ages. Shakespeare has allowed the nurse of Juliet to offend much more grievously. Old Translation.</note>
<note n="169.2">2 See <bibl>Abresch's</bibl> learned note.</note>
<note n="169.3">3 Ambiguously spoken, as it may mean "<quote xml:lang="eng">with hatred of our master</quote>" or "<quote xml:lang="eng">our hated master.</quote>" See <bibl>Paley</bibl>.</note>
<note n="169.4">4 Read <quote xml:lang="grc">κυπτός.</quote></note>
<pb n="170"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="783-818"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="783" end-line="818">CHORUS<ref n="170.1"/></speaker><p>O Jupiter! sire of the Olympian gods, grant to me now
beseeching thee that my fortunes may turn out successfully, in
a manner that may be beheld by the wise well seeking<ref n="170.2">2</ref>. In
integrity<ref n="170.3">3</ref> have I uttered every word. O Jupiter ! do protect
them. Ah ! ah! and set thou [him] before his foes within
the house, since, if thou exaltest him to glory, thou shalt, if thou
pleasest, receive in return a double and threefold recompense.
Bethink thee too of a beloved hero's orphan youngling yoked
In harness of sufferings, and prescribe thou a limit to his race.
Who<ref n="170.4">4</ref> might see this striding of completed paces across the
plain keeping due time? Ye too, that haunt the alcove that
exults in opulence, give ear, propitious gods. Come, make
atonement for the bloodshed of those that were done to death
in the olden time by fresh vengeance. No more let ancient
murder spawn in the halls. O thou that tenantest the vast
chasm, graciously grant that the hero's home may at the same
time witness this righteous execution<ref n="170.5">5</ref>, and that he may look
forth fearlessly and brightly with friendly eyes from out the
veil of gloom. May Maia's most propitious<ref n="170.6">6</ref> son also, willing
him an auspicious issue, rightfully take up the cause. Many
other mysterious things too will he develope if he be willing ;
and uttering obscure language, both by night he brings dark-
ness before the eyes, and in the daytime he is nought clearer.</p></sp>
<note n="170.1">1 This Chorus is so corrupt, that no satisfactory conclusions can be formed respecting either the metre or sense. <bibl>Klausen</bibl> and <bibl>Peile</bibl> have done little that can be considered even as approximating to the truth, and <bibl>Paley</bibl> alone has displayed any taste in examining the text.</note>
<note n="170.2">2 I have imitated the perfect unintelligibility of the original. <bibl>Paley</bibl> reads <quote xml:lang="grc">δὸς τύχας μου τυχεῖν κυρίως, Εὐφροσύναν μαιομένας ἰδεῖν.</quote> I cannot give an opinion. Linwood. s. v. <quote xml:lang="grc">τύχη,</quote> considers the passage hopeless.</note>
<note n="170.3">3 <quote xml:lang="grc">διὰ δίκας,</quote> <bibl>Pauw</bibl>, <bibl>Dindorf</bibl>, and <bibl>Paley</bibl>.</note>
<note n="170.4">4 See <bibl>Paley</bibl>. I must confess my unmitigated ignorance of what a single sentence of this passage means.</note>
<note n="170.5">5 We must remove the stop after <quote xml:lang="grc">κτάμενον,</quote> which <bibl>Paley</bibl> would treat as an accusative absolute. But <bibl>Dindorf</bibl> seems to approve the conjecture of Bamberger <quote xml:lang="grc">τὸ δὲ καλῶς κτίμενον .... στόμιον.</quote> This is certainly ingenious, but I have my doubts about applying the epithet <quote xml:lang="grc">κτίμενον</quote> to a natural cave. But as Heath and <bibl>Blomfield</bibl> seem right in referring this to the abode of Delphic Apollo, this difficulty is easily surmounted. <bibl>Blomfield</bibl> appositely quotes Strabo, IX. p. 641. <quote xml:lang="grc">ὐπερκεῖσι δὲ του̃ στομίου τρίποδα</quote> See also an important passage of Diodorus, XVI. p. 523, 524.</note>
<note n="170.6">6 See <bibl>Paley</bibl>.</note>
<pb n="171"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="819-854"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="819" end-line="837">CHORUS</speaker><p>And then at length will we pour forth<ref n="171.1">1</ref> a loud song to celebrate
the deliverance of the palace ; such as may suit a woman's
tongue, auspiciously raised, and withal the lyre-struck strain
of mourners: for the city this is well; my gain too, mine
is enhanced, and evil withdraws from my friends. But do
thou boldly, when thy share of the deed shall have come, after
shouting thy father's name over a deed done for thy father's
sake, in answer to her shrieking, “ My son !" consummate a
vengeance not wholly blameless<ref n="171.2">2</ref>. Maintaining too within thy
bosom the spirit of Perseus, in the cause of those dear to thee
both above and below the earth, working out bitter wrath
rather than to affection<ref n="171.3">3</ref>, accomplishing a murderous destruc­
tion on those within, cutting off utterly the author of murder.</p></sp>
<stage>Enter AEGISTHUS</stage>
<sp><speaker start-line="838" end-line="847">AEGISTHUS</speaker>
<p>I have come not unbidden, but summoned by a messenger ;
and I understand that some strangers who have arrived tell
us news by no means welcome, to wit, the death of Orestes.
And the imputation of this upon the house would be a blood-
dripping burthen upon one still ulcerated and irritated by the
former murder<ref n="171.4">4</ref>. How am I to deem these tidings true and
clear? or can it be that alarming rumours in the minds of
women are flitting in mid-air, such as die away without
effect ? What of these things shouldst thou say, so as to
prove it to my mind ?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="848" end-line="850">CHORUS</speaker><p>We heard it indeed, but go thou within and question
the strangers ; the authority of messengers is no way so good
as for a man himself to make enquiry about the tidings which
they bring<ref n="171.5">5</ref>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="851" end-line="854">AEGISTHUS</speaker><p>I wish to see and question farther the messenger,
whether he himself was present close at hand where he died,
or whether he is telling what he has learned from obscure re­
port. He certainly will not be able to delude a discerning
mind. <stage>Exit AEGISTHUS.</stage></p></sp>
<note n="171.1">1 All the merit of illustrating this passage is due to <bibl>Blomfield</bibl>, whom <bibl>Dindorf</bibl> closely follows (see notes). He rightly reads <quote xml:lang="grc">πολὺν</quote> for <quote xml:lang="grc">πλου̃τον,</quote> and puts the full stop after <quote xml:lang="grc">μεθήσομεν,</quote> instead of after <quote xml:lang="grc">πόλει.</quote> So also <bibl>Paley</bibl>. <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl>'s</bibl> notes are an instance of the utter uselessness of lengthy commentaries upon a corrupted text.</note>
<note n="171.2">2 Thus <bibl>Paley</bibl>. The readings arc, however, not quite satisfactory.</note>
<note n="171.3">3 But see <bibl>Linwood's Lex</bibl>.</note>
<note n="171.4">4 I have adopted <bibl>Klausen</bibl>'s construction, with Linwood and <bibl>Paley</bibl>.</note>
<note n="171.5">5 Cf. <bibl>Soph. Œd. Tyr. 6</bibl>.</note>
<pb n="172"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="855-889"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="855" end-line="868">CHORUS</speaker><p>O Jupiter ! Jupiter! what am I to say ? whence shall I
commence thus praying and importunating<ref n="172.1">1</ref>? How, speaking
from good feeling, shall I obtain an equivalent boon ?</p>
<p>For now either the gore-stained attempts of the man-slaying
axes are on the point of working the destruction of the family
of Agamemnon throughout all time, or he, kindling fire and
light for liberty, and the authorities that give laws to the state,
shall enjoy the great weal of his fathers. Upon such a con­
flict as this is god-like Orestes, a solitary single-handed
champion, on the point of entering against two. And may it
be for victory!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="869" end-line="869">AEGISTHUS</speaker><p>(from within the palace.)—Ah ! what, ho !</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="870" end-line="874">CHORUS</speaker><p>Ah! ah ! again ! How stands the matter ? how are
things accomplished in the house ? Stand we aloof from the
consummation of the business, that we may seem to be no way
implicated in these horrors ; for the issue of the conflict hath
assuredly been settled.</p></sp>
<stage>Enter a DOMESTIC.</stage>
<sp><speaker start-line="875" end-line="884">DOMESTIC</speaker>
<p>Woe's me! ay every woe's me, for my slain lord! yet
once more woe's me ! in a third exclamation. Aegisthus is
no more : but open as quickly as ye may, and unclose, by [re­
moving] the bars, the doors of the women's apartments ; and
need there surely is of a vigorous arm; but not to succour the
slain ; what need of that ? What, hoa ! I am shouting to the
deaf, and calling in vain to those that are madly sleeping.
Where is Clytemnestra ? what is she doing ? It seems now
that her neck is soon to fall on the edge of the steel, she being
justly smitten<ref n="172.2">2</ref>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="885" end-line="885">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>(coming forward).—What is the matter? what meant
the outcry thou art raising in the house ?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="886" end-line="886">DOMESTIC</speaker><p>I tell thee that the dead are slaying the living.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="887" end-line="891">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Ah me! I apprehend thy meaning from thy dark
expressions. By treachery shall we perish exactly as we slew.
Some one hand me a deathly axe with all speed. Let us see
<note n="172.1">1 This is the sense given to <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐπιθοάζουσα</quote> by <bibl>Buttmann Lexil. p. 349</bibl>. but <bibl>Blomfield</bibl> reads <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐπιθεάζουσα,</quote> with the approbation of <bibl>Paley</bibl>, and apparently of <bibl>Dindorf</bibl>.</note>
<note n="172.2">2 The structure seems to hang between the proverbial form <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔοικε νυ̃ν αὐτὴ ἐπὶ ξυρου̃ ἱστάναι,</quote> and <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔοικε αὐτη̃ς αὐχὴν ἐπὶ ξυρου̃</quote> flat. The first verse denotes that Clytemnestra is in extreme danger, and the second shows how</note>
<pb n="173"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="890-918"/>
whether we are to be victors or vanquished; for unto that
crisis of this evil am I come.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="892" end-line="892">ORESTES</speaker><p>(bursting in.)—Thee too am I seeking-this wretch
here has enough.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="893" end-line="893">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Ah me ! thou art dead, dearest Aegisthus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="894" end-line="895">ORESTES</speaker><p>Lovest thou the man ? then shalt thou lie in the
same tomb, and thou shalt never desert him in death.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="896" end-line="898">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Hold thee, my son! and revere this breast on which
thou full often slumbering wast wont at the same time to suck
with thy gums the well-nourishing milk.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="899" end-line="899">ORESTES</speaker><p>Pylades, how am I to act? is reverence to restrain
me from slaying my mother ?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="900" end-line="902">PYLADES</speaker><p>Where, then, are the oracles of Apollo uttered at
Pytho, and the faithful oaths well plighted ? Deem all thine
enemies rather than the gods<ref n="173.1">1</ref>.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="903" end-line="907">ORESTES</speaker><p>I decide that thou prevailest, and admonishest me
well: (turning to his mother,) follow me. I wish to slay thee
close beside his corpse here ; for when he was alive too, thou
didst use to deem him better than my father. Go sleep with
him in death, since thou dost love this man, and him whom
thou wast bound to love thou loathest.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="908" end-line="908">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>I reared thee, and with thee I would spend my age.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="909" end-line="909">ORESTES</speaker><p>What! having murdered my sire, shalt thou dwell
with me ?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="910" end-line="910">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Destiny, my child, was an accessory to these things.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="911" end-line="911">ORESTES</speaker><p>Ay, and so Destiny provides the doom that is now
before thee.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="912" end-line="912">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Hast thou no awe of a parent's curses, my child ?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="913" end-line="913">ORESTES</speaker><p>No ; for after giving me birth thou didst cast me out
into misery.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="914" end-line="914">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Surely I did not cast thee out [when I sent thee] to
the house of a friend.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="915" end-line="915">ORESTES</speaker><p>In two ways was I sold, son though I was of a free-
father.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="916" end-line="916">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Where then is the price which I received for bartering
thee away ?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="917" end-line="917">ORESTES</speaker><p>I am ashamed to reproach thee in plain terms with
this deed of thine.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="918" end-line="918">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Nay, only tell equally the follies of thy father.</p></sp>
<note n="173.1">1 i. e. prefer the enmity of Clytemnestra to that of Apollo.</note>
<pb n="174"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="919-942"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="919" end-line="919">ORESTES</speaker><p>Reproach not him that bore the toil, thou that didst
sit within the house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="920" end-line="920">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>'Tis a sorrow to women to be debarred from a hus-
band, my child.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="921" end-line="921">ORESTES</speaker><p>Yet sure it is the husband's toiling that supports them
as they sit within.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="922" end-line="922">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>It seems, then, that thou wilt slay thy mother, my
child.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="923" end-line="923">ORESTES</speaker><p>'Tis thou wilt work thine own destruction, not I.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="924" end-line="924">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Look to it, beware of the wrathful furies of a
mother.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="925" end-line="925">ORESTES</speaker><p>But how am I to escape those of my father if I neglect
this?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="926" end-line="926">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>I, a living woman, seem to be vainly making my
moan to a sepulchre.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="927" end-line="927">ORESTES</speaker><p>Ay, for the fate of my father wafts<ref n="174.1">1</ref> down upon thee
the doom that now awaits thee.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="928" end-line="928">CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker><p>Ah me! this is the serpent that I bore and nurtured.
In truth the panic occasioned by my dreams has been indeed
prophetic.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="929" end-line="929">ORESTES</speaker><p>Thou didst in truth slay one whom it became thee
not, so suffer what becomes thee not. <stage>ORESTES forces his mother into the palace.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="931" end-line="945">CHORUS</speaker><p>Let us then bewail the twofold calamity even of this
wretched pair. And since the hapless Orestes hath attained
the consummation of many slaughters, this notwithstanding
we prefer, that the eye of the house has not fallen in utter
destruction.</p>
<p>There hath come after a time vengeance for the chil-
dren of Priam, heavy-avenging retribution; and there hath
come into the dwelling of Agamemnon, a twofold lion, a
twofold Mars. The exile of whom Apollo spake hath been
successful<ref n="174.2">2</ref> in every respect, having been rightly excited by
the counsels of heaven. Celebrate ye with a loud shout the
<note n="174.1">1 Compare Henry VI, part 2. TV. 1.— <quote xml:lang="eng">Come, Suffolk, I must waft thee to thy death.</quote></note>
<note n="174.2">2 Read <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔλαχε</quote> with <bibl>Schutz</bibl>, or <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔλαβε</quote> with the <bibl>Medicean MS</bibl>. The passage is not however satisfactory, even then. I shall not offend against common sense by quoting <bibl>Klausen</bibl>'s attempted explanation of the common reading. <bibl>Paley</bibl> with much ingenuity proposes <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔμολε.</quote></note>
<pb n="175"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="942-979"/>
escape<ref n="175.1">1</ref> of our master's house from evils, and from the dilapidation of its treasures by the defiling pair, a mournful fate. There hath come to one whose care is lurking warfare, Retribution of wily soul. The daughter of Jove too hath in very truth lent a hand to the battle,—and correctly do we mortals style her Justice,—breathing deadly wrath against her foes: whom Apollo, the god of Parnassus, that haunts the mighty cavern of the earth, upon the summit, hath led, without guile he comes upon one guileful, halting in delay. The divinity is in a manner prevented from aiding the wicked. Meet it is that we revere the power of the celestials. We are permitted to behold the light, and the great fetter<ref n="175.2">2</ref> of the mansion hath been taken off. Arise ye now, however, ye palaces! for too long a period did ye lie ever grovelling on the earth. Soon too will all-completing Time pass the vestibule of the palace, when he shall have driven from the hearth every abomination by lustral observances that expel calamities<ref n="175.3">3</ref>, and it shall be permitted us mourners to see and hear every thing in a lucky posture. The outcasts from the house shall be restored. We are permitted to behold the light.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="973" end-line="979">ORESTES</speaker><p>Behold ye the two sovereigns of the realm and the pillagers of this mansion that murdered my father. Proud were they, when sitting on their thrones, and now too [are they] loving, as we may guess from what has befallen them, and the oath remains to their pledges [unbroken]<ref n="175.4">4</ref>. They conspired indeed [to work] the death of my unhappy father, and to die together; and this result is according to the oath. Furthermore
<note n="175.1">1 As not even <bibl>Peile</bibl> has attempted to explain this passage, I have made my version as literal and unintelligible as the original. <bibl>Klausen</bibl> is painfully wrong, and <bibl>Paley</bibl> alone shows any sagacity. He would read <quote xml:lang="grc">τπορθιάζων</quote> in lieu of <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐπ ὄχθει ἄξεν.</quote> <bibl>Dindorf</bibl> marks a lacuna of several lines, without reason, as far as I can see. I will merely remark that <quote xml:lang="grc">έποίχεσθαι</quote> is properly used of the attacks of Apollo, as <quote xml:lang="grc">11.</quote> A.</note>
<note n="175.2">2 The reading <quote xml:lang="grc">μέγαν</quote> points to some other noun than <quote xml:lang="grc">ψάλιον,</quote> and the commentators have accordingly altered it to <quote xml:lang="grc">μέγα.</quote> <bibl>Paley</bibl> suspects that the reading has been interpolated, and that we should read <quote xml:lang="grc">χαλινὸν δόμων.</quote></note>
<note n="175.3">3 I have followed <bibl>Dindorf</bibl>'s text, which is a great improvement upon the old readings. So also <bibl>Paley</bibl>.</note>
<note n="175.4">4 <bibl>Hermann</bibl>'s emendation <quote xml:lang="grc">εὐπϱοσωποκοίτᾳ</quote> has been unanimously received by the later editors. The metaphor is taken from the dice, as is also the following <quote xml:lang="grc">πεσου̃νται.</quote></note>

<pb n="176"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="980-1014"/>
 behold ye<ref n="176.1">1</ref>,—ye that are hearers of these ills, the
contrivance, the shackles of my unhappy father, both the fet-
ters for his hands and the yoke for his feet! Stretch it out,
and standing round in a circle display the robe that enshrouded
the hero, in order that the father may see—not mine, but he
that beholdeth all these things, the Sun—the unhallowed
doings of my mother; that so he may be present to me in my
trial some future time, as an evidence, that with justice I pro-
secuted this doom; of my mother I mean, for I am not speak-
ing of that of Aegisthus, for he has undergone the sentence of
an adulterer, as the law prescribes. But she who plotted this
detestable deed against a husband, from whom she had been
wont to bear the burthen of children beneath her zone—a
burthen once dear, but now, as is plain, an hostile ill—what
thinkest thou? assuredly she was a conger, or a viper<ref n="176.2">2</ref>, that
could canker by a touch one who had not suffered from her
bite, by reason of her daring and her unrighteous spirit; what
shall I call it, and succeed in giving it a correct name? a
snare for a wild beast, or a canopy of a bath that enshrouded
the feet of the dead ? nay rather, thou mightest call it a net
or toils, and a robe for snaring the feet. A thing like this a
robber might have in his possession; one that deceives stran-
gers, that leads a life of plunder, and cutting off many by
this device, he might nurse many a hot deed in his mind. Be
never woman like this an inmate in my house: sooner may I
be doomed by the gods to die childless.</p>
</sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1007" end-line="1009">CHORUS</speaker><p>Alas! alas for the sad deeds! by a hateful death wast
thou despatched, and for the survivor also suffering blame.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="980" end-line="1006">ORESTES</speaker><p>Did he or did he not do it? but this vest bears witness
to me that the sword of Aegisthus stained it. The stain of
the gore too coincides with the time [of the deed,] damaging
the various hues of the embroidery. Now I praise him<ref n="176.3">3</ref>, now

<note n="176.1">1 Compare Shakespere, Julius Caesar, III. 2.</note>
<note n="176.2">2 See <bibl>Paley</bibl>. <bibl>Blomfield</bibl> elegantly and truly reads <quote xml:lang="grc">μύϱαινά</quote> y <quote xml:lang="grc">εἴτ ἔχιδν ἔφυ .... μα̃λλον.</quote> <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl>'s</bibl> note will tell the student a great deal more about Greek syntax, than he will probably wish to remember.</note>

<note n="176.3">I think with <bibl>Scholefield</bibl> that <quote xml:lang="grc">αἰνω̃ αὐτὸν</quote> does refer to Aegisthus, and is introduced as a touch of nature by the poet. Having slain his enemy, the wrath of Orestes is at an end. If am wrong, I can only allege the following lines of Young in my excuse:
  <cit>
  <quote xml:lang="eng">

<l>Is this Alonzo ? Where's the haughty mein ? </l>
<l>Is that the hand which smote me ? Heavens, how pale ! </l>
<l>And art thou dead ? So is my I war not with the dust. </l>
<l>* * * * * </l>
<l>Terror and doubt fall on me : all thy good </l>
<l>Now blazes, all thy guilt is in the grave. </l>
<l>Never had man such funeral applause.—</l>
    </quote>
    <bibl>The Revenge V. ult.</bibl></cit>

    And <cit><bibl>King Henry IV. First Part, IV. 4,—</bibl>
      <quote>
<l>Adieu, and take thy praise with thee to heaven ? </l>
<l>Thy ignominy sleep with thee in the grave, </l>
<l>But not remember'd in thy epitaph!</l>
  </quote></cit>

  </note>
<pb n="177"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="1014-1040"/>
upon the spot I bemoan him; and addressing his vestment,
that wrought my father's fall, I grieve for the offences and
the suffering, and the entire family, having the unenviable
pollutions of this victory which I have achieved.</p>
</sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1018" end-line="1020">CHORUS</speaker><p>No one of human kind shall spend unscathed a life
free from ill throughout its whole length. Alas! alas! of
troubles one is this very instant upon us, and another will
come.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1021" end-line="1043">ORESTES</speaker><p>But, that you may learn, I of a truth know to what
issue it will come<ref n="177.1">1</ref>: as though with horses of a charioteer I am
wandering wide of the course; for thoughts hard to be con-
trolled are hurrying me away overcome by them. And at my
heart fear is ready to sing or dance in phrensy.</p>
<p>But while I am still in my senses, I make declaration to
my friends, and assert that with justice I slew my mother,
an abomination, murdering my father, and detested of the
gods. And as for my provocatives to this daring, I prize most
highly Loxias, the prophet of Pytho, who announced to me
by oracle, that if I did this I should be beyond the reach of
evil censure; but if I had neglected it, I will not tell the
penalty; for no one will arrive at the agonies by conjecture.
And now behold me, how arrayed with this branch and chaplet
I will draw nigh unto the central shrine, the spot trodden by<ref n="177.2">2</ref>
Loxias, and the blaze of fire that hath been called imperish-
able, fleeing from this kindred blood: nay Loxias charged me
not to betake myself to any other shrine. And I bid all the

<note n="177.1">1 So <bibl>Blomfield</bibl> and <bibl>Dindorf</bibl>. I prefer Emper's reading,—<quote xml:lang="grc">ἀλλ᾽, ὠς ὰν εἰῦη̃τ᾽,</quote> (<quote xml:lang="grc">οὐ γὰρ οἰδ. κ. τ. λ.</quote>) <bibl><bibl>Peile</bibl>'s</bibl> criticism is in his best style.</note>
<note n="177.2">2 Literally, <gloss>by the bow</gloss>. <bibl>Peile</bibl> renders <quote xml:lang="grc">πέδον</quote> <gloss>the footstool</gloss>. See blomfield.</note>
<pb n="178"/>
<milestone unit="linechunk" n="1041-1076"/>
Argives bear witness to me, how that after a lapse of time
these evils were dealt out by me: but I a vagabond, estranged
from this land, living and dying having left this fame.</p>
</sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1044" end-line="1047">CHORUS</speaker><p>But since thou hast done well, neither yoke thy mouth
to evil-omened words, nor with thy tongue bode horrors, after
having given liberty to the whole state of the Argives, success-
fully lopping the heads of two serpents.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1048" end-line="1050">ORESTES</speaker><p>Ah! ah! ye handmaids, here they are in the guise of
Gorgons, in sable vestments, and entwined with densely-woven
snakes. I can stay no longer.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1051" end-line="1052">CHORUS</speaker><p>What fancies disturb thee, thou dearest of men to thy
father ? command thyself, be not scared after achieving a sig-
nal victory.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1053" end-line="1054">ORESTES</speaker><p>They are not fancies of these agonies that are upon
me; for here are plainly the angry hell-hounds of my mother.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1055" end-line="1056">CHORUS</speaker><p>Aye, for the fresh blood is still upon thine hands, hence
is it that perturbation falls upon thy mind.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1057" end-line="1058">ORESTES</speaker><p>Sovereign Apollo! now they are swarming; and from
their eyes they still loathly gore.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1059" end-line="1060">CHORUS</speaker><p>Within there is purification for thee ; but if thou touch-
est Loxias, he will set thee free from these sufferings.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1061" end-line="1062">ORESTES</speaker><p>Ye indeed see not these, but I do see them<ref n="178.1">1</ref>; and I am
driven away, and can stay no longer. <stage>Exit ORESTES.</stage></p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1063" end-line="1076">CHORUS</speaker><p>But mayest thou be happy, and may the deity, graci-
ously regarding thee, protect thee for a better hap. This
third tempest arising out of the family, after having blown In
its turn in the royal halls, like as a family wind<ref n="178.2">2</ref> hath come to
an end. First of all there were the child-devouring wretched
troubles of Thyestes. Next came a hero's kingly sufferings,
and stabbed in a bath the warrior chieftain of the Greeks
perished. Now too once more, third in order, there hath
come, we know not whence, a saviour, or should I call it
doom. Where then is the violence of calamity, when lulled,
to find an end; or where is it to reach a termination?</p></sp>
<note n="178.1">1 So in Tickell's Colin and Lucy,— <quote xml:lang="eng">I hear a voice you cannot hear, Which says I must not stay; I see a hand you cannot see, Which beckons me away. OLD TRANSLATION.</quote></note>
<note n="178.2">2 See <bibl>Blomfield</bibl>.</note>







 </div>
    </body>

  </text>
</TEI>
