<TEI>
    <text>
        <body>
<pb n="82"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="1" end-line="38">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>You I ask, you intolerable creatures, Is it the best [method of bringing] safety to the city and confidence to this army here beleaguered, that you should thus prostrated before the images of our tutelary gods cry aloud and shriek, O abominations of the self-controlled? Neither <lb n="170"/> in dangers nor in welcome prosperity may I ever be companion of the female sex; for a woman, when she has her way, is a bold thing impossible to live with, and when she is terrified, is a yet greater mischief to home and city. So now ye, by making these flights hither and thither, inspire with your clamour spiritless cowardice in the citizens; and, though things outside are going as much as possible in our favour, yet we by our own folk are being ruined from within. Now if there be any that will not give ear to my authority—be it man or woman or aught neutral —against them shall a vote of death be cast,<ref n="82.3">3</ref> and in no <lb n="180"/> wise shall [the condemned one] escape death from stoning
<note type="footnote" n="82.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">παῖ Διὸς, ὅθεν</foreign> von den Bergh [<foreign xml:lang="grc">καὶ Διόθεν</foreign> M.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="82.2">2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">λυτήριοι</foreign> <add><foreign xml:lang="grc">δ'</foreign></add>, answering <foreign xml:lang="grc">μὴ προδῶτε</foreign> above [&lt;<foreign xml:lang="grc">τ</foreign>'&gt; Seidler: <foreign xml:lang="grc">λυτήριοι</foreign> M.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="82.3">3 <foreign xml:lang="grc">βεβλήσεται</foreign> Tucker [<foreign xml:lang="grc">βουλεύσεται</foreign> M.].</note>
<pb n="83"/>
by the people. Outside matters are a man's business; let not a woman advise as to them. Remain thou within doors, and create not mischief. Hearest thou or hearest thou not, or am I speaking to a deaf woman?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="78" end-line="164">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>O beloved son of Oedipus, I shuddered at hearing the din of rumbling chariots, when the naves screamed as the wheels revolved, and the noise<ref n="83.1">1</ref> of the guides in the horses' mouths—their fire-forged bridles.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="69" end-line="77">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>What then? Surely the sailor never yet found <lb n="190"/> means of safety by fleeing from the helm to the bows when his ship was labouring in the ocean waves?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="185" end-line="191">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>But it was in reliance upon the gods that I came out from the house<ref n="83.2">2</ref> to the ancient images of the divinities, when the roar of the deadly pelting storm arose at our gates: then indeed was I impelled by terror to <lb n="200"/> supplications of the gods that they would extend their aid to the city.</p></sp>

<sp><speaker start-line="165" end-line="184">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Let your prayer be that the defences may keep out the foe. This will be for the gods to grant. But, all the same, 'tis said that when a city is taken, her gods desert her.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="195" end-line="201">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Never during my life may this assemblage of divinities desert us: never may I live to see this city overrun by conquerors and their army kindling it with destructive flames.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="192" end-line="194">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>I pray you be not ill-advised in thus calling to the gods. Obedience is the mother of Success, spouse of <lb n="210"/> one who gives safety. Such is the saying.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="205" end-line="208">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>'Tis so. Yet is the might of Heaven above all: and doth oft in dangers, even after sore distress, lift the cloud of despair hanging over men's eyes.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="202" end-line="204">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Men's business it is to manage sacrifices and
    <note type="footnote" n="83.1">1 Reading provisionally <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀπύαν</foreign> anon. in Paley [<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀύπνων</foreign> M.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="83.2">2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόδομος</foreign>, cf. <bibl>Æsch. frag. 386</bibl> [<foreign xml:lang="grc">πρόδρομος</foreign> M.].</note>
<pb n="84"/>
consultations of the gods, when about to try the strength of their foes; but thy part it is to keep silence and remain within the chambers.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="219" end-line="221">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Through the gods it is that we enjoy a city unconquered, and that our defences keep off a horde of ill-wishers. What just censure objects to this [attitude of ours]?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="222" end-line="224">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>I have no objection to your honouring the race <lb n="220"/> of gods. But, that ye may not make the citizens lose heart, be quiet; and do not over-much give way to terror.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="225" end-line="227">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>It was on hearing a sudden din that in trembling fear I came all in confusion to the acropolis, the abode of honour.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="228" end-line="230">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Do not ye, if ye hear of any dying or wounded, be eager to receive them with cries of sorrow. For the slaughter of men is that whereon Ares is maintained.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="231" end-line="231">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Aye, and hark! I hear the neighing of steeds.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="232" end-line="232">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Though thou hearest it, show not over-plainly <lb n="230"/> that thou hearest.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="233" end-line="233">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>The city groans from earth beneath, as though men were surrounding it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="234" end-line="234">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Then it is enough that I should take measures about this.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="235" end-line="235">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>I am in fear: a battering is increasing at the gates.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="236" end-line="236">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Will you keep silence, and say nought about it up and down the city?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="237" end-line="237">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>O ye assembled gods, desert not our defences.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="238" end-line="238">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Will you be silent—a curse on you,—and refrain from this talk?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="239" end-line="239">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Gods of our city, let me not meet with a slave's fate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="240" end-line="240">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>'Tis thou thyself that art like to enslave both me and the whole city.</p></sp>
<lb n="240"/>
<pb n="85"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="241" end-line="241">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>O almighty Zeus, turn thy bolt against our enemies.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="242" end-line="242">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>O Zeus, what a race of women hast thou given to us!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="243" end-line="243">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Truly a miserable one—as are men whose city has been taken by the enemy.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="244" end-line="244">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Dost thou speak ill-omened words, and that whilst touching the images?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="245" end-line="245">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Through timidity fear runs away with my tongue.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="246" end-line="246">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>If only thou wouldst grant a trifling boon to my request!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="247" end-line="247">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Speak it as quickly as may be, and I shall quickly know.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="248" end-line="248">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Be silent then, wretched woman; terrify not your friends.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="249" end-line="249">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>I am silent. In company with others I will endure my appointed fate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="250" end-line="273">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>This speech of thine I prefer to those others. <lb n="250"/> Now in addition come thou outside the [precinct of] the images, and implore the gods to be our helpers in victory: and, after hearing my prayer, then do thou loudly chant a solemn strain of well-wishing, the cry accompanying sacrifice [prescribed by] Hellenic custom, an encouragement to friends, removing thus their fear of the foe. And I to the tutelary gods of the country, both those that haunt the plain and those that watch over the market, and to the waters of Dircè—nor do I leave out Ismenus—do vow that we, when things have gone well and the city is saved, drenching with <lb n="260"/> blood of sheep the altars of the gods and sacrificing bulls in their honour, will set up trophies; and upon the sacred buildings will I hang in front of the temples spear-won spoils of foemen, the vestments of our enemies.<ref n="86.1">1</ref> Make
<pb n="86"/>
such thy prayer to the gods, not indulging in lamentation; nor with vain and threatening bluster, for no whit the more by that wilt thou escape thy destiny. For my part, I will go and station six champions against six with myself as seventh, as opponents to the foe in heroic style, at the seven <lb n="270"/> exits from the walls, ere messengers in hot haste and flying rumour of report arrive and set us on fire by [the urgency of] the need.</p><stage>[Exit ETEOCLES.]</stage></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="86.1">1 In v. 263 <foreign xml:lang="grc">πολεμίων ἐσθήμασι</foreign> is probably part of a gloss upon <foreign xml:lang="grc">λάφυρα δαΐων</foreign>.</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="274" end-line="355">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>I make it my care: but through fear my spirit is not lulled to rest. Near to my heart, anxieties are kindling terror of the folk around our walls, as a timid dove dreads on behalf of her nestlings snakes dangerous to her brood. For <lb n="280"/> some are advancing in full force and close array against the towers, (what will become of me!) and some are hurling pebbles at our citizens exposed on both sides. By every means, O gods of Zeus' race, rescue the city and host of Cadmus' line.</p>
<p>What land better than this will ye get in exchange, if ye <lb n="290"/> abandon to its foes this deep-soiled country and the water of Dircè, most healthful of all draughts that Poseidon the encompasser of earth sends up, and the children of Tethys? Therefore, O tutelary gods, by sending upon<ref n="87.1">1</ref> those outside <lb n="300"/> our towers disaster with slaughter of men and flinging away of shields, earn for yourselves praise in the eyes of these citizens; and be ye securely established as rescuers of the city [in response] to our prayers. For piteous it is to send to the Under-world, a prize of the spear reduced to slavery, an ancient city dishonourably brought to ruin in crumbling dust by an Argive warrior through the will of the gods; and that these women should <lb n="310"/> be dragged away as captives, young and old (ah me, ah me!) by their hair, like horses by their manes, with tearing of their robes about them. The city groans being made
<pb n="87"/>
desolate, as the captives of mingled speech<ref n="87.2">1</ref> are carried away. I anticipate with dread a grievous fate.</p>
<note type="footnote" n="87.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατὰ</foreign> (with <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐμβαλόντες</foreign>) <foreign xml:lang="grc">ῥίψοπλον</foreign>, κ.τ.λ.</note>
<note type="footnote" n="87.2">1 I.e. including the female slaves, cf. v. 350 sqq.</note>
<p>Pitiful indeed it is that maidens of marriageable age, before <lb n="320"/> the rites which cull the flower of virginity, should pass from their homes on a hated journey,—what say you? I count that one who perishes has far better fortune than this,—for numerous (ah me!) when a city is captured are the ills it suffers. One drags off another, slays, sets fire to parts of the town: all the citadel is murky with smoke. Ares in frenzy, <lb n="330"/> subduer of men, is the inspirer—desecrating all ties of piety. Tumults arise in the citadel, and the towered circumvallation<ref n="87.3">2</ref> is pushed close to the town; and man by man is slain with the spear; and wailing cries, choked in blood, of young children resound, cries of infants at the breast. And there are plunderings, near allied to dispersed flights: pillager meets with pillager, and the empty-handed calls to the <lb n="340"/> empty-handed wishing to have a partner, greedy each of them for a share neither less nor [only] equal. What after this is it natural to conjecture?</p>
<note type="footnote" n="87.3">2 On the use of towers both in attack and defence, cf. <bibl>C. W. C. Oman, <title>Mediæval Warfare</title></bibl>.</note>
<p>And fruits of the earth of all sorts strewn upon the ground cause sorrow as they meet the eye; and sad are the faces of the waiting-maids. Freely is earth's produce swept a medley away in valueless streams. And young female slaves have new sorrows, unhappy in their union by right of <lb n="350"/> capture with some victorious warrior, since now that the foe is conqueror they must expect a nightly office to come, increasing still their tearful griefs.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="356" end-line="358">Semichorus</speaker><p>The scout, my friends, is bringing us, as it seems to me, some fresh information; urging in haste the forwarding axles of his feet.</p></sp>
<pb n="88"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="359" end-line="361">Semichorus</speaker><p>Lo! the king himself, son of Oedipus, is here at<ref n="88.1">1</ref> just the moment to hear the scout's report; and <lb n="360"/> haste makes his gait, too, uneven.</p></sp>
<stage>(Enter from opposite sides of stage ETEOCLES and MESSENGER.)</stage>
<sp><speaker start-line="362" end-line="383">MESSENGER</speaker><p>I can tell from full observation the doings of our opponents, and how each has drawn his allotted station at our gates. Tydeus already at the gate of Prœtus is fretting —yet the seer forbids him to cross the Ismenus, since the sacrifices are not propitious. But Tydeus in wild excitement and eager for the fray is uttering sounds like hissings of a snake in the mid-day heat; and assails with taunts the seer, wise Œcleides, that 'out of cowardice he is shrinking <lb n="370"/> before [the approach of] death and battle.' Shouting such words, he shakes three overshadowing crests, the hairy plume of his helmet; and from beneath his shield bells of wrought brass are making a terrifying din. And upon his shield he bears a vaunting device as follows—a sky fashioned ablaze with stars; and in the middle of the shield a brilliant full moon, most august of the stars, the eye of Night, stands out conspicuous. In such wild exultation, with armour of boastful device, he is shouting on the river-bank; longing for the combat, like a horse fighting against the bit in his impatience who chafes as he hears<ref n="88.2">2</ref> the trumpet-call. Whom <lb n="380"/> wilt thou station to oppose this champion? Who, when the bolts of the gate of Prœtus are withdrawn, can be trusted to defend it?</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="88.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰς</foreign> Porson.</note>
<note type="footnote" n="88.2">2 Reading provisionally <foreign xml:lang="grc">κλύων</foreign> Tyrrwhit [<foreign xml:lang="grc">μένων</foreign> Μ.].</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="384" end-line="403">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>At no man's fancy costume shall I be frightened. Your devices make no wounds: crests and bell hurt not without a spear-thrust. And as for this Night glittering
<pb n="89"/>
with stars which thou sayest occupies the sky upon his shield, perhaps the conceit<ref n="89.1">1</ref> may prove prophetic to one I know. For if in death night descends upon his eyes, then <lb n="390"/> to him that bears it this high-vaunting device will prove itself rightly and correctly named, and he himself shall make this insolence prophetic against himself. Now against Tydeus I will station the brave son of Astacus here, as defender of the gate,—a man of right noble birth who worships the throne of Honour and detests arrogant speech; for idle in mean actions, but no coward, is he wont to be; and from the Sown Heroes, they whom Ares spared, his stock is sprung, and truly a native of this soil is he,—Melanippus. <lb n="400"/> The issue will Ares with his dice determine. Justice however, his near kinswoman, makes him her champion to keep off the foeman's spear from the mother who bore him.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="89.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἡ ’ννοία</foreign> Dindorf [<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἡ ἀνοία</foreign> Μ.].</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="404" end-line="408">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>May the gods grant that our champion gains the victory, who in a just cause speeds forth to fight for his city. Yet I fear on behalf of my friends to look on deaths by bloodshed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="409" end-line="423">MESSENGER</speaker><p>To him may the gods so grant to be victorious. But at the Electran gate Capaneus is stationed by lot; a <lb n="410"/> giant this man—taller than the one before mentioned;—and his boasting words betoken thoughts unsuited to a mortal, and he threatens terrible things (which may the gods not bring to pass!) against our defences; for he declares that, whether Heaven wills it or wills it not, he will sack our town, and not even the wrath of Zeus striking down upon the plain in his path shall restrain him. Lightning flashes and thunderbolts he compares to the warmth of the noon-tide sun. And he bears for device a naked man carrying fire, and a torch ready for action is blazing in his hands; <lb n="420"/> and in letters of gold he announces, 'I will burn the city.' To a man like this do thou send—who shall engage with
<pb n="90"/>
him, who shall abide without a tremor so vaunting a warrior?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="424" end-line="438">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>To this advantage of ours<ref n="90.1">1</ref> [in his over-confidence] yet another is added [in his impiety].<ref n="90.2">2</ref> Of a foolish mind surely his own tongue is true evidence against him. Capaneus utters threats, prepared to carry them out, and, slighting the gods as he exercises his tongue in foolish exultation, sends, though a mortal, swelling words ringing up to Zeus,—yet am I confident that against him <lb n="430"/> will justly come the fiery thunderbolt in no way to be compared to the warmth of the noontide sun. And against him, for all his insolence of speech, is ranged a champion fiery of spirit, stalwart Polyphontes, one to be relied upon as a guard, by favour of protecting Artemis and with aid of the other gods. Tell of another that hath his post at some other gate.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="90.1">1 Or (with Blomfield), 'In the case of this man too advantage is added to advantage.'</note>
<note type="footnote" n="90.2">2 Cf. v. 430.</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="439" end-line="443">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>May he perish who makes great boasts against our city, and may a thunderbolt restrain him ere he burst <lb n="440"/> into my chambers, or ever with insolent spear make havoc of maiden bowers.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="444" end-line="458">MESSENGER</speaker><p>Hear then, I will tell of him that next in order hath his station at the gates. The third for whom the lot leapt forth from the upturned helm was Eteoclus, that he should lead his company against the gate of Neïs. And he is wheeling to and fro his mares snorting in their headgear, willing to meet their death at the gate; and, in barbaric fashion, the nose-bands filled with breathings <lb n="450"/> from the nostrils of his steeds are making a whistling sound. And his shield is blazoned in no mean style:—a man in armour is ascending the steps of a scaling-ladder to an enemy's tower, seeking to storm it. And this one too in a
<pb n="91"/>
string of letters cries that, 'Not even Ares shall dash him down from the defences.' So against this one do thou send him who can be trusted to keep the yoke of slavery from this town.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="459" end-line="467">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>I will send at once this man here: and with good luck<ref n="91.1">1</ref> . . . There now he is sent on his way, bearing <lb n="460"/> his boast in his hands, Megareus—the seed of Creon of the race of the Sown—who will go forth from the gate no whit alarmed at the noise of the snortings of excited horses; but either in death will pay in full his debt of nurture to the land, or having captured two men and the citadel upon the shield will deck with trophies his father's house. Tell me of the vauntings of another of them. Spare me nothing in thy tale.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="91.1">1 There is a lacuna, probably of several lines, at this place.</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="468" end-line="472">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Hail, O champion of our homes! I pray that our side may be victorious, and that defeat may be the portion of our foes. Even as with frenzied mind they shout boastful threats against the city, so may Zeus the avenger <lb n="470"/> look upon them in wrath.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="473" end-line="487">MESSENGER</speaker><p>Another, fourth in order, having as his post the neighbouring gate of Onca Athena, is taking station by it with a shout, the form and mighty bulk of Hippomedon. And at the mighty orb—I mean the circle of his shield—I shuddered, as he twirled it: I will not speak beside the truth.<ref n="91.2">2</ref> And no mean artificer was the contriver of the device, who wrought upon the shield a work of art as follows:—Typhon sending forth from his <lb n="480"/> fire-breathing mouth black smoke, flickering sister of flame; and the rim running round the convex boss of the shield is made solid all round with coils of snakes. And the warrior himself raises ever and anon a shout, and inspired by Ares is wildly raving like a Mænad for the fray, glaring terribly.
<note type="footnote" n="91.2">2 Cf. <bibl>Theocritus xv</bibl>.</note>
<pb n="92"/>
The enterprise of such a man must be well guarded against; for panic is being already boastfully predicted at the gate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="488" end-line="507">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>In the first place Onca Pallas, as having her abode near the city hard by the gate, loathing the warrior's insolence will keep him away, as it were a dangerous snake, <lb n="490"/> from her brood. And Hyperbius, stout son of Oenops, has been chosen as a champion against yon champion, willing enough to discover what fate [he may expect] of Fortune<ref n="92.1">1</ref> in time of need,—a man not to be despised either in form or spirit or in the fashion of his equipment. And with good reason did Hermes pair them; for hostile is our hero to the champion with whom he will engage, and they twain will bring into conflict gods [depicted] on their shields who are hostile to each other. For the one bears [as device] fire-breathing Typhon, and Hyperbius has father Zeus, standing upright, planted upon the shield, making his thunder- <lb n="500"/> bolt blaze in his hand; and no one, I think, yet saw Zeus vanquished. Such then is the favour of the divinities on both sides, we are on the side of the conquerors, they on that of the conquered. And, inasmuch as Zeus was conqueror of Typhon in battle, it is likely that the men opposed to each other will fare even as [the gods they bear]; and for Hyperbius, in conformity with his device, may Zeus prove a protector.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="92.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐξιστορῆσαι μοῖραν τύχης=δαίμονος πειρᾶσθαι</foreign>. <bibl><title>Choeph.</title> 511</bibl>, <bibl><title>Ag.</title> 1163</bibl>.</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="508" end-line="512">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>I have full confidence that he who bears on his shield the unloved form of the under-world divinity who strove against Zeus, a presentment detestable to man- <lb n="510"/> kind and to the long-lived gods, will leave his head in front of our gate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="513" end-line="536">MESSENGER</speaker><p>May it prove so. I tell next of the fifth, who received the fifth station at the Borræan gate, over against the tomb of Zeus-born Amphion. He vows by
<pb n="93"/>
the spear which he carries, having the hardihood to reverence it more than any god and as more precious than his eyes, that surely he will sack the Cadmean city in spite of Zeus. Such is the speech of the handsome-faced offspring of a mountain-nurtured mother, a youth with a man's <lb n="520"/> spirit; and whiskers are just coming on his cheeks, his time of life producing them, thick hair growing up. And he, fierce in spirit that recalls not a maiden's name, and with grim countenance, stands nigh. Not indeed without a vaunting device does he station himself at the gate. On his bronze-wrought shield, the rounded defence of his body, he was swinging a Sphinx fastened to it with rivets, she that eats men raw, the reproach to our city, a shining figure hammered out from within. And beneath her she is carrying one of the Cadmeans, so that most shafts are <lb n="530"/> launched against this man. And now that he is come it is likely he will be no petty trafficker in battle,—nor bring discredit on his long journey hither, Parthenopaeus of Arcadia. A man of such quality is he, who has left his country and in repayment to Argos for her care in rearing him to comely manhood is threatening against these towers things which may Heaven not accomplish.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="537" end-line="549">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Yes, for if they obtain from Heaven what they design against us, with those impious vaunts of theirs, in utter ruin and misery will they perish. For this one too, the Arcadian as thou callest him, is there a warrior who <lb n="540"/> boasts not, but his hand looks for vigorous employment, Actor; brother of him I named before; who will not suffer a tongue unattended by deeds to find its way within the gates and breed mischief, nor him that bears upon his hostile shield the image of a hateful monster to enter; but remaining outside she<ref n="93.1">1</ref> shall have reason to complain of
<note type="footnote" n="93.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔξωθ᾽ δ’</foreign> Hermann [<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔξωθεν</foreign> M.]. Probably, however, there is a lacuna after v. 546.</note>

<pb n="94"/>
him that seeks to carry her within, meeting with repeated batterings at the foot of the city-wall. And by favour of the gods I shall be found to speak true.<ref n="94.1">1</ref></p></sp>


<sp><speaker start-line="550" end-line="554">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>The tale goes through my heart: the tresses of <lb n="550"/> my lifted hair stand on end to hear the high words of high-vaunting impious men. May the gods destroy them on our land.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="555" end-line="583">MESSENGER</speaker><p>I will speak now of the sixth, a warrior of much modesty and valiant in combat, a seer,—the doughty Amphiaraus. Stationed at the Homoloïan gate he is shouting repeatedly at the stalwart Tydeus with reproaches as, 'the murderer, the troubler of the city, greatest teacher of evil ways to Argos, a priest of Erinys, a minister<ref n="94.3">3</ref> of slaughter, and adviser of this evil course to Adrastus'; and, <lb n="560"/> again, . . . uplifting his eyes, and twice reproachfully dividing the name at the end [of his speech], he calls thy brother Poly-nices<ref n="94.4">4</ref> and from his mouth utters these words:—Is a deed like this acceptable to the gods and honourable for those who come after to hear<ref n="94.2">2</ref> and relate, an attempt to sack thy ancestral city and the [shrines of] thy kinsmen's gods by launching against them an army of mercenaries. What <lb n="570"/> plea can extinguish [the guilt of] a mother's murder? How shall thy motherland, made captive by the spear through thy rash enterprise, be thine ally? I myself shall doubtless enrich this soil with my blood, a seer lying in darkness beneath an enemy's land. Let us to the combat: I look for death but not dishonour. Such words spoke the seer, handling his rounded shield of bronze; and upon its circle there was no device, for his wish is, not to appear, but to be, a man of merit—reaping the harvest of a furrow deep in <lb n="580"/> his mind, whence spring his worthy resolves.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="94.1">1 The reading of this line is doubtful.</note>
<note type="footnote" n="94.2">2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">κλύειν</foreign> Paley [<foreign xml:lang="grc">κλύων</foreign> Μ.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="94.3">3 <foreign xml:lang="grc">λῃτῆρα</foreign> H. L. Ahrens [<foreign xml:lang="grc">κλητῆρα</foreign> Μ].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="94.4">4 <foreign xml:lang="grc">προσμόραν ἀδελφεόν</foreign> (563) is corrupt.</note>
<pb n="95"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="584" end-line="612">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Alas, for the luck which in mortal affairs associates the just man with the impious! In every undertaking nothing is worse than evil company: there no fruit is to be gathered. The [field of] infatuate daring has death produced as its harvest. Indeed a righteous man, embarked on a ship as associate of reckless sailors and some criminal <lb n="590"/> act, has ere now perished with the Heaven-detested crew. Or again, a just man associated with churlish citizens who forget the gods falling himself, in spite of his merits, into the same snare with them, has ere now been laid low by the scourge of Heaven that visits all alike. Even so the seer, I mean the son of Oecles, a man modest and just and brave and righteous, a prophet of renown, through his association with impious men of unbridled tongues, who are going a long march in despite of reason, shall by Zeus' will be dragged down with them to reach that far-off city. I think indeed that he will <lb n="600"/> not even assault the gate, not as being wanting in courage<ref n="95.1">1</ref> or from cowardice of spirit; but he knows in what fashion he is to meet his death in combat, if the divine warnings of Loxias bear fruit. And Loxias is wont either to keep silence, or to speak what is to the point. Yet will I station one to oppose him, the stalwart Lasthenes, a guardian of the gate surly to strangers. He shows a mature mind, though a youthful frame; a man of<ref n="95.2">2</ref> swift-glancing eye, and as to his hand, he is not slow to snatch the naked <lb n="610"/> spear from alongside the shield. But a man's good fortune is the gift of Heaven.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="95.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄθυμον</foreign> Turnebus (<foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐχ ὡς δειλόν</foreign> scholiast) [<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄθυμος</foreign> M.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="95.2">2 The accusatives added, as commonly, in description.</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="613" end-line="617">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Ye gods who listen to these our just supplications, in order that the city may prosper make them accomplished,
<pb n="96"/>
turning from us the evils of war upon the invaders.<ref n="96.1">1</ref> May Zeus cast them forth from the towers and destroy them with his thunderbolt.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="618" end-line="639">MESSENGER</speaker><p>The seventh here at the seventh gate will I now tell of, thine own brother, the fate that he vows and prays for to befall our city. Standing upon the towers and <lb n="620"/> having been proclaimed King to the whole land, raising in triumph a shout as over a captured city, [he vows] to engage with thee and having slain thee to die near by; or, if he lives, to punish thee, as one who<ref n="96.2">2</ref> dishonoured him by driving him from his home, with banishment in the same fashion as a revenge. Thus shouts the stalwart Polynices, and calls upon the gods of his family to see to the full accomplishment of his prayers. And he carries a handy buckler, newly wrought, and a device of two figures attached to it by <lb n="630"/> rivets:—a Man in semblance of a warrior in beaten gold a Woman is leading, preceding him with modest gait. She declares herself to be Justice, as the letters announce, [with the legend], 'I will restore this man from exile, and he shall have his city and the range of his ancestral home.' Of such nature are the inventions of our foes. Do thou thyself now decide whom to send forth: for in regard to the present speaker thou wilt never find reason to complain of his report; but it is for thee to decide of thyself how to guide the ship of state.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="96.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰς ἐπιμόλους</foreign> Seidler.</note>
<note type="footnote" n="96.2">2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀτιμαστηρά γ' ὡς</foreign> Walter Headlam [<foreign xml:lang="grc">τῶς</foreign> mutatum in <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὼς</foreign> Μ., <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὼς</foreign> G. mutatum in <foreign xml:lang="grc">θ' ὡς</foreign> quod habet Taur.].</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="640" end-line="663">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>O miserable our race descended from Oedipus, <lb n="640"/> infatuated by the Gods and an object of their hate! Alas! now indeed are my father's curses being accomplished. Still it becomes us not either to wail or weep, lest [cause for] lamentation even harder to bear may be produced thereby. But for him so justly named, Polynices I mean,
<pb n="97"/>
we shall soon know for certain in what that device of his will result: whether gold-wrought letters on his shield idly bragging in company with wandering of mind will bring him from exile. Had Justice, virgin daughter of Zeus, been companion of his deeds and mind, that would perhaps have come to pass. But neither when brought forth to light by <lb n="650"/> his mother, nor in his growth, nor when he reached youthful manhood, nor at the first harvest of a bearded chin, did Justice ever regard him or admit him to her presence; nor yet will she, I think, stand by to aid him in this evil treatment of his own land,—she who would falsely be named Justice if she associated with one of so reckless a mind. In this have I full confidence, and will engage with him <lb n="660"/> myself: what other has the better right?—prince with prince and brother with brother, foe with foe, I shall engage. Bring my greaves at once, my defences against point and stone.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="664" end-line="669">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Child of Oedipus, most dear to us, prove not thyself like in temper to him that hath the worst of names. No! let it suffice that Cadmean warriors do battle with Argive; for blood so shed may be expiated. But of warriors who are brothers death thus inflicted by each other's hands —of pollution such as this there is no decay.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="670" end-line="672">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>If indeed a man may suffer a wrong without <lb n="670"/> dishonour, then let it be so: that alone counts as gain among the dead. But of wrongs which involve disgrace, thou wilt find no glory to tell of.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="673" end-line="675">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Child, for what art thou fain? Let not wrathful lust of combat infatuate carry thee away. Cast away from thee the beginnings of desire for evil.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="676" end-line="678">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Since Heaven is urging on the event, let the wave of Cocytus go with the breeze, having made its own the whole race of Laius that is abhorred of Phoebus.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="679" end-line="681">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>A fiercely gnawing desire doth impel thee to
<pb n="98"/>
accomplish slaughter bitter in its fruits by the shedding of blood forbidden to thee.</p></sp>
<lb n="680"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="682" end-line="684">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Aye, for nigh to me sits in anger the black<ref n="98.1">1</ref> curse of my dear father with dry tearless eyes, telling me of gain which ranks before death which counts for less.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="685" end-line="688">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>But do not thou be hasty. Thou wilt not be called cowardly, since thou hast ordered thy life well [until now]. Erinys of dark ægis will go from the house when the gods receive propitiatory offerings at thy hands.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="689" end-line="691">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>By the gods we are already it seems made of no account, and the favour they pay regard to is the favour of our death. Why then should we shrink before our fatal doom?</p></sp>
<lb n="690"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="692" end-line="695">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>[Seize the occasion] now when [doom] stands near at hand; since Fortune may yet<ref n="98.2">2</ref> come with a fresher breeze in thy favour, shifting with a change of thy disposition made at the last moment, although now she is still stormy against thee.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="98.1">1 Reading provisionally <foreign xml:lang="grc">μέλαιν' ἀρὰ</foreign> Weil [<foreign xml:lang="grc">τελεῖ ἀρὰ</foreign> M.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="98.2">2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">αὖ τροπαίᾳ</foreign> Paley [<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀντροπαΐα</foreign> M.].</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="696" end-line="698">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>[Stormy indeed] for the curses of Oedipus have broken out in fury. Too true were the visions assigning the division of our ancestral wealth, that appeared in dreams by night.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="699" end-line="699">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Yield to women, although thou dislikest to do so.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="700" end-line="700">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Let something be said of which the doing is possible. No need of a long speech.</p></sp>
<lb n="700"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="701" end-line="701">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Go not thou on this errand [to station thyself] at the seventh gate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="702" end-line="702">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>Now that I am whetted for the contest, thou wilt not blunt me with thy talk.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="703" end-line="703">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Yet is there a victory, even if it means defeat, which the gods hold in honour.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="704" end-line="704">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>It is not for a man who bears arms to approve such a saying.</p></sp>
<pb n="99"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="705" end-line="705">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Art thou willing to cull the fruit of a brother's murder?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="706" end-line="706">ETEOCLES</speaker><p>When Heaven sends them thou canst not escape from misfortunes.</p><stage>[Exit ETEOCLES.]</stage></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="707" end-line="776">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>I shudder at the goddess who destroys homes, unlike to the other deities, prophet of evil true to the uttermost, Erinys of a father-invoked to fulfil the wrathful <lb n="710"/> imprecations of distraught Oedipus. This strife disastrous to his children is urging them on.</p>
<p>A Chalybian stranger is apportioning their shares, coming from his Scythian home as a fatal distributer of possessions, —the cruel steel, which hath allotted to them so much land to dwell in as they occupy in death, [deciding that] <lb n="720"/> they share not between them the broad plains.</p>
<p>When by each other's hand they shall have perished by mutual wounds, and the dust of earth hath drunk the dark-clotted blood of their slaughter, who can bring purification? who is to cleanse them [of their guilt]? O fresh troubles of the house mingling with ancient ill-fortune!</p>
<p>Of ancient origin I say was the transgression so swiftly avenged. To the third generation it remains, ever since <lb n="730"/> Laius in defiance of Apollo, after that the god had three times announced at the Pythian oracle at the centre of earth that by dying without offspring he would<ref n="99.1">1</ref> preserve the State, yet over-persuaded by the foolish advice of those dear to him did beget his own destruction, Oedipus the son who slew his sire: even he who dared to sow the sacred field of his mother where he himself was fostered with a root [prolific of] bloodshed. It was aberration of mind that <lb n="740"/> brought to wedlock the insensate pair.</p>
<note type="footnote" n="99.1">1 The present infinitive represents the historic present habitual in oracular utterances, e.g. <bibl><title>Ag.</title> 131</bibl>.</note>
<p>And, as it were, a surge of ills carries them along; one sinking, then it raises another with triple crest which
<pb n="100"/>
dashes at last over the poop the ship of State; and between us [and the sea] our protection extends but a little way in thickness, [the breadth only of] a tower. I fear lest together with its kings the city may be laid low.</p>
<p>For of curses uttered of old brought now to effect<ref n="100.1">1</ref> <lb n="750"/> mournful is the reconciliation. Calamity passes by men of little substance, but wealth of traders when too densely packed<ref n="100.2">2</ref> causes wholesale throwing overboard [of cargo].</p>
<p>For what man did the gods and his fellow-citizens and the thronged meetings of men so reverence as in days gone by they honoured Oedipus, when he removed from <lb n="760"/> the land the ravening goddess of death?</p>
<p>But when he came to true knowledge, unhappy man, of his wretched marriage unable to bear his woes he wrought in his misery with frenzied heart a double mischief. With the hand that slew his sire, he deprived himself of his eyes dearer than his children,</p>
<p>And let loose against his children a curse, in anger at the <lb n="770"/> maintenance they afforded him—bitter-tongued curses alas! even that they should divide his possessions with hands that settled their shares by the steel. And now I tremble lest nimble-footed Erinys may bring [those curses] to effect.</p></sp>
<stage>(Enter MESSENGER.)</stage>
<sp><speaker start-line="777" end-line="787">MESSENGER</speaker><p>Take courage, mother's darlings,<ref n="100.3">3</ref> this city has escaped destruction. The vauntings of stalwart men are fallen low. The city is in calm, and from many buffetings <lb n="780"/> of the surge [of war] has let in no water; the defences still are proof, and we keep the gates secure by our champions in single combat who have fulfilled their trust. At six of the gates all for the most part is well; but the seventh has
<note type="footnote" n="100.1">1 <foreign xml:lang="grc">τελειᾶν</foreign> Dindorf in <bibl>Steph. <foreign xml:lang="grc">τέλειος</foreign> p. 1958</bibl> [<foreign xml:lang="grc">τέλειαι</foreign> M.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="100.2">2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">πολύβατος</foreign> ex schol. Blomfield; <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀγὼν</foreign> Weil [<foreign xml:lang="grc">πολύβοτός τ' ἀνιὼ</foreign> M.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="100.3">3 Ironical, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">μαμμόθρεπτοι</foreign>. Cf. <foreign xml:lang="grc">τηθαλλοδοῦς</foreign>.</note>
<pb n="101"/>
Apollo to whom sacrifice is offered on the seventh day taken for his own, bringing to their appointed end upon the race of Oedipus the errors of Laius.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="788" end-line="788">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>What new happening is then so advantageous to the city?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="789" end-line="790">MESSENGER</speaker><p>The city is saved; the King's sons,<ref n="101.1">1</ref> the warriors are dead of wounds inflicted by each other's hand.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="791" end-line="791">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Who? What didst thou say? I am distraught <lb n="790"/> with anxiety as to thy announcement.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="792" end-line="792">MESSENGER</speaker><p>Listen now with sober mind. The two sons of Oedipus—</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="793" end-line="793">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Ah, woe is me! I have a presentiment of their evil fate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="794" end-line="794">MESSENGER</speaker><p>—in no doubtful fashion are indeed destroyed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="795" end-line="795">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Do they both lie yonder? Mournful though it be, yet explain thou all.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="795" end-line="795">MESSENGER</speaker><p>...</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="796" end-line="796">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Were they thus so much disfigured each by his brother's hand?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="797" end-line="806">MESSENGER</speaker><p>Even in this was their Fortune common to both. Of itself it now makes an end indeed of a luckless race. Such are the reasons we have to rejoice and to mourn—a city safe and sound, and on the other hand the <lb n="800"/> leaders, the two captains, have received by hammer-wrought Scythian iron each their full property in the city's wealth. They will have for their own the ground they occupy in their burial, carried thither on the course set them by their father's curse. The city is saved; and the land has drunk the blood of two royal brothers through their slaughter of one another.</p></sp>
<note type="footnote" n="101.1">1 This line, which interrupts the stichomuthia, was deleted by Porson as imported from v. 805.</note>
<sp><speaker start-line="807" end-line="940">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>O mighty Zeus, and guardian gods of our city
<pb n="102"/>
who are the preservers of these towers of Cadmus, whether <lb n="810"/> am I to rejoice and raise a cry of gladness for the security<ref n="102.1">1</ref> which is our rescuer, or am I to bewail the leaders in war thus unfortunate, luckless, childless—who all too truly in accordance with their name 'the men of strife' have perished in impious intent?</p>
<note type="footnote" n="102.1">1 Reading provisionally <foreign xml:lang="grc">σωτῆρι πόλεως ἀσινείᾳ</foreign> Hermann [<foreign xml:lang="grc">π. ἀσινεῖ σ.</foreign> M.].</note>
<p>O black Curse of Oedipus and his race now brought to accomplishment, a chill of sorrow falls upon my heart! Inspired [by grief], I compose a dirge for the grave, now <lb n="820"/> that I hear of their corpses dripping blood by evil fate thus dead. Ill omened indeed was their concert of spears.</p>
<p>It worked to fulfilment, nor did it relax—that solemn utterance from a father's lips; and the resolves of Laius due to his want of faith have had effect till now. Anxiety remains as to the city; for divine warnings do not lose their potency. Ah! ye whom we bewail, this that we <lb n="830"/> never looked for have ye done, and lamentable grief has come out of all reason.</p>
<stage>(The bearers carrying the corpses come into view.)</stage>
<p>Here now all is plain of itself. What the messenger told is now before our eyes. Twofold is our grief, double the evil fortune they have brought upon themselves, double the fated calamity now fulfilled. What shall I say? What else than that trouble is in the house? Come, dear ones, as the breeze of sorrow carries us along, wave your hands about your heads as ye escort the dead, in rhythmic movement which accompanies the passage across Acheron of the <lb n="840"/> unvoyaging ship with black sails, that is not trodden for the God of Day nor knows the sun, to the unseen landing-place that is the bourne of all.</p>
<p>But see, here are come Antigone and Ismene for this
<pb n="103"/>
mournful office, a dirge for their brethren. In no half-hearted fashion, I trow, will they for their loved ones utter from their deep-girdled bosoms a [strain of] grief befitting <lb n="850"/> the occasion. Us it behoves to sing, before their voice is heard, the sad-sounding Erinys-song and to raise thereafter the unwelcome Hades-chant. O ye most luckless in their brethren of all women who clasp the girdle about their robes, I weep for you and wail; and it is no guile to say that truly from my heart I raise this loud lament.</p>
<p>O misguided men, who would not be persuaded by your <lb n="860"/> friends, and in misfortune inexhaustible; unhappy ones, who ruined your ancestral homes by recourse to the spear. —Unhappy ones indeed, for ye found unhappy deaths, fraught with disaster to your house.</p>
<p>O ye who overthrew the walls of your home, and came to the sight of a fatal kingship, now are ye reconciled by recourse to the steel.—The awful curse of your father <lb n="870"/> Oedipus wrought a fulfilment true in deed. Stricken through the left sides, aye, stricken through sides born of a common mother, alas! thou wondrous ones; alas! for the curses resulting in death by each other's hand.—A home-thrust to house and body was [the blow] whereby thou sayest they were smitten in wrath that bears not telling, by a destiny due to a father's curse which they shared alike.</p>
<p>Through the city too there goes a sound of wailing; the <lb n="880"/> towers groan, and the plain that loved her heroes groans; whilst the possessions through which came strife, through which came doom of death to the ill-fated ones, will be for their descendants.—They made in their bitter wrath such <lb n="890"/> division of the possessions between themselves that each has now an equal share. The arbitrator at any rate has no blame from the friends [of either party], nor is Ares hailed as showing favour [to either side].</p>
<p>By the stroke of the steel they are as they are now, and
<pb n="104"/>
by stroke of steel there awaits them—what? some one may say—their share in the ancestral tomb.—A loud-sounding cry<ref n="104.1">1</ref> escorts them, a lamentation for these two princes, <lb n="900"/> heart-rending, bewailing its own griefs and its own woes, in anguish of mind, with no thought of joy, weeping tears that are truly from my heart, which as I mourn is wasting away.</p>
<note type="footnote" n="104.1">1 Reading provisionally <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀχάεσσ' ἰὰ</foreign> Weil.</note>
<p>[As epitaph] over the unhappy pair one may say, Much sorrow did they bring on their citizens and on all the ranks of foreigners who were destroyed in battle.—Hapless <lb n="910"/> beyond all women who have the name of mother was she who bore them. Having taken as husband her own son, she bore these princes; who have met their end, as ye see, in mutual slaughter each by the hand of his brother.</p>
<p>Brothers indeed, and now utterly destroyed by wounds unkind in frenzied strife as a termination to their feud.— Their hatred is stilled, and their life-blood is mingled with <lb n="920"/> the gory dust: thus are they united by blood indeed. A fatal resolver of contentions was the stranger that came from over-sea, the whetted steel; and fatal was that ill-divider of possessions, Ares, who brought to fulfilment their father's curse.</p>
<p>They have their shares, unhappy men, of heaven-sent sorrows, receiving each his portion; and underneath their <lb n="930"/> bodies they shall have a bottomless wealth of earth.—O ye who have made your family blossom forth in many a sorrow, at the last have the Curses cried over you their high-pitched strain, now that the whole race has been put to flight in utter rout. A monument of Calamity is set up at the gates, whereat they were done to death; and the divinity ceased its work when it laid both of them low.</p></sp>
<lb n="940"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="941" end-line="941">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Struck thou didst strike again.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="942" end-line="942">ISMENE</speaker><p>And thou in slaying wert slain.</p></sp>
<pb n="105"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="943" end-line="943">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>By the spear thou didst kill.</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="943" end-line="943">ISMENE</speaker><p>By the spear thou diedst.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="945" end-line="945">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Miserable thy deed.</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="945" end-line="945">ISMENE</speaker><p>Miserable thy fate.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="947" end-line="947">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Let lament go forth.</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="947" end-line="947">ISMENE</speaker><p>Let tears go forth.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="949" end-line="949">ANTIGONE and ISMENE</speaker><p>Thou liest low in death.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="950" end-line="950">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Ah me!</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="950" end-line="950">ISMENE</speaker><p>Ah me!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="952" end-line="952">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>My mind is distraught with wailing.</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="952" end-line="952">ISMENE</speaker><p>My heart <lb n="950"/> within me sighs.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="954" end-line="954">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>O thou most lamentable.</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="954" end-line="954">ISMENE</speaker><p>And thou too, most unhappy.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="956" end-line="956">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>By one dear to thee didst thou perish.</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="956" end-line="956">ISMENE</speaker><p>And one dear to thee didst thou slay.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="958" end-line="958">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>A twofold sorrow to relate.</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="958" end-line="958">ISMENE</speaker><p>A twofold grief to see.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="960" end-line="960">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Near to such griefs is this.<ref n="105.1">1</ref></p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="960" end-line="960">ISMENE</speaker><p>And here sisters <lb n="960"/> near to sisters.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="962" end-line="964">ANTIGONE and ISMENE</speaker><p>O grievous Fate, giver of ill gifts, and awful shade of Oedipus, a black Curse mighty indeed in power art thou!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="965" end-line="965">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Ah me!</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="965" end-line="965">ISMENE</speaker><p>Ah me!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="967" end-line="967">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Disaster sad to see</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="967" end-line="967">ISMENE</speaker><p>have ye shown to me after banishment.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="969" end-line="969">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>This one came with intent to slay,<ref n="105.2">2</ref></p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="969" end-line="969">ISMENE</speaker><p>and on <lb n="970"/> that errand lost his life.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="971" end-line="971">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>He perished indeed,</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="971" end-line="971">ISMENE</speaker><p>and slew this one here.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="973" end-line="973">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Hapless race!</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="973" end-line="973">ISMENE</speaker><p>Hapless affliction!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="975" end-line="975">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Lamentable in their relationship and lamentable in their woe.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="944" end-line="944">ISMENE</speaker><p>Steeped in calamity thrice over.<ref n="105.3">3</ref></p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="977" end-line="979">ANTIGONE and ISMENE</speaker><p>O grievous Fate, giver of ill gifts,
<note type="footnote" n="105.1">1 The text in this and the following line is uncertain.</note>
<note type="footnote" n="105.2">2 <foreign xml:lang="grc">κατακτενῶν</foreign> Halm [<foreign xml:lang="grc">κατάκτανεν</foreign> M.].</note>
<note type="footnote" n="105.3">3 Possibly <foreign xml:lang="grc">δίδυμα τριπλᾶ τε</foreign> should be read.</note>

<pb n="106"/>
and awful shade of Oedipus, a black curse mighty indeed in
power art thou!</p></sp>


<sp><speaker start-line="980" end-line="980">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Thou knowest [thy destiny] by going through it,</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="981" end-line="981">ISMENE</speaker><p>And thou art no whit behind in knowledge of <lb n="980"/> thine,</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="982" end-line="982">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>—when thou didst return to the city,</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="983" end-line="983">ISMENE</speaker><p>—aye, as opponent to this man here in combat.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="984" end-line="984">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Deadly it is to tell.</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="984" end-line="984">ISMENE</speaker><p>Deadly it is to see.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="986" end-line="986">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>O trouble!</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="986" end-line="986">ISMENE</speaker><p>O sorrow!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="988" end-line="988">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>—to home and land,</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="988" end-line="988">ISMENE</speaker><p>—aye, and moreover to me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="990" end-line="990">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>O prince, man of grievous misery!</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="990" end-line="990">ISMENE</speaker><p>O ye ful- <lb n="990"/> filled of sorrows beyond all men!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="992" end-line="992">ANTIGONE and ISMENE</speaker><p>O ye whom all divinities impelled on your fatal course!</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="993" end-line="993">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>O where shall we lay them in earth?</p></sp><sp><speaker start-line="993" end-line="993">ISMENE</speaker><p>O where-soever is most honourable.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="995" end-line="995">ANTIGONE and ISMENE</speaker><p>O calamity that was mated with their father!</p></sp>
<stage>(Enter the HERALD.)</stage>
<sp><speaker start-line="996" end-line="1016">HERALD</speaker><p>It is my office to announce what by the chief advisers of the city of Cadmus has been, and is, decreed. Eteocles yonder, for his friendship towards this country, it is resolved to bury with loving interment in the earth; for it was in striving to keep out the foe that he got his own death <lb n="1000"/> at this city. Pure in respect of the shrines of his ancestors and free from blame, he is dead [on the field of battle] where 'tis honourable for a young man to die. Thus with respect to him is it enjoined upon me to proclaim. But this man's brother, the dead body yonder of Polynices, [it is resolved] to cast out unburied, a prey to dogs, as one that would have been destroyer of the Cadmean town unless some divinity had stood in the way of his spear; and even
<pb n="107"/>
in death he shall have [the brand of] guilt in respect of his ancestral gods, without regard for whom he sought to take this city by launching against it a band of mercenaries. So <lb n="1010"/> it is decreed that he shall receive his reward by being buried in unseemly wise by the fowls of the air; and there shall attend him neither raising of a mound by hand nor shall any show him respect with loud strains of mourning, but he shall be without honour of burial by his friends. Such is the decree of the Cadmean authority.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1017" end-line="1032">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Aye, but this have I to say to the Cadmean authorities:—Though none other consent to aid me in burying this man, I myself will bury him, and will undertake the risk of burying my own brother; nor am I ashamed at incurring [the reproach of] disobedience that refuses <lb n="1020"/> submission to the State. A mighty influence is the common blood whence we are sprung, from an unhappy mother and an ill-fated sire. Willingly, therefore, for one who would not have willed it so, does my heart—the living for the dead— take a share in his misfortunes in sisterly spirit. His flesh never shall empty-bellied wolves gorge upon. Let no one think it. For I, though but a woman, will of myself contrive a tomb and [means of] interment for him, carrying [earth] <lb n="1030"/> in the bosom of my linen robe, and with my own hands will cover him. Let no one think the contrary. To my courage a plan will occur that will prove effective.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1033" end-line="1033">HERALD</speaker><p>I give thee notice not to act in defiance of the State in this matter.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1034" end-line="1034">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>I give notice to thee not to make useless proclamations to me.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1035" end-line="1035">HERALD</speaker><p>Yet the people is severe, now that it has escaped danger.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1036" end-line="1036">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Talk as you will of severity. This man shall not be deprived of burial.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1037" end-line="1037">HERALD</speaker><p>But wilt thou honour one whom the city hates?</p></sp>
<pb n="108"/>
<sp><speaker start-line="1038" end-line="1038">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Yes, for his condition is not beyond honour in the sight of the gods.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1039" end-line="1039">HERALD</speaker><p>It was not so, before he brought his country into danger.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1040" end-line="1040">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Having suffered wrong, he was but requiting it with wrong.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1041" end-line="1041">HERALD</speaker><p>But against all the citizens, instead of against <lb n="1040"/> one man only, was this enterprise of his directed.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1042" end-line="1043">ANTIGONE</speaker><p>Contention is the last of the goddesses to make an end of her tale. But I shall bury this man. Spare thy speeches.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1044" end-line="1044">HERALD</speaker><p>Well, be self-willed; but I forbid thee to do it.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1045" end-line="1057">CHORUS OF THEBAN MAIDENS</speaker><p>Alas, alas! O high-vaunting fatal Furies, ruiners of the race, who have thus destroyed root and branch the stock of Oedipus! what is to be my fate, what am I to do? What shall I attempt? How shall I endure neither to <lb n="1050"/> bewail thee, nor escort thee to the tomb? Yet am I afraid, and would fain avoid having dread of my own citizens. Thou indeed shalt find many to be thy mourners; but he there shall go unwept for, having only the single voice of a sister's lament. Who is there would so far yield obedience?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1058" end-line="1063">SEMICHORUS</speaker><p>Let the city punish those who mourn for Polynices, or let it not; for we here will go as his escort, <lb n="1060"/> and aid in burying him. For this grief is shared by all his race, whereas the city approves, now one way of justice, now another.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker start-line="1064" end-line="1070">SEMICHORUS</speaker><p>And we will go with this one here, as the city and justice join in approving. For, next to the Blessed Ones and the might of Zeus, this was he who chiefly rescued the Cadmean city from being overwhelmed, and submerged by a wave of foreign folk.</p></sp>
<lb n="1070"/>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
