<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="eng">The Odyssey of Homer</title>
            <author>Homer</author>
            <editor role="translator">George Chapman</editor>
            <editor>Rev. Richard Hooper</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial text generation from OCR and primary TEI XML encoding by</resp>
               <name>Gemini 3.5</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">New TEI XML edition started from OCR-generated text under the supervision of Gregory Crane.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Homer</author>
                  <title>The Odyssey of Homer</title>
                  <title type="sub">translated according to the Greek by George Chapman ; with an introduction and notes by Rev. Richard Hooper M.A.</title>
                  <editor>George Chapman</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>John Russell Smith</publisher>
                     <date>1857</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volumes">2 vol.</biblScope>

               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>           
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="line" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
               replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']//tei:l[@n='$2'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Line</p>
            </cRefPattern>
            <cRefPattern n="book" matchPattern="(\w+)"
               replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <refState delim="." unit="book"/>
            <refState unit="card"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <refState unit="book" delim="."/>
            <refState unit="line"/>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-07-10" who="Gemini 3.5">Initial file creation, OCR text generation, and basic EpiDoc TEI header tagging under Gregory Crane's supervision.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.chapman1611hooper1887-eng2" >
<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
  <pb n="1" facs="#63"/>
  <head rend="center">THE FIRST BOOK OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</head>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="1">
    <head rend="center">THE ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">THE Gods in council sit, to call</l>
    <l n="2">Ulysses from Calypso's thrall,</l>
    <l n="3">And order their high pleasures thus :</l>
    <l n="4">Grey Pallas to Telemachus</l>
    <l n="5">(In Ithaca) her way addrest;</l>
    <l n="6">And did her heavenly limbs invest</l>
    <l n="7">In Mentas' likeness, that did reign</l>
    <l n="8">King of the Taphians, in the main</l>
    <l n="9">Whose rough waves near Leucadia run,</l>
    <l n="10">Advising wise Ulysses' son</l>
    <l n="11">To seek his father, and address</l>
    <l n="12">His course to young Tantalides</l>
    <l n="13">That govern'd Sparta. Thus much said,</l>
    <l n="14">She shew'd she was Heaven's martial Maid,</l>
    <l n="15">And vanish'd from him. Next to this,</l>
    <l n="16">The Banquet of the Wooers is.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="2">
    <head rend="center">ANOTHER ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">"Αλφα. The Deities sit;</l>
    <l n="2">The Man retired;</l>
    <l n="3">The Ulyssean wit</l>
    <l n="4">By Pallas fired.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="text">
    <l n="1"><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>HE man, O Muse, inform, that many a way</l>
    <l n="2">Wound with his wisdom to his wished stay;</l>
    <l n="3">That wandered wondrous far, when he the town</l>
    <l n="4">Of sacred Troy had sack'd and shivered down;</l>

    <note xml:id="n1.1_note">The information or fashion of an absolute man; and necessary (or fatal) passage through many afflictions (according with the most Sacred Letter) to his natural haven and country; is the whole argument and scope of this inimitable and miraculous poem. And therefore is the epithet πολύτροπον given him in the first verse: πολύτροπος signifying, Homo cujus ingenium velut per multas et varias vias vertitur in veram.—CHAPMAN.</note>

    <pb n="2" facs="#64"/>

    <l n="5">The cities of a world of nations,</l>
    <l n="6">With all their manners, minds, and fashions,</l>
    <l n="7">He saw and knew; at sea felt many woes,</l>
    <l n="8">Much care sustained, to save from overthrows</l>
    <l n="9">Himself and friends in their retreat for home;</l>
    <l n="10">But so their fates he could not overcome,</l>
    <l n="11">Though much he thirsted it. O men unwise,</l>
    <l n="12">They perish'd by their own impieties,</l>
    <l n="13">That in their hunger's rapine would not shun</l>
    <l n="14">The oxen of the lofty-going Sun,</l>
    <l n="15">Who therefore from their eyes the day bereft</l>
    <l n="16">Of safe return. These acts, in some part left,</l>
    <l n="17">Tell us, as others, deified Seed of Jove.</l>
    <l n="18">Now all the rest that austere death outstrove</l>
    <l n="19">At Troy's long siege at home safe anchor'd are,</l>
    <l n="20">Free from the malice both of sea and war;</l>
    <l n="21">Only Ulysses is denied access</l>
    <l n="22">To wife and home. The grace of Goddesses,</l>
    <l n="23">The reverend nymph Calypso, did detain</l>
    <l n="24">Him in her caves, past all the race of men</l>
    <l n="25">Enflam'd to make him her lov'd lord and spouse.</l>
    <l n="26">And when the Gods had destin'd that his house,</l>
    <l n="27">Which Ithaca on her rough bosom bears,</l>
    <l n="28">(The point of time wrought out by ambient years)</l>
    <l n="29">Should be his haven, Contention still extends</l>
    <l n="30">Her envy to him, even amongst his friends.</l>
    <l n="31">All Gods took pity on him; only he,</l>
    <l n="32">That girds earth in the cincture of the sea,<anchor xml:id="n1.32_ref"/></l>

    <note target="#n1.32_ref"><mentioned>Neptune</mentioned>.</note>

    <pb n="3" facs="#65"/>

    <l n="33">Divine Ulysses ever did envy,</l>
    <l n="34">And made the fix'd port of his birth to fly.</l>
    <l n="35">But he himself solemnized a retreat</l>
    <l n="36">To th' Æthiops, far dissunder'd in their seat,</l>
    <l n="37">(In two parts parted, at the sun's descent,</l>
    <l n="38">And underneath his golden orient,</l>
    <l n="39">The first and last of men) t' enjoy their feast</l>
    <l n="40">Of bulls and lambs, in hecatombs address'd;<anchor xml:id="n1.40_ref"/></l>
    <l n="41">At which he sat, given over to delight.</l>
    <l n="42">The other Gods in heaven's supremest height</l>
    <l n="43">Were all in council met; to whom began</l>
    <l n="44">The mighty Father both of God and man</l>
    <l n="45">Discourse, inducing matter that inclined</l>
    <l n="46">To wise Ulysses, calling to his mind</l>
    <l n="47">Faultful Ægisthus, who to death was done<anchor xml:id="n1.47_ref"/></l>
    <l n="48">By young Orestes, Agamemnon's son.</l>
    <l n="49">His memory to the Immortals then</l>
    <l n="50">Mov'd Jove thus deeply : " O how falsely men</l>
    <l n="51">Accuse us Gods as authors of their ill,</l>
    <l n="52">When by the bane their own bad lives instil</l>
    <l n="53">They suffer all the miseries of their states,</l>
    <l n="54">Past our inflictions, and beyond their fates.</l>
    <l n="55">As now Ægisthus, past his fate, did wed</l>
    <l n="56">The wife of Agamemnon, and (in dread</l>

    <note target="#n1.40_ref">These notes following I am inforced to insert (since the words they contain differ from all other translations) lest I be thought to err out of that ignorance that may perhaps possess my depraver.—CHAPMAN.</note>
    <note target="#n1.47_ref">᾿Αμύμονος translated in this place inculpabilis, and made the epithet of Ægisthus, is from the true sense of the word, as it is here to be understood; which is quite contrary. As ἀντίθεος is to be expounded in some place Divinus, or Deo similis, but in another (soon after) contrarius Deo. The person to whom the epithet is given giving reason to distinguish it. And so ὀλοόφρων, an epithet given to Atlas, instantly following, in one place signifies mente perniciosus, in the next, qui universa mente gerit.—CHAPMAN.</note>

    <pb n="4" facs="#66"/>

    <l n="57">To suffer death himself) to shun his ill,</l>
    <l n="58">Incurred it by the loose bent of his will,</l>
    <l n="59">In slaughtering Atrides in retreat.<anchor xml:id="n1.59_ref"/></l>
    <l n="60">Which we foretold him would so hardly set</l>
    <l n="61">To his murderous purpose, sending Mercury</l>
    <l n="62">That slaughter'd Argus, our considerate spy,</l>
    <l n="63">To give him this charge: 'Do not wed his wife,</l>
    <l n="64">Nor murder him; for thou shalt buy his life</l>
    <l n="65">With ransom of thine own, imposed on thee</l>
    <l n="66">By his Orestes, when in him shall be</l>
    <l n="67">Atrides' self renew'd, and but the prime</l>
    <l n="68">Of youth's spring put abroad, in thirst to climb</l>
    <l n="69">His haughty father's throne by his high acts.'</l>
    <l n="70">These words of Hermes wrought not into facts</l>
    <l n="71">Ægisthus' powers; good counsel he despised,</l>
    <l n="72">And to that good his ill is sacrificed."</l>
    <l n="73">Pallas, whose eyes did sparkle like the skies,</l>
    <l n="74">Answer'd: "O Sire! Supreme of Deities,</l>
    <l n="75">Ægisthus past his fate, and had desert</l>
    <l n="76">To warrant our infliction; and convert</l>
    <l n="77">May all the pains such impious men inflict</l>
    <l n="78">On innocent sufferers to revenge as strict,</l>
    <l n="79">Their own hearts eating. But, that Ithacus,</l>
    <l n="80">Thus never meriting, should suffer thus,</l>
    <l n="81">I deeply suffer. His more pious mind</l>
    <l n="82">Divides him from these fortunes. Though unkind</l>
    <l n="83">Is piety to him, giving him a fate</l>
    <l n="84">More suffering than the most unfortunate,</l>
    <l n="85">So long kept friendless in a sea-girt soil,</l>
    <l n="86">Where the sea's navel is a sylvan isle,</l>

    <note target="#n1.59_ref"><mentioned>Retreat</mentioned>. It will be observed that Chapman frequently uses this word in the sense of return.</note>

    <pb n="5" facs="#67"/>
  

    <l n="87">In which the Goddess dwells that doth derive</l>
    <l n="88">Her birth from Atlas, who of all alive</l>
    <l n="89">The motion and the fashion doth command</l>
    <l n="90">With his wise mind, whose forces understand<anchor xml:id="n1.90_ref"/></l>
    <l n="91">The inmost deeps and gulfs of all the seas,</l>
    <l n="92">Who (for his skill of things superior) stays</l>
    <l n="93">The two steep columns that prop earth and heaven.</l>
    <l n="94">His daughter 'tis, who holds this homeless-driven<anchor xml:id="n1.94_ref"/></l>
    <l n="95">Still mourning with her; evermore profuse</l>
    <l n="96">Of soft and winning speeches, that abuse</l>
    <l n="97">And make so languishingly, and possest<anchor xml:id="n1.97_ref"/></l>
    <l n="98">With so remiss a mind her loved guest,</l>
    <l n="99">Manage the action of his way for home.</l>
    <l n="100">Where he, though in affection overcome,</l>
    <l n="101">In judgment yet more longs to show his hopes,</l>
    <l n="102">His country's smoke leap from her chimney tops,</l>
    <l n="103">And death asks in her arms. Yet never shall</l>
    <l n="104">Thy lov'd heart be converted on his thrall,</l>

    <note target="#n1.90_ref">In this place is Atlas given the epithet ὀλοόφρων, which signifies qui universa mente agitat, here given him for the power the stars have in all things. Yet this receives other interpretation in other places, as abovesaid. CHAPMAN.</note>
    <note target="#n1.94_ref">Δύσηνος is here turned by others, infelix, in the general collection; when it hath here a particular exposition, applied to express Ulysses' desert errors, παρὰ τὸ στῆναι, ut sit, qui vix locum invenire potest ubi consistat. CHAPMAN.</note>
    <note target="#n1.97_ref">This is thus translated, the rather to express and approve the allegory driven through the whole Odysseys. Deciphering the intangling of the wisest in his affections; and the torments that breed in every pious mind; to be thereby hindered to arrive so directly as he desires, at the proper and only true natural country of every worthy man, whose haven is heaven and the next life, to which, this life is but a sea in continual æsture and vexation. The words occasioning all this are μαλακοῖς λόγοις : μαλακὸς signifying, qui languide, et animo remisso rem aliquam gerit; which being the effect of Calypso's sweet words in Ulysses, is here applied passively to his own sufferance of their operation.—CHAPMAN.</note>

    <pb n="6" facs="#68"/>

    <l n="105">Austere Olympius. Did not ever he,</l>
    <l n="106">In ample Troy, thy altars gratify,</l>
    <l n="107">And Grecians' fleet make in thy offerings swim?</l>
    <l n="108">O Jove, why still then burns thy wrath to him?"</l>
    <l n="109">The Cloud-assembler answer'd: "What words fly,</l>
    <l n="110">Bold daughter, from thy pale of ivory?<anchor xml:id="n1.110_ref"/></l>
    <l n="111">As if I ever could cast from my care</l>
    <l n="112">Divine Ulysses, who exceeds so far</l>
    <l n="113">All men in wisdom, and so oft hath given</l>
    <l n="114">To all th' Immortals throned in ample heaven</l>
    <l n="115">So great and sacred gifts? But his decrees,</l>
    <l n="116">That holds the earth in with his nimble knees,<anchor xml:id="n1.116_ref"/></l>
    <l n="117">Stand to Ulysses' longings so extreme,</l>
    <l n="118">For taking from the God-foe Polypheme</l>
    <l n="119">His only eye; a Cyclop, that excelled</l>
    <l n="120">All other Cyclops, with whose burden swell'd</l>
    <l n="121">The nymph Thoosa, the divine increase</l>
    <l n="122">Of Phorcys' seed, a great God of the seas.</l>
    <l n="123">She mix'd with Neptune in his hollow caves,</l>
    <l n="124">And bore this Cyclop to that God of waves.</l>
    <l n="125">For whose lost eye, th' Earth-shaker did not kill</l>
    <l n="126">Erring Ulysses,<anchor xml:id="n1.126_ref"/> but reserves him still</l>
    <l n="127">In life for more death. But use we our powers,</l>
    <l n="128">And round about us cast these cares of ours,</l>

    <note target="#n1.110_ref">"Ερκος ὀδόντων, viz. vallum or claustrum dentium, which, for the better sound in our language, is here turned, Pale of Ivory. The teeth being that rampire or pale, given us by nature in that part for restraint and compression of our speech, till the imagination, appetite, and soul (that ought to rule in their examination, before their delivery) have given worthy pass to them. The most grave and divine poet teaching therein, that not so much for the necessary chewing of our sustenance our teeth are given us, as for their stay of our words, lest we utter them rashly.—CHAPMAN.</note>
    <note target="#n1.116_ref"><mentioned>Neptune</mentioned>.</note>
    <note target="#n1.126_ref"><mentioned>Erring</mentioned>—wandering.</note>

    <pb n="7" facs="#69"/>
    

    <l n="129">All to discover how we may prefer</l>
    <l n="130">His wished retreat, and Neptune make forbear</l>
    <l n="131">His stern eye to him, since no one God can,</l>
    <l n="132">In spite of all, prevail, but 'gainst a man."</l>
    <l n="133">To this, this answer made the grey-eyed Maid:</l>
    <l n="134">"Supreme of rulers, since so well apaid<anchor xml:id="n1.134_ref_1"/></l>
    <l n="135">The blessed Gods are all then, now, in thee,</l>
    <l n="136">To limit wise Ulysses' misery,</l>
    <l n="137">And that you speak as you referred to me</l>
    <l n="138">Prescription for the means, in this sort be</l>
    <l n="139">Their sacred order: Let us now address</l>
    <l n="140">With utmost speed our swift Argicides,</l>
    <l n="141">To tell the nymph that bears the golden tress</l>
    <l n="142">In th' isle Ogygia, that 'tis our will</l>
    <l n="143">She should not stay our loved Ulysses still,</l>
    <l n="144">But suffer his return; and then will I</l>
    <l n="145">To Ithaca, to make his son apply</l>
    <l n="146">His sire's inquest<anchor xml:id="n1.146_ref"/> the more; infusing force</l>
    <l n="147">Into his soul, to summon the concourse</l>
    <l n="148">Of curl'd-head Greeks to council, and deter</l>
    <l n="149">Each wooer, that hath been the slaughterer</l>
    <l n="150">Of his fat sheep and crooked-headed beeves,</l>
    <l n="151">From more wrong to his mother, and their leaves</l>
    <l n="152">Take in such terms, as fit deserts so great.</l>
    <l n="153">To Sparta then, and Pylos, where doth beat</l>
    <l n="154">Bright Amathus, the flood, and epithet<anchor xml:id="n1.154_ref"/></l>
    <l n="155">To all that kingdom, my advice shall send</l>
    <l n="156">The spirit-advanced Prince, to the pious end</l>
    <l n="157">Of seeking his lost father, if he may</l>
    <l n="158">Receive report from Fame where rests his stay,</l>

    <note target="#n1.134_ref_1"><mentioned>Apaid</mentioned>—satisfied, content.</note>
    <note target="#n1.146_ref"><mentioned>Inquest</mentioned>—search.</note>
    <note target="#n1.154_ref"><mentioned>Epithet</mentioned>—i. e. gives the epithet ἠμαθόεις, sandy, to Pylos.</note>

    <pb n="8" facs="#70"/>
    

    <l n="159">And make, besides, his own sucessive worth</l>
    <l n="160">Known to the world, and set in action forth."</l>
    <l n="161">This said, her wing'd shoes to her feet she tied,</l>
    <l n="162">Formed all of gold, and all eternified,</l>
    <l n="163">That on the round earth or the sea sustain'd</l>
    <l n="164">Her ravish'd substance swift as gusts of wind.</l>
    <l n="165">Then took she her strong lance with steel made keen,</l>
    <l n="166">Great, massy, active, that whole hosts of men,</l>
    <l n="167">Though all heroës, conquers, if her ire</l>
    <l n="168">Their wrongs inflame, back'd by so great a Sire.</l>
    <l n="169">Down from Olympus' tops she headlong dived,</l>
    <l n="170">And swift as thought in Ithaca arriv'd,</l>
    <l n="171">Close at Ulysses' gates; in whose first court</l>
    <l n="172">She made her stand, and, for her breast's support,</l>
    <l n="173">Leaned on her iron lance; her form impress'd</l>
    <l n="174">With Mentas' likeness,<anchor xml:id="n1.174_ref"/> come, as being a guest.</l>
    <l n="175">There found she those proud wooers, that were then</l>
    <l n="176">Set on those ox-hides that themselves had slain,</l>
    <l n="177">Before the gates, and all at dice were playing.</l>
    <l n="178">To them the heralds, and the rest obeying,</l>
    <l n="179">Fill'd wine and water; some, still as they play'd,</l>
    <l n="180">And some, for solemn supper's state, purvey'd,</l>
    <l n="181">With porous sponges, cleansing tables, serv'd</l>
    <l n="182">With much rich feast; of which to all they kerv'd.<anchor xml:id="n1.182_ref"/></l>
    <l n="183">God-like Telemachus amongst them sat,</l>
    <l n="184">Griev'd much in mind; and in his heart begat</l>
    <l n="185">All representment of his absent sire,</l>
    <l n="186">How, come from far-off parts, his spirits would fire</l>
    <l n="187">With those proud wooers' sight, with slaughter parting</l>
    <l n="188">Their bold concourse, and to himself converting</l>

    <note target="#n1.174_ref"><mentioned>Mentas' likeness</mentioned>—Mentes, son of Anchialus, king of the Taphians, north of Ithaca.</note>
    <note target="#n1.182_ref"><mentioned>Kerved</mentioned>—carved.</note>

    <pb n="9" facs="#71"/>
    

    <l n="189">The honours they usurp'd, his own commanding.</l>
    <l n="190">In this discourse, he first saw Pallas standing,</l>
    <l n="191">Unbidden entry; up rose, and address'd</l>
    <l n="192">His pace right to her, angry that a guest</l>
    <l n="193">Should stand so long at gate; and, coming near,</l>
    <l n="194">Her right hand took, took in his own her spear,</l>
    <l n="195">And thus saluted: "Grace to your repair,</l>
    <l n="196">Fair guest, your welcome shall be likewise fair.</l>
    <l n="197">Enter, and, cheer'd with feast, disclose th' intent</l>
    <l n="198">That caused your coming." This said, first he went,</l>
    <l n="199">And Pallas follow'd. To a room they came,</l>
    <l n="200">Steep, and of state; the javelin of the Dame</l>
    <l n="201">He set against a pillar vast and high,</l>
    <l n="202">Amidst a large and bright-kept armory,</l>
    <l n="203">Which was, besides, with woods of lances grac'd</l>
    <l n="204">Of his grave father's. In a throne he plac'd</l>
    <l n="205">The man-turn'd Goddess, under which was spread</l>
    <l n="206">A carpet, rich and of deviceful thread;</l>
    <l n="207">A footstool staying her feet; and by her chair</l>
    <l n="208">Another seat (all garnish'd wondrous fair,</l>
    <l n="209">To rest or sleep on in the day) he set,</l>
    <l n="210">Far from the prease of wooers, lest at meat</l>
    <l n="211">The noise they still made might offend his guest,</l>
    <l n="212">Disturbing him at banquet or at rest,</l>
    <l n="213">Even to his combat with that pride of theirs,</l>
    <l n="214">That kept no noble form in their affairs.</l>
    <l n="215">And these he set far from them, much the rather</l>
    <l n="216">To question freely of his absent father.</l>
    <l n="217">A table fairly-polish'd then was spread,</l>
    <l n="218">On which a reverend officer set bread,</l>
    <l n="219">And other servitors all sorts of meat</l>
    <l n="220">(Salads, and flesh, such as their haste could get)</l>

    <pb n="10" facs="#72"/>
    

    <l n="221">Serv'd with observance in. And then the sewer</l>
    <l n="222">Pour'd water from a great and golden ewer,</l>
    <l n="223">That from their hands t' a silver caldron ran.</l>
    <l n="224">Both wash'd, and seated close, the voiceful man</l>
    <l n="225">Fetch'd cups of gold, and set by them, and round</l>
    <l n="226">Those cups with wine with all endeavour crown'd.</l>
    <l n="227">Then rush'd in the rude wooers, themselves plac'd;</l>
    <l n="228">The heralds water gave; the maids in haste</l>
    <l n="229">Serv'd bread from baskets. When, of all prepar'd</l>
    <l n="230">And set before them, the bold wooers shar'd,</l>
    <l n="231">Their pages plying their cups past the rest.</l>
    <l n="232">But lusty wooers must do more than feast;</l>
    <l n="233">For now, their hungers and their thirsts allay'd,</l>
    <l n="234">They call'd for songs and dances; those, they said,</l>
    <l n="235">Were th' ornaments of feast. The herald straight</l>
    <l n="236">A harp, carv'd full of artificial sleight,</l>
    <l n="237">Thrust into Phemius', a learn'd singer's, hand,</l>
    <l n="238">Who, till he much was urged, on terms did stand,</l>
    <l n="239">But, after, play'd and sung with all his art.</l>
    <l n="240">Telemachus to Pallas then (apart,</l>
    <l n="241">His ear inclining close, that none might hear)</l>
    <l n="242">In this sort said: "My guest, exceeding dear,</l>
    <l n="243">Will you not sit incens'd with what I say?</l>
    <l n="244">These are the cares these men take; feast and play.</l>
    <l n="245">Which eas'ly they may use, because they eat,</l>
    <l n="246">Free and unpunish'd, of another's meat;</l>
    <l n="247">And of a man's, whose white bones wasting lie</l>
    <l n="248">In some far region, with th' incessancy</l>
    <l n="249">Of showers pour'd down upon them, lying ashore,</l>
    <l n="250">Or in the seas wash'd naked. Who, if he wore</l>
    <l n="251">Those bones with flesh and life and industry,</l>
    <l n="252">And these might here in Ithaca set eye</l>

    <pb n="11" facs="#73"/>
    

    <l n="253">On him return'd, they all would wish to be</l>
    <l n="254">Either past other in celerity</l>
    <l n="255">Of feet and knees, and not contend t' exceed</l>
    <l n="256">In golden garments. But his virtues feed</l>
    <l n="257">The fate of ill death; nor is left to me</l>
    <l n="258">The least hope of his life's recovery,</l>
    <l n="259">No, not if any of the mortal race</l>
    <l n="260">Should tell me his return; the cheerful face</l>
    <l n="261">Of his return'd day never will appear.</l>
    <l n="262">But tell me, and let Truth your witness bear,</l>
    <l n="263">Who, and from whence you are? What city's birth?</l>
    <l n="264">What parents? In what vessel set you forth?</l>
    <l n="265">And with what mariners arrived you here?</l>
    <l n="266">I cannot think you a foot passenger.</l>
    <l n="267">Recount then to me all, to teach me well</l>
    <l n="268">Fit usage for your worth. And if it fell</l>
    <l n="269">In chance now first that you thus see us here,</l>
    <l n="270">Or that in former passages you were</l>
    <l n="271">My father's guest? For many men have been</l>
    <l n="272">Guests to my father. Studious of men</l>
    <l n="273">His sociable nature ever was."</l>
    <l n="274">On him again the grey-eyed Maid did pass</l>
    <l n="275">This kind reply: " I'll answer passing true</l>
    <l n="276">All thou hast ask'd: My birth his honour drew</l>
    <l n="277">From wise Anchialus. The name I bear</l>
    <l n="278">Is Mentas, the commanding islander</l>
    <l n="279">Of all the Taphians studious in the art</l>
    <l n="280">Of navigation; having touch'd this part</l>
    <l n="281">With ship and men, of purpose to maintain</l>
    <l n="282">Course through the dark seas t' other-languag'd men;</l>
    <l n="283">And Temesis sustains the city's name</l>
    <l n="284">For which my ship is bound, made known by fame</l>

    <pb n="12" facs="#74"/>
    

    <l n="285">For rich in brass, which my occasions need,</l>
    <l n="286">And therefore bring I shining steel in stead,</l>
    <l n="287">Which their use wants, yet makes my vessel's freight,</l>
    <l n="288">That near a plough'd field rides at anchor's weight,</l>
    <l n="289">Apart this city, in the harbour call'd</l>
    <l n="290">Rethrus, whose waves with Neius' woods are wall'd.</l>
    <l n="291">Thy sire and I were ever mutual guests,</l>
    <l n="292">At either's house still interchanging feasts.</l>
    <l n="293">I glory in it. Ask, when thou shalt see</l>
    <l n="294">Laertes, th' old heroë, these of me,</l>
    <l n="295">From the beginning. He, men say, no more</l>
    <l n="296">Visits the city, but will needs deplore</l>
    <l n="297">His son's believed loss in a private field;</l>
    <l n="298">One old maid only at his hands to yield</l>
    <l n="299">Food to his life, as oft as labour makes</l>
    <l n="300">His old limbs faint; which, though he creeps, he takes</l>
    <l n="301">Along a fruitful plain, set all with vines,</l>
    <l n="302">Which husbandman-like, though a king, he proins.</l>
    <l n="303">But now I come to be thy father's guest;</l>
    <l n="304">I hear he wanders, while these wooers feast.</l>
    <l n="305">And (as th' Immortals prompt me at this hour)</l>
    <l n="306">I'll tell thee, out of a prophetic power,</l>
    <l n="307">(Not as profess'd a prophet, nor clear seen</l>
    <l n="308">At all times what shall after chance to men)</l>
    <l n="309">What I conceive, for this time, will be true:</l>
    <l n="310">The Gods' inflictions keep your sire from you.</l>
    <l n="311">Divine Ulysses, yet, abides not dead</l>
    <l n="312">Above earth, nor beneath, nor buried</l>
    <l n="313">In any seas, as you did late conceive,</l>
    <l n="314">But, with the broad sea sieged, is kept alive</l>
    <l n="315">Within an isle by rude and upland men,</l>
    <l n="316">That in his spite his passage home detain.</l>
    <l n="317">Yet long it shall not be before he tread</l>

    <pb n="13" facs="#75"/>
    

    <l n="318">His country's dear earth, though solicited,</l>
    <l n="319">And held from his return, with iron chains;</l>
    <l n="320">For he hath wit to forge a world of trains,</l>
    <l n="321">And will, of all, be sure to make good one</l>
    <l n="322">For his return, so much relied upon.</l>
    <l n="323">But tell me, and be true: Art thou indeed</l>
    <l n="324">So much a son, as to be said the seed<anchor xml:id="n1.324_ref"/></l>
    <l n="325">Of Ithacus himself? Exceeding much</l>
    <l n="326">Thy forehead and fair eyes at his form touch;</l>
    <l n="327">For oftentimes we met, as you and I</l>
    <l n="328">Meet at this hour, before he did apply</l>
    <l n="329">His powers for Troy, when other Grecian states<anchor xml:id="n1.329_ref"/></l>
    <l n="330">In hollow ships were his associates.</l>
    <l n="331">But, since that time, mine eyes could never see</l>
    <l n="332">Renown'd Ulysses, nor met his with me."</l>
    <l n="333">The wise Telemachus again replied:</l>
    <l n="334">"You shall with all I know be satisfied.</l>
    <l n="335">My mother certain says I am his son;</l>
    <l n="336">I know not; nor was ever simply known</l>
    <l n="337">By any child the sure truth of his sire.</l>
    <l n="338">But would my veins had took in living fire</l>
    <l n="339">From some man happy, rather than one wise,</l>
    <l n="340">Whom age might see seis'd of what youth made prise.<anchor xml:id="n1.340_ref"/></l>
    <l n="341">But he whoever of the mortal race</l>
    <l n="342">Is most unblest, he holds my father's place.</l>
    <l n="343">This, since you ask, I answer." She, again:</l>
    <l n="344">"The Gods sure did not make the future strain<anchor xml:id="n1.344_ref"/></l>

    <note target="#n1.324_ref">Τόσος παῖς, Tantus filius. Pallas thus enforcing her question, to stir up the son the more to the father's worthiness. CHAPMAN.</note>
    <note target="#n1.329_ref"><mentioned>States</mentioned>—princes. See Iliad 11. 69.</note>
    <note target="#n1.340_ref"><mentioned>Seised</mentioned>—in possession of.</note>
    <note target="#n1.344_ref"><mentioned>Strain</mentioned>—descent. So Shakespeare, "Thus far I can praise him; he is of a noble strain, of approved valour, and confirmed honesty. —Much Ado, II. 1.</note>

    <pb n="14" facs="#76"/>
    

    <l n="345">Both of thy race and days obscure to thee,</l>
    <l n="346">Since thou wert born so of Penelope.</l>
    <l n="347">The style may by thy after acts be won,</l>
    <l n="348">Of so great sire the high undoubted son.</l>
    <l n="349">Say truth in this then: What's this feasting here?</l>
    <l n="350">What all this rout? Is all this nuptial cheer?</l>
    <l n="351">Or else some friendly banquet made by thee?</l>
    <l n="352">For here no shots are, where all sharers be.<anchor xml:id="n1.352_ref"/></l>
    <l n="353">Past measure contumeliously this crew</l>
    <l n="354">Fare through thy house; which should th' ingenuous view</l>
    <l n="355">Of any good or wise man come and find,</l>
    <l n="356">(Impiety seeing play'd in every kind)</l>
    <l n="357">He could not but through every vein be mov'd."</l>
    <l n="358">Again Telemachus: "My guest much loved,</l>
    <l n="359">Since you demand and sift these sights so far,</l>
    <l n="360">I grant 'twere fit a house so regular,</l>
    <l n="361">Rich, and so faultless once in government,</l>
    <l n="362">Should still at all parts the same form present</l>
    <l n="363">That gave it glory while her lord was here.</l>
    <l n="364">But now the Gods, that us displeasure bear,</l>
    <l n="365">Have otherwise appointed, and disgrace<anchor xml:id="n1.365_ref"/></l>
    <l n="366">My father most of all the mortal race.</l>
    <l n="367">For whom I could not mourn so were he dead,</l>
    <l n="368">Amongst his fellow captains slaughtered</l>

    <note target="#n1.352_ref"><mentioned>Shots</mentioned>—reckoning, sum charged. Though now only used as a vulgar term, it was not uncommon in our older writers. Shakespeare, "A man is never welcome to a place till some certain shot be paid, and the hostess say, welcome." Two Gent. Veron. 11. 5. The derivation is from Anglo-Sax. sceat, tax, treasure, or a piece of metal in an uncoined state equal to a penny. See BOSWORTH'S Anglo-Sax. Dict. It occurs in almost every language. See Ital. scotto and Cotgrave in v. escot.</note>
    <note target="#n1.365_ref"><mentioned>Disgrace</mentioned>—put out of favour, are unkind to.</note>
<pb n="15"/>

<l n="369">By common enemies, or in the hands</l>
        <l n="370">Of his kind friends had ended his commands,</l>
        <l n="371">After he had egregiously bestow'd</l>
        <l n="372">His power and order in a war so vow'd,</l>
        <l n="373">And to his tomb all Greeks their grace had done,</l>
        <l n="374">That to all ages he might leave his son</l>
        <l n="375">Immortal honour; but now Harpies have</l>
        <l n="376">Digg'd in their gorges his abhorred grave.</l>
        <l n="377">Obscure, inglorious, death hath made his end,</l>
        <l n="378">And me, for glories, to all griefs contend.</l>
        <l n="379">Nor shall I any more mourn him alone,</l>
        <l n="380">The Gods have given me other cause of moan.</l>
        <l n="381">For look how many optimates remain</l>
        <l n="382">In Samos, or the shores Dulichian,</l>
        <l n="383">Shady Zacynthus, or how many bear</l>
        <l n="384">Rule in the rough brows of this island here;</l>
        <l n="385">So many now my mother and this house</l>
        <l n="386">At all parts make defamed and ruinous;</l>
        <l n="387">And she her hateful nuptials nor denies,</l>
        <l n="388">Nor will dispatch their importunities,</l>
        <l n="389">Though she beholds them spoil still as they feast</l>
        <l n="390">All my free house yields, and the little rest</l>
        <l n="391">Of my dead sire in me perhaps intend</l>
        <l n="392">To bring ere long to some untimely end."</l>
        <l n="393">This Pallas sigh'd and answer'd: "O," said she,</l>
        <l n="394">" Absent Ulysses is much miss'd by thee,</l>
        <l n="395">That on these shameless suitors he might lay</l>
        <l n="396">His wreakful hands. Should he now come, and stay</l>
        <l n="397">In thy court's first gates, arm'd with helm and shield,</l>
        <l n="398">And two such darts as I have seen him wield,</l>
        <l n="399">When first I saw him in our Taphian court,</l>
        <l n="400">Feasting, and doing his desert's disport;</l>

        <pb n="16" facs="#78"/>
        

        <l n="401">When from Ephyrus he return'd by us</l>
        <l n="402">From Ilus, son to Centaur Mermerus,</l>
        <l n="403">To whom he travell'd through the watery dreads,</l>
        <l n="404">For bane to poison his sharp arrows' heads,</l>
        <l n="405">That death, but touch'd, caused; which he would not give,</l>
        <l n="406">Because he fear'd the Gods that ever live</l>
        <l n="407">Would plague such death with death; and yet their fear</l>
        <l n="408">Was to my father's bosom not so dear</l>
        <l n="409">As was thy father's love; (for what he sought</l>
        <l n="410">My loving father found him to a thought.)</l>
        <l n="411">If such as then Ulysses might but meet</l>
        <l n="412">With these proud wooers, all were at his feet</l>
        <l n="413">But instant dead men, and their nuptials</l>
        <l n="414">Would prove as bitter as their dying galls.</l>
        <l n="415">But these things in the Gods' knees are reposed,</l>
        <l n="416">If his return shall see with wreak inclosed,</l>
        <l n="417">These in his house, or he return no more;</l>
        <l n="418">And therefore I advise thee to explore</l>
        <l n="419">All ways thyself, to set these wooers gone;</l>
        <l n="420">To which end give me fit attention:</l>
        <l n="421">To-morrow into solemn council call</l>
        <l n="422">The Greek heroës, and declare to all</l>
        <l n="423">(The Gods being witness) what thy pleasure is.</l>
        <l n="424">Command to towns of their nativity,</l>
        <l n="425">These frontless wooers. If thy mother's mind</l>
        <l n="426">Stands to her second nuptials so inclined,</l>
        <l n="427">Return she to her royal father's towers,</l>
        <l n="428">Where th' one of these may wed her, and her dowers</l>
        <l n="429">Make rich, and such as may consort with grace</l>
        <l n="430">So dear a daughter of so great a race.</l>
        <l n="431">And thee I warn as well (if thou as well</l>
        <l n="432">Wilt hear and follow) take thy best built sail,</l>

        <pb n="17" facs="#79"/>
        

        <l n="433">With twenty oars mann'd, and haste t' inquire</l>
        <l n="434">Where the abode is of thy absent sire,</l>
        <l n="435">If any can inform thee, or thine ear</l>
        <l n="436">From Jove the fame of his retreat may hear,</l>
        <l n="437">For chiefly Jove gives all that honours men.</l>
        <l n="438">To Pylos first be thy addression then,</l>
        <l n="439">To god-like Nestor; thence to Sparta haste,</l>
        <l n="440">To gold-lock'd Menelaus, who was last</l>
        <l n="441">Of all the brass-arm'd Greeks that sail'd from Troy;</l>
        <l n="442">And try from both these, if thou canst enjoy</l>
        <l n="443">News of thy sire's returned life, anywhere,</l>
        <l n="444">Though sad thou suffer'st in his search a year.</l>
        <l n="445">If of his death thou hear'st, return thou home,</l>
        <l n="446">And to his memory erect a tomb,</l>
        <l n="447">Performing parent-rites, of feast and game,</l>
        <l n="448">Pompous, and such as best may fit his fame;</l>
        <l n="449">And then thy mother a fit husband give.</l>
        <l n="450">These past, consider how thou mayst deprive</l>
        <l n="451">Of worthless life these wooers in thy house,</l>
        <l n="452">By open force, or projects enginous.<anchor xml:id="n1.452_ref"/></l>
        <l n="453">Things childish fit not thee; th' art so no more.</l>
        <l n="454">Hast thou not heard, how all men did adore</l>
        <l n="455">Divine Orestes, after he had slain</l>
        <l n="456">Ægisthus murdering by a treacherous train</l>
        <l n="457">His famous father? Be then, my most loved,</l>
        <l n="458">Valiant and manly, every way approved</l>
        <l n="459">As great as he. I see thy person fit,</l>
        <l n="460">Noble thy mind, and excellent thy wit,</l>
        <l n="461">All given thee so to use and manage here</l>
        <l n="462">That even past death they may their memories bear.</l>

        <note target="#n1.452_ref"><mentioned>Enginous</mentioned>—ingenious. See Nares on the words, engine, and inginous.</note>

        <pb n="18" facs="#80"/>
        

        <l n="463">In mean time I'll descend to ship and men,</l>
        <l n="464">That much expect me. Be observant then</l>
        <l n="465">Of my advice, and careful to maintain</l>
        <l n="466">In equal acts thy royal father's reign."</l>
        <l n="467">Telemachus replied: "You ope, fair guest,</l>
        <l n="468">A friend's heart in your speech, as well express'd</l>
        <l n="469">As might a father serve t' inform his son brass-arm'd</l>
        <l n="470">All which sure place have in my memory won.</l>
        <l n="471">Abide yet, though your voyage calls away,</l>
        <l n="472">That, having bath'd, and dignified your stay</l>
        <l n="473">With some more honour, you may yet beside</l>
        <l n="474">Delight your mind by being gratified</l>
        <l n="475">With some rich present taken in your way,</l>
        <l n="476">That, as a jewel, your respect may lay</l>
        <l n="477">Up in your treasury, bestow'd by me,</l>
        <l n="478">As free friends use to guests of such degree."</l>
        <l n="479">" Detain me not," said she, " so much inclined</l>
        <l n="480">To haste my voyage. What thy loved mind</l>
        <l n="481">Commands to give, at my return this way,</l>
        <l n="482">Bestow on me, that I directly may</l>
        <l n="483">Convey it home; which more of price to me</l>
        <l n="484">The more it asks my recompence to thee."</l>
        <l n="485">This said, away grey-eyed Minerva flew,</l>
        <l n="486">Like to a mounting lark; and did endue</l>
        <l n="487">His mind with strength and boldness, and much more</l>
        <l n="488">Made him his father long for than before;</l>
        <l n="489">And weighing better who his guest might be,</l>
        <l n="490">He stood amaz'd, and thought a Deity</l>
        <l n="491">Was there descended; to whose will he fram'd</l>
        <l n="492">His powers at all parts, and went so inflam'd</l>
        <l n="493">Amongst the wooers, who were silent set,</l>
        <l n="494">To hear a poet sing the sad retreat</l>

        <pb n="19" facs="#81"/>
        

        <l n="495">The Greeks perform'd from Troy; which was from thence</l>
        <l n="496">Proclaim'd by Pallas, pain of her offence.</l>
        <l n="497">When which divine song was perceived to bear</l>
        <l n="498">That mournful subject by the listening ear</l>
        <l n="499">Of wise Penelope, Icarius' seed,</l>
        <l n="500">Who from an upper room had given it heed,</l>
        <l n="501">Down she descended by a winding stair,</l>
        <l n="502">Not solely, but the state in her repair</l>
        <l n="503">Two maids of honour made. And when this queen</l>
        <l n="504">Of women stoop'd so low, she might be seen</l>
        <l n="505">By all her wooers. In the door, aloof,</l>
        <l n="506">Entering the hall grac'd with a goodly roof,</l>
        <l n="507">She stood, in shade of graceful veils, implied</l>
        <l n="508">About her beauties; on her either side,</l>
        <l n="509">Her honour'd women. When, to tears mov'd, thus</l>
        <l n="510">She chid the sacred singer: "Phemius,</l>
        <l n="511">You know a number more of these great deeds</l>
        <l n="512">Of Gods and men, that are the sacred seeds,</l>
        <l n="513">And proper subjects, of a poet's song,</l>
        <l n="514">And those due pleasures that to men belong,</l>
        <l n="515">Besides these facts that furnish Troy's retreat,</l>
        <l n="516">Sing one of those to these, that round your seat</l>
        <l n="517">They may with silence sit, and taste their wine;</l>
        <l n="518">But cease this song, that through these ears of mine</l>
        <l n="519">Conveys deserv'd occasion to my heart</l>
        <l n="520">Of endless sorrows, of which the desert</l>
        <l n="521">In me unmeasur'd is past all these men,</l>
        <l n="522">So endless is the memory I retain,</l>
        <l n="523">And so desertful is that memory,</l>
        <l n="524">Of such a man as hath a dignity</l>
        <l n="525">So broad it spreads itself through all the pride</l>
        <l n="526">Of Greece and Argos." To the queen replied</l>

         <pb n="20"/>
         <l n="527">Inspired Telemachus: "Why thus envies</l>
        <l n="528">My mother him that fits societies<anchor xml:id="n1.528_ref"/></l>
        <l n="529">With so much harmony, to let him please</l>
        <l n="530">His own mind in his will to honour these?</l>
        <l n="531">For these ingenious and first sort of men,</l>
        <l n="532">That do immediately from Jove retain<anchor xml:id="n1.532_ref"/></l>
        <l n="533">Their singing raptures, are by Jove as well</l>
        <l n="534">Inspir'd with choice of what their songs impell,</l>
        <l n="535">Jove's will is free in it, and therefore theirs.</l>
        <l n="536">Nor is this man to blame, that the repairs</l>
        <l n="537">The Greeks make homeward sings; for his fresh muse</l>
        <l n="538">Men still most celebrate that sings most news.</l>
        <l n="539">And therefore in his note your ears employ :</l>
        <l n="540">For not Ulysses only lost in Troy</l>
        <l n="541">The day of his return, but numbers more</l>
        <l n="542">The deadly ruins of his fortunes bore.</l>
        <l n="543">Go you then in, and take your work in hand,</l>
        <l n="544">Your web, and distaff; and your maids command</l>
        <l n="545">To ply their fit work. Words to men are due,</l>
        <l n="546">And those reproving counsels you pursue,</l>
        <l n="547">And most to me of all men, since I bear</l>
        <l n="548">The rule of all things that are managed here."</l>
        <l n="549">She went amaz'd away, and in her heart</l>
        <l n="550">Laid up the wisdom Pallas did impart</l>

        <note target="#n1.528_ref">Ἐριήρος ἀοιδὸς. Cantor, cujus tam apta est societas homi- nibus. CHAPMAN.</note>
        <note target="#n1.532_ref">᾿Ανδράσιν ἀλφηςῇσιν. ᾿Αλφηςῇσιν is an epithet proper to poets for their first finding out of arts and documents tend- ing to elocution and government, inspired only by Jove, and are here called the first of men, since first they gave rules to manly life, and have their information immediately from Jove (as Plato in Ione witnesseth); the word deduced from ἄλφα, which is taken for him qui primas teneat aliquâ in re, and will ἀλφηςῇσιν then be sufficiently expressed with ingeniosis, than which no exposition goes further.—CHAPMAN.</note>

        <pb n="21" facs="#83"/>
        

        <l n="551">To her lov'd son so lately, turn'd again</l>
        <l n="552">Up to her chamber, and no more would reign</l>
        <l n="553">In manly counsels. To her women she</l>
        <l n="554">Applied her sway; and to the wooers he</l>
        <l n="555">Began new orders, other spirits bewray'd</l>
        <l n="556">Than those in spite of which the wooers sway'd.</l>
        <l n="557">And (whiles his mother's tears still wash'd her eyes,</l>
        <l n="558">Till grey Minerva did those tears surprise</l>
        <l n="559">With timely sleep, and that her wooers did rouse</l>
        <l n="560">Rude tumult up through all the shady house,</l>
        <l n="561">Disposed to sleep because their widow was)</l>
        <l n="562">Telemachus this new-given spirit did pass</l>
        <l n="563">On their old insolence: "Ho! you that are</l>
        <l n="564">My mother's wooers! Much too high ye bear</l>
        <l n="565">Your petulant spirits; sit; and, while ye may</l>
        <l n="566">Enjoy me in your banquets, see ye lay</l>
        <l n="567">These loud notes down, nor do this man the wrong,</l>
        <l n="568">Because my mother hath disliked his song,</l>
        <l n="569">To grace her interruption. 'Tis a thing</l>
        <l n="570">Honest, and honour'd too, to hear one sing</l>
        <l n="571">Numbers so like the Gods in elegance,</l>
        <l n="572">As this man flows in. By the morn's first light,<anchor xml:id="n1.572_ref"/></l>
        <l n="573">I'll call ye all before me in a Court,</l>
        <l n="574">That I may clearly banish your resort,</l>
        <l n="575">With all your rudeness, from these roofs of mine.</l>
        <l n="576">Away; and elsewhere in your feasts combine.</l>
        <l n="577">Consume your own goods, and make mutual feast</l>
        <l n="578">At either's house. Or if ye still hold best,</l>
        <l n="579">And for your humours' more sufficed fill,</l>
        <l n="580">To feed, to spoil, because unpunish'd still,</l>
        <l n="581">On other findings, spoil; but here I call</l>

        <note target="#n1.572_ref">᾿Ηῶθεν, prima luce.—CHAPMAN.</note>

        <pb n="22" facs="#84"/>
        

        <l n="582">Th' Eternal Gods to witness, if it fall</l>
        <l n="583">In my wish'd reach once to be dealing wreaks,</l>
        <l n="584">By Jove's high bounty, these your present checks</l>
        <l n="585">To what I give in charge shall add more reins</l>
        <l n="586">To my revenge hereafter; and the pains</l>
        <l n="587">Ye then must suffer shall pass all your pride</l>
        <l n="588">Ever to see redress'd, or qualified."</l>
        <l n="589">At this all bit their lips, and did admire</l>
        <l n="590">His words sent from him with such phrase and fire;</l>
        <l n="591">Which so much mov'd them that Antinous,</l>
        <l n="592">Eupitheus' son, cried out : "Telemachus!</l>
        <l n="593">The Gods, I think, have rapt thee to this height</l>
        <l n="594">Of elocution, and this great conceit</l>
        <l n="595">Of self-ability. We all may pray,</l>
        <l n="596">That Jove invest not in this kingdom's sway</l>
        <l n="597">Thy forward forces, which I see put forth</l>
        <l n="598">A hot ambition in thee for thy birth."</l>
        <l n="599">"Be not offended," he replied, " if I</l>
        <l n="600">Shall say, I would assume this empery,<anchor xml:id="n1.600_ref"/></l>
        <l n="601">If Jove gave leave. You are not he that sings:</l>
        <l n="602">The rule of kingdoms is the worst of things.</l>
        <l n="603">Nor is it ill, at all, to sway a throne;</l>
        <l n="604">A man may quickly gain possession</l>

        <note target="#n1.600_ref">Upon this answer of Telemachus, because it hath so sudden a change, and is so far let down from his late height of heat, altering and tempering so commandingly his affections, I thought not amiss to insert here Spondanus' further annotation, which is this: Prudenter Telemachus joco furorem Antinoi ac asperitatem emolliit. Nam ita dictum illius interpre- tatur, ut existimetur censere jocosè illa etiam ab Antinoo adversum se pronunciata. Et primum ironicè se Regem esse exoptat propter commoda quæ Reges solent comitari. Ne tamen invidiam in se am- bitionis concitet, testatur se regnum Ithacæ non ambire, mortuo Ulysse, cum id alii possidere queant se longe præstantiores ac digniores: hoc unum ait se moliri, ut propriarum ædium et bonorum solus sit dominus, iis exclusis ac ejectis, qui vi illa occupare ac disperdere conantur. CHAPMAN.</note>

        <pb n="23" facs="#85"/>
        

        <l n="605">Of mighty riches, make a wondrous prize</l>
        <l n="606">Set of his virtues; but the dignities</l>
        <l n="607">That deck a king, there are enough beside</l>
        <l n="608">In this circumfluous isle that want no pride</l>
        <l n="609">To think them worthy of, as young as I,</l>
        <l n="610">And old as you are. An ascent so high</l>
        <l n="611">My thoughts affect not. Dead is he that held</l>
        <l n="612">Desert of virtue to have so excell'd.</l>
        <l n="613">But of these turrets I will take on me</l>
        <l n="614">To be the absolute king, and reign as free,</l>
        <l n="615">As did my father, over all his hand</l>
        <l n="616">Left here in this house slaves to my command."</l>
        <l n="617">Eurymachus, the son of Polybus,</l>
        <l n="618">To this made this reply: "Telemachus!</l>
        <l n="619">The girlond of this kingdom let the knees<anchor xml:id="n1.619_ref"/></l>
        <l n="620">Of Deity run for; but the faculties</l>
        <l n="621">This house is seised of, and the turrets here,</l>
        <l n="622">Thou shalt be lord of, nor shall any bear</l>
        <l n="623">The least part off of all thou dost possess,</l>
        <l n="624">As long as this land is no wilderness,</l>
        <l n="625">Nor ruled by out-laws. But give these their pass,</l>
        <l n="626">And tell me, best of princes, who he was</l>
        <l n="627">That guested here so late? From whence? And what</l>
        <l n="628">In any region boasted he his state?</l>
        <l n="629">His race? His country? Brought he any news</l>
        <l n="630">Of thy returning father? Or for dues</l>
        <l n="631">Of moneys to him made he fit repair?</l>
        <l n="632">How suddenly he rush'd into the air,</l>

        <note target="#n1.619_ref"><mentioned>Girlond</mentioned>—garland, crown, sovereignty. Shakespeare, " Cate. <quote><l>It is a reeling world, indeed, my lord;</l> <l>And, I believe, will never stand upright, </l> <l>Till Richard wear the garland of the realm. </l> <l>Hast. How! wear the garland! dost thou mean the crown? </l> <l>Cate. Ay, my good lord.</l></quote>—Richard III. III. 2.</note>

        <pb n="24" facs="#86"/>
        

        <l n="633">Nor would sustain to stay and make him known!</l>
        <l n="634">His port show'd no debauch'd companion."</l>
        <l n="635">He answer'd: "The return of my lov'd sire</l>
        <l n="636">Is past all hope; and should rude Fame inspire</l>
        <l n="637">From any place a flattering messenger</l>
        <l n="638">With news of his survival, he should bear</l>
        <l n="639">No least belief off from my desperate love.</l>
        <l n="640">Which if a sacred prophet should approve,</l>
        <l n="641">Call'd by my mother for her care's unrest,</l>
        <l n="642">It should not move me. For my late fair guest,</l>
        <l n="643">He was of old my father's, touching here</l>
        <l n="644">From sea-girt Taphos, and for name doth bear</l>
        <l n="645">Mentas, the son of wise Anchialus,</l>
        <l n="646">And governs all the Taphians studious</l>
        <l n="647">Of navigation." This he said, but knew</l>
        <l n="648">It was a Goddess. These again withdrew</l>
        <l n="649">To dances and attraction of the song;</l>
        <l n="650">And while their pleasures did the time prolong,</l>
        <l n="651">The sable Even descended, and did steep</l>
        <l n="652">The lids of all men in desire of sleep.</l>
        <l n="653">Telemachus, into a room built high</l>
        <l n="654">Of his illustrious court, and to the eye</l>
        <l n="655">Of circular prospect, to his bed ascended,</l>
        <l n="656">And in his mind much weighty thought contended.</l>
        <l n="657">Before him Euryclea (that well knew</l>
        <l n="658">All the observance of a handmaid's due,</l>
        <l n="659">Daughter to Opis Pisenorides)</l>
        <l n="660">Bore two bright torches; who did so much please</l>

        <pb n="25" facs="#87"/>
        

        <l n="661">Laërtes in her prime, that, for the price</l>
        <l n="662">Of twenty oxen, he made merchandize</l>
        <l n="663">Of her rare beauties; and love's equal flame</l>
        <l n="664">To her he felt, as to his nuptial dame,</l>
        <l n="665">Yet never durst he mix with her in bed,</l>
        <l n="666">So much the anger of his wife he fled.</l>
        <l n="667">She, now grown old, to young Telemachus</l>
        <l n="668">Two torches bore, and was obsequious</l>
        <l n="669">Past all his other maids, and did apply</l>
        <l n="670">Her service to him from his infancy.</l>
        <l n="671">His well-built chamber reach'd, she op'd the door,</l>
        <l n="672">He on his bed sat, the soft weeds he wore</l>
        <l n="673">Put off, and to the diligent old maid</l>
        <l n="674">Gave all; who fitly all in thick folds laid,</l>
        <l n="675">And hung them on a beam-pin near the bed,</l>
        <l n="676">That round about was rich embroidered.</l>
        <l n="677">Then made she haste forth from him, and did bring</l>
        <l n="678">The door together with a silver ring,</l>
        <l n="679">And by a string a bar to it did pull.</l>
        <l n="680">He, laid, and cover'd well with curled wool</l>
        <l n="681">Woven in silk quilts, all night employ'd his mind</l>
        <l n="682">About the task that Pallas had design'd.</l>
  </div>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="2">
  <pb n="26" facs="#88"/>
  <head rend="center">THE SECOND BOOK OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</head>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="1">
    <head rend="center">THE ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">TELEMACHUS to court doth call</l>
    <l n="2">The Wooers, and commands them all</l>
    <l n="3">To leave his house; and, taking then</l>
    <l n="4">From wise Minerva ship and men,</l>
    <l n="5">And all things fit for him beside,</l>
    <l n="6">That Euryclea could provide</l>
    <l n="7">For sea-rites, till he found his sire,</l>
    <l n="8">He hoists sail; when Heaven stoops his fire.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="2">
    <head rend="center">ANOTHER ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">Βῆτα. The old Maid's store</l>
    <l n="2">The voyage cheers.</l>
    <l n="3">The ship leaves shore,</l>
    <l n="4">Minerva steers.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="text">
    <l n="1"><hi rend="dropcap">N</hi>OW when with rosy fingers, th' early born</l>
    <l n="2">And thrown through all the air, appear'd the Morn,</l>
    <l n="3">Ulysses' lov'd son from his bed appear'd,</l>
    <l n="4">His weeds put on, and did about him gird</l>
    <l n="5">His sword that thwart his shoulders hung, and tied</l>
    <l n="6">To his fair feet fair shoes, and all parts plied</l>
    <l n="7">For speedy readiness; who, when he trod</l>
    <l n="8">The open earth, to men show'd like a God.</l>

    <pb n="27" facs="#89"/>
    

    <l n="9">The heralds then he straight charg'd to consort</l>
    <l n="10">The curl'd-head Greeks, with loud calls, to a Court.</l>
    <l n="11">They summon'd; th' other came in utmost haste.</l>
    <l n="12">Who all assembled, and in one heap plac'd,</l>
    <l n="13">He likewise came to council, and did bear</l>
    <l n="14">In his fair hand his iron-headed spear.</l>
    <l n="15">Nor came alone, nor with men troops prepar'd,</l>
    <l n="16">But two fleet dogs made both his train and guard.</l>
    <l n="17">Pallas supplied with her high wisdom's grace,</l>
    <l n="18">That all men's wants supplies, State's painted face.</l>
    <l n="19">His ent'ring presence all men did admire;</l>
    <l n="20">Who took seat in the high throne of his sire,</l>
    <l n="21">To which the grave peers gave him reverend way.</l>
    <l n="22">Amongst whom, an Egyptian heroë</l>
    <l n="23">(Crooked with age, and full of skill) begun</l>
    <l n="24">The speech to all; who had a loved son</l>
    <l n="25">That with divine Ulysses did ascend</l>
    <l n="26">His hollow fleet to Troy; to serve which end,</l>
    <l n="27">He kept fair horse, and was a man at arms,</l>
    <l n="28">And in the cruel Cyclops' stern alarms</l>
    <l n="29">His life lost by him in his hollow cave,</l>
    <l n="30">Whose entrails open'd his abhorred grave,</l>
    <l n="31">And made of him, of all Ulysses' train,</l>
    <l n="32">His latest supper, being latest slain;</l>
    <l n="33">His name was Antiphus. And this old man,</l>
    <l n="34">This crooked grown, this wise Egyptian,</l>
    <l n="35">Had three sons more; of which one riotous</l>
    <l n="36">A wooer was, and call'd Eurynomus;</l>
    <l n="37">The other two took both his own wish'd course.</l>
    <l n="38">Yet both the best fates weigh'd not down the worse,</l>
    <l n="39">But left the old man mindful still of moan;</l>
    <l n="40">Who, weeping, thus bespake the session :</l>

    <pb n="28" facs="#90"/>
    

    <l n="41">"Hear, Ithacensians, all I fitly say:</l>
    <l n="42">Since our divine Ulysses' parting day</l>
    <l n="43">Never was council call'd, nor session,</l>
    <l n="44">And now by whom is this thus undergone?</l>
    <l n="45">Whom did necessity so much compell,</l>
    <l n="46">Of young or old? Hath any one heard tell</l>
    <l n="47">Of any coming army, that he thus now</l>
    <l n="48">May openly take boldness to avow,</l>
    <l n="49">First having heard it? Or will any here</l>
    <l n="50">Some motion for the public good prefer?</l>
    <l n="51">Some worth of note there is in this command;</l>
    <l n="52">And, methinks, it must be some good man's hand</l>
    <l n="53">That's put to it, that either hath direct</l>
    <l n="54">Means to assist, or, for his good affect,</l>
    <l n="55">Hopes to be happy in the proof he makes;</l>
    <l n="56">And that Jove grant, whate'er he undertakes."</l>
    <l n="57">Telemachus (rejoicing much to hear</l>
    <l n="58">The good hope and opinion men did bear</l>
    <l n="59">Of his young actions) no longer sat,</l>
    <l n="60">But long'd t' approve what this man pointed at,</l>
    <l n="61">And make his first proof in a cause so good;</l>
    <l n="62">And in the council's chief place up he stood;</l>
    <l n="63">When straight Pisenor (herald to his sire,</l>
    <l n="64">And learn'd in counsels) felt his heart on fire</l>
    <l n="65">To hear him speak, and put into his hand</l>
    <l n="66">The sceptre that his father did command;</l>
    <l n="67">Then, to the old Egyptian turn'd, he spoke:</l>
    <l n="68">"Father, not far he is that undertook</l>
    <l n="69">To call this Council; whom you soon shall know.</l>
    <l n="70">Myself, whose wrongs my griefs will make me show, 70</l>
    <l n="71">Am he that author'd this assembly here.</l>
    <l n="72">Nor have I heard of any army near,</l>

    <pb n="29" facs="#91"/>
    

    <l n="73">Of which, being first told, I might iterate,</l>
    <l n="74">Nor for the public good can aught relate,</l>
    <l n="75">Only mine own affairs all this procure,</l>
    <l n="76">That in my house a double ill endure;</l>
    <l n="77">One, having lost a father so renown'd,</l>
    <l n="78">Whose kind rule once with your command was crown'd;</l>
    <l n="79">The other is, what much more doth augment</l>
    <l n="80">His weighty loss, the ruin imminent</l>
    <l n="81">Of all my house by it, my goods all spent.</l>
    <l n="82">And of all this the wooers, that are sons</l>
    <l n="83">To our chief peers, are the confusions,</l>
    <l n="84">Importuning my mother's marriage</l>
    <l n="85">Against her will; nor dares their blood's bold rage</l>
    <l n="86">Go to Icarius', her father's, court,</l>
    <l n="87">That, his will ask'd in kind and comely sort,</l>
    <l n="88">He may endow his daughter with a dower,</l>
    <l n="89">And, she consenting, at his pleasure's power</l>
    <l n="90">Dispose her to a man, that, thus behav'd,</l>
    <l n="91">May have fit grace, and see her honour sav'd;</l>
    <l n="92">But these, in none but my house, all their lives</l>
    <l n="93">Resolve to spend; slaught'ring my sheep and beeves,</l>
    <l n="94">And with my fattest goats lay feast on feast,</l>
    <l n="95">My generous wine consuming as they list.</l>
    <l n="96">A world of things they spoil, here wanting one,</l>
    <l n="97">That, like Ulysses, quickly could set gone</l>
    <l n="98">These peace-plagues from his house, that spoil like war;</l>
    <l n="99">Whom my powers are unfit to urge so far,</l>
    <l n="100">Myself immartial. But, had I the power,</l>
    <l n="101">My will should serve me to exempt this hour</l>
    <l n="102">From out my life-time. For, past patience,</l>
    <l n="103">Base deeds are done here, that exceed defence</l>
    <l n="104">Of any honour. Falling is my house,</l>

    <pb n="30" facs="#92"/>
    

    <l n="105">Which you should shame to see so ruinous.</l>
    <l n="106">Reverence the censures that all good men give,</l>
    <l n="107">That dwell about you; and for fear to live</l>
    <l n="108">Exposed to heaven's wrath (that doth ever pay</l>
    <l n="109">Pains for joys forfeit) even by Jove I pray,</l>
    <l n="110">Or Themis, both which powers have to restrain,</l>
    <l n="111">Or gather, councils, that ye will abstain</l>
    <l n="112">From further spoil, and let me only waste</l>
    <l n="113">In that most wretched grief I have embrac'd</l>
    <l n="114">For my lost father. And though I am free</l>
    <l n="115">From meriting your outrage, yet, if he,</l>
    <l n="116">Good man, hath ever with a hostile heart</l>
    <l n="117">Done ill to any Greek, on me convert</l>
    <l n="118">Your like hostility, and vengeance take</l>
    <l n="119">Of his ill on my life, and all these make</l>
    <l n="120">Join in that justice; but, to see abused</l>
    <l n="121">Those goods that do none ill but being ill used,</l>
    <l n="122">Exceeds all right. Yet better 'tis for me,</l>
    <l n="123">My whole possessions and my rents to see</l>
    <l n="124">Consum'd by you, than lose my life and all;</l>
    <l n="125">For on your rapine a revenge may fall,</l>
    <l n="126">While I live; and so long I may complain</l>
    <l n="127">About the city, till my goods again,</l>
    <l n="128">Oft ask'd, may be with all amends repaid.</l>
    <l n="129">But in the mean space your misrule hath laid</l>
    <l n="130">Griefs on my bosom, that can only speak,</l>
    <l n="131">And are denied the instant power of wreak."</l>
    <l n="132">This said, his sceptre 'gainst the ground he threw,</l>
    <l n="133">And tears still'd from him; which mov'd all the crew,</l>
    <l n="134">The court struck silent, not a man did dare</l>
    <l n="135">To give a word that might offend his ear.</l>
    <l n="136">Antinous only in this sort replied:</l>

    <pb n="31" facs="#93"/>
    

    <l n="137">"High spoken, and of spirit unpacified,</l>
    <l n="138">How have you sham'd us in this speech of yours!</l>
    <l n="139">Will you brand us for an offence not ours?</l>
    <l n="140">Your mother, first in craft, is first in cause.</l>
    <l n="141">Three years are past, and near the fourth now draws,</l>
    <l n="142">Since first she mock'd the peers Achaian.</l>
    <l n="143">All she made hope, and promis'd every man,</l>
    <l n="144">Sent for us ever, left love's show in nought,</l>
    <l n="145">But in her heart conceal'd another thought.</l>
    <l n="146">Besides, as curious in her craft, her loom</l>
    <l n="147">She with a web charg'd, hard to overcome,</l>
    <l n="148">And thus bespake us: 'Youths, that seek my bed,</l>
    <l n="149">Since my divine spouse rests amongst the dead,</l>
    <l n="150">Hold on your suits but till I end, at most,</l>
    <l n="151">This funeral weed, lest what is done be lost.</l>
    <l n="152">Besides, I purpose, that when th' austere fate</l>
    <l n="153">Of bitter death shall take into his state</l>
    <l n="154">Laertes the heroë, it shall deck</l>
    <l n="155">His royal corse, since I should suffer check</l>
    <l n="156">In ill report of every common dame,</l>
    <l n="157">If one so rich should show in death his shame.'</l>
    <l n="158">This speech she used; and this did soon persuade</l>
    <l n="159">Our gentle minds. But this a work she made</l>
    <l n="160">So hugely long, undoing still in night,</l>
    <l n="161">By torches, all she did by day's broad light,</l>
    <l n="162">That three years her deceit div'd past our view,</l>
    <l n="163">And made us think that all she feign'd was true.</l>
    <l n="164">But when the fourth year came, and those sly hours</l>
    <l n="165">That still surprise at length dames' craftiest powers,<anchor xml:id="n2.165_ref"/></l>
    <l n="166">One of her women, that knew all, disclos'd</l>
    <l n="167">The secret to us, that she still unloosed</l>
    <l n="168">Her whole day's fair affair in depth of night.</l>

    <note target="#n2.165_ref"><mentioned>Owes</mentioned>—owns, possesses.</note>

    <pb n="32" facs="#94"/>
    

    <l n="169">And then no further she could force her sleight,</l>
    <l n="170">But, of necessity, her work gave end.</l>
    <l n="171">And thus, by me, doth every other friend,</l>
    <l n="172">Professing love to her, reply to thee;</l>
    <l n="173">That even thyself, and all Greeks else, may see,</l>
    <l n="174">That we offend not in our stay, but she.</l>
    <l n="175">To free thy house then, send her to her sire,</l>
    <l n="176">Commanding that her choice be left entire</l>
    <l n="177">To his election, and one settled will.</l>
    <l n="178">Nor let her vex with her illusions still</l>
    <l n="179">Her friends that woo her, standing on her wit,</l>
    <l n="180">Because wise Pallas hath given wills to it</l>
    <l n="181">So full of art, and made her understand</l>
    <l n="182">All works in fair skill of a lady's hand.</l>
    <l n="183">But (for her working mind) we read of none</l>
    <l n="184">Of all the old world, in which Greece hath shown</l>
    <l n="185">Her rarest pieces, that could equal her:</l>
    <l n="186">Tyro, Alcmena, and Mycena, were</l>
    <l n="187">To hold comparison in no degree,</l>
    <l n="188">For solid brain, with wise Penelope.</l>
    <l n="189">And yet, in her delays of us, she shows</l>
    <l n="190">No prophet's skill with all the wit she owes;</l>
    <l n="191">For all this time thy goods and victuals go</l>
    <l n="192">To utter ruin; and shall ever so,</l>
    <l n="193">While thus the Gods her glorious mind dispose.</l>
    <l n="194">Glory herself may gain, but thou shalt lose</l>
    <l n="195">Thy longings even for necessary food,</l>
    <l n="196">For we will never go where lies our good,</l>
    <l n="197">Nor any other where, till this delay</l>
    <l n="198">She puts on all, she quits with th' endless stay</l>
    <l n="199">Of some one of us, that to all the rest</l>
    <l n="200">May give free farewell with his nuptial feast."</l>

    <pb n="33" facs="#95"/>
    

    <l n="201">The wise young prince replied: "Antinous!</l>
    <l n="202">I may by no means turn out of my house</l>
    <l n="203">Her that hath brought me forth and nourish'd me.</l>
    <l n="204">Besides, if quick or dead my father be</l>
    <l n="205">In any region, yet abides in doubt;</l>
    <l n="206">And 'twill go hard, my means being so run out,</l>
    <l n="207">To tender to Icarius again,</l>
    <l n="208">If he again my mother must maintain</l>
    <l n="209">In her retreat, the dower she brought with her.</l>
    <l n="210">And then a double ill it will confer,</l>
    <l n="211">Both from my father and from God on me,</l>
    <l n="212">When, thrust out of her house, on her bent knee,</l>
    <l n="213">My mother shall the horrid Furies raise</l>
    <l n="214">With imprecations, and all men dispraise</l>
    <l n="215">My part in her exposure. Never then</l>
    <l n="216">Will I perform this counsel. If your spleen</l>
    <l n="217">Swell at my courses, once more I command</l>
    <l n="218">Your absence from my house; some other's hand</l>
    <l n="219">Charge with your banquets; on your own goods eat,</l>
    <l n="220">And either other mutually intreat,</l>
    <l n="221">At either of your houses, with your feast.</l>
    <l n="222">But if ye still esteem more sweet and best</l>
    <l n="223">Another's spoil, so you still wreakless live,</l>
    <l n="224">Gnaw, vermin-like, things sacred, no laws give<anchor xml:id="n2.224_ref"/></l>
    <l n="225">To your devouring; it remains that I</l>
    <l n="226">Invoke each Ever-living Deity,</l>
    <l n="227">And vow, if Jove shall deign in any date</l>
    <l n="228">Power of like pains for pleasure so past rate,</l>
    <l n="229">From thenceforth look, where ye have revelled so</l>
    <l n="230">Unwreak'd, your ruins all shall undergo."</l>

    <note target="#n2.224_ref">The word is κείρετε, κείρω signifying, insatiabili quâdam edacitate voro.—CHAPMAN.</note>

    <pb n="34" facs="#96"/>
    

    <l n="231">Thus spake Telemachus; t'assure whose threat,</l>
    <l n="232">Far-seeing Jove upon their pinions set</l>
    <l n="233">Two eagles from the high brows of a hill,</l>
    <l n="234">That, mounted on the winds, together still</l>
    <l n="235">Their strokes extended; but arriving now</l>
    <l n="236">Amidst the Council, over every brow</l>
    <l n="237">Shook their thick wings and, threat'ning death's cold fears,</l>
    <l n="238">Their necks and cheeks tore with their eager seres;</l>
    <l n="239">Then, on the court's right-hand away they flew,</l>
    <l n="240">Above both court and city. With whose view,</l>
    <l n="241">And study what events they might foretell,</l>
    <l n="242">The Council into admiration fell.</l>
    <l n="243">The old heroë, Halitherses, then,</l>
    <l n="244">The son of Nestor, that of all old men,</l>
    <l n="245">His peers in that court, only could foresee</l>
    <l n="246">By flight of fowls man's fixed destiny,</l>
    <l n="247">'Twixt them and their amaze, this interpos'd:</l>
    <l n="248">"Hear, Ithacensians, all your doubts disclos'd.</l>
    <l n="249">The Wooers most are touch'd in this ostent,</l>
    <l n="250">To whom are dangers great and imminent;</l>
    <l n="251">For now not long more shall Ulysses bear</l>
    <l n="252">Lack of his most lov'd, but fills some place near,</l>
    <l n="253">Addressing to these Wooers fate and death.</l>
    <l n="254">And many more this mischief menaceth</l>
    <l n="255">Of us inhabiting this famous isle.</l>
    <l n="256">Let us consult yet, in this long forewhile,</l>
    <l n="257">How to ourselves we may prevent this ill.</l>
    <l n="258">Let these men rest secure, and revel still;</l>
    <l n="259">Though they might find it safer, if with us</l>
    <l n="260">They would in time prevent what threats them thus ;</l>
    <l n="261">Since not without sure trial I foretell</l>
    <l n="262">These coming storms, but know their issue well.</l>

    <pb n="35" facs="#97"/>
    

    <l n="263">For to Ulysses all things have event,<anchor xml:id="n2.263_ref"/></l>
    <l n="264">As I foretold him, when for Ilion went</l>
    <l n="265">The whole Greek fleet together, and with them</l>
    <l n="266">Th' abundant-in-all-counsels took the stream.</l>
    <l n="267">I told him, that, when much ill he had passed,</l>
    <l n="268">And all his men were lost, he should at last,</l>
    <l n="269">The twentieth year, turn home, to all unknown;</l>
    <l n="270">All which effects are to perfection grown."</l>
    <l n="271">Eurymachus, the son of Polybus,</l>
    <l n="272">Opposed this man's presage, and answer'd thus :</l>
    <l n="273">"Hence, great in years, go, prophesy at home,</l>
    <l n="274">Thy children teach to shun their ills to come.</l>
    <l n="275">In these superior far to thee am I.</l>
    <l n="276">A world of fowls beneath the sun-beams fly</l>
    <l n="277">That are not fit t' inform a prophecy.</l>
    <l n="278">Besides, Ulysses perish'd long ago;</l>
    <l n="279">And would thy fates to thee had destin'd so,</l>
    <l n="280">Since so thy so much prophecy had spar'd</l>
    <l n="281">Thy wronging of our rights, which, for reward</l>
    <l n="282">Expected home with thee, hath summon'd us</l>
    <l n="283">Within the anger of Telemachus.</l>
    <l n="284">But this I will presage, which shall be true:</l>
    <l n="285">If any spark of anger chance t' ensue</l>
    <l n="286">Thy much old art in these deep auguries,</l>
    <l n="287">In this young man incensed by thy lies,</l>
    <l n="288">Even to himself his anger shall confer</l>
    <l n="289">The greater anguish, and thine own ends err</l>
    <l n="290">From all their objects; and, besides, thine age</l>
    <l n="291">Shall feel a pain, to make thee curse presage</l>
    <l n="292">With worthy cause, for it shall touch thee near.</l>
    <l n="293">But I will soon give end to all our fear,</l>

    <note target="#n2.263_ref"><mentioned>Ulysses</mentioned>.</note>

    <pb n="36" facs="#98"/>
    

    <l n="294">Preventing whatsoever chance can fall,</l>
    <l n="295">In my suit to the young prince for us all,</l>
    <l n="296">To send his mother to her father's house,</l>
    <l n="297">That he may sort her out a worthy spouse,</l>
    <l n="298">And such a dower bestow, as may befit</l>
    <l n="299">One lov'd, to leave her friends and follow it.</l>
    <l n="300">Before which course be, I believe that none</l>
    <l n="301">Of all the Greeks will cease th' ambition</l>
    <l n="302">Of such a match. For, chance what can to us,</l>
    <l n="303">We no man fear, no not Telemachus,</l>
    <l n="304">Though ne'er so greatly spoken. Nor care we</l>
    <l n="305">For any threats of austere prophecy,</l>
    <l n="306">Which thou, old dotard, vaunt'st of so in vain.</l>
    <l n="307">And thus shalt thou in much more hate remain;</l>
    <l n="308">For still the Gods shall bear their ill expense,</l>
    <l n="309">Nor ever be dispos'd by competence,</l>
    <l n="310">Till with her nuptials she dismiss our suits,</l>
    <l n="311">Our whole lives' days shall sow hopes for such fruits.</l>
    <l n="312">Her virtues we contend to, nor will go</l>
    <l n="313">To any other, be she never so</l>
    <l n="314">Worthy of us, and all the worth we owe."</l>
    <l n="315">He answer'd him: "Eurymachus, and all</l>
    <l n="316">Ye generous Wooers, now, in general,</l>
    <l n="317">I see your brave resolves, and will no more</l>
    <l n="318">Make speech of these points, and, much less, implore.</l>
    <l n="319">It is enough, that all the Grecians here,</l>
    <l n="320">And all the Gods besides, just witness bear,</l>
    <l n="321">What friendly premonitions have been spent</l>
    <l n="322">On your forbearance, and their vain event.</l>
    <l n="323">Yet, with my other friends, let love prevail</l>
    <l n="324">To fit me with a vessel free of sail,</l>

    <pb n="37" facs="#99"/>
    

    <l n="325">And twenty men, that may divide to me</l>
    <l n="326">My ready passage through the yielding sea.</l>
    <l n="327">For Sparta, and Amathoan Pylos' shore,<anchor xml:id="n2.327_ref"/></l>
    <l n="328">I now am bound, in purpose to explore</l>
    <l n="329">My long-lack'd father, and to try if fame</l>
    <l n="330">Or Jove, most author of man's honour'd name,</l>
    <l n="331">With his return and life may glad mine ear,</l>
    <l n="332">Though toil'd in that proof I sustain a year.</l>
    <l n="333">If dead I hear him, nor of more state, here</l>
    <l n="334">Retir'd to my lov'd country, I will rear</l>
    <l n="335">A sepulchre to him, and celebrate</l>
    <l n="336">Such royal parent-rites, as fits his state;</l>
    <l n="337">And then my mother to a spouse dispose."</l>
    <l n="338">This said, he sat; and to the rest arose</l>
    <l n="339">Mentor, that was Ulysses' chosen friend,</l>
    <l n="340">To whom, when he set forth, he did commend</l>
    <l n="341">His complete family, and whom he will'd</l>
    <l n="342">To see the mind of his old sire fulfill'd,</l>
    <l n="343">All things conserving safe, till his retreat.</l>
    <l n="344">Who, tender of his charge, and seeing to set</l>
    <l n="345">In slight care of their king his subjects there,</l>
    <l n="346">Suffering his son so much contempt to bear,</l>
    <l n="347">Thus gravely, and with zeal, to him began :</l>
    <l n="348">"No more let any sceptre-bearing man,</l>
    <l n="349">Benevolent, or mild, or human be,</l>
    <l n="350">Nor in his mind form acts of piety,</l>
    <l n="351">But ever feed on blood, and facts unjust</l>
    <l n="352">Commit, even to the full swing of his lust,</l>
    <l n="353">Since of divine Ulysses no man now,</l>
    <l n="354">Of all his subjects, any thought doth show.</l>

    <note target="#n2.327_ref">The original is Πύλον ἠμαθόεντα, sandy Pylos. See Book 1. 154.</note>

    <pb n="38" facs="#100"/>
    

    <l n="355">All whom he govern'd, and became to them,</l>
    <l n="356">Rather than one that wore a diadem,</l>
    <l n="357">A most indulgent father. But, for all</l>
    <l n="358">That can touch me, within no envy fall</l>
    <l n="359">These insolent Wooers, that in violent kind</l>
    <l n="360">Commit things foul by th' ill wit of the mind,</l>
    <l n="361">And with the hazard of their heads devour</l>
    <l n="362">Ulysses' house, since his returning hour</l>
    <l n="363">They hold past hope. But it affects me much,</l>
    <l n="364">Ye dull plebeians, that all this doth touch</l>
    <l n="365">Your free states nothing; who, struck dumb, afford</l>
    <l n="366">These Wooers not so much wreak as a word,</l>
    <l n="367">Though few, and you with only number might</l>
    <l n="368">Extinguish to them the profaned light."</l>
    <l n="369">Evenor's son, Leocritus, replied:</l>
    <l n="370">"Mentor! the railer, made a fool with pride,</l>
    <l n="371">What language giv'st thou that would quiet us</l>
    <l n="372">With putting us in storm, exciting thus</l>
    <l n="373">The rout against us? Who, though more than we,</l>
    <l n="374">Should find it is no easy victory</l>
    <l n="375">To drive men, habited in feast, from feasts,</l>
    <l n="376">No not if Ithacus himself such guests</l>
    <l n="377">Should come and find so furnishing his Court,</l>
    <l n="378">And hope to force them from so sweet a fort.</l>
    <l n="379">His wife should little joy in his arrive,<anchor xml:id="n2.379_ref"/></l>
    <l n="380">Though much she wants him; for, where she alive</l>
    <l n="381">Would her's enjoy, there death should claim his rights.</l>
    <l n="382">He must be conquer'd that with many fights.</l>
    <l n="383">Thou speak'st unfit things. To their labours then</l>
    <l n="384">Disperse these people; and let these two men,</l>
    <l n="385">Mentor and Halitherses, that so boast</l>

    <note target="#n2.379_ref"><mentioned>Arrive</mentioned>—arrival.</note>

   <pb n="38"/>
   
<l n="386">From the beginning to have govern'd most</l>
        <l n="387">In friendship of the father, to the son</l>
        <l n="388">Confirm the course he now affects to run.</l>
        <l n="389">But my mind says, that, if he would but use</l>
        <l n="390">A little patience, he should here hear news</l>
        <l n="391">Of all things that his wish would understand,</l>
        <l n="392">But no good hope for of the course in hand."</l>
        <l n="393">This said, the Council rose; when every peer</l>
        <l n="394">And all the people in dispersion were</l>
        <l n="395">To houses of their own; the Wooers yet</l>
        <l n="396">Made to Ulysses' house their old retreat.</l>
        <l n="397">Telemachus, apart from all the prease,</l>
        <l n="398">Prepar'd to shore, and, in the aged seas</l>
        <l n="399">His fair hands wash'd, did thus to Pallas pray:</l>
        <l n="400">"Hear me, O Goddess, that but yesterday</l>
        <l n="401">Didst deign access to me at home, and lay</l>
        <l n="402">Grave charge on me to take ship, and inquire</l>
        <l n="403">Along the dark seas for mine absent sire !</l>
        <l n="404">Which all the Greeks oppose; amongst whom most</l>
        <l n="405">Those that are proud still at another's cost,</l>
        <l n="406">Past measure, and the civil rights of men,</l>
        <l n="407">My mother's Wooers, my repulse maintain."</l>
        <l n="408">Thus spake he praying; when close to him came</l>
        <l n="409">Pallas, resembling Mentor both in frame</l>
        <l n="410">Of voice and person, and advised him thus:</l>
        <l n="411">"Those Wooers well might know, Telemachus,</l>
        <l n="412">Thou wilt not ever weak and childish be,</l>
        <l n="413">If to thee be instill'd the faculty</l>
        <l n="414">Of mind and body that thy father grac'd;</l>
        <l n="415">And if, like him, there be in thee enchac'd</l>
        <l n="416">Virtue to give words works, and works their end.</l>
        <l n="417">This voyage, that to them thou didst commend,</l>

        <pb n="40" facs="#102"/>
        

        <l n="418">Shall not so quickly, as they idly ween,</l>
        <l n="419">Be vain, or giv'n up, for their opposite spleen.</l>
        <l n="420">But, if Ulysses nor Penelope</l>
        <l n="421">Were thy true parents, I then hope in thee</l>
        <l n="422">Of no more urging thy attempt in hand;</l>
        <l n="423">For few, that rightly bred on both sides stand,</l>
        <l n="424">Are like their parents, many that are worse,</l>
        <l n="425">And most few better. Those then that the nurse</l>
        <l n="426">Or mother call true born yet are not so,</l>
        <l n="427">Like worthy sires much less are like to grow.</l>
        <l n="428">But thou show'st now that in thee fades not quite</l>
        <l n="429">Thy father's wisdom; and that future light</l>
        <l n="430">Shall therefore show thee far from being unwise,</l>
        <l n="431">Or touch'd with stain of bastard cowardice.</l>
        <l n="432">Hope therefore says, that thou wilt to the end</l>
        <l n="433">Pursue the brave act thou didst erst intend.</l>
        <l n="434">But for the foolish Wooers, they bewray</l>
        <l n="435">They neither counsel have nor soul, since they</l>
        <l n="436">Are neither wise nor just, and so must needs</l>
        <l n="437">Rest ignorant how black above their heads</l>
        <l n="438">Fate hovers holding Death, that one sole day</l>
        <l n="439">Will make enough to make them all away.</l>
        <l n="440">For thee, the way thou wishest shall no more</l>
        <l n="441">Fly thee a step; I, that have been before</l>
        <l n="442">Thy father's friend, thine likewise now will be,</l>
        <l n="443">Provide thy ship myself, and follow thee.</l>
        <l n="444">Go thou then home, and sooth each Wooer's vein,</l>
        <l n="445">But under hand fit all things for the main;</l>
        <l n="446">Wine in as strong and sweet casks as you can,</l>
        <l n="447">And meal, the very marrow of a man,</l>
        <l n="448">Which put in good sure leather sacks, and see</l>
        <l n="449">That with sweet food sweet vessels still agree.</l>

        <pb n="41" facs="#103"/>
        

        <l n="450">I from the people straight will press for you</l>
        <l n="451">Free voluntaries; and, for ships, enow</l>
        <l n="452">Sea-circled Ithaca contains, both new</l>
        <l n="453">And old-built; all which I'll exactly view,</l>
        <l n="454">And choose what one soever most doth please;</l>
        <l n="455">Which rigg'd, we'll straight launch, and assay the seas."</l>
        <l n="456">This spake Jove's daughter, Pallas; whose voice heard,</l>
        <l n="457">No more Telemachus her charge deferr'd,</l>
        <l n="458">But hasted home, and, sad at heart, did see</l>
        <l n="459">Amidst his hall th' insulting Wooers flea<anchor xml:id="n2.459_ref"/></l>
        <l n="460">Goats, and roast swine. 'Mongst whom, Antinous</l>
        <l n="461">Careless, discovering in Telemachus</l>
        <l n="462">His grudge to see them, laugh'd, met, took his hand,</l>
        <l n="463">And said: "High-spoken, with the mind so mann'd!</l>
        <l n="464">Come, do as we do, put not up your spirits</l>
        <l n="465">With these low trifles, nor our loving merits</l>
        <l n="466">In gall of any hateful purpose steep,</l>
        <l n="467">But eat egregiously, and drink as deep.</l>
        <l n="468">The things thou think'st on, all at full shall be</l>
        <l n="469">By th' Achives thought on, and perform'd to thee;</l>
        <l n="470">Ship, and choice oars, that in a trice will land</l>
        <l n="471">Thy hasty fleet on heavenly Pylos' sand,</l>
        <l n="472">And at the fame of thy illustrous sire."</l>
        <l n="473">He answer'd: "Men, whom pride did so inspire,</l>
        <l n="474">Are not fit consorts for an humble guest;</l>
        <l n="475">Nor are constrain'd men merry at their feast.</l>
        <l n="476">Is't not enough, that all this time ye have</l>
        <l n="477">Op'd in your entrails my chief goods a grave,</l>
        <l n="478">And, while I was a child, made me partake?</l>
        <l n="479">My now more growth more grown my mind doth make,</l>

        <note target="#n2.459_ref"><mentioned>Flea</mentioned>—flay.</note>

        <pb n="42" facs="#104"/>
        

        <l n="480">And, hearing speak more judging men than you,</l>
        <l n="481">Perceive how much I was misgovern'd now.</l>
        <l n="482">I now will try if I can bring ye home</l>
        <l n="483">An ill Fate to consort you; if it come</l>
        <l n="484">From Pylos, or amongst the people here.</l>
        <l n="485">But thither I resolve, and know that there</l>
        <l n="486">I shall not touch in vain. Nor will I stay,</l>
        <l n="487">Though in a merchant's ship I steer my way;</l>
        <l n="488">Which shows in your sights best; since me ye know</l>
        <l n="489">Incapable of ship, or men to row."</l>
        <l n="490">This said, his hand he coyly snatch'd away</l>
        <l n="491">From forth Antinous' hand. The rest the day</l>
        <l n="492">Spent through the house with banquets; some with jests,</l>
        <l n="493">And some with railings, dignifying their feasts.</l>
        <l n="494">To whom a jest-proud youth the wit began:</l>
        <l n="495">" Telemachus will kill us every man.</l>
        <l n="496">From Sparta, to the very Pylian sand,</l>
        <l n="497">He will raise aids to his impetuous hand.</l>
        <l n="498">O he affects it strangely! Or he means</l>
        <l n="499">To search Ephyra's fat shores, and from thence</l>
        <l n="500">Bring deathful poisons, which amongst our bowls</l>
        <l n="501">Will make a general shipwrack of our souls."</l>
        <l n="502">Another said: “Alas, who knows but he</l>
        <l n="503">Once gone, and erring like his sire at sea,</l>
        <l n="504">May perish like him, far from aid of friends,</l>
        <l n="505">And so he makes us work? For all the ends</l>
        <l n="506">Left of his goods here we shall share, the house</l>
        <l n="507">Left to his mother and her chosen spouse."</l>
        <l n="508">Thus they; while he a room ascended, high</l>
        <l n="509">And large, built by his father, where did lie</l>
        <l n="510">Gold and brass heap'd up, and in coffers were</l>
        <l n="511">Rich robes, great store of odorous oils, and there</l>

        <pb n="43" facs="#105"/>
        

        <l n="512">Stood tuns of sweet old wines along the wall,</l>
        <l n="513">Neat and divine drink, kept to cheer withall</l>
        <l n="514">Ulysses' old heart, if he turn'd again</l>
        <l n="515">From labours fatal to him to sustain.<anchor xml:id="n2.515_ref"/></l>
        <l n="516">The doors of plank were, their close exquisite,</l>
        <l n="517">Kept with a double key, and day and night</l>
        <l n="518">A woman lock'd within; and that was she</l>
        <l n="519">Who all trust had for her sufficiency,</l>
        <l n="520">Old Euryclea, one of Opis' race,</l>
        <l n="521">Son to Pisenor, and in passing grace</l>
        <l n="522">With grey Minerva; her the prince did call,</l>
        <l n="523">And said: "Nurse! Draw me the most sweet of all</l>
        <l n="524">The wine thou keep'st; next that which for my sire</l>
        <l n="525">Thy care reserves, in hope he shall retire.</l>
        <l n="526">Twelve vessels fill me forth, and stop them well.</l>
        <l n="527">Then into well-sew'd sacks of fine ground meal</l>
        <l n="528">Pour twenty measures. Nor, to any one</l>
        <l n="529">But thee thyself, let this design be known.</l>
        <l n="530">All this see got together; I it all</l>
        <l n="531">In night will fetch off, when my mother shall</l>
        <l n="532">Ascend her high room, and for sleep prepare.</l>
        <l n="533">Sparta and Pylos I must see, in care</l>
        <l n="534">To find my father." Out Euryclea cried,</l>
        <l n="535">And ask'd with tears: "Why is your mind applied,</l>
        <l n="536">Dear son, to this course? Whither will you go?</l>
        <l n="537">So far off leave us, and beloved so,</l>
        <l n="538">So only? And the sole hope of your race?</l>
        <l n="539">Royal Ulysses, far from the embrace</l>
        <l n="540">Of his kind country, in a land unknown</l>

        <note target="#n2.515_ref"><mentioned>Fatal</mentioned>—fated. See Iliad.</note>

        <pb n="44" facs="#106"/>
        

        <l n="541">Is dead; and, you from your lov'd country gone,</l>
        <l n="542">The Wooers will with some deceit assay</l>
        <l n="543">To your destruction, making then their prey</l>
        <l n="544">Of all your goods. Where, in your own y'are strong,</l>
        <l n="545">Make sure abode. It fits not you so young</l>
        <l n="546">To suffer so much by the aged seas,</l>
        <l n="547">And err in such a wayless wilderness."</l>
        <l n="548">"Be cheer'd, lov'd nurse," said he, "for, not without</l>
        <l n="549">The will of God, go my attempts about.</l>
        <l n="550">Swear therefore, not to wound my mother's ears</l>
        <l n="551">With word of this, before from heaven appears</l>
        <l n="552">Th' eleventh or twelfth light, or herself shall please</l>
        <l n="553">To ask of me, or hears me put to seas,</l>
        <l n="554">Lest her fair body with her woe be wore.'</l>
        <l n="555">To this the great oath of the Gods she swore;</l>
        <l n="556">Which having sworn, and of it every due</l>
        <l n="557">Perform'd to full, to vessels wine she drew,</l>
        <l n="558">And into well-sew'd sacks pour'd foody meal.</l>
        <l n="559">In mean time he, with cunning to conceal</l>
        <l n="560">All thought of this from others, himself bore</l>
        <l n="561">In broad house, with the Wooers, as before.</l>
        <l n="562">Then grey-eyed Pallas other thoughts did own,</l>
        <l n="563">And like Telemachus trod through the town,</l>
        <l n="564">Commanding all his men in th' even to be</l>
        <l n="565">Aboard his ship. Again then question'd she</l>
        <l n="566">Noemon, famed for aged Phronius' son,</l>
        <l n="567">About his ship; who all things to be done</l>
        <l n="568">Assured her freely should. The sun then set,</l>
        <l n="569">And sable shadows slid through every street,</l>
        <l n="570">When forth they launch'd, and soon aboard did bring</l>
        <l n="571">All arms, and choice of every needful thing</l>
        <l n="572">That fits a well-rigg'd ship. The Goddess then</l>
        <l n="573">Stood in the port's extreme part, where her men,</l>
        <l n="574">Nobly appointed, thick about her came,</l>

        <pb n="45" facs="#107"/>
        

        <l n="575">Whose every breast she did with spirit enflame.</l>
        <l n="576">Yet still fresh projects laid the grey-eyed Dame.</l>
        <l n="577">Straight to the house she hasted, and sweet sleep</l>
        <l n="578">Pour'd on each Wooer; which so laid in steep</l>
        <l n="579">Their drowsy temples, that each brow did nod,</l>
        <l n="580">As all were drinking, and each hand his load,</l>
        <l n="581">The cup, let fall. All start up, and to bed,</l>
        <l n="582">Nor more would watch, when sleep so surfeited</l>
        <l n="583">Their leaden eye-lids. Then did Pallas call</l>
        <l n="584">Telemachus, in body, voice, and all,</l>
        <l n="585">Resembling Mentor, from his native nest,</l>
        <l n="586">And said, that all his arm'd men were addrest</l>
        <l n="587">To use their oars, and all expected now</l>
        <l n="588">He should the spirit of a soldier show.</l>
        <l n="589">"Come then," said she, " no more let us defer</l>
        <l n="590">Our honour'd action." Then she took on her</l>
        <l n="591">A ravish'd spirit, and led as she did leap;</l>
        <l n="592">And he her most haste took out step by step.</l>
        <l n="593">Arrived at sea and ship, they found ashore</l>
        <l n="594">The soldiers that their fashion'd-long hair wore;</l>
        <l n="595">To whom the prince said: "Come, my friends, let's bring</l>
        <l n="596">Our voyage's provision; every thing</l>
        <l n="597">Is heap'd together in our court; and none,</l>
        <l n="598">No not my mother, nor her maids, but one</l>
        <l n="599">Knows our intention." This express'd, he led,</l>
        <l n="600">The soldiers close together followed;</l>
        <l n="601">And all together brought aboard their store.</l>
        <l n="602">Aboard the prince went; Pallas still before</l>
        <l n="603">Sat at the stern, he close to her, the men</l>
        <l n="604">Up hasted after. He and Pallas then</l>
        <l n="605">Put from the shore. His soldiers then he bad</l>
        <l n="606">See all their arms fit; which they heard, and had.</l>

        <pb n="46" facs="#108"/>
        

        <l n="607">A beechen mast, then, in the hollow base</l>
        <l n="608">They put, and hoisted, fix'd it in his place</l>
        <l n="609">With cables; and with well-wreath'd halsers hoise</l>
        <l n="610">Their white sails, which grey Pallas now employs</l>
        <l n="611">With full and fore-gales through the dark deep main.</l>
        <l n="612">The purple waves, so swift cut, roar'd again</l>
        <l n="613">Against the ship sides, that now ran and plow'd</l>
        <l n="614">The rugged seas up. Then the men bestow'd</l>
        <l n="615">Their arms about the ship, and sacrifice</l>
        <l n="616">With crown'd wine-cups to th' endless Deities</l>
        <l n="617">They offer'd up. Of all yet throned above,</l>
        <l n="618">They most observed the grey-eyed seed of Jove;</l>
        <l n="619">Who, from the evening till the morning rose,</l>
        <l n="620">And all day long, their voyage did dispose.</l>
  </div>

</div>
  

   <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3">
  <pb n="47" facs="#109"/>
  <head rend="center">THE THIRD BOOK OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</head>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="1">
    <head rend="center">THE ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">TELEMACHUS, and Heaven's wise* Dame<note place="inline">* Pallas.</note></l>
    <l n="2">That never husband had, now came</l>
    <l n="3">To Nestor; who his either guest</l>
    <l n="4">Received at the religious feast</l>
    <l n="5">He made to Neptune, on his shore;</l>
    <l n="6">And there told what was done before</l>
    <l n="7">The Trojan turrets, and the state</l>
    <l n="8">Of all the Greeks since Ilion's fate.</l>
    <l n="9">This book † these three of greatest place<note place="inline">† Minerva, Nestor, and Telemachus.</note></l>
    <l n="10">Doth serve with many a varied grace.</l>
    <l n="11">Which past, Minerva takes her leave.</l>
    <l n="12">Whose state when Nestor doth perceive,</l>
    <l n="13">With sacrifice he makes it known,</l>
    <l n="14">Where many a pleasing rite is shown.</l>
    <l n="15">Which done, Telemachus hath gain'd</l>
    <l n="16">A chariot of him; who ordain'd</l>
    <l n="17">Pisistratus, his son, his guide</l>
    <l n="18">To Sparta; and when starry eyed</l>
    <l n="19">The ample heaven began to be,</l>
    <l n="20">All house-rites to afford them free,</l>
    <l n="21">In Pheris, Diocles did please,</l>
    <l n="22">His surname Ortilochides.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="2">
    <head rend="center">ANOTHER ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">Γάμμα. Ulysses son</l>
    <l n="2">With Nestor lies,</l>
    <l n="3">To Sparta gone;</l>
    <l n="4">Thence Pallas flies.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="text">
    <l n="1"><hi rend="dropcap">T</hi>HE sun now left the great and goodly lake,</l>
    <l n="2">And to the firm heaven bright ascent did make,</l>
    <l n="3">To shine as well upon the mortal birth,</l>
    <l n="4">Inhabiting the plow'd life-giving earth,</l>
    <l n="5">As on the ever treaders upon death.<anchor xml:id="n3.5_ref"/></l>
    <l n="6">And now to Pylos, that so garnisheth</l>
    <l n="7">Herself with buildings, old Neleus' town,</l>
    <l n="8">The prince and Goddess come had strange sights shown,</l>
    <l n="9">For, on the marine shore, the people there</l>
    <l n="10">To Neptune, that the azure looks doth wear,</l>
    <l n="11">Beeves that were wholly black gave holy flame.</l>
    <l n="12">Nine seats of state they made to his high name;</l>
    <l n="13">And every seat set with five hundred men,</l>
    <l n="14">And each five hundred was to furnish then</l>
    <l n="15">With nine black oxen every sacred seat.</l>
    <l n="16">These of the entrails only pleas'd to eat,</l>
    <l n="17">And to the God enflam'd the fleshy thighs.</l>
    <l n="18">By this time Pallas with the sparkling eyes,</l>
    <l n="19">And he she led, within the haven bore,</l>
    <l n="20">Struck sail, cast anchor, and trod both the shore,</l>
    <l n="21">She first, he after. Then said Pallas: "Now</l>
    <l n="22">No more befits thee the least bashful brow;</l>
    <l n="23">T' embolden which this act is put on thee,</l>
    <l n="24">To seek thy father both at shore and sea,</l>
    <l n="25">And learn in what clime he abides so close,</l>
    <l n="26">Or in the power of what Fate doth repose.</l>
    <l n="27">Come then, go right to Nestor; let us see,</l>
    <l n="28">If in his bosom any counsel be,</l>
    <l n="29">That may inform us. Pray him not to trace</l>
    <l n="30">The common courtship, and to speak in grace</l>

    <note target="#n3.5_ref"><mentioned>The ever treaders upon death</mentioned>—The Gods.</note>

    <pb n="49" facs="#111"/>
    

    <l n="31">Of the demander, but to tell the truth;</l>
    <l n="32">Which will delight him, and commend thy youth</l>
    <l n="33">For such prevention; for he loves no lies,</l>
    <l n="34">Nor will report them, being truly wise."</l>
    <l n="35">He answer'd: "Mentor! how, alas! shall I</l>
    <l n="36">Present myself? How greet his gravity?</l>
    <l n="37">My youth by no means that ripe form affords,</l>
    <l n="38">That can digest my mind's instinct in words</l>
    <l n="39">Wise, and beseeming th' ears of one so sage.</l>
    <l n="40">Youth of most hope blush to use words with age."</l>
    <l n="41">She said: "Thy mind will some conceit impress,</l>
    <l n="42">And something God will prompt thy towardness ;</l>
    <l n="43">For, I suppose, thy birth, and breeding too,</l>
    <l n="44">Were not in spite of what the Gods could do."</l>
    <l n="45">This said, she swiftly went before, and he</l>
    <l n="46">Her steps made guides, and follow'd instantly.</l>
    <l n="47">When soon they reach'd the Pylian throngs and seats,</l>
    <l n="48">Where Nestor with his sons sat; and the meats,</l>
    <l n="49">That for the feast serv'd, round about them were</l>
    <l n="50">Adherents dressing, all their sacred cheer,</l>
    <l n="51">Being roast and boil'd meats. When the Pylians saw</l>
    <l n="52">These strangers come, in thrust did all men draw</l>
    <l n="53">About their entry, took their hands, and pray'd</l>
    <l n="54">They both would sit; their entry first assay'd</l>
    <l n="55">By Nestor's son, Pisistratus. In grace</l>
    <l n="56">Of whose repair, he gave them honour'd place</l>
    <l n="57">Betwixt his sire and brother Thrasymed,</l>
    <l n="58">Who sat at feast on soft fells that were spread<anchor xml:id="n3.58_ref"/></l>
    <l n="59">Along the sea sands, kerv'v, and reach'd to them<anchor xml:id="n3.59_ref"/></l>
    <l n="60">Parts of the inwards, and did make a stream</l>
    <l n="61">Of spritely wine into a golden bowl;</l>

    <note target="#n3.58_ref"><mentioned>Fells</mentioned>—sheep-skins, skins of beasts.</note>
    <note target="#n3.59_ref"><mentioned>Kerved</mentioned>—carved.</note>

    <pb n="50" facs="#112"/>
    

    <l n="62">Which to Minerva with a gentle soul</l>
    <l n="63">He gave, and thus spake : "Ere you eat, fair guest,</l>
    <l n="64">Invoke the Seas' King, of whose sacred feast</l>
    <l n="65">Your travel hither makes ye partners now;</l>
    <l n="66">When, sacrificing as becomes, bestow</l>
    <l n="67">This bowl of sweet wine on your friend, that he</l>
    <l n="68">May likewise use these rites of piety;</l>
    <l n="69">For I suppose his youth doth prayers use,</l>
    <l n="70">Since all men need the Gods. But you I choose</l>
    <l n="71">First in this cup's disposure, since his years</l>
    <l n="72">Seem short of yours, who more like me appears."</l>
    <l n="73">Thus gave he her the cup of pleasant wine;</l>
    <l n="74">And since a wise and just man did design</l>
    <l n="75">The golden bowl first to her free receit,</l>
    <l n="76">Even to the Goddess it did add delight,</l>
    <l n="77">Who thus invok'd: "Hear thou, whose vast embrace</l>
    <l n="78">Enspheres the whole earth, nor disdain thy grace</l>
    <l n="79">To us that ask it in performing this:</l>
    <l n="80">To Nestor first, and these fair sons of his,</l>
    <l n="81">Vouchsafe all honour; and, next them, bestow</l>
    <l n="82">On all these Pylians, that have offer'd now</l>
    <l n="83">This most renowned hecatomb to thee,</l>
    <l n="84">Remuneration fit for them, and free;</l>
    <l n="85">And lastly deign Telemachus and me,</l>
    <l n="86">The work perform'd for whose effect we came,</l>
    <l n="87">Our safe return, both with our ship and fame."</l>
    <l n="88">Thus prayed she; and herself herself obey'd,</l>
    <l n="89">In th' end performing all for which she pray'd.</l>
    <l n="90">And now, to pray, and do as she had done,</l>
    <l n="91">She gave the fair round bowl t' Ulysses' son.</l>
    <l n="92">The meat then dress'd, and drawn, and serv'd t' each guest,</l>
    <l n="93">They celebrated a most sumptuous feast.</l>

    <pb n="51" facs="#113"/>
    

    <l n="94">When appetite to wine and food allay'd,</l>
    <l n="95">Horse-taming Nestor then began, and said:</l>
    <l n="96">"Now life's desire is serv'd, as far as fare,</l>
    <l n="97">Time fits me to enquire what guests these are.</l>
    <l n="98">Fair guests, what are ye? And for what coast tries</l>
    <l n="99">Your ship the moist deeps? For fit merchandise,</l>
    <l n="100">Or rudely coast ye, like our men of prise,</l>
    <l n="101">The rough seas tempting, desperately erring,</l>
    <l n="102">The ill of others in their good conferring?"</l>
    <l n="103">The wise prince now his boldness did begin,</l>
    <l n="104">For Pallas' self had harden'd him within,</l>
    <l n="105">By this device of travel to explore</l>
    <l n="106">His absent father; which two girlonds wore;<anchor xml:id="n3.106_ref"/></l>
    <l n="107">His good by manage of his spirits; and then</l>
    <l n="108">To gain him high grace in th' accounts of men.</l>
    <l n="109">"O Nestor! still in whom Neleus lives!</l>
    <l n="110">And all the glory of the Greeks survives,</l>
    <l n="111">You ask from whence we are, and I relate:</l>
    <l n="112">From Ithaca (whose seat is situate</l>
    <l n="113">Where Neius, the renowned mountain, rears</l>
    <l n="114">His haughty forehead, and the honour bears</l>
    <l n="115">To be our sea-mark) we assay'd the waves.</l>
    <l n="116">The business, I must tell, our own good craves,</l>
    <l n="117">And not the public. I am come t' enquire,</l>
    <l n="118">If, in the fame that best men doth inspire</l>
    <l n="119">Of my most-suffering father, I may hear</l>
    <l n="120">Some truth of his estate now, who did bear</l>
    <l n="121">The name, being join'd in fight with you alone,</l>
    <l n="122">To even with earth the height of Ilion.</l>
    <l n="123">Of all men else, that any name did bear,</l>
    <l n="124">And fought for Troy, the several ends we hear;</l>
    <pb n="52"/>
    <l n="125">But his death Jove keeps from the world unknown,</l>
        <l n="126">The certain fame thereof being told by none;<anchor xml:id="n3.126_ref"/></l>
        <l n="127">If on the continent by enemies slain,</l>
        <l n="128">Or with the waves eat of the ravenous main.</l>
        <l n="129">For his love 'tis that to your knees I sue,</l>
        <l n="130">That you would please, out of your own clear view,</l>
        <l n="131">T'assure his sad end; or say, if your ear</l>
        <l n="132">Hath heard of the unhappy wanderer,</l>
        <l n="133">To too much sorrow whom his mother bore.</l>
        <l n="134">You then by all your bounties I implore,</l>
        <l n="135">(If ever to you deed or word hath stood,</l>
        <l n="136">By my good father promis'd, rendered good</l>
        <l n="137">Amongst the Trojans, where ye both have tried</l>
        <l n="138">The Grecian suff'rance) that in nought applied</l>
        <l n="139">To my respect or pity you will glose,<anchor xml:id="n3.139_ref"/></l>
        <l n="140">But uncloth'd truth to my desires disclose."</l>
        <l n="141">"O my much-lov'd," said he, " since you renew</l>
        <l n="142">Remembrance of the miseries that grew</l>
        <l n="143">Upon our still-in-strength-opposing Greece</l>
        <l n="144">Amongst Troy's people, I must touch a piece</l>
        <l n="145">Of all our woes there, either in the men</l>
        <l n="146">Achilles brought by sea and led to gain</l>
        <l n="147">About the country, or in us that fought</l>
        <l n="148">About the city, where to death were brought</l>
        <l n="149">All our chief men, as many as were there.</l>
        <l n="150">There Mars-like Ajax lies; Achilles there;</l>
        <l n="151">There the in-counsel-like-the-Gods, his friend;<anchor xml:id="n3.151_ref"/></l>
        <l n="152">There my dear son Antilochus took end,</l>
        <l n="153">Past measure swift of foot, and staid in fight.</l>
        <l n="154">A number more that ills felt infinite;</l>

        <note target="#n3.126_ref"><mentioned>Fame</mentioned> (Latin) report.</note>
        <note target="#n3.139_ref"><mentioned>Glose</mentioned>—gloss over.</note>
        <note target="#n3.151_ref"><mentioned>Patroclus</mentioned>.</note>

        <pb n="53" facs="#115"/>
        

        <l n="155">Of which to reckon all, what mortal man,</l>
        <l n="156">If five or six years you should stay here, can</l>
        <l n="157">Serve such enquiry? You would back again,</l>
        <l n="158">Affected with unsufferable pain,</l>
        <l n="159">Before you heard it. Nine years sieged we them,</l>
        <l n="160">With all the depth and sleight of stratagem</l>
        <l n="161">That could be thought. Ill knit to ill past end.</l>
        <l n="162">Yet still they toil'd us; nor would yet Jove send</l>
        <l n="163">Rest to our labours, nor will scarcely yet.</l>
        <l n="164">But no man lived, that would in public set</l>
        <l n="165">His wisdom by Ulysses' policy,</l>
        <l n="166">As thought his equal; so excessively</l>
        <l n="167">He stood superior all ways. If you be</l>
        <l n="168">His son indeed, mine eyes even ravish me</l>
        <l n="169">To admiration. And in all consent</l>
        <l n="170">Your speech puts on his speech's ornament.</l>
        <l n="171">Nor would one say, that one so young could use,</l>
        <l n="172">Unless his son, a rhetoric so profuse.</l>
        <l n="173">And while we lived together, he and I</l>
        <l n="174">Never in speech maintain'd diversity;</l>
        <l n="175">Nor set in counsel but, by one soul led,</l>
        <l n="176">With spirit and prudent counsel furnished</l>
        <l n="177">The Greeks at all hours, that, with fairest course,</l>
        <l n="178">What best became them, they might put in force.</l>
        <l n="179">But when Troy's high towers we had levell'd thus,</l>
        <l n="180">We put to sea, and God divided us.</l>
        <l n="181">And then did Jove our sad retreat devise;</l>
        <l n="182">For all the Greeks were neither just nor wise,</l>
        <l n="183">And therefore many felt so sharp a fate,</l>
        <l n="184">Sent from Minerva's most pernicious hate;</l>
        <l n="185">Whose mighty Father can do fearful things.</l>
        <l n="186">By whose help she betwixt the brother kings</l>

        <pb n="54" facs="#116"/>
        

        <l n="187">Let fall contention; who in council met</l>
        <l n="188">In vain, and timeless, when the sun was set,</l>
        <l n="189">And all the Greeks call'd, that came charged with wine.</l>
        <l n="190">Yet then the kings would utter their design,</l>
        <l n="191">And why they summon'd. Menelaus, he</l>
        <l n="192">Put all in mind of home, and cried, To sea.</l>
        <l n="193">But Agamemnon stood on contraries,</l>
        <l n="194">Whose will was, they should stay and sacrifice</l>
        <l n="195">Whole hecatombs to Pallas, to forego</l>
        <l n="196">Her high wrath to them. Fool! that did not know</l>
        <l n="197">She would not so be won; for not with ease</l>
        <l n="198">Th' Eternal Gods are turn'd from what they please.</l>
        <l n="199">So they, divided, on foul language stood.</l>
        <l n="200">The Greeks in huge rout rose, their wine-heat blood</l>
        <l n="201">Two ways affecting. And, that night's sleep too,</l>
        <l n="202">We turn'd to studying either other's woe;</l>
        <l n="203">When Jove besides made ready woes enow.</l>
        <l n="204">Morn came, we launch'd, and in our ships did stow</l>
        <l n="205">Our goods, and fair-girt women. Half our men</l>
        <l n="206">The people's guide, Atrides, did contain,</l>
        <l n="207">And half, being now aboard, put forth to sea.</l>
        <l n="208">A most free gale gave all ships prosperous way.</l>
        <l n="209">God settled then the huge whale-bearing lake,</l>
        <l n="210">And Tenedos we reach'd; where, for time's sake,</l>
        <l n="211">We did divine rites to the Gods. But Jove,</l>
        <l n="212">Inexorable still, bore yet no love</l>
        <l n="213">To our return, but did again excite</l>
        <l n="214">A second sad contention, that turn'd quite</l>
        <l n="215">A great part of us back to sea again;</l>
        <l n="216">Which were th' abundant-in-all-counsels man,</l>
        <l n="217">Your matchless father, who, to gratify</l>
        <l n="218">The great Atrides, back to him did fly.</l>

        <pb n="55" facs="#117"/>
        

        <l n="219">But I fled all, with all that follow'd me,</l>
        <l n="220">Because I knew God studied misery,</l>
        <l n="221">To hurl amongst us. With me likewise fled</l>
        <l n="222">Martial Tydides. I the men he led</l>
        <l n="223">Gat to go with him. Winds our fleet did bring</l>
        <l n="224">To Lesbos, where the yellow-headed king,</l>
        <l n="225">Though late, yet found us, as we put to choice</l>
        <l n="226">A tedious voyage; if we sail should hoise</l>
        <l n="227">Above rough Chius, left on our left hand,</l>
        <l n="228">To th' isle of Psyria, or that rugged land</l>
        <l n="229">Sail under, and for windy Mimas steer.</l>
        <l n="230">We ask'd of God that some ostent might clear</l>
        <l n="231">Our cloudy business, who gave us sign,</l>
        <l n="232">And charge, that all should, in a middle line,</l>
        <l n="233">The sea cut for Eubœa, that with speed</l>
        <l n="234">Our long-sustain'd infortune might be freed.</l>
        <l n="235">Then did a whistling wind begin to rise,</l>
        <l n="236">And swiftly flew we through the fishy skies,</l>
        <l n="237">Till to Geræstus we in night were brought;</l>
        <l n="238">Where, through the broad sea since we safe had wrought,</l>
        <l n="239">At Neptune's altars many solid thighs</l>
        <l n="240">Of slaughter'd bulls we burn'd for sacrifice.</l>
        <l n="241">The fourth day came, when Tydeus' son did greet</l>
        <l n="242">The haven of Argos with his complete fleet.</l>
        <l n="243">But I for Pylos straight steer'd on my course,</l>
        <l n="244">Nor ever left the wind his foreright force,</l>
        <l n="245">Since God fore-sent it first. And thus I came,</l>
        <l n="246">Dear son, to Pylos, uninform'd by fame,</l>
        <l n="247">Nor know one saved by Fate, or overcome.</l>
        <l n="248">Whom I have heard of since, set here at home,</l>
        <l n="249">As fits, thou shalt be taught, nought left unshown.</l>
        <l n="250">The expert spear-men, every Myrmidon,</l>

        <pb n="56" facs="#118"/>
        

        <l n="251">Led by the brave heir of the mighty-soul'd</l>
        <l n="252">Unpeer'd Achilles, safe of home got hold;</l>
        <l n="253">Safe Philoctetes, Pœan's famous seed;</l>
        <l n="254">And safe Idomenæus his men led</l>
        <l n="255">To his home, Crete, who fled the armed field,</l>
        <l n="256">Of whom yet none the sea from him withheld.</l>
        <l n="257">Atrides, you have both heard, though ye be</l>
        <l n="258">His far-off dwellers, what an end had he,</l>
        <l n="259">Done by Ægisthus to a bitter death;</l>
        <l n="260">Who miserably paid for forced breath,</l>
        <l n="261">Atrides leaving a good son, that dyed,</l>
        <l n="262">In blood of that deceitful parricide,<anchor xml:id="n3.262_ref"/></l>
        <l n="263">His wreakful sword. And thou my friend, as he</l>
        <l n="264">For this hath his fame, the like spirit in thee</l>
        <l n="265">Assume at all parts. Fair and great, I see,</l>
        <l n="266">Thou art in all hope, make it good to th' end,</l>
        <l n="267">That after-times as much may thee commend."</l>
        <l n="268">He answer'd: "O thou greatest grace of Greece,</l>
        <l n="269">Orestes made that wreak his master-piece,</l>
        <l n="270">And him the Greeks will give a master-praise,</l>
        <l n="271">Verse finding him to last all after-days.</l>
        <l n="272">And would to God the Gods would favour me</l>
        <l n="273">With his performance, that my injury,</l>
        <l n="274">Done by my mother's Wooers, being so foul,</l>
        <l n="275">I might revenge upon their every soul;</l>
        <l n="276">Who, pressing me with contumelies, dare</l>
        <l n="277">Such things as past the power of utt'rance are.</l>
        <l n="278">But Heaven's great Powers have graced my destiny</l>
        <l n="279">With no such honour. Both my sire and I</l>
        <l n="280">Are born to suffer everlastingly."</l>

        <note target="#n3.262_ref"><mentioned>Parricide</mentioned>—this is a somewhat uncommon use of the word. Orestes slew his father's murderer.</note>

        <pb n="57" facs="#119"/>
        

        <l n="281">"Because you name those Wooers, friend," said he,</l>
        <l n="282">"Report says, many such, in spite of thee,</l>
        <l n="283">Wooing thy mother, in thy house commit</l>
        <l n="284">The ills thou nam'st. But say: Proceedeth it</l>
        <l n="285">From will in thee to bear so foul a foil?</l>
        <l n="286">Or from thy subjects' hate, that wish thy spoil,</l>
        <l n="287">And will not aid thee, since their spirits rely,</l>
        <l n="288">Against thy rule, on some grave augury?</l>
        <l n="289">What know they, but at length thy father may</l>
        <l n="290">Come, and with violence their violence pay;</l>
        <l n="291">Or he alone, or all the Greeks with him?</l>
        <l n="292">But if Minerva now did so esteem</l>
        <l n="293">Thee, as thy father in times past; whom, past</l>
        <l n="294">All measure, she with glorious favours grac't</l>
        <l n="295">Amongst the Trojans, where we suffered so;</l>
        <l n="296">(O! I did never see, in such clear show,</l>
        <l n="297">The Gods so grace a man, as she to him,</l>
        <l n="298">To all our eyes, appear'd in all her trim)</l>
        <l n="299">If so, I say, she would be pleased to love,</l>
        <l n="300">And that her mind's care thou so much couldst move,</l>
        <l n="301">As did thy father, every man of these</l>
        <l n="302">Would lose in death their seeking marriages."</l>
        <l n="303">" O father," answer'd he, " you make amaze</l>
        <l n="304">Seize me throughout. Beyond the height of phrase</l>
        <l n="305">You raise expression; but 'twill never be,</l>
        <l n="306">That I shall move in any Deity</l>
        <l n="307">So blest an honour. Not by any means,</l>
        <l n="308">If Hope should prompt me, or blind Confidence,</l>
        <l n="309">(The God of Fools) or every Deity</l>
        <l n="310">Should will it; for 'tis past my destiny."</l>
        <l n="311">The burning-eyed Dame answer'd: "What a speech</l>
        <l n="312">Hath past the teeth-guard Nature gave to teach</l>

        <pb n="58" facs="#120"/>
        

        <l n="313">Fit question of thy words before they fly!</l>
        <l n="314">God easily can (when to a mortal eye<anchor xml:id="n3.314_ref"/></l>
        <l n="315">He's furthest off) a mortal satisfy;</l>
        <l n="316">And does the more still. For thy cared-for sire,</l>
        <l n="317">I rather wish, that I might home retire,</l>
        <l n="318">After my sufferance of a world of woes,</l>
        <l n="319">Far off, and then my glad eyes might disclose</l>
        <l n="320">The day of my return, then straight retire,</l>
        <l n="321">And perish standing by my household fire;</l>
        <l n="322">As Agamemnon did, that lost his life</l>
        <l n="323">By false Ægisthus, and his falser wife.</l>
        <l n="324">For Death to come at length, 'tis due to all;</l>
        <l n="325">Nor can the Gods themselves, when Fate shall call</l>
        <l n="326">Their most loved man, extend his vital breath</l>
        <l n="327">Beyond the fix'd bounds of abhorred Death."</l>
        <l n="328">"Mentor!" said he, " let's dwell no more on this,</l>
        <l n="329">Although in us the sorrow pious is.</l>
        <l n="330">No such return, as we wish, Fates bequeath</l>
        <l n="331">My erring father; whom a present death</l>
        <l n="332">The Deathless have decreed. I'll now use speech</l>
        <l n="333">That tends to other purpose; and beseech</l>
        <l n="334">Instruction of grave Nestor, since he flows</l>
        <l n="335">Past shore in all experience, and knows</l>
        <l n="336">The sleights and wisdoms, to whose heights aspire</l>
        <l n="337">Others, as well as my commended sire,</l>
        <l n="338">Whom Fame reports to have commanded three</l>
        <l n="339">Ages of men, and doth in sight to me</l>
        <l n="340">Show like th' Immortals. Nestor! the renown</l>
        <l n="341">Of old Neleius, make the clear truth known,</l>
        <l n="342">How the most great in empire, Atreus son,</l>
        <l n="343">Sustain'd the act of his destruction.</l>

        <note target="#n3.314_ref">Volente Deo, nihil est difficile.—CHAPMAN.</note>

        <pb n="59" facs="#121"/>
        

        <l n="344">Where then was Menelaus? How was it</l>
        <l n="345">That false Ægisthus, being so far unfit</l>
        <l n="346">A match for him, could his death so enforce?</l>
        <l n="347">Was he not then in Argos? or his course</l>
        <l n="348">With men so left, to let a coward breathe</l>
        <l n="349">Spirit enough to dare his brother's death?"</l>
        <l n="350">"I'll tell thee truth in all, fair son," said he:</l>
        <l n="351">"Right well was this event conceiv'd by thee.</l>
        <l n="352">If Menelaus in his brother's house</l>
        <l n="353">Had found the idle liver with his spouse,</l>
        <l n="354">Arriv'd from Troy, he had not liv'd, nor dead</l>
        <l n="355">Had the digg'd heap pour'd on his lustful head,</l>
        <l n="356">But fowls and dogs had torn him in the fields,</l>
        <l n="357">Far off of Argos; not a dame it yields</l>
        <l n="358">Had given him any tear, so foul his fact</l>
        <l n="359">Show'd even to women. Us Troy's wars had rack'd</l>
        <l n="360">To every sinew's sufferance, while he</l>
        <l n="361">In Argos' uplands liv'd, from those works free,</l>
        <l n="362">And Agamemnon's wife with force of word</l>
        <l n="363">Flatter'd and soften'd, who, at first, abhorr'd</l>
        <l n="364">A fact so infamous. The heav'nly dame</l>
        <l n="365">A good mind had, but was in blood too blame.<anchor xml:id="n3.365_ref"/></l>
        <l n="366">There was a poet, to whose care the king</l>
        <l n="367">His queen committed, and in every thing,</l>
        <l n="368">When he from Troy went, charg'd him to apply</l>
        <l n="369">Himself in all guard to her dignity.</l>
        <l n="370">But when strong Fate so wrapt-in her effects,</l>
        <l n="371">That she resolv'd to leave her fit respects,</l>

        <note target="#n3.365_ref">But was in blood too blame.—The expression too blame was not unusual in old writers. NARES has illustrated it from Shakespeare, Heywood, and others. Our modern phrase that a person is to blame, i. e. to be blamed, is a modification of this old form too blame, i. e. too blameable. See Shakespeare, 1 Henry IV. 111. 1.</note>

        <pb n="60" facs="#122"/>
        

        <l n="372">Into a desert isle her guardian led,</l>
        <l n="373">There left, the rapine of the vultures fed.</l>
        <l n="374">Then brought he willing home his will's won prize,</l>
        <l n="375">On sacred altars offer'd many thighs,</l>
        <l n="376">Hung in the God's fanes many ornaments,</l>
        <l n="377">Garments and gold, that he the vast events</l>
        <l n="378">Of such a labour to his wish had brought,</l>
        <l n="379">As neither fell into his hope nor thought.</l>
        <l n="380">At last, from Troy sail'd Sparta's king and I,</l>
        <l n="381">Both holding her untouch'd. And, that his eye</l>
        <l n="382">Might see no worse of her, when both were blown</l>
        <l n="383">To sacred Sunium, of Minerva's town</l>
        <l n="384">The goodly promontory, with his shafts severe</l>
        <l n="385">Augur Apollo slew him that did steer</l>
        <l n="386">Atrides' ship, as he the stern did guide,</l>
        <l n="387">And She the full speed of her sail applied.</l>
        <l n="388">He was a man that nations of men</l>
        <l n="389">Excell'd in safe guide of a vessel, when</l>
        <l n="390">A tempest rush'd in on the ruffled seas;</l>
        <l n="391">His name was Phrontis Onetorides.</l>
        <l n="392">And thus was Menelaus held from home,</l>
        <l n="393">Whose way he thirsted so to overcome,</l>
        <l n="394">To give his friend the earth, being his pursuit,</l>
        <l n="395">And all his exsequies to execute.</l>
        <l n="396">But sailing still the wine-hued seas, to reach<anchor xml:id="n3.396_ref"/></l>
        <l n="397">Some shore for fit performance, he did fetch</l>
        <l n="398">The steep mount of the Malians, and there,</l>
        <l n="399">With open voice, offended Jupiter</l>
        <l n="400">Proclaim'd the voyage his repugnant mind,<anchor xml:id="n3.400_ref"/></l>

        <note target="#n3.396_ref">Οἴνοπα πόντον: οἴνοψ cujus facies vinum repræsentat.—CHAPMAN.</note>
        <note target="#n3.400_ref">i. e. Proclaimed the voyage was in opposition to his will, was distasteful to him.</note>

        <pb n="61" facs="#123"/>
        

        <l n="401">And pour'd the puffs out of a shrieking wind,</l>
        <l n="402">That nourish'd billows heighten'd like to hills;</l>
        <l n="403">And with the fleet's division fulfills</l>
        <l n="404">His hate proclaim'd; upon a part of Crete</l>
        <l n="405">Casting the navy, where the sea-waves meet</l>
        <l n="406">Rough Jardanus, and where the Cydons live.</l>
        <l n="407">There is a rock, on which the sea doth drive,</l>
        <l n="408">Bare, and all broken, on the confines set</l>
        <l n="409">Of Gortys, that the dark seas likewise fret;</l>
        <l n="410">And hither sent the South a horrid drift</l>
        <l n="411">Of waves against the top, that was the left</l>
        <l n="412">Of that torn cliff as far as Phæstus' strand.</l>
        <l n="413">A little stone the great sea's rage did stand.</l>
        <l n="414">The men here driven 'scap'd hard the ships' sore shocks,</l>
        <l n="415">The ships themselves being wrack'd against the rocks,</l>
        <l n="416">Save only five, that blue fore-castles bore,</l>
        <l n="417">Which wind and water cast on Egypt's shore.</l>
        <l n="418">When he (there victling well, and store of gold</l>
        <l n="419">Aboard his ships brought) his wild way did hold,</l>
        <l n="420">And t' other languag'd men was forced to roam.</l>
        <l n="421">Mean space Ægisthus made sad work at home,</l>
        <l n="422">And slew his brother, forcing to his sway</l>
        <l n="423">Atrides' subjects, and did seven years lay</l>
        <l n="424">His yoke upon the rich Mycenian state.</l>
        <l n="425">But in the eighth, to his affrighting fate,</l>
        <l n="426">Divine Orestes home from Athens came,</l>
        <l n="427">And what his royal father felt, the same</l>
        <l n="428">He made the false Ægisthus groan beneath.</l>
        <l n="429">Death evermore is the reward of death.</l>
        <l n="430">Thus having slain him, a sepulchral feast</l>
        <l n="431">He made the Argives for his lustful guest,</l>
        <l n="432">And for his mother whom he did detest.</l>

        <pb n="62"/>

        <l n="433">The self-same day upon him stole the king</l>
        <l n="434">Good-at-a-martial-shout, and goods did bring,<anchor xml:id="n3.434_ref"/></l>
        <l n="435">As many as his freighted fleet could bear.</l>
        <l n="436">But thou, my son, too long by no means err,</l>
        <l n="437">Thy goods left free from many a spoilful guest,</l>
        <l n="438">Lest they consume some, and divide the rest,</l>
        <l n="439">And thou, perhaps, besides, thy voyage lose.</l>
        <l n="440">To Menelaus yet thy course dispose</l>
        <l n="441">I wish and charge thee; who but late arriv'd</l>
        <l n="442">From such a shore and men, as to have liv'd</l>
        <l n="443">In a return from them he never thought,</l>
        <l n="444">And whom black whirlwinds violently brought</l>
        <l n="445">Within a sea so vast, that in a year</l>
        <l n="446">Not any fowl could pass it anywhere,</l>
        <l n="447">So huge and horrid was it. But go thou</l>
        <l n="448">With ship and men (or, if thou pleases now</l>
        <l n="449">To pass by land, there shall be brought for thee</l>
        <l n="450">Both horse and chariot, and thy guides shall be</l>
        <l n="451">My sons themselves) to Sparta the divine,</l>
        <l n="452">And to the king whose locks like amber shine.</l>
        <l n="453">Intreat the truth of him, nor loves he lies,</l>
        <l n="454">Wisdom in truth is, and he's passing wise."</l>
        <l n="455">This said, the Sun went down, and up rose Night,</l>
        <l n="456">When Pallas spake: " O father, all good right</l>
        <l n="457">Bear thy directions. But divide we now</l>
        <l n="458">The sacrifices' tongues, mix wines, and vow</l>
        <l n="459">To Neptune, and the other Ever-Blest,</l>
        <l n="460">That, having sacrific'd, we may to rest.</l>
        <l n="461">The fit hour runs now, light dives out of date,</l>
        <l n="462">At sacred feasts we must not sit too late."</l>
        <l n="463">She said; they heard; the herald water gave;</l>

        <note target="#n3.434_ref"><mentioned>Good-at-a-martial-shout</mentioned>—Menelaus.</note>

        <pb n="63" facs="#125"/>
   

        <l n="464">The youths crown'd cups with wine, and let all have</l>
        <l n="465">Their equal shares, beginning from the cup</l>
        <l n="466">Their parting banquet. All the tongues cut up,</l>
        <l n="467">The fire they gave them, sacrific'd, and rose,</l>
        <l n="468">Wine, and divine rites used, to each dispose;</l>
        <l n="469">Minerva and Telemachus desir'd</l>
        <l n="470">They might to ship be, with his leave, retir'd.</l>
        <l n="471">He, mov'd with that, provok'd thus their abodes:<anchor xml:id="n3.471_ref"/></l>
        <l n="472">"Now Jove forbid, and all the long-liv'd Gods,</l>
        <l n="473">Your leaving me, to sleep aboard a ship;</l>
        <l n="474">As I had drunk of poor Penia's whip,<anchor xml:id="n3.474_ref"/></l>
        <l n="475">Even to my nakedness, and had nor sheet</l>
        <l n="476">Nor covering in my house; that warm nor sweet</l>
        <l n="477">A guest, nor I myself, had means to sleep;</l>
        <l n="478">Where I, both weeds and wealthy coverings keep</l>
        <l n="479">For all my guests. Nor shall Fame ever say,</l>
        <l n="480">The dear son of the man Ulysses lay</l>
        <l n="481">All night a-ship-board here while my days shine,</l>
        <l n="482">Or in my court whiles any son of mine</l>
        <l n="483">Enjoys survival, who shall guests receive,</l>
        <l n="484">Whomever my house hath a nook to leave."</l>
        <l n="485">"My much-lov'd father," said Minerva, " well</l>
        <l n="486">All this becomes thee. But persuade to dwell</l>
        <l n="487">This night with thee thy son Telemachus,</l>
        <l n="488">For more convenient is the course for us,</l>
        <l n="489">That he may follow to thy house and rest,</l>
        <l n="490">And I may board our black-sail, that address'd</l>
        <l n="491">At all parts I may make our men, and cheer</l>
        <l n="492">All with my presence, since of all men there</l>

        <note target="#n3.471_ref"><mentioned>Abodes</mentioned>—stay.</note>
        <note target="#n3.474_ref"><mentioned>Penia's</mentioned>—i.e. poverty's. Greek Πενία. A pedantic conceit in Chapman.</note>

        <pb n="64" facs="#126"/>
      

        <l n="493">I boast myself the senior, th' others are</l>
        <l n="494">Youths, that attend in free and friendly care</l>
        <l n="495">Great-soul'd Telemachus, and are his peers</l>
        <l n="496">In fresh similitude of form and years.</l>
        <l n="497">For their confirmance, I will therefore now</l>
        <l n="498">Sleep in our black bark. But, when light shall show</l>
        <l n="499">Her silver forehead, I intend my way</l>
        <l n="500">Amongst the Caucons, men that are to pay</l>
        <l n="501">A debt to me, nor small, nor new. For this,</l>
        <l n="502">Take you him home; whom in the morn dismiss,</l>
        <l n="503">With chariot and your sons, and give him horse</l>
        <l n="504">Ablest in strength, and of the speediest course."</l>
        <l n="505">This said, away she flew, form'd like the fowl</l>
        <l n="506">Men call the ossifrage; when every soul<anchor xml:id="n3.506_ref"/></l>
        <l n="507">Amaze invaded; even th' old man admir'd,</l>
        <l n="508">The youth's hand took, and said: "O most desir'd,</l>
        <l n="509">My hope says thy proof will no coward show,</l>
        <l n="510">Nor one unskill'd in war, when Deities now</l>
        <l n="511">So young attend thee, and become thy guides;</l>
        <l n="512">Nor any of the heaven-housed States besides,</l>
        <l n="513">But Tritogenia's self, the Seed of Jove,</l>
        <l n="514">The great in prey, that did in honour move</l>
        <l n="515">So much about thy father, amongst all</l>
        <l n="516">The Grecian army. Fairest queen, let fall</l>
        <l n="517">On me like favours! Give me good renown!</l>
        <l n="518">Which, as on me, on my lov'd wife let down,</l>

        <pb n="65"/>
        <l n="519">And all my children. I will burn to thee</l>
        <l n="520">An ox right bred, broad-headed, and yoke-free,</l>
        <l n="521">To no man's hand yet humbled. Him will I,</l>
        <l n="522">His horns in gold hid, give thy Deity."</l>
        <l n="523">Thus pray'd he, and she heard; and home he led</l>
        <l n="524">His sons, and all his heaps of kindered.</l>
        <l n="525">Who ent'ring his court royal, every one</l>
        <l n="526">He marshall'd in his several seat and throne;</l>
        <l n="527">And every one, so kindly come, he gave</l>
        <l n="528">His sweet-wine cup; which none was let to have</l>
        <l n="529">Before his 'leventh year landed him from Troy;</l>
        <l n="530">Which now the butleress had leave t' employ,</l>
        <l n="531">Who therefore pier'd it, and did give it vent.</l>
        <l n="532">Of this the old duke did a cup present</l>
        <l n="533">To every guest; made his Maid many a prayer<anchor xml:id="n3.533_ref"/></l>
        <l n="534">That wears the shield fring'd with his nurse's hair,<anchor xml:id="n3.534_ref"/></l>
        <l n="535">And gave her sacrifice. With this rich wine</l>
        <l n="536">And food sufficed, sleep all eyes did decline,</l>
        <l n="537">And all for home went; but his court alone</l>
        <l n="538">Telemachus, divine Ulysses' son,</l>
        <l n="539">Must make his lodging, or not please his heart.</l>
        <l n="540">A bed, all chequer'd with elaborate art,</l>
        <l n="541">Within a portico that rung like brass,</l>
        <l n="542">He brought his guest to; and his bedfere was<anchor xml:id="n3.542_ref"/></l>
        <l n="543">Pisistratus, the martial guide of men,</l>
        <l n="544">That liv'd, of all his sons, unwed till then.</l>
        <l n="545">Himself lay in a by-room, far above,</l>
        <l n="546">His bed made by his barren wife, his love.</l>

        <note target="#n3.533_ref"><mentioned>Minerva</mentioned>.</note>
        <note target="#n3.534_ref"><mentioned>Jupiter</mentioned>.</note>
        <note target="#n3.542_ref"><mentioned>Bedfere</mentioned>—bed-fellow.</note>

        <pb n="66" facs="#128"/>
        

        <l n="547">The rosy-finger'd Morn no sooner shone,</l>
        <l n="548">But up he rose, took air, and sat upon</l>
        <l n="549">A seat of white and goodly polish'd stone,</l>
        <l n="550">That such a gloss as richest ointments wore,</l>
        <l n="551">Before his high gates; where the counsellor</l>
        <l n="552">That match'd the Gods (his father) used to sit,</l>
        <l n="553">Who now, by fate forc'd, stoop'd as low as it.</l>
        <l n="554">And here sat Nestor, holding in his hand</l>
        <l n="555">A sceptre; and about him round did stand,</l>
        <l n="556">As early up, his sons' troop; Perseus,</l>
        <l n="557">The god-like Thrasymed, and Aretus,</l>
        <l n="558">Echephron, Stratius, the sixth and last</l>
        <l n="559">Pisistratus, and by him (half embrac'd</l>
        <l n="560">Still as they came) divine Telemachus ;</l>
        <l n="561">To these spake Nestor, old Gerenius :</l>
        <l n="562">"Haste, loved sons, and do me a desire,</l>
        <l n="563">That, first of all the Gods, I may aspire</l>
        <l n="564">To Pallas' favour, who vouchsafed to me</l>
        <l n="565">At Neptune's feast her sight so openly.</l>
        <l n="566">Let one to field go, and an ox with speed</l>
        <l n="567">Cause hither brought, which let the herdsman lead;</l>
        <l n="568">Another to my dear guest's vessel go,</l>
        <l n="569">And all his soldiers bring, save only two;</l>
        <l n="570">A third the smith that works in gold command</l>
        <l n="571">(Laertius) to attend, and lend his hand,</l>
        <l n="572">To plate the both horns round about with gold;</l>
        <l n="573">The rest remain here close. But first, see told</l>
        <l n="574">The maids within, that they prepare a feast,</l>
        <l n="575">Set seats through all the court, see straight address'd</l>
        <l n="576">The purest water, and get fuel fell'd."</l>
        <l n="577">This said, not one but in the service held</l>
        <l n="578">Officious hand. The ox came led from field;</l>
        <l n="579">The soldiers troop'd from ship; the smith he came,</l>
        <l n="580">And those tools brought that serv'd the actual frame</l>
        <l n="581">His art conceiv'd, brought anvil, hammers brought,</l>

        <pb n="67" facs="#129"/>
      

        <l n="582">Fair tongs, and all, with which the gold was wrought.</l>
        <l n="583">Minerva likewise came, to set the crown</l>
        <l n="584">On that kind sacrifice, and make 't her own.</l>
        <l n="585">Then th' old knight Nestor gave the smith the gold,</l>
        <l n="586">With which he straight did both the horns infold,</l>
        <l n="587">And trimm'd the offering so, the Goddess joy'd.</l>
        <l n="588">About which thus were Nestor's sons employ'd :</l>
        <l n="589">Divine Echephron, and fair Stratius,</l>
        <l n="590">Held both the horns. The water odorous,</l>
        <l n="591">In which they wash'd, what to the rites was vow'd,</l>
        <l n="592">Aretus, in a caldron all bestrow'd</l>
        <l n="593">With herbs and flowers, serv'd in from th' holy room</l>
        <l n="594">Where all were drest, and whence the rites must come.</l>
        <l n="595">And after him a hallow'd virgin came,</l>
        <l n="596">That brought the barley-cake, and blew the flame.</l>
        <l n="597">The axe, with which the ox should both be fell'd</l>
        <l n="598">And cut forth, Thrasymed stood by and held.</l>
        <l n="599">Perseus the vessel held that should retain</l>
        <l n="600">The purple liquor of the offering slain.</l>
        <l n="601">Then wash'd the pious father, then the cake</l>
        <l n="602">(Of barley, salt, and oil, made) took, and brake,</l>
        <l n="603">Ask'd many a boon of Pallas, and the state</l>
        <l n="604">Of all the offering did initiate,</l>
        <l n="605">In three parts cutting off the hair, and cast</l>
        <l n="606">Amidst the flame. All th' invocation past,</l>
        <l n="607">And all the cake broke, manly Thrasymed</l>
        <l n="608">Stood near, and sure, and such a blow he laid</l>
        <l n="609">Aloft the offering, that to earth he sunk,</l>
        <l n="610">His neck-nerves sunder'd, and his spirits shrunk.</l>
        <l n="611">Out shriek'd the daughters, daughter-in-laws, and wife</l>
        <l n="612">Of three-aged Nestor, who had eldest life</l>

        <pb n="68" facs="#130"/>


        <l n="613">Of Clymen's daughters, chaste Eurydice.</l>
        <l n="614">The ox on broad earth then laid laterally</l>
        <l n="615">They held, while duke Pisistratus the throat</l>
        <l n="616">Dissolv'd, and set the sable blood afloat,</l>
        <l n="617">And then the life the bones left. Instantly</l>
        <l n="618">They cut him up; apart flew either thigh,</l>
        <l n="619">That with the fat they dubb'd, with art alone,</l>
        <l n="620">The throat-brisk, and the sweet-bread pricking on.</l>
        <l n="621">Then Nestor broil'd them on the coal-turn'd wood,</l>
        <l n="622">Pour'd black wine on; and by him young men stood,</l>
        <l n="623">That spits fine-pointed held, on which, when burn'd</l>
        <l n="624">The solid thighs were, they transfix'd, and turn'd</l>
        <l n="625">The inwards, cut in cantles; which, the meat<anchor xml:id="n3.625_ref"/></l>
        <l n="626">Vow'd to the Gods consum'd, they roast and eat.</l>
        <l n="627">In mean space, Polycaste (call'd the fair,</l>
        <l n="628">Nestor's young'st daughter) bath'd Ulysses' heir;</l>
        <l n="629">Whom having cleans'd, and with rich balms bespread,</l>
        <l n="630">She cast a white shirt quickly o'er his head,</l>
        <l n="631">And then his weeds put on; when forth he went,</l>
        <l n="632">And did the person of a God present,</l>
        <l n="633">Came, and by Nestor took his honour'd seat,</l>
        <l n="634">This pastor of the people. Then, the meat</l>
        <l n="635">Of all the spare parts roasted, off they drew,</l>
        <l n="636">Sat, and fell to. But soon the temperate few</l>
        <l n="637">Rose, and in golden bowls fill'd others wine.</l>
        <l n="638">Till, when the rest felt thirst of feast decline,</l>
        <l n="639">Nestor his sons bad fetch his high-man'd horse,</l>
        <l n="640">And them in chariot join, to run the course</l>

        <note target="#n3.625_ref"><mentioned>Cantles</mentioned>—portions. One of our oldest words, and frequently occurring in our best writers. The French have chanteau and chantelle; and the Dutch kanteel; the Latin quantulum. See Jamieson's Scottish Dictionary; and Cotgrave in v. eschanteler.</note>

        <pb n="69" facs="#131"/>
   

        <l n="641">The prince resolv'd. Obey'd, as soon as heard,</l>
        <l n="642">Was Nestor by his sons, who straight prepar'd</l>
        <l n="643">Both horse and chariot. She that kept the store,</l>
        <l n="644">Both bread and wine, and all such viands more,</l>
        <l n="645">As should the feast of Jove-fed kings compose,</l>
        <l n="646">Purvey'd the voyage. To the rich coach rose</l>
        <l n="647">Ulysses' son, and close to him ascended</l>
        <l n="648">The duke Pisistratus, the reins intended,<anchor xml:id="n3.648_ref"/></l>
        <l n="649">And scourg'd, to force to field, who freely flew;</l>
        <l n="650">And left the town that far her splendour threw,</l>
        <l n="651">Both holding yoke, and shook it all the day.</l>
        <l n="652">But now the sun set, dark'ning every way,</l>
        <l n="653">When they to Pheris came; and in the house</l>
        <l n="654">Of Diocles (the son t' Orsilochus,</l>
        <l n="655">Whom flood Alpheus got) slept all that night;</l>
        <l n="656">Who gave them each due hospitable rite.</l>
        <l n="657">But when the rosy-finger'd Morn arose,</l>
        <l n="658">They went to coach, and did their horse inclose,<anchor xml:id="n3.658_ref"/></l>
        <l n="659">Drave forth the fore-court, and the porch that yields</l>
        <l n="660">Each breath a sound, and to the fruitful fields</l>
        <l n="661">Rode scourging still their willing flying steeds,</l>
        <l n="662">Who strenuously perform'd their wonted speeds.</l>
        <l n="663">Their journey ending just when sun went down,</l>
        <l n="664">And shadows all ways through the earth were thrown.</l>

        <note target="#n3.648_ref"><mentioned>Intended</mentioned>—used by old writers in sense of attended to; hence superintend.</note>
        <note target="#n3.658_ref"><mentioned>Inclose</mentioned>—i. e. put in harness.</note>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="4">
  <pb n="70" facs="#132"/>
  <head rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</head>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="1">
    <head rend="center">THE ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">RECEIVED now in the Spartan court,</l>
    <l n="2">Telemachus prefers report</l>
    <l n="3">To Menelaus of the throng</l>
    <l n="4">Of Wooers with him, and their wrong.</l>
    <l n="5">Atrides tells the Greeks' retreat,</l>
    <l n="6">And doth a prophecy repeat</l>
    <l n="7">That Proteus made, by which he knew</l>
    <l n="8">His brother's death; and then doth show</l>
    <l n="9">How with Calypso lived the sire</l>
    <l n="10">Of his young guest. The Wooers conspire</l>
    <l n="11">Their prince's death. Whose treachery known,</l>
    <l n="12">Penelope in tears doth drown.</l>
    <l n="13">Whom Pallas by a dream doth cheer,</l>
    <l n="14">And in similitude appear</l>
    <l n="15">Of fair Iphthima, known to be</l>
    <l n="16">The sister of Penelope.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="2">
    <head rend="center">ANOTHER ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">Δέλτα. Here of the sire</l>
    <l n="2">The son doth hear.</l>
    <l n="3">The Wooers conspire.</l>
    <l n="4">The Mother's fear.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="text">
    <l n="1"><hi rend="dropcap">I</hi>N Lacedæmon now, the nurse of whales,<anchor xml:id="n4.1_ref"/></l>
    <l n="2">These two arriv'd, and found at festivals,</l>
    <l n="3">With mighty concourse, the renowned king,</l>
    <l n="4">His son and daughter jointly marrying.</l>
    <l n="5">Alector's daughter he did give his son,</l>
    <l n="6">Strong Megapenthes, who his life begun</l>
    <l n="7">By Menelaus' bondmaid; whom he knew</l>
    <l n="8">In years when Helen could no more renew</l>
    <l n="9">In issue like divine Hermione,</l>
    <l n="10">Who held in all fair form as high degree</l>
    <l n="11">As golden Venus. Her he married now</l>
    <l n="12">To great Achilles' son, who was by vow</l>
    <l n="13">Betrothed to her at Troy. And thus the Gods</l>
    <l n="14">To constant loves give nuptial periods.</l>
    <l n="15">Whose state here past, the Myrmidons' rich town</l>
    <l n="16">Of which she shar'd in the imperial crown)</l>
    <l n="17">With horse and chariots he resign'd her to.</l>
    <l n="18">Mean space, the high huge house with feast did flow</l>
    <l n="19">Of friends and neighbours, joying with the king.</l>
    <l n="20">Amongst whom did a heavenly poet sing,</l>
    <l n="21">And touch his harp. Amongst whom likewise danc'd</l>
    <l n="22">Two, who in that dumb motion advanc'd,<anchor xml:id="n4.22_ref"/></l>
    <l n="23">Would prompt the singer what to sing and play.</l>
    <l n="24">All this time in the utter court did stay,</l>
    <l n="25">With horse and chariot, Telemachus,</l>
    <l n="26">And Nestor's noble son Pisistratus.</l>
    <l n="27">Whom Eteoneus, coming forth, descried,</l>
    <l n="28">And, being a servant to the king, most tried</l>
    <l n="29">In care and his respect, he ran and cried:</l>
    <l n="30">"Guests, Jove-kept Menelaus, two such men</l>
    <l n="31">As are for form of high Saturnius' strain.<anchor xml:id="n4.31_ref"/></l>

    <note target="#n4.1_ref">Λακεδαίμονα κητώεσσαν which is expounded Spartam amplam, or μεγάλην magnam; where κητώεσσαν signifies properly plurima cete nutrientem.—CHAPMAN.</note>
    <note target="#n4.22_ref">Μολπῆς ἐξάρχοντες Cantum auspicantes: of which place, the critics affirm, that saltatores motu suo indicant cantori quo genere cantus saltaturi forent. The rapture of Eteoneus at sight of Telemachus and Pisistratus.—CHAPΜΑΝ.</note>
    <note target="#n4.31_ref">Strain. See Book 1. 344.</note>

    <pb n="72" facs="#134"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="32">Inform your pleasure, if we shall unclose</l>
    <l n="33">Their horse from coach, or say they must dispose</l>
    <l n="34">Their way to some such house, as may embrace</l>
    <l n="35">Their known arrival with more welcome grace?"</l>
    <l n="36">He, angry, answer'd: "Thou didst never show</l>
    <l n="37">Thyself a fool, Boethides, till now;</l>
    <l n="38">But now, as if turn'd child, a childish speech</l>
    <l n="39">Vents thy vain spirits. We ourselves now reach</l>
    <l n="40">Our home by much spent hospitality</l>
    <l n="41">Of other men; nor know if Jove will try</l>
    <l n="42">With other after-wants our state again;</l>
    <l n="43">And therefore from our feast no more detain</l>
    <l n="44">Those welcome guests, but take their steeds from coach,</l>
    <l n="45">And with attendance guide in their approach."</l>
    <l n="46">This said, he rush'd abroad, and call'd some more</l>
    <l n="47">Tried in such service, that together bore</l>
    <l n="48">Up to the guests, and took their steeds that swet<anchor xml:id="n4.48_ref"/></l>
    <l n="49">Beneath their yokes from coach; at mangers set,</l>
    <l n="50">Wheat and white barley gave them mix'mixed; and plac'd</l>
    <l n="51">Their chariot by a wall so clear, it cast</l>
    <l n="52">A light quite through it. And then they led</l>
    <l n="53">Their guests to the divine house; which so fed</l>
    <l n="54">Their eyes at all parts with illustrious sights,</l>
    <l n="55">That admiration seized them. Like the lights</l>
    <l n="56">The sun and moon gave, all the palace threw</l>
    <l n="57">A lustre through it. Satiate with whose view,</l>
    <l n="58">Down to the king's most bright-kept baths they went;</l>

    <note target="#n4.48_ref">Swet. This orthography of the past tense is not infrequent in our old writers, as may be seen in the Iliad. Chapman uses het for heated in a similar way:— "Her blushing het her chamber; she look'd out, / And all the air she purpled round about." — MARLOW AND CHAPMAN'S MUSÆUS. Sestyad III.</note>

    <pb n="73" facs="#135"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="59">Where handmaids did their services present,</l>
    <l n="60">Bath'd, balm'd them, shirts and well-napt weeds put on,</l>
    <l n="61">And by Atrides' side set each his throne.</l>
    <l n="62">Then did the handmaid-royal water bring,</l>
    <l n="63">And to a laver, rich and glittering,</l>
    <l n="64">Of massy gold, pour'd; which she plac'd upon</l>
    <l n="65">A silver caldron, into which might run</l>
    <l n="66">The water as they wash'd. Then set she near</l>
    <l n="67">A polish'd table, on which all the cheer</l>
    <l n="68">The present could afford a reverend dame,</l>
    <l n="69">That kept the larder, set. A cook then came,</l>
    <l n="70">And divers dishes, borne thence, serv'd again;</l>
    <l n="71">Furnish'd the board with bowls of gold. And then,</l>
    <l n="72">His right hand given the guests, Atrides said:</l>
    <l n="73">"Eat, and be cheerful. Appetite allay'd,</l>
    <l n="74">I long to ask, of what stock ye descend;</l>
    <l n="75">For not from parents whose race nameless end</l>
    <l n="76">We must derive your offspring. Men obscure</l>
    <l n="77">Could get none such as you. The portraiture</l>
    <l n="78">Of Jove-sustain'd and sceptre-bearing kings</l>
    <l n="79">Your either person in his presence brings."</l>
    <l n="80">An ox's fat chine then they up did lift,</l>
    <l n="81">And set before the guests; which was a gift,</l>
    <l n="82">Sent as an honour to the king's own taste.</l>
    <l n="83">They saw yet 'twas but to be eaten plac'd,</l>
    <l n="84">And fell to it. But food and wine's care past,</l>
    <l n="85">Telemachus thus prompted Nestor's son,</l>
    <l n="86">(His ear close laying, to be heard of none)<anchor xml:id="n4.86_ref"/></l>
    <l n="87">" Consider, thou whom most my mind esteems,</l>

    <note target="#n4.86_ref">Telemachus to Pisistratus, in observation of the house, not so much that he heartily admired it, as to please Menelaus, who he knew heard, though he seemed desirous he should not hear.—CHAPMAN.</note>

    <pb n="74" facs="#136"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="88">The brass-work here, how rich it is in beams,</l>
    <l n="89">And how, besides, it makes the whole house sound;</l>
    <l n="90">What gold, and amber, silver, ivory, round</l>
    <l n="91">Is wrought about it. Out of doubt, the hall</l>
    <l n="92">Of Jupiter Olympius hath of all</l>
    <l n="93">This state the like. How many infinites</l>
    <l n="94">Take up to admiration all men's sights!"</l>
    <l n="95">Atrides over-heard, and said: "Lov'd son,</l>
    <l n="96">No mortal must affect contention</l>
    <l n="97">With Jove, whose dwellings are of endless date.</l>
    <l n="98">Perhaps of men some one may emulate,</l>
    <l n="99">Or none, my house, or me; for I am one</l>
    <l n="100">That many a grave extreme have undergone,</l>
    <l n="101">Much error felt by sea, and till th' eighth year,</l>
    <l n="102">Had never stay, but wander'd far and near,</l>
    <l n="103">Cyprus, Phœnicia, and Sidonia,</l>
    <l n="104">And fetch'd the far-off Æthiopia,</l>
    <l n="105">Reach'd the Erembi of Arabia,</l>
    <l n="106">And Lybia, where with horns ewes yean their lambs,</l>
    <l n="107">Which every full year ewes are three times dams,</l>
    <l n="108">Where neither king, nor shepherd, want comes near</l>
    <l n="109">Of cheese, or flesh, or sweet milk; all the year</l>
    <l n="110">They ever milk their ewes. And here while I</l>
    <l n="111">Err'd, gathering means to live, one, murderously,</l>
    <l n="112">Unwares, unseen, bereft my brother's life,</l>
    <l n="113">Chiefly betray'd by his abhorred wife.</l>
    <l n="114">So hold I, not enjoying, what you see.</l>
    <l n="115">And of your fathers, if they living be,</l>
    <l n="116">You must have heard this, since my sufferings were</l>
    <l n="117">So great and famous; from this palace here</l>
    <l n="118">(So rarely-well-built, furnished so well,</l>
    <l n="119">And substanced with such a precious deal</l>

    <pb n="75" facs="#137"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="120">Of well-got treasure) banish'd by the doom</l>
    <l n="121">Of Fate, and erring as I had no home.</l>
    <l n="122">And now I have, and use it, not to take</l>
    <l n="123">Th' entire delight it offers, but to make</l>
    <l n="124">Continual wishes, that a triple part</l>
    <l n="125">Of all it holds were wanting, so my heart</l>
    <l n="126">Were eas'd of sorrows, taken for their deaths</l>
    <l n="127">That fell at Troy, by their revived breaths.</l>
    <l n="128">And thus sit I here weeping, mourning still</l>
    <l n="129">Each least man lost; and sometimes make mine ill,</l>
    <l n="130">In paying just tears for their loss, my joy.</l>
    <l n="131">Sometimes I breathe my woes, for in annoy</l>
    <l n="132">The pleasure soon admits satiety.</l>
    <l n="133">But all these men's wants wet not so mine eye,</l>
    <l n="134">Though much they move me, as one sole man's miss,</l>
    <l n="135">For which my sleep and meat even loathsome is</l>
    <l n="136">In his renew'd thought, since no Greek hath won</l>
    <l n="137">Grace for such labours as Laërtes' son</l>
    <l n="138">Hath wrought and suffer'd, to himself nought else</l>
    <l n="139">But future sorrows forging, to me hells</l>
    <l n="140">For his long absence, since I cannot know</l>
    <l n="141">If life or death detain him; since such woe</l>
    <l n="142">For his love, old Laërtes, his wise wife,</l>
    <l n="143">And poor young son sustains, whom new with life</l>
    <l n="144">He left as sireless." This speech grief to tears</l>
    <l n="145">(Pour'd from the son's lids on the earth) his ears,</l>
    <l n="146">Told of the father, did excite; who kept</l>
    <l n="147">His cheeks dry with his red weed as he wept,</l>
    <l n="148">His both hands used therein. Atrides then</l>
    <l n="149">Began to know him, and did strife retain,</l>
    <l n="150">If he should let himself confess his sire,</l>
    <l n="151">Or with all fitting circumstance enquire.</l>

    <pb n="76" facs="#138"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="152">While this his thoughts disputed, forth did shine,</l>
    <l n="153">Like to the golden distaff-deck'd Divine,<anchor xml:id="n4.153_ref"/></l>
    <l n="154">From her bed's high and odoriferous room,</l>
    <l n="155">Helen. To whom, of an elaborate loom,</l>
    <l n="156">Adresta set a chair; Alcippe brought</l>
    <l n="157">A piece of tapestry of fine wool wrought;</l>
    <l n="158">Phylo a silver cabinet conferr'd,</l>
    <l n="159">Given by Alcandra, nuptially endear'd</l>
    <l n="160">To lord Polybius, whose abode in Thebes</l>
    <l n="161">Th' Ægyptian city was, where wealth in heaps</l>
    <l n="162">His famous house held, out of which did go,</l>
    <l n="163">In gift t' Atrides, silver bath-tubs two,</l>
    <l n="164">Two tripods, and of fine gold talents ten.</l>
    <l n="165">His wife did likewise send to Helen then</l>
    <l n="166">Fair gifts, a distaff that of gold was wrought,</l>
    <l n="167">And that rich cabinet that Phylo brought,</l>
    <l n="168">Round, and with gold ribb'd, now of fine thread full;</l>
    <l n="169">On which extended (crown'd with finest wool,</l>
    <l n="170">Of violet gloss) the golden distaff lay.</l>
    <l n="171">She took her state-chair, and a foot-stool's stay</l>
    <l n="172">Had for her feet; and of her husband thus</l>
    <l n="173">Ask'd to know all things: "Is it known to us,</l>
    <l n="174">King Menelaus, whom these men commend</l>
    <l n="175">Themselves for, that our court now takes to friend?</l>
    <l n="176">I must affirm, be I deceived or no,</l>
    <l n="177">I never yet saw man nor woman so</l>
    <l n="178">Like one another, as this man is like</l>
    <l n="179">Ulysses' son. With admiration strike</l>
    <l n="180">His looks my thoughts, that they should carry now</l>
    <l n="181">Power to persuade me thus, who did but know,</l>
    <l n="182">When newly he was born, the form they bore.</l>
    <l n="183">But 'tis his father's grace, whom more and more</l>

    <note target="#n4.153_ref"><mentioned>Diana</mentioned>.</note>

    <pb n="77" facs="#139"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="184">His grace resembles, that makes me retain</l>
    <l n="185">Thought that he now is like Telemachus, then</l>
    <l n="186">Left by his sire, when Greece did undertake</l>
    <l n="187">Troy's bold war for my impudency's sake."</l>
    <l n="188">He answer'd: "Now wife, what you think I know,</l>
    <l n="189">The true cast of his father's eye doth show</l>
    <l n="190">In his eyes order. Both his head and hair,</l>
    <l n="191">His hands and feet, his very father's are.</l>
    <l n="192">Of whom, so well remember'd, I should now</l>
    <l n="193">Acknowledge for me his continual flow</l>
    <l n="194">Of cares and perils, yet still patient.</l>
    <l n="195">But I should too much move him, that doth vent</l>
    <l n="196">Such bitter tears for that which hath been spoke,</l>
    <l n="197">Which, shunning soft show, see how he would cloak,</l>
    <l n="198">And with his purple weed his weepings hide."</l>
    <l n="199">Then Nestor's son, Pisistratus, replied:</l>
    <l n="200">"Great pastor of the people, kept of God!</l>
    <l n="201">He is Ulysses' son, but his abode</l>
    <l n="202">Not made before here, and he modest too,</l>
    <l n="203">He holds it an indignity to do</l>
    <l n="204">A deed so vain, to use the boast of words,</l>
    <l n="205">Where your words are on wing; whose voice affords</l>
    <l n="206">Delight to us as if a God did break</l>
    <l n="207">The air amongst us, and vouchsafe to speak.</l>
    <l n="208">But me my father, old duke Nestor, sent</l>
    <l n="209">To be his consort hither; his content</l>
    <l n="210">Not to be heighten'd so as with your sight,</l>
    <l n="211">In hope that therewith words and actions might</l>
    <l n="212">Inform his comforts from you, since he is</l>
    <l n="213">Extremely grieved and injured by the miss</l>
    <l n="214">Of his great father; suffering even at home,</l>
    <l n="215">And few friends found to help him overcome</l>

    <pb n="78" facs="#140"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="216">His too weak suff'rance, now his sire is gone;</l>
    <l n="217">Amongst the people, not afforded one</l>
    <l n="218">To check the miseries that mate him thus.<anchor xml:id="n4.218_ref"/></l>
    <l n="219">And this the state is of Telemachus."</l>
    <l n="220">"O Gods," said he, "how certain, now, I see</l>
    <l n="221">My house enjoys that friend's son, that for me</l>
    <l n="222">Hath undergone so many willing fights!</l>
    <l n="223">Whom I resolved, past all the Grecian knights,</l>
    <l n="224">To hold in love, if our return by seas</l>
    <l n="225">The far-off Thunderer did ever please</l>
    <l n="226">To grant our wishes. And to his respect</l>
    <l n="227">A palace and a city to erect,</l>
    <l n="228">My vow had bound me; whither bringing then</l>
    <l n="229">His riches, and his son, and all his men,</l>
    <l n="230">From barren Ithaca, (some one sole town</l>
    <l n="231">Inhabited about him batter'd down)</l>
    <l n="232">All should in Argos live. And there would I</l>
    <l n="233">Ease him of rule, and take the empery</l>
    <l n="234">Of all on me. And often here would we,</l>
    <l n="235">Delighting, loving either's company,</l>
    <l n="236">Meet and converse; whom nothing should divide,</l>
    <l n="237">Till death's black veil did each all over hide.</l>
    <l n="238">But this perhaps hath been a mean to take seawards</l>
    <l n="239">Even God himself with envy; who did make</l>
    <l n="240">Ulysses therefore only the unblest,</l>
    <l n="241">That should not reach his loved country's rest."</l>
    <l n="242">These woes made every one with woe in love;</l>
    <l n="243">Even Argive Helen wept, the seed of Jove;</l>

    <note target="#n4.218_ref"><mentioned>Mate</mentioned>—oppose. Shakespeare (Henry VIII. 111. 2.) "Dare mate a sounder man than Surrey can be." Beaum. and Fletcher (Rule a Wife, 111. 1.) "The piece of ignorant dough! He stood up to me, / And mated my commands."</note>

    <pb n="79" facs="#141"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="244">Ulysses' son wept; Atreus' son did weep;<anchor xml:id="n4.244_ref"/></l>
    <l n="245">And Nestor's son his eyes in tears did steep,</l>
    <l n="246">But his tears fell not from the present cloud</l>
    <l n="247">That from Ulysses was exhaled, but flow'd</l>
    <l n="248">From brave Antilochus' remember'd due,</l>
    <l n="249">Whom the renown'd Son of the Morning slew,<anchor xml:id="n4.249_ref"/></l>
    <l n="250">Which yet he thus excused: "O Atreus' son!</l>
    <l n="251">Old Nestor says, there lives not such a one</l>
    <l n="252">Amongst all mortals as Atrides is</l>
    <l n="253">For deathless wisdom. 'Tis a praise of his,</l>
    <l n="254">Still given in your remembrance, when at home</l>
    <l n="255">Our speech concerns you. Since then overcome</l>
    <l n="256">You please to be with sorrow, even to tears,</l>
    <l n="257">That are in wisdom so exempt from peers,</l>
    <l n="258">Vouchsafe the like effect in me excuse,</l>
    <l n="259">If it be lawful, I affect no use</l>
    <l n="260">Of tears thus after meals; at least, at night;</l>
    <l n="261">But when the morn brings forth, with tears, her light,</l>
    <l n="262">It shall not then impair me to bestow</l>
    <l n="263">My tears on any worthy's overthrow.</l>
    <l n="264">It is the only rite that wretched men</l>
    <l n="265">Can do dead friends, to cut hair, and complain.</l>
    <l n="266">But Death my brother took, whom none could call</l>
    <l n="267">The Grecian coward, you best knew of all.</l>
    <l n="268">I was not there, nor saw, but men report</l>
    <l n="269">Antilochus excell'd the common sort</l>
    <l n="270">For footmanship, or for the chariot race,</l>
    <l n="271">Or in the fight for hardy hold of place."</l>
    <l n="272">" O friend," said he, " since thou hast spoken so,</l>
    <l n="273">At all parts as one wise should say and do,</l>
    <l n="274">And like one far beyond thyself in years,</l>
    <l n="275">Thy words shall bounds be to our former tears.</l>

    <note target="#n4.244_ref"><mentioned>Menelaus</mentioned>.</note>
    <note target="#n4.249_ref"><mentioned>Memnon</mentioned>.</note>

    <pb n="80" facs="#142"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK.</fw>

    <l n="276">O he is questionless a right born son,</l>
    <l n="277">That of his father hath not only won</l>
    <l n="278">The person but the wisdom; and that sire</l>
    <l n="279">Complete himself that hath a son entire,</l>
    <l n="280">Jove did not only his full fate adorn,</l>
    <l n="281">When he was wedded, but when he was born.</l>
    <l n="282">As now Saturnius, through his life's whole date,</l>
    <l n="283">Hath Nestor's bliss raised to as steep a state,</l>
    <l n="284">Both in his age to keep in peace his house,</l>
    <l n="285">And to have children wise and valorous.</l>
    <l n="286">But let us not forget our rear feast thus.<anchor xml:id="n4.286_ref"/></l>
    <l n="287">Let some give water here. Telemachus!</l>
    <l n="288">The morning shall yield time to you and me</l>
    <l n="289">To do what fits, and reason mutually."</l>
    <l n="290">This said, the careful servant of the king,</l>
    <l n="291">Asphalion, pour'd on th' issue of the spring;</l>
    <l n="292">And all to ready feast set ready hand.</l>
    <l n="293">But Helen now on new device did stand,</l>
    <l n="294">Infusing straight a medicine to their wine,</l>
    <l n="295">That, drowning cares and angers, did decline</l>
    <l n="296">All thought of ill. Who drunk her cup could shed</l>
    <l n="297">All that day not a tear, no not if dead</l>
    <l n="298">That day his father or his mother were,</l>
    <l n="299">Not if his brother, child, or chiefest dear,</l>
    <l n="300">He should see murder'd then before his face.</l>
    <l n="301">Such useful medicines, only borne in grace</l>
    <l n="302">Of what was good, would Helen ever have.</l>
    <l n="303">And this juice to her Polydamna gave</l>
    <l n="304">The wife of Thoon, an Ægyptian born,</l>
    <l n="305">Whose rich earth herbs of medicine do adorn</l>
    <l n="306">In great abundance. Many healthful are,</l>

    <note target="#n4.286_ref"><mentioned>Rear feast</mentioned>—i. e. the latter portion of our feast.</note>

    <pb n="81" facs="#143"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="307">And many baneful. Every man is there</l>
    <l n="308">A good physician out of Nature's grace,</l>
    <l n="309">For all the nation sprung of Pæon's race.</l>
    <l n="310">When Helen then her medicine had infus'd,</l>
    <l n="311">She bad pour wine to it, and this speech us'd :</l>
    <l n="312">"Atrides, and these good men's sons, great Jove</l>
    <l n="313">Makes good and ill one after other move,</l>
    <l n="314">In all things earthly; for he can do all.</l>
    <l n="315">The woes past, therefore, he so late let fall,</l>
    <l n="316">The comforts he affords us let us take;</l>
    <l n="317">Feast, and, with fit discourses, merry make.</l>
    <l n="318">Nor will I other use. As then our blood</l>
    <l n="319">Griev'd for Ulysses', since he was so good,</l>
    <l n="320">Since he was good, let us delight to hear</l>
    <l n="321">How good he was, and what his sufferings were ;</l>
    <l n="322">Though every fight, and every suffering deed,</l>
    <l n="323">Patient Ulysses underwent, exceed</l>
    <l n="324">My woman's power to number, or to name.</l>
    <l n="325">But what he did, and suffer's, when he came</l>
    <l n="326">Amongst the Trojans, where ye Grecians all</l>
    <l n="327">Took part with suff'rance, I in part can call</l>
    <l n="328">To your kind memories. How with ghastly wounds</l>
    <l n="329">Himself he mangled, and the Trojan bounds,</l>
    <l n="330">Thrust thick with enemies, adventur'd on,</l>
    <l n="331">His royal shoulders having cast upon</l>
    <l n="332">Base abject weeds, and enter'd like a slave.</l>
    <l n="333">Then, beggar-like, he did of all men crave,</l>
    <l n="334">And such a wretch was, as the whole Greek fleet</l>
    <l n="335">Brought not besides. And thus through every street</l>
    <l n="336">He crept discovering, of no one man known.</l>
    <l n="337">And yet through all this difference, I alone</l>

    <pb n="82"/>

    <l n="338">Smoked his true person, talk'd with him; but he<anchor xml:id="n4.338_ref"/></l>
        <l n="339">Fled me with wiles still. Nor could we agree,</l>
        <l n="340">Till I disclaim'd him quite; and so (as mov'd</l>
        <l n="341">With womanly remorse of one that prov'd<anchor xml:id="n4.341_ref"/></l>
        <l n="342">So wretched an estate, whate'er he were)</l>
        <l n="343">Won him to take my house. And yet even there,</l>
        <l n="344">Till freely I, to make him doubtless, swore</l>
        <l n="345">A powerful oath, to let him reach the shore</l>
        <l n="346">Of ships and tents before Troy understood,</l>
        <l n="347">I could not force on him his proper good.</l>
        <l n="348">But then I bath'd and sooth'd him, and he then</l>
        <l n="349">Confess'd, and told me all; and, having slain</l>
        <l n="350">A number of the Trojan guards, retired,</l>
        <l n="351">And reach'd the fleet, for sleight and force admired.</l>
        <l n="352">Their husbands' deaths by him the Trojan wives</l>
        <l n="353">Shreek'd for; but I made triumphs for their lives,</l>
        <l n="354">For then my heart conceiv'd, that once again</l>
        <l n="355">I should reach home; and yet did still retain</l>
        <l n="356">Woe for the slaughters Venus made for me,</l>
        <l n="357">When both my husband, my Hermione,</l>
        <l n="358">And bridal room, she robb'd of so much right,</l>
        <l n="359">And drew me from my country with her sleight,</l>
        <l n="360">Though nothing under heaven I here did need,</l>
        <l n="361">That could my fancy or my beauty feed."</l>
        <l n="362">Her husband said: "Wife! what you please to tell</l>
        <l n="363">Is true at all parts, and becomes you well;</l>
        <l n="364">And I myself, that now may say have seen</l>
        <l n="365">The minds and manners of a world of men,</l>

        <note target="#n4.338_ref"><mentioned>Smoked</mentioned>—discovered. Shakespeare, "He was smoked by the old Lord Lafew, when his disguise, &amp;c."—All's Well that ends Well, III. 6.</note>
        <note target="#n4.341_ref"><mentioned>Remorse</mentioned>—pity. See Iliad VIII. 208.</note>

        <pb n="83" facs="#145"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="366">And great heroës, measuring many a ground,</l>
        <l n="367">Have never, by these eyes that light me, found</l>
        <l n="368">One with a bosom so to be beloved,</l>
        <l n="369">As that in which th' accomplish'd spirit moved</l>
        <l n="370">Of patient Ulysses. What, brave man,</l>
        <l n="371">He both did act, and suffer, when he wan</l>
        <l n="372">The town of Ilion, in the brave-built horse,</l>
        <l n="373">When all we chief states of the Grecian force</l>
        <l n="374">Were hous'd together, bringing Death and Fate</l>
        <l n="375">Amongst the Trojans, you, wife, may relate;</l>
        <l n="376">For you, at last, came to us; God, that would</l>
        <l n="377">The Trojans' glory give, gave charge you should</l>
        <l n="378">Approach the engine; and Deiphobus,</l>
        <l n="379">The god-like, follow'd. Thrice ye circled us</l>
        <l n="380">With full survey of it; and often tried</l>
        <l n="381">The hollow crafts that in it were implied.<anchor xml:id="n4.381_ref"/></l>
        <l n="382">When all the voices of their wives in it</l>
        <l n="383">You took on you with voice so like and fit,</l>
        <l n="384">And every man by name so visited,</l>
        <l n="385">That I, Ulysses, and king Diomed,</l>
        <l n="386">(Set in the midst, and hearing how you call'd)</l>
        <l n="387">Tydides, and myself (as half appall'd</l>
        <l n="388">With your remorseful plaints) would passing fain</l>
        <l n="389">Have broke our silence, rather than again</l>
        <l n="390">Endure, respectless, their so moving cries.<anchor xml:id="n4.390_ref"/></l>
        <l n="391">But Ithacus our strongest phantasies</l>
        <l n="392">Contain'd within us from the slenderest noise,</l>
        <l n="393">And every man there sat without a voice.</l>
        <l n="394">Anticlus only would have answer'd thee,</l>

        <note target="#n4.381_ref">Helen counterfeited the wives' voices of those kings of Greece that were in the wooden horse, and calls their husbands.—CHAPMAN.</note>
        <note target="#n4.390_ref"><mentioned>Respectless</mentioned>—without taking notice.</note>

        <pb n="84" facs="#146"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="395">But his speech Ithacus incessantly</l>
        <l n="396">With strong hand held in, till, Minerva's call</l>
        <l n="397">Charging thee off, Ulysses sav'd us all."</l>
        <l n="398">Telemachus replied: "Much greater is</l>
        <l n="399">My grief, for hearing this high praise of his.</l>
        <l n="400">For all this doth not his sad death divert,</l>
        <l n="401">Nor can, though in him swell'd an iron heart.</l>
        <l n="402">Prepare, and lead then, if you please, to rest:</l>
        <l n="403">Sleep, that we hear not, will content us best."</l>
        <l n="404">Then Argive Helen made her handmaid go,</l>
        <l n="405">And put fair bedding in the portico,</l>
        <l n="406">Lay purple blankets on, rugs warm and soft,</l>
        <l n="407">And cast an arras coverlet aloft.</l>
        <l n="408">They torches took, made haste, and made the bed;</l>
        <l n="409">When both the guests were to their lodgings led</l>
        <l n="410">Within a portico without the house.</l>
        <l n="411">Atrides, and his large-train-wearing spouse,</l>
        <l n="412">The excellent of women, for the way,</l>
        <l n="413">In a retired receit, together lay.</l>
        <l n="414">The Morn arose; the king rose, and put on</l>
        <l n="415">His royal weeds, his sharp sword hung upon</l>
        <l n="416">His ample shoulders, forth his chamber went,</l>
        <l n="417">And did the person of a God present.</l>
        <l n="418">Telemachus accosts him, who begun<anchor xml:id="n4.418_ref"/></l>
        <l n="419">Speech of his journey's proposition :</l>
        <l n="420">" And what, my young Ulyssean heroë,</l>
        <l n="421">Provoked thee on the broad back of the sea,</l>
        <l n="422">To visit Lacedæmon the divine?</l>

        <note target="#n4.418_ref"><mentioned>Accosts</mentioned>—draws near, approaches to his side. Fr. accoster, (on which word see Cotgrave) or Latin ad and costa. The word was not used in the sense of "to address," "speak to first" so early as Chapman's time.</note>

        <pb n="85" facs="#147"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="423">Speak truth, some public [good] or only thine?"<anchor xml:id="n4.423_ref"/></l>
        <l n="424">" I come," said he, " to hear, if any fame</l>
        <l n="425">Breath'd of my father to thy notice came.</l>
        <l n="426">My house is sack'd, my fat works of the field</l>
        <l n="427">Are all destroy'd; my house doth nothing yield</l>
        <l n="428">But enemies, that kill my harmless sheep,</l>
        <l n="429">And sinewy oxen, nor will ever keep</l>
        <l n="430">Their steels without them. And these men are they</l>
        <l n="431">That woo my mother, most inhumanly</l>
        <l n="432">Committing injury on injury.</l>
        <l n="433">To thy knees therefore I am come, t' attend</l>
        <l n="434">Relation of the sad and wretched end</l>
        <l n="435">My erring father felt, if witness'd by</l>
        <l n="436">Your own eyes, or the certain news that fly</l>
        <l n="437">From others' knowledges. For, more than is</l>
        <l n="438">The usual heap of human miseries,</l>
        <l n="439">His mother bore him to. Vouchsafe me then,</l>
        <l n="440">Without all ruth of what I can sustain,</l>
        <l n="441">The plain and simple truth of all you know.</l>
        <l n="442">Let me beseech so much, if ever vow</l>
        <l n="443">Was made, and put in good effect to you,</l>
        <l n="444">At Troy, where suff'rance bred you so much smart,</l>
        <l n="445">Upon my father good Ulysses' part,</l>
        <l n="446">And quit it now to me (himself in youth)</l>
        <l n="447">Unfolding only the unclosed truth."</l>
        <l n="448">He, deeply sighing, answer'd him : " O shame,</l>
        <l n="449">That such poor vassals should affect the fame</l>
        <l n="450">To share the joys of such a worthy's bed!</l>
        <l n="451">As when a hind, her calves late farrowed,<anchor xml:id="n4.51_ref_err"/></l>

        <note target="#n4.423_ref">[Good].—A word is wanting here which I have thus supplied.</note>
        <note target="#n4.51_ref_err">This is the first simile in the Odyssey, and Chapman has made it very confused. The original is simply: "As when a hind, having laid her new-born suckling fawns in the den of a strong lion, searches out the lower parts of a hill (see κνημὸς) and grassy vallies for food, but he then has entered his lair, &amp;c." Chapman, however, makes the lion hunting in the vales for food (deer) feeding there. See Bk. XVII. 157.</note>

        <pb n="86" facs="#148"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="452">To give suck, enters the bold lion's den,</l>
        <l n="453">He roots of hills and herby vallies then</l>
        <l n="454">For food (there feeding) hunting; but at length</l>
        <l n="455">Returning to his cavern, gives his strength</l>
        <l n="456">The lives of both the mother and her brood</l>
        <l n="457">In deaths indecent; so the Wooers' blood</l>
        <l n="458">Must pay Ulysses' powers as sharp an end.</l>
        <l n="459">O would to Jove, Apollo, and thy friend</l>
        <l n="460">The wise Minerva, that thy father were</l>
        <l n="461">As once he was, when he his spirits did rear</l>
        <l n="462">Against Philomelides, in a fight</l>
        <l n="463">Perform'd in well-built Lesbos, where, down-right</l>
        <l n="464">He strook the earth with him, and gat a shout</l>
        <l n="465">Of all the Grecians! O, if now full out</l>
        <l n="466">He were as then, and with the Wooers coped,</l>
        <l n="467">Short-liv'd they all were, and their nuptials hoped</l>
        <l n="468">Would prove as desperate. But, for thy demand</l>
        <l n="469">Enforc'd with prayers, I'll let thee understand</l>
        <l n="470">The truth directly, nor decline a thought,</l>
        <l n="471">Much less deceive, or sooth thy search in ought;</l>
        <l n="472">But what the old and still-true-spoken God,</l>
        <l n="473">That from the sea breathes oracles abroad,</l>
        <l n="474">Disclosed to me, to thee I'll all impart,</l>
        <l n="475">Nor hide one word from thy sollicitous heart.</l>
        <l n="476">I was in Ægypt, where a mighty time</l>
        <l n="477">The Gods detained me, though my natural clime</l>
        <l n="478">I never so desired, because their homes</l>

        <pb n="87" facs="#149"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="479">I did not greet with perfect hecatombs.</l>
        <l n="480">For they will put men evermore in mind,</l>
        <l n="481">How much their masterly commandments bind.</l>
        <l n="482">There is, besides, a certain island, called</l>
        <l n="483">Pharos, that with the high-wav'd sea is wall'd,</l>
        <l n="484">Just against Ægypt, and so much remote,</l>
        <l n="485">As in a whole day, with a fore-gale smote,</l>
        <l n="486">A hollow ship can sail. And this isle bears</l>
        <l n="487">A port most portly, where sea-passengers</l>
        <l n="488">Put in still for fresh water, and away</l>
        <l n="489">To sea again. Yet here the Gods did stay</l>
        <l n="490">My fleet full twenty days; the winds, that are</l>
        <l n="491">Masters at sea, no prosp'rous puff would spare</l>
        <l n="492">To put us off; and all my victuals here</l>
        <l n="493">Had quite corrupted, as my men's minds were,</l>
        <l n="494">Had not a certain Goddess given regard,</l>
        <l n="495">And pitied me in an estate so hard;</l>
        <l n="496">And 'twas Idothea, honour'd Proteus' seed,</l>
        <l n="497">That old sea-farer. Her mind I made bleed</l>
        <l n="498">With my compassion, when (walk'd all alone,</l>
        <l n="499">From all my soldiers, that were ever gone</l>
        <l n="500">About the isle on fishing with hooks bent;</l>
        <l n="501">Hunger their bellies on her errand sent)</l>
        <l n="502">She came close to me, spake, and thus began:</l>
        <l n="503">Of all men thou art the most foolish man,</l>
        <l n="504">Or slack in business, or stay'st here of choice,</l>
        <l n="505">And dost in all thy suff'rances rejoice,</l>
        <l n="506">That thus long liv'd detain'd here, and no end</l>
        <l n="507">Canst give thy tarriance? Thou dost much offend</l>
        <l n="508">The minds of all thy fellows.' I replied:</l>
        <l n="509">'Whoever thou art of the Deified,</l>
        <l n="510">I must affirm, that no way with my will</l>

        <pb n="88" facs="#150"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="511">I make abode here; but, it seems, some ill</l>
        <l n="512">The Gods, inhabiting broad heaven, sustain</l>
        <l n="513">Against my getting off. Inform me then,</l>
        <l n="514">For Godheads all things know, what God is he</l>
        <l n="515">That stays my passage from the fishy sea?"</l>
        <l n="516">'Stranger,' said she, 'I'll tell thee true: There lives</l>
        <l n="517">An old sea-farer in these seas, that gives</l>
        <l n="518">A true solution of all secrets here,</l>
        <l n="519">Who deathless Proteus is, th' Ægyptian peer,</l>
        <l n="520">Who can the deeps of all the seas exquire,</l>
        <l n="521">Who Neptune's priest is, and, they say, the sire</l>
        <l n="522">That did beget me. Him, if any way</l>
        <l n="523">Thou couldst inveigle, he would clear display</l>
        <l n="524">Thy course from hence, and how far off doth lie</l>
        <l n="525">Thy voyage's whole scope through Neptune's sky.</l>
        <l n="526">Informing thee, O God-preserved, beside,</l>
        <l n="527">If thy desires would so be satisfied,</l>
        <l n="528">Whatever good or ill hath got event,</l>
        <l n="529">In all the time thy long and hard course spent,</l>
        <l n="530">Since thy departure from thy house.' This said;</l>
        <l n="531">Again I answer'd: 'Make the sleights display'd</l>
        <l n="532">Thy father useth, lest his foresight see,</l>
        <l n="533">Or his foreknowledge taking note of me,</l>
        <l n="534">He flies the fixt place of his used abode.</l>
        <l n="535">'Tis hard for man to countermine with God.'</l>
        <l n="536">She straight replied: 'I'll utter truth in all :</l>
        <l n="537">When heaven's supremest height the sun doth skall,<anchor xml:id="n4.537_ref"/></l>
        <l n="538">The old Sea-tell-truth leaves the deeps, and hides</l>
        <l n="539">Amidst a black storm, when the West Wind chides,</l>
        <l n="540">In caves still sleeping. Round about him sleep</l>
        <l n="541">(With short feet swimming forth the foamy deep)</l>

        <note target="#n4.537_ref"><mentioned>Skall</mentioned>—scale.</note>

        <pb n="89" facs="#151"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="542">The sea-calves, lovely Halosydnes call'd,</l>
        <l n="543">From whom a noisome odour is exhaled,</l>
        <l n="544">Got from the whirl-pools, on whose earth they lie.</l>
        <l n="545">Here, when the morn illustrates all the sky,</l>
        <l n="546">I'll guide, and seat thee in the fittest place</l>
        <l n="547">For the performance thou hast now in chace.</l>
        <l n="548">In mean time, reach thy fleet, and choose out three</l>
        <l n="549">Of best exploit, to go as aids to thee.</l>
        <l n="550">But now I'll show thee all the old God's sleights:</l>
        <l n="551">He first will number, and take all the sights</l>
        <l n="552">Of those his guard, that on the shore arrives.</l>
        <l n="553">When having view'd, and told them forth by fives,</l>
        <l n="554">He takes place in their midst, and there doth sleep,</l>
        <l n="555">Like to a shepherd midst his flock of sheep.</l>
        <l n="556">In his first sleep, call up your hardiest cheer,</l>
        <l n="557">Vigour and violence, and hold him there,</l>
        <l n="558">In spite of all his strivings to be gone.</l>
        <l n="559">He then will turn himself to every one</l>
        <l n="560">Of all things that in earth creep and respire,</l>
        <l n="561">In water swim, or shine in heavenly fire.</l>
        <l n="562">Yet still hold you him firm, and much the more</l>
        <l n="563">Press him from passing. But when, as before,</l>
        <l n="564">When sleep first bound his powers, his form ye see,</l>
        <l n="565">Then cease your force, and th' old heroë free,</l>
        <l n="566">And then demand, which heaven-born it may be</l>
        <l n="567">That so afflicts you, hindering your retreat,</l>
        <l n="568">And free sea-passage to your native seat.'</l>
        <l n="569">This said, she div'd into the wavy seas,</l>
        <l n="570">And I my course did to my ships address,</l>
        <l n="571">That on the sands stuck; where arriv'd, we made</l>
        <l n="572">Our supper ready. Then th' ambrosian shade</l>
        <l n="573">Of night fell on us, and to sleep we fell.</l>

        <pb n="90" facs="#152"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="574">Rosy Aurora rose; we rose as well,</l>
        <l n="575">And three of them on whom I most relied,</l>
        <l n="576">For firm at every force, I choosed, and hied</l>
        <l n="577">Straight to the many-river-served seas;</l>
        <l n="578">And all assistance ask'd the Deities.</l>
        <l n="579">Mean time Idothea the sea's broad breast</l>
        <l n="580">Embrac'd, and brought for me, and all my rest,</l>
        <l n="581">Four of the sea-calves' skins but newly flay'd,</l>
        <l n="582">To work a wile which she had fashioned</l>
        <l n="583">Upon her father. Then, within the sand</l>
        <l n="584">A covert digging, when these calves should land,</l>
        <l n="585">She sat expecting. We came close to her;</l>
        <l n="586">She plac'd us orderly, and made us wear</l>
        <l n="587">Each one his calf's skin. But we then must pass</l>
        <l n="588">A huge exploit. The sea-calf's savour was</l>
        <l n="589">So passing sour, they still being bred at seas,</l>
        <l n="590">It much afflicted us; for who can please</l>
        <l n="591">To lie by one of these same sea-bred whales?</l>
        <l n="592">But she preserves us, and to memory calls</l>
        <l n="593">A rare commodity; she fetch'd to us</l>
        <l n="594">Ambrosia, that an air most odorous</l>
        <l n="595">Bears still about it, which she nointed round</l>
        <l n="596">Our either nosthrils, and in it quite drown'd<anchor xml:id="n4.596_ref"/></l>
        <l n="597">The nasty whale-smell. Then the great event</l>
        <l n="598">The whole morn's date, with spirits patient,</l>
        <l n="599">We lay expecting. When bright noon did flame,</l>
        <l n="600">Forth from the sea in shoals the sea-calves came,</l>
        <l n="601">And orderly, at last lay down and slept</l>
        <l n="602">Along the sands. And then th' old Sea-God crept</l>
        <l n="603">From forth the deeps, and found his fat calves there,</l>

        <note target="#n4.596_ref"><mentioned>Nosthrils</mentioned>. The etymological spelling of the word is nos and thirl, a perforation; Anglo-Sax.</note>

        <pb n="91"/>

        <l n="604">Survey'd, and number'd, and came never near</l>
        <l n="605">The craft we used, but told us five for calves.</l>
        <l n="606">His temples then dis-eased with sleep he salves;<anchor xml:id="n4.606_ref"/></l>
        <l n="607">And in rush'd we, with an abhorred cry,</l>
        <l n="608">Cast all our hands about him manfully;</l>
        <l n="609">And then th' old Forger all his forms began :</l>
        <l n="610">First was a lion with a mighty mane,</l>
        <l n="611">Then next a dragon, a pied panther then,</l>
        <l n="612">A vast boar next, and suddenly did strain</l>
        <l n="613">All into water. Last he was a tree,</l>
        <l n="614">Curl'd all at top, and shot up to the sky.</l>
        <l n="615">We, with resolv'd hearts, held him firmly still,</l>
        <l n="616">When th' old one (held too straight for all his skill</l>
        <l n="617">To extricate) gave words, and question'd me:</l>
        <l n="618">'Which of the Gods, O Atreus' son,' said he,</l>
        <l n="619">• Advised and taught thy fortitude this sleight,</l>
        <l n="620">To take and hold me thus in my despite?'</l>
        <l n="621">• What asks thy wish now?" I replied. Thou know'st.</l>
        <l n="622">Why dost thou ask? What wiles are these thou show'st?</l>
        <l n="623">I have within this isle been held for wind</l>
        <l n="624">A wondrous time, and can by no means find</l>
        <l n="625">An end to my retention. It hath spent</l>
        <l n="626">The very heart in me. Give thou then vent</l>
        <l n="627">To doubts thus bound in me, ye Gods know all,</l>
        <l n="628">Which of the Godheads doth so foully fall</l>
        <l n="629">On my addression home, to stay me here,</l>
        <l n="630">Avert me from my way, the fishy clear</l>
        <l n="631">Barr'd to my passage?" He replied: ' Of force,</l>
        <l n="632">If to thy home thou wishest free recourse,</l>
        <l n="633">To Jove, and all the other Deities,</l>
        <l n="634">Thou must exhibit solemn sacrifice;</l>

        <note target="#n4.606_ref"><mentioned>Dis-eased</mentioned>—tired. See infrà, 1087, and Iliad, x. 45.</note>

        <pb n="92" facs="#154"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="635">And then the black sea for thee shall be clear,</l>
        <l n="636">Till thy lov'd country's settled reach. But where</l>
        <l n="637">Ask these rites thy performance? 'Tis a fate</l>
        <l n="638">To thee and thy affairs appropriate,</l>
        <l n="639">That thou shalt never see thy friends, nor tread</l>
        <l n="640">Thy country's earth, nor see inhabited</l>
        <l n="641">Thy so magnificent house, till thou make good</l>
        <l n="642">Thy voyage back to the Ægyptian flood,</l>
        <l n="643">Whose waters fell from Jove, and there hast given</l>
        <l n="644">To Jove, and all Gods housed in ample heaven,</l>
        <l n="645">Devoted hecatombs, and then free ways</l>
        <l n="646">Shall open to thee, clear'd of all delays.'</l>
        <l n="647">This told he; and, methought, he brake my heart,</l>
        <l n="648">In such a long and hard course to divert</l>
        <l n="649">My hope for home, and charge my back retreat</l>
        <l n="650">As far as Ægypt. I made answer yet:</l>
        <l n="651">"Father, thy charge I'll perfect; but before</l>
        <l n="652">Resolve me truly, if their natural shore</l>
        <l n="653">All those Greeks, and their ships, do safe enjoy,</l>
        <l n="654">That Nestor and myself left, when from Troy</l>
        <l n="655">We first raised sail? Or whether any died</l>
        <l n="656">At sea a death unwish'd? Or, satisfied,</l>
        <l n="657">When war was past, by friends embrac'd, in peace</l>
        <l n="658">Resign'd their spirits?" He made answer: " Cease</l>
        <l n="659">To ask so far. It fits thee not to be</l>
        <l n="660">So cunning in thine own calamity.</l>
        <l n="661">Nor seek to learn what learn'd thou shouldst forget.</l>
        <l n="662">Men's knowledges have proper limits set,</l>
        <l n="663">And should not prease into the mind of God.</l>
        <l n="664">But 'twill not long be, as my thoughts abode,<anchor xml:id="n4.664_ref"/></l>
        <l n="665">Before thou buy this curious skill with tears.</l>

        <note target="#n4.664_ref"><mentioned>Abode</mentioned>—prognosticate. A common word.</note>

        <pb n="93" facs="#155"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="666">Many of those, whose states so tempt thine ears,</l>
        <l n="667">Are stoop'd by death, and many left alive,</l>
        <l n="668">One chief of which in strong hold doth survive,</l>
        <l n="669">Amidst the broad sea. Two, in their retreat,</l>
        <l n="670">Are done to death. I list not to repeat</l>
        <l n="671">Who fell at Troy, thyself was there in fight.</l>
        <l n="672">But in return swift Ajax lost the light,<anchor xml:id="n4.672_ref"/></l>
        <l n="673">In his long-oar'd ship. Neptune, yet, awhile</l>
        <l n="674">Saft him unwrack'd, to the Gyræan isle,</l>
        <l n="675">A mighty rock removing from his way.</l>
        <l n="676">And surely he had 'scap'd the fatal day,</l>
        <l n="677">In spite of Pallas, if to that foul deed</l>
        <l n="678">He in her fane did, (when he ravished</l>
        <l n="679">The Trojan prophetess) he had not here<anchor xml:id="n4.679_ref"/></l>
        <l n="680">Adjoin'd an impious boast, that he would bear,</l>
        <l n="681">Despite the Gods, his ship safe through the waves</l>
        <l n="682">Then raised against him. These his impious braves</l>
        <l n="683">When Neptune heard, in his strong hand he took</l>
        <l n="684">His massy trident, and so soundly strook</l>
        <l n="685">The rock Gyræan, that in two it cleft;</l>
        <l n="686">Of which one fragment on the land he left,</l>
        <l n="687">The other fell into the troubled seas,</l>
        <l n="688">At which first rush'd Ajax Oiliades,</l>
        <l n="689">And split his ship, and then himself afloat</l>
        <l n="690">Swum on the rough waves of the world's vast mote,</l>
        <l n="691">Till having drunk a salt cup for his sin,</l>
        <l n="692">There perish'd he. Thy brother yet did win</l>
        <l n="693">The wreath from death, while in the waves they strove,</l>
        <l n="694">Afflicted by the reverend wife of Jove.</l>
        <l n="695">But when the steep mount of the Malian shore</l>
        <l n="696">He seem'd to reach, a most tempestuous blore,</l>

        <note target="#n4.672_ref"><mentioned>Ajax Oïleus</mentioned>.</note>
        <note target="#n4.679_ref"><mentioned>Cassandra</mentioned>.</note>

        <pb n="94" facs="#156"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="697">Far to the fishy world that sighs so sore,</l>
        <l n="698">Straight ravish'd him again as far away,</l>
        <l n="699">As to th' extreme bounds where the Agrians stay,</l>
        <l n="700">Where first Thyestes dwelt, but then his son</l>
        <l n="701">Ægisthus Thyestiades lived. This done,</l>
        <l n="702">When his return untouch'd appear'd again,</l>
        <l n="703">Back turn'd the Gods the wind, and set him then</l>
        <l n="704">Hard by his house. Then, full of joy, he left</l>
        <l n="705">His ship, and close t' his country earth he cleft,</l>
        <l n="706">Kiss'd it, and wept for joy, pour'd tear on tear,</l>
        <l n="707">To set so wishedly his footing there.</l>
        <l n="708">But see, a sentinel that all the year</l>
        <l n="709">Crafty Ægisthus in a watchtower set</l>
        <l n="710">To spy his landing, for reward as great</l>
        <l n="711">As two gold talents, all his powers did call</l>
        <l n="712">To strict remembrance of his charge, and all</l>
        <l n="713">Discharged at first sight, which at first he cast</l>
        <l n="714">On Agamemnon, and with all his haste</l>
        <l n="715">Inform'd Ægisthus. He an instant train</l>
        <l n="716">Laid for his slaughter: Twenty chosen men</l>
        <l n="717">Of his plebeians he in ambush laid;</l>
        <l n="718">His other men he charged to see purvey'd</l>
        <l n="719">A feast; and forth, with horse and chariots graced,</l>
        <l n="720">He rode t' invite him, but in heart embraced</l>
        <l n="721">Horrible welcomes, and to death did bring,</l>
        <l n="722">With treacherous slaughter, the unwary king,</l>
        <l n="723">Received him at a feast, and, like an ox</l>
        <l n="724">Slain at his manger, gave him bits and knocks.</l>
        <l n="725">No one left of Atrides' train, nor one</l>
        <l n="726">Saved to Ægisthus, but himself alone,</l>
        <l n="727">All strew'd together there the bloody court.'</l>
        <l n="728">This said, my soul he sunk with his report,</l>

        <pb n="95" facs="#157"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="729">Flat on the sands I fell, tears spent their store,</l>
        <l n="730">I light abhorr'd, my heart would live no more.</l>
        <l n="731">When dry of tears, and tired of tumbling there,</l>
        <l n="732">Th' old Tell-truth thus my daunted spirits did cheer:</l>
        <l n="733">'No more spend tears nor time, O Atreus' son,</l>
        <l n="734">With ceaseless weeping never wish was won.</l>
        <l n="735">Use uttermost assay to reach thy home,</l>
        <l n="736">And all unwares upon the murderer come,</l>
        <l n="737">For torture, taking him thyself alive;</l>
        <l n="738">Or let Orestes, that should far out-strive</l>
        <l n="739">Thee in fit vengeance, quickly quit the light</l>
        <l n="740">Of such a dark soul, and do thou the rite</l>
        <l n="741">Of burial to him with a funeral feast.'</l>
        <l n="742">With these last words I fortified my breast,</l>
        <l n="743">In which again a generous spring began</l>
        <l n="744">Of fitting comfort, as I was a man;</l>
        <l n="745">But, as a brother, I must ever mourn.</l>
        <l n="746">Yet forth I went, and told him the return</l>
        <l n="747">Of these I knew; but he had named a third,</l>
        <l n="748">Held on the broad sea, still with life inspired,</l>
        <l n="749">Whom I besought to know, though likewise dead,</l>
        <l n="750">And I must mourn alike. He answered:</l>
        <l n="751">'He is Laertes' son; whom I beheld</l>
        <l n="752">In nymph Calypso's palace, who compell'd</l>
        <l n="753">His stay with her, and, since he could not see</l>
        <l n="754">His country earth, he mournm'd incessantly.</l>
        <l n="755">For he had neither ship instruct with oars,</l>
        <l n="756">Nor men to fetch him from those stranger shores.</l>
        <l n="757">Where leave we him, and to thy self descend,</l>
        <l n="758">Whom not in Argos Fate nor Death shall end,</l>
        <l n="759">But the immortal ends of all the earth,</l>
        <l n="760">So ruled by them that order death by birth,</l>

        <pb n="96" facs="#158"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="761">The fields Elysian, Fate to thee will give;</l>
        <l n="762">Where Rhadamanthus rules, and where men live</l>
        <l n="763">A never-troubled life, where snow, nor showers,</l>
        <l n="764">Nor irksome Winter spends his fruitless powers,</l>
        <l n="765">But from the ocean Zephyr still resumes</l>
        <l n="766">A constant breath, that all the fields perfumes.</l>
        <l n="767">Which, since thou marriedst Helen, are thy hire,</l>
        <l n="768">And Jove himself is by her side thy sire.'</l>
        <l n="769">This said; he dived the deepsome watery heaps;</l>
        <l n="770">I and my tried men took us to our ships,</l>
        <l n="771">And worlds of thoughts I varied with my steps.</l>
        <l n="772">Arrived and shipp'd, the silent solemn night</l>
        <l n="773">And sleep bereft us of our visual light.</l>
        <l n="774">At morn, masts, sails, rear'd, we sat, left the shores,</l>
        <l n="775">And beat the foamy ocean with our oars.</l>
        <l n="776">Again then we the Jove-fall'n flood did fetch,</l>
        <l n="777">As far as Ægypt; where we did beseech</l>
        <l n="778">The Gods with hecatombs; whose angers ceast,</l>
        <l n="779">I tomb'd my brother that I might be blest.</l>
        <l n="780">All rites perform'd, all haste I made for home,</l>
        <l n="781">And all the prosp'rous winds about were come,</l>
        <l n="782">I had the passport now of every God,</l>
        <l n="783">And here closed all these labours period.</l>
        <l n="784">Here stay then till th' eleventh or twelfth day's light,</l>
        <l n="785">And I'll dismiss thee well, gifts exquisite</l>
        <l n="786">Preparing for thee, chariot, horses three,</l>
        <l n="787">A cup of curious frame to serve for thee</l>
        <l n="788">To serve th' immortal Gods with sacrifice,</l>
        <l n="789">Mindful of me while all suns light thy skies."</l>
        <l n="790">He answer'd; "Stay me not too long time here,</l>
        <l n="791">Though I could sit attending all the year.</l>

        <pb n="97" facs="#159"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="792">Nor should my house, nor parents, with desire,</l>
        <l n="793">Take my affections from you, so on fire</l>
        <l n="794">With love to hear you are my thoughts; but so</l>
        <l n="795">My Pylian friends I shall afflict with woe,</l>
        <l n="796">Who mourn even this stay. Whatsoever be</l>
        <l n="797">The gifts your grace is to bestow on me,</l>
        <l n="798">Vouchsafe them such as I may bear and save</l>
        <l n="799">For your sake ever. Horse, I list not have,</l>
        <l n="800">To keep in Ithaca, but leave them here,</l>
        <l n="801">To your soil's dainties, where the broad fields bear</l>
        <l n="802">Sweet cypers grass, where men-fed lote doth flow,<anchor xml:id="n4.802_ref"/></l>
        <l n="803">Where wheat-like spelt, and wheat itself, doth grow,</l>
        <l n="804">Where barley, white, and spreading like a tree;</l>
        <l n="805">But Ithaca hath neither ground to be,</l>
        <l n="806">For any length it comprehends, a race</l>
        <l n="807">To try a horse's speed, nor any place</l>
        <l n="808">To make him fat in; fitter far to feed</l>
        <l n="809">A cliff-bred goat, than raise or please a steed.</l>
        <l n="810">Of all isles, Ithaca doth least provide</l>
        <l n="811">Or meads to feed a horse, or ways to ride."</l>
        <l n="812">He, smiling, said: " Of good blood art thou, son.</l>
        <l n="813">What speech, so young! What observation</l>
        <l n="814">Hast thou made of the world! I well am pleased</l>
        <l n="815">To change my gifts to thee, as being confess'd</l>
        <l n="816">Unfit indeed, my store is such I may.</l>
        <l n="817">Of all my house-gifts then, that up I lay</l>
        <l n="818">For treasure there, I will bestow on thee</l>
        <l n="819">The fairest, and of greatest price to me.</l>
        <l n="820">I will bestow on thee a rich carv'd cup,</l>

        <note target="#n4.802_ref"><mentioned>Cypers grass</mentioned>. The cyperus, or galingale. (See shadow. xx1. 333.) Men-fed—on which men feed. The reader will find an interesting paper on the Botany of Homer in the Classical Museum, vol. v. p. 40.</note>

        <pb n="98" facs="#160"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="821">Of silver all, but all the brims wrought up</l>
        <l n="822">With finest gold; it was the only thing</l>
        <l n="823">That the heroical Sidonian king</l>
        <l n="824">Presented to me, when we were to part</l>
        <l n="825">At his receipt of me, and 'twas the art</l>
        <l n="826">Of that great Artist that of heaven is free;<anchor xml:id="n4.826_ref"/></l>
        <l n="827">And yet even this will I bestow on thee."</l>
        <l n="828">This speech thus ended, guests came, and did bring</l>
        <l n="829">Muttons, for presents, to the God-like king,</l>
        <l n="830">And spirit-prompting wine, that strenuous makes.</l>
        <l n="831">Their riband-wreathed wives brought fruit and cakes.</l>
        <l n="832">Thus in this house did these their feast apply;</l>
        <l n="833">And in Ulysses' house activity</l>
        <l n="834">The Wooers practised; tossing of the spear,</l>
        <l n="835">The stone, and hurling; thus delighted, where</l>
        <l n="836">They exercised such insolence before,</l>
        <l n="837">Even in the court that wealthy pavements wore.</l>
        <l n="838">Antinous did still their strifes decide,</l>
        <l n="839">And he that was in person deified</l>
        <l n="840">Eurymachus; both ring-leaders of all,</l>
        <l n="841">For in their virtues they were principal.</l>
        <l n="842">These by Noemon, son to Phronius,</l>
        <l n="843">Were sided now, who made the question thus:</l>
        <l n="844">"Antinous! Does any friend here know,</l>
        <l n="845">When this Telemachus returns, or no,</l>
        <l n="846">From sandy Pylos? He made bold to take</l>
        <l n="847">My ship with him; of which, I now should make</l>
        <l n="848">Fit use myself, and sail in her as far</l>
        <l n="849">As spacious Elis, where of mine there are</l>
        <l n="850">Twelve delicate mares, and under their sides go</l>
        <l n="851">Laborious mules, that yet did never know</l>
        <l n="852">The yoke, nor labour; some of which should bear</l>

        <note target="#n4.826_ref"><mentioned>Vulcan</mentioned>.</note>

        <pb n="99" facs="#161"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="853">The taming now, if I could fetch them there."</l>
        <l n="854">This speech the rest admired, nor dream'd that he<anchor xml:id="n4.854_ref"/></l>
        <l n="855">Neleïan Pylos ever thought to see,</l>
        <l n="856">But was at field about his flocks' survey,</l>
        <l n="857">Or thought his herdsmen held him so away.</l>
        <l n="858">Eupitheus son, Antinous, then replied:</l>
        <l n="859">"When went he, or with what train dignified?</l>
        <l n="860">Of his selected Ithacensian youth?</l>
        <l n="861">Prest men, or bond men, were they? Tell the truth.<anchor xml:id="n4.861_ref"/></l>
        <l n="862">Could he effect this? Let me truly know.</l>
        <l n="863">To gain thy vessel did he violence show,</l>
        <l n="864">And used her 'gainst thy will? or had her free,</l>
        <l n="865">When fitting question he had made with thee?”</l>
        <l n="866">Noemon answer'd: "I did freely give</l>
        <l n="867">My vessel to him. Who deserves to live</l>
        <l n="868">That would do other, when such men as he</l>
        <l n="869">Did in distress ask? He should churlish be</l>
        <l n="870">That would deny him. Of our youth the best</l>
        <l n="871">Amongst the people, to the interest</l>
        <l n="872">His charge did challenge in them, giving way,</l>
        <l n="873">With all the tribute all their powers could pay.</l>
        <l n="874">Their captain, as he took the ship, I knew,</l>
        <l n="875">Who Mentor was, or God. A Deity's shew</l>
        <l n="876">Mask'd in his likeness. But, to think 'twas he,</l>
        <l n="877">I much admire, for I did clearly see,</l>
        <l n="878">But yester-morning, God-like Mentor here;</l>
        <l n="879">Yet th' other evening he took shipping there,</l>
        <l n="880">And went for Pylos." Thus went he for home,</l>
        <l n="881">And left the rest with envy overcome;</l>

        <note target="#n4.854_ref"><mentioned>Admired</mentioned>—were astonished at. <mentioned>He</mentioned>—Telemachus.</note>
        <note target="#n4.861_ref"><mentioned>Prest men</mentioned>—hired men; men for hire ready (prest) to march. See Todd's Johnson.</note>

        <pb n="100"/>

        <l n="882">Who sat, and pastime left. Eupitheus son,</l>
        <l n="883">Sad, and with rage his entrails overrun,</l>
        <l n="884">His eyes like flames, thus interposed his speech :</l>
        <l n="885">"Strange thing! An action of how proud a reach</l>
        <l n="886">Is here committed by Telemachus!</l>
        <l n="887">A boy, a child, and we, a sort of us,<anchor xml:id="n4.887_ref"/></l>
        <l n="888">Vow'd 'gainst his voyage, yet admit it thus!</l>
        <l n="889">With ship and choice youth of our people too!</l>
        <l n="890">But let him on, and all his mischief do,</l>
        <l n="891">Jove shall convert upon himself his powers,</l>
        <l n="892">Before their ill presum'd he brings on ours.</l>
        <l n="893">Provide me then a ship, and twenty men</l>
        <l n="894">To give her manage, that, against again</l>
        <l n="895">He turns for home, on th' Ithacensian seas,</l>
        <l n="896">Or cliffy Samian, I may interprease,<anchor xml:id="n4.896_ref"/></l>
        <l n="897">Way-lay, and take him, and make all his craft</l>
        <l n="898">Sail with his ruin for his father saft."</l>
        <l n="899">This all applauded, and gave charge to do,</l>
        <l n="900">Rose, and to greet Ulysses' house did go.</l>
        <l n="901">But long time past not, ere Penelope</l>
        <l n="902">Had notice of their far-fetch'd treachery.</l>
        <l n="903">Medon the herald told her, who had heard</l>
        <l n="904">Without the hall how they within conferr'd,</l>
        <l n="905">And hasted straight to tell it to the queen,</l>
        <l n="906">Who, from the entry having Medon seen,</l>
        <l n="907">Prevents him thus: "Now herald, what affair</l>
        <l n="908">Intend the famous Wooers, in your repair?</l>
        <l n="909">To tell Ulysses' maids that they must cease</l>
        <l n="910">From doing our work, and their banquets dress?</l>
        <l n="911">I would to heaven, that, leaving wooing me,</l>

        <note target="#n4.887_ref"><mentioned>Sort</mentioned>—number. See Iliad Iv. 460.</note>
        <note target="#n4.896_ref"><mentioned>Interprease</mentioned>—i. e. interpress, interpose.</note>

        <pb n="101" facs="#163"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="912">Nor ever troubling other company,</l>
        <l n="913">Here might the last feast be, and most extreme,</l>
        <l n="914">That ever any shall address for them.</l>
        <l n="915">They never meet but to consent in spoil,</l>
        <l n="916">And reap the free fruits of another's toil.</l>
        <l n="917">O did they never, when they children were,</l>
        <l n="918">What to their fathers was Ulysses, hear?</l>
        <l n="919">Who never did 'gainst any one proceed</l>
        <l n="920">With unjust usage, or in word or deed?</l>
        <l n="921">'Tis yet with other kings another right,</l>
        <l n="922">One to pursue with love, another spite;</l>
        <l n="923">He still yet just, nor would, though might, devour,</l>
        <l n="924">Nor to the worst did ever taste of power.</l>
        <l n="925">But their unrul'd acts show their minds' estate.<anchor xml:id="n4.925_ref"/></l>
        <l n="926">Good turns received once, thanks grow out of date."</l>
        <l n="927">Medon, the learn'd in wisdom, answer'd her:</l>
        <l n="928">" I wish, O queen, that their ingratitudes were</l>
        <l n="929">Their worst ill towards you; but worse by far,</l>
        <l n="930">And much more deadly, their endeavours are,</l>
        <l n="931">Which Jove will fail them in. Telemachus</l>
        <l n="932">Their purpose is, as he returns to us,</l>
        <l n="933">To give their sharp steels in a cruel death;</l>
        <l n="934">Who now is gone to learn, if fame can breathe</l>
        <l n="935">News of his sire, and will the Pylian shore,</l>
        <l n="936">And sacred Sparta, in his search explore."</l>
        <l n="937">This news dissolv'd to her both knees and heart,</l>
        <l n="938">Long silence held her ere one word would part,</l>
        <l n="939">Her eyes stood full of tears, her small soft voice</l>
        <l n="940">All late use lost; that yet at last had choice</l>
        <l n="941">Of wonted words, which briefly thus she used :</l>
        <l n="942">"Why left my son his mother? Why refused</l>

        <note target="#n4.925_ref"><mentioned>Unruled</mentioned>—irregular, not to be ruled.</note>

        <pb n="102" facs="#164"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="943">His wit the solid shore, to try the seas,</l>
        <l n="944">And put in ships the trust of his distress,</l>
        <l n="945">That are at sea to men unbridled horse,</l>
        <l n="946">And run, past rule, their far-engaged course,</l>
        <l n="947">Amidst a moisture past all mean unstaid?</l>
        <l n="948">No need compell'd this. Did he it, afraid</l>
        <l n="949">To live and leave posterity his name?"</l>
        <l n="950">" I know not," he replied, " if th' humour came</l>
        <l n="951">From current of his own instinct, or flow'd</l>
        <l n="952">From others' instigations; but he vow'd</l>
        <l n="953">Attempt to Pylos, or to see descried</l>
        <l n="954">His sire's return, or know what death he died."</l>
        <l n="955">This said, he took him to Ulysses' house</l>
        <l n="956">After the Wooers; the Ulyssean spouse,</l>
        <l n="957">Run through with woes, let Torture seize her mind,</l>
        <l n="958">Nor in her choice of state chairs stood inclined</l>
        <l n="959">To take her seat, but th' abject threshold chose</l>
        <l n="960">Of her fair chamber for her loath'd repose,</l>
        <l n="961">And mournm'd most wretch-like. Round about her fell</l>
        <l n="962">Her handmaids, join'd in a continuate yell.</l>
        <l n="963">From every corner of the palace, all</l>
        <l n="964">Of all degrees tuned to her comfort's fall</l>
        <l n="965">Their own dejections; to whom her complaint</l>
        <l n="966">She thus enforc'd: "The Gods, beyond constraint</l>
        <l n="967">Of any measure, urge these tears on me;</l>
        <l n="968">Nor was there ever dame of my degree</l>
        <l n="969">So past degree grieved. First, a lord so good,</l>
        <l n="970">That had such hardy spirits in his blood,</l>
        <l n="971">That all the virtues was adorn'd withal,</l>
        <l n="972">That all the Greeks did their superior call,</l>
        <l n="973">To part with thus, and lose! And now a son,</l>
        <l n="974">So worthily belov'd, a course to run</l>

        <pb n="103" facs="#165"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="975">Beyond my knowledge; whom rude tempests have</l>
        <l n="976">Made far from home his most inglorious grave!</l>
        <l n="977">Unhappy wenches, that no one of all<anchor xml:id="n4.977_ref"/></l>
        <l n="978">Though in the reach of every one must fall</l>
        <l n="979">His taking ship) sustain'd the careful mind,</l>
        <l n="980">To call me from my bed, who this design'd</l>
        <l n="981">And most vow'd course in him had either stay'd,</l>
        <l n="982">How much soever hasted, or dead laid</l>
        <l n="983">He should have left me. Many a man I have,</l>
        <l n="984">That would have call'd old Dolius my slave,</l>
        <l n="985">(That keeps my orchard, whom my father gave</l>
        <l n="986">At my departure) to have run, and told</l>
        <l n="987">Laertes this; to try if he could hold</l>
        <l n="988">From running through the people, and from tears,</l>
        <l n="989">In telling them of these vow'd murderers;</l>
        <l n="990">That both divine Ulysses' hope, and his,</l>
        <l n="991">Resolv'd to end in their conspiracies."</l>
        <l n="992">His nurse then, Euryclea, made reply:</l>
        <l n="993">" Dear sovereign, let me with your own hands die,</l>
        <l n="994">Or cast me off here, I'll not keep from thee</l>
        <l n="995">One word of what I know. He trusted me</l>
        <l n="996">With all his purpose, and I gave him all</l>
        <l n="997">The bread and wine for which he pleased to call.</l>
        <l n="998">But then a mighty oath he made me swear,</l>
        <l n="999">Not to report it to your royal ear</l>
        <l n="1000">Before the twelfth day either should appear,</l>
        <l n="1001">Or you should ask me when you heard him gone.</l>
        <l n="1002">Impair not then your beauties with your moan,</l>
        <l n="1003">But wash, and put untear-stain'd garments on,</l>
        <l n="1004">Ascend your chamber with your ladies here,</l>

        <note target="#n4.977_ref"><mentioned>Wenches</mentioned>—young women. Though now degenerated, the word was formerly used in a good sense. See Iliad xvI. 78.</note>

        <pb n="104" facs="#166"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="1005">And pray the seed of goat-nurs'd Jupiter,</l>
        <l n="1006">Divine Athenia, to preserve your son,</l>
        <l n="1007">And she will save him from confusion.</l>
        <l n="1008">Th' old king, to whom your hopes stand so inclin'd</l>
        <l n="1009">For his grave counsels, you perhaps may find</l>
        <l n="1010">Unfit affected, for his age's sake.</l>
        <l n="1011">But heaven-kings wax not old, and therefore make</l>
        <l n="1012">Fit prayers to them; for my thoughts never will</l>
        <l n="1013">Believe the heavenly Powers conceit so ill</l>
        <l n="1014">The seed of righteous Arcesiades,</l>
        <l n="1015">To end it utterly, but still will please</l>
        <l n="1016">In some place evermore some one of them</l>
        <l n="1017">To save, and deck him with a diadem,</l>
        <l n="1018">Give him possession of erected tow'rs,</l>
        <l n="1019">And far-stretch'd fields, crown'd all of fruits and flow'rs."</l>
        <l n="1020">This eas'd her heart, and dried her humorous eyes,<anchor xml:id="n4.1020_ref"/></l>
        <l n="1021">When having wash'd, and weeds of sacrifice</l>
        <l n="1022">Pure, and unstain'd with her distrustful tears,</l>
        <l n="1023">Put on, with all her women-ministers</l>
        <l n="1024">Up to a chamber of most height she rose,</l>
        <l n="1025">And cakes of salt and barley did impose</l>
        <l n="1026">Within a wicker basket; all which broke</l>
        <l n="1027">In decent order, thus she did invoke :</l>
        <l n="1028">"Great Virgin of the goat-preserved God,</l>
        <l n="1029">If ever the inhabited abode</l>
        <l n="1030">Of wise Ulysses held the fatted thighs</l>
        <l n="1031">Of sheep and oxen, made thy sacrifice</l>
        <l n="1032">By his devotion, hear me, nor forget</l>
        <l n="1033">His pious services, but safe see set</l>
        <l n="1034">His dear son on these shores, and banish hence</l>
        <l n="1035">These Wooers past all mean in insolence."</l>

        <note target="#n4.1020_ref"><mentioned>Humorous</mentioned>—moist (Lat.) See Iliad xxx. 186.</note>

        <pb n="105" facs="#167"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="1036">This said, she shriek'd, and Pallas heard her prayer.</l>
        <l n="1037">The Wooers broke with tumult all the air</l>
        <l n="1038">About the shady house; and one of them,</l>
        <l n="1039">Whose pride his youth had made the more extreme,</l>
        <l n="1040">Said: "Now the many-wooer-honour'd queen</l>
        <l n="1041">Will surely satiate her delayful spleen,</l>
        <l n="1042">And one of us in instant nuptials take.</l>
        <l n="1043">Poor dame, she dreams not, what design we make</l>
        <l n="1044">Upon the life and slaughter of her son."</l>
        <l n="1045">So said he; but so said was not so done;</l>
        <l n="1046">Whose arrogant spirit in a vaunt so vain</l>
        <l n="1047">Antinous chid, and said: "For shame, contain</l>
        <l n="1048">These braving speeches. Who can tell who hears?</l>
        <l n="1049">Are we not now in reach of others' ears?</l>
        <l n="1050">If our intentions please us, let us call</l>
        <l n="1051">Our spirits up to them, and let speeches fall.</l>
        <l n="1052">By watchful danger men must silent go.</l>
        <l n="1053">What we resolve on, let's not say, but do."</l>
        <l n="1054">This said, he choos'd out twenty men, that bore</l>
        <l n="1055">Best reckoning with him, and to ship and shore</l>
        <l n="1056">All hasted, reach'd the ship, launch'd, rais'd the mast,</l>
        <l n="1057">Put sails in, and with leather loops made fast</l>
        <l n="1058">The oars; sails hoisted, arms their men did bring,</l>
        <l n="1059">All giving speed and form to everything.</l>
        <l n="1060">Then to the high deeps their rigg'd vessel driven,</l>
        <l n="1061">They supp'd, expecting the approaching even.<anchor xml:id="n4.1061_ref"/></l>
        <l n="1062">Mean space, Penelope her chamber kept</l>
        <l n="1063">And bed, and neither eat, nor drank, nor slept,</l>
        <l n="1064">Her strong thoughts wrought so on her blameless son,</l>
        <l n="1065">Still in contention, if he should be done</l>
        <l n="1066">To death, or 'scape the impious Wooers' design.</l>

        <note target="#n4.1061_ref"><mentioned>Expecting</mentioned>—(Latin) awaiting.</note>

        <pb n="106" facs="#168"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="1067">Look how a lion, whom men-troops combine</l>
        <l n="1068">To hunt, and close him in a crafty ring,</l>
        <l n="1069">Much varied thought conceives, and fear doth sting</l>
        <l n="1070">For urgent danger; so fared she, till sleep,</l>
        <l n="1071">All juncture of her joints and nerves did steep</l>
        <l n="1072">In his dissolving humour. When, at rest,</l>
        <l n="1073">Pallas her favours varied, and addressed</l>
        <l n="1074">An idol, that Iphthima did present<anchor xml:id="n4.1074_ref"/></l>
        <l n="1075">In structure of her every lineament,<anchor xml:id="n4.1075_ref"/></l>
        <l n="1076">Great-soul'd Icarius' daughter, whom for spouse</l>
        <l n="1077">Eumelus took, that kept in Pheris' house.<anchor xml:id="n4.1077_ref"/></l>
        <l n="1078">This to divine Ulysses' house she sent,</l>
        <l n="1079">To try her best mean how she might content</l>
        <l n="1080">Mournful Penelope, and make relent</l>
        <l n="1081">The strict addiction in her to deplore.</l>
        <l n="1082">This idol, like a worm, that less or more<anchor xml:id="n4.1082_ref"/></l>
        <l n="1083">Contracts or strains her, did itself convey,</l>
        <l n="1084">Beyond the wards or windings of the key,</l>
        <l n="1085">Into the chamber, and, above her head</l>
        <l n="1086">Her seat assuming, thus she comforted</l>
        <l n="1087">Distress'd Penelope : "Doth sleep thus seize</l>
        <l n="1088">Thy powers, affected with so much dis-ease?<anchor xml:id="n4.1088_ref"/></l>
        <l n="1089">The Gods, that nothing troubles, will not see</l>
        <l n="1090">Thy tears nor griefs, in any least degree,</l>
        <l n="1091">Sustain'd with cause, for they will guard thy son</l>
        <l n="1092">Safe to his wish'd and native mansion,</l>
        <l n="1093">Since he is no offender of their states,</l>

        <note target="#n4.1074_ref"><mentioned>Idol</mentioned>—image, figure, εἴδωλον. See Iliad xxi. 94.</note>
        <note target="#n4.1075_ref">Δέμας, membrorum structura.—CHAPMAN.</note>
        <note target="#n4.1077_ref"><mentioned>Kept</mentioned>—dwelt. A common use in Shakespeare and his contemporaries: and still a provincialism.</note>
        <note target="#n4.1082_ref">Παρὰ κληῖδος ἱμάντα. ῾Ιμὰς, affectus curculionis significat quod longior et gracilior evaserit.—CHAPMAN.</note>
        <note target="#n4.1088_ref"><mentioned>Disease</mentioned>—unrest. See suprà, 605.</note>

        <pb n="107" facs="#169"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="1094">And they to such are firmer than their fates."</l>
        <l n="1095">The wise Penelope receiv'd her thus,</l>
        <l n="1096">Bound with a slumber most delicious,</l>
        <l n="1097">And in the port of dreams: "O sister, why</l>
        <l n="1098">Repair you hither, since so far off lie</l>
        <l n="1099">Your house and household? You were never here</l>
        <l n="1100">Before this hour, and would you now give cheer</l>
        <l n="1101">To my so many woes and miseries,</l>
        <l n="1102">Affecting fitly all the faculties</l>
        <l n="1103">My soul and mind hold, having lost before</l>
        <l n="1104">A husband, that of all the virtues bore</l>
        <l n="1105">The palm amongst the Greeks, and whose renown</l>
        <l n="1106">So ample was that Fame the sound hath blown</l>
        <l n="1107">Through Greece and Argos to her very heart?</l>
        <l n="1108">And now again, a son, that did convert</l>
        <l n="1109">My whole powers to his love, by ship is gone;</l>
        <l n="1110">A tender plant, that yet was never grown</l>
        <l n="1111">To labour's taste, nor the commerce of men;</l>
        <l n="1112">For whom more than my husband I complain,</l>
        <l n="1113">And lest he should at any suff'rance touch</l>
        <l n="1114">Or in the sea, or by the men so much</l>
        <l n="1115">Estrang'd to him that must his consorts be)</l>
        <l n="1116">Fear and chill tremblings shake each joint of me.</l>
        <l n="1117">Besides, his danger sets on foes profess'd</l>
        <l n="1118">To way-lay his return, that have address'd</l>
        <l n="1119">Plots for his death." The scarce-discerned Dream,</l>
        <l n="1120">Said: "Be of comfort, nor fears so extreme</l>
        <l n="1121">Let thus dismay thee; thou hast such a mate</l>
        <l n="1122">Attending thee, as some at any rate</l>
        <l n="1123">Would wish to purchase, for her power is great;</l>
        <l n="1124">Minerva pities thy delights' defeat,</l>
        <l n="1125">Whose grace hath sent me to foretell thee these."</l>

        <pb n="108" facs="#170"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FOURTH BOOK.</fw>

        <l n="1126">" If thou," said she, " be of the Goddesses,</l>
        <l n="1127">And heardst her tell thee these, thou mayst as well</l>
        <l n="1128">From her tell all things else. Deign then to tell,</l>
        <l n="1129">If yet the man to all misfortunes born, shadow</l>
        <l n="1130">My husband, lives, and sees the sun adorn</l>
        <l n="1131">The darksome earth, or hides his wretched head</l>
        <l n="1132">In Pluto's house, and lives amongst the dead?"</l>
        <l n="1133">" I will not," she replied, " my breath exhale</l>
        <l n="1134">In one continued and perpetual tale,</l>
        <l n="1135">Lives he or dies he. 'Tis a filthy use,</l>
        <l n="1136">To be in vain and idle speech profuse."</l>
        <l n="1137">This said, she, through the key-hole of the door,</l>
        <l n="1138">Vanish'd again into the open blore.<anchor xml:id="n4.1138_ref"/></l>
        <l n="1139">Icarius' daughter started from her sleep,</l>
        <l n="1140">And Joy's fresh humour her lov'd breast did steep,</l>
        <l n="1141">When now so clear, in that first watch of night,</l>
        <l n="1142">She saw the seen Dream vanish from her sight.</l>
        <l n="1143">The Wooers' ship the sea's moist waves did ply,</l>
        <l n="1144">And thought the prince a haughty death should die.</l>
        <l n="1145">There lies a certain island in the sea,</l>
        <l n="1146">Twixt rocky Samos and rough Ithaca,</l>
        <l n="1147">That cliffy is itself, and nothing great,</l>
        <l n="1148">Yet holds convenient havens that two ways let</l>
        <l n="1149">Ships in and out, call'd Asteris; and there</l>
        <l n="1150">The Wooers hoped to make their massacre.</l>

        <note target="#n4.1138_ref"><mentioned>Blore</mentioned>—is generally used for a blast, or gale of wind, (see shadow. 11. 122,) but here would seem simply the air.</note>
  </div>
  
<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="5">
  <pb n="109" facs="#171"/>
  <head rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</head>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="1">
    <head rend="center">THE ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">A SECOND Court on Jove attends;</l>
    <l n="2">Who Hermes to Calypso sends,</l>
    <l n="3">Commanding her to clear the ways</l>
    <l n="4">Ulysses sought; and she obeys.</l>
    <l n="5">When Neptune saw Ulysses free,</l>
    <l n="6">And so in safety plough the sea,</l>
    <l n="7">Enraged, he ruffles up the waves,</l>
    <l n="8">And splits his ship. Leucothea saves</l>
    <l n="9">His person yet, as being a Dame</l>
    <l n="10">Whose Godhead govern'd in the frame</l>
    <l n="11">Of those seas' tempers. But the mean,</l>
    <l n="12">By which she curbs dread Neptune's spleen,</l>
    <l n="13">Is made a jewel, which she takes</l>
    <l n="14">From off her head, and that she makes</l>
    <l n="15">Ulysses on his bosom wear,</l>
    <l n="16">About his neck, she ties it there,</l>
    <l n="17">And, when he is with waves beset,</l>
    <l n="18">Bids wear it as an amulet,</l>
    <l n="19">Commanding him, that not before</l>
    <l n="20">He touch'd upon Phæacia's shore,</l>
    <l n="21">He should not part with it, but then</l>
    <l n="22">Return it to the sea again,</l>
    <l n="23">And cast it from him. He performs;</l>
    <l n="24">Yet, after this, bides bitter storms,</l>
    <l n="25">And in the rocks sees death engraved,</l>
    <l n="26">But on Phæacia's shore is saved.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="2">
    <head rend="center">ANOTHER ARGUMENT.</head>
    <l n="1">E. Ulysses builds</l>
    <l n="2">A ship; and gains</l>
    <l n="3">The glassy fields;</l>
    <l n="4">Pays Neptune pains.</l>
  </div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="text">
    <l n="1"><hi rend="dropcap">U</hi>RORA rose from high-born Tithon's bed,</l>
    <l n="2">That men and Gods might be illustrated,</l>
    <l n="3">And then the Deities sat. Imperial Jove,</l>
    <l n="4">That makes the horrid murmur beat above,</l>
    <l n="5">Took place past all, whose height for ever springs,</l>
    <l n="6">And from whom flows th' eternal power of things.</l>
    <l n="7">Then Pallas, mindful of Ulysses, told</l>
    <l n="8">The many cares that in Calypso's hold</l>
    <l n="9">He still sustain'd, when he had felt before</l>
    <l n="10">So much affliction, and such dangers more.</l>
    <l n="11">" O Father," said she, " and ye Ever-blest,</l>
    <l n="12">Give never king hereafter interest</l>
    <l n="13">In any aid of yours, by serving you,</l>
    <l n="14">By being gentle, human, just, but grow</l>
    <l n="15">Rude, and for ever scornful of your rights,</l>
    <l n="16">All justice ordering by their appetites,</l>
    <l n="17">Since he, that ruled as it in right behoved,</l>
    <l n="18">That all his subjects as his children loved,</l>
    <l n="19">Finds you so thoughtless of him and his birth.</l>
    <l n="20">Thus men begin to say, ye rule in earth,</l>
    <l n="21">And grudge at what ye let him undergo,</l>
    <l n="22">Who yet the least part of his suff'rance know:</l>
    <l n="23">Thrall'd in an island, shipwrack'd in his tears,</l>
    <l n="24">And, in the fancies that Calypso bears,</l>
    <l n="25">Bound from his birthright, all his shipping gone,</l>
    <l n="26">And of his soldiers not retaining one.</l>
    <l n="27">And now his most-lov'd son's life doth inflame</l>
    <l n="28">Their slaught'rous envies; since his father's fame</l>
    <l n="29">He puts in pursuit, and is gone as far</l>
    <l n="30">As sacred Pylos, and the singular</l>

    <pb n="111" facs="#173"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="31">Dame-breeding Sparta." This, with this reply,</l>
    <l n="32">The Cloud-assembler answer'd: "What words fly</l>
    <l n="33">Thine own remembrance, daughter? Hast not thou</l>
    <l n="34">The counsel given thyself, that told thee how</l>
    <l n="35">Ulysses shall with his return address</l>
    <l n="36">His Wooers wrongs? And, for the safe access</l>
    <l n="37">His son shall make to his innative port,</l>
    <l n="38">Do thou direct it, in as curious sort</l>
    <l n="39">As thy wit serves thee; it obeys thy powers;</l>
    <l n="40">And in their ship return the speedless Wooers."</l>
    <l n="41">Then turn'd he to his issue Mercury,</l>
    <l n="42">And said: "Thou hast made good our ambassy</l>
    <l n="43">To th' other Statists, to the Nymph then now,</l>
    <l n="44">On whose fair head a tuft of gold doth grow,</l>
    <l n="45">Bear our true-spoken counsel, for retreat</l>
    <l n="46">Of patient Ulysses; who shall get</l>
    <l n="47">No aid from us, nor any mortal man,</l>
    <l n="48">But in a patch'd-up skiff (built as he can,<anchor xml:id="n5.48_ref"/></l>
    <l n="49">And suffering woes enough) the twentieth day</l>
    <l n="50">At fruitful Scheria let him breathe his way,</l>
    <l n="51">With the Phæacians, that half Deities live,</l>
    <l n="52">Who like a God will honour him, and give</l>
    <l n="53">His wisdom clothes, and ship, and brass, and gold,</l>
    <l n="54">More than for gain of Troy he ever told;</l>
    <l n="55">Where, at the whole division of the prey,</l>
    <l n="56">If he a saver were, or got away</l>
    <l n="57">Without a wound, if he should grudge, 'twas well.</l>
    <l n="58">But th' end shall crown all; therefore Fate will deal</l>
    <l n="59">So well with him, to let him land, and see</l>
    <l n="60">His native earth, friends, house, and family."</l>

    <note target="#n5.48_ref">Ἐπὶ σχεδίης πολυδέσμου, in rate multis vinculis ligatus.—CHAPMAN.</note>

    <pb n="112" facs="#174"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="61">Thus charged he; nor Argicides denied,</l>
    <l n="62">But to his feet his fair wing'd shoes he tied,</l>
    <l n="63">Ambrosian, golden, that in his command</l>
    <l n="64">Put either sea, or the unmeasured land,</l>
    <l n="65">With pace as speedy as a puft of wind.</l>
    <l n="66">Then up his rod went, with which he declined</l>
    <l n="67">The eyes of any waker, when he pleased,</l>
    <l n="68">And any sleeper, when he wish'd, diseased.<anchor xml:id="n5.68_ref"/></l>
    <l n="69">This took; he stoop'd Pieria, and thence</l>
    <l n="70">Glid through the air, and Neptune's confluence</l>
    <l n="71">Kiss'd as he flew, and check'd the waves as light</l>
    <l n="72">As any sea-mew in her fishing flight,</l>
    <l n="73">Her thick wings sousing in the savory seas.</l>
    <l n="74">Like her, he pass'd a world of wilderness;</l>
    <l n="75">But when the far-off isle he touch'd, he went</l>
    <l n="76">Up from the blue sea to the continent,</l>
    <l n="77">And reach'd the ample cavern of the Queen,</l>
    <l n="78">Whom he within found, without seldom seen.</l>
    <l n="79">A sun-like fire upon the hearth did flame,</l>
    <l n="80">The matter precious, and divine the frame,</l>
    <l n="81">Of cedar cleft and incense was the pile,</l>
    <l n="82">That breathed an odour round about the isle.</l>
    <l n="83">Herself was seated in an inner room,</l>
    <l n="84">Whom sweetly sing he heard, and at her loom,</l>
    <l n="85">About a curious web, whose yarn she threw</l>
    <l n="86">In with a golden shittle. A grove grew</l>
    <l n="87">In endless spring about her cavern round,</l>
    <l n="88">With odorous cypress, pines, and poplars, crown'd,</l>
    <l n="89">Where hawks, sea-owls, and long-tongued bittours bred,<anchor xml:id="n5.89_ref"/></l>
    <l n="90">And other birds their shady pinions spread;</l>

    <note target="#n5.68_ref"><mentioned>Diseased</mentioned>—aroused. See Bk. 1v.</note>
    <note target="#n5.89_ref"><mentioned>Bittours</mentioned>—bitterns.</note>

    <pb n="113" facs="#175"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="91">All fowls maritimal; none roosted there,</l>
    <l n="92">But those whose labours in the waters were.</l>
    <l n="93">A vine did all the hollow cave embrace,</l>
    <l n="94">Still green, yet still ripe bunches gave it grace.</l>
    <l n="95">Four fountains, one against another, pour'd</l>
    <l n="96">Their silver streams; and meadows all enflower'd</l>
    <l n="97">With sweet balm-gentle, and blue violets hid,</l>
    <l n="98">That deck'd the soft breasts of each fragrant mead.</l>
    <l n="99">Should any one, though he immortal were,</l>
    <l n="100">Arrive and see the sacred objects there,</l>
    <l n="101">He would admire them, and be over-joy'd;</l>
    <l n="102">And so stood Hermes' ravish'd powers employed.</l>
    <l n="103">But having all admired, he enter'd on</l>
    <l n="104">The ample cave, nor could be seen unknown</l>
    <l n="105">Of great Calypso (for all Deities are</l>
    <l n="106">Prompt in each other's knowledge, though so far</l>
    <l n="107">Sever'd in dwellings) but he could not see</l>
    <l n="108">Ulysses there within; without was he</l>
    <l n="109">Set sad ashore, where 'twas his use to view</l>
    <l n="110">Th' unquiet sea, sigh'd, wept, and empty drew</l>
    <l n="111">His heart of comfort. Placed here in her throne,</l>
    <l n="112">That beams cast up to admiration,</l>
    <l n="113">Divine Calypso question'd Hermes thus :</l>
    <l n="114">" For what cause, dear, and much-esteem'd by us,</l>
    <l n="115">Thou golden-rod-adorned Mercury,</l>
    <l n="116">Arriv'st thou here? Thou hast not used t' apply</l>
    <l n="117">Thy passage this way. Say, whatever be</l>
    <l n="118">Thy heart's desire, my mind commands it thee,</l>
    <l n="119">If in my means it lie, or power of fact.</l>
    <l n="120">But first, what hospitable rights exact,</l>
    <l n="121">Come yet more near, and take." This said, she set</l>
    <l n="122">A table forth, and furnish'd it with meat,</l>

    <pb n="114" facs="#176"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="123">Such as the Gods taste; and serv'd in with it</l>
    <l n="124">Vermilion nectar. When with banquet fit</l>
    <l n="125">He had confirm'd his spirits, he thus express'd</l>
    <l n="126">His cause of coming: "Thou hast made request,</l>
    <l n="127">Goddess of Goddesses, to understand</l>
    <l n="128">My cause of touch here; which thou shalt command,</l>
    <l n="129">And know with truth: Jove caused my course to thee</l>
    <l n="130">Against my will, for who would willingly</l>
    <l n="131">Lackey along so vast a lake of brine,<anchor xml:id="n5.131_ref"/></l>
    <l n="132">Near to no city that the Powers divine</l>
    <l n="133">Receives with solemn rites and hecatombs?</l>
    <l n="134">But Jove's will ever all law overcomes,</l>
    <l n="135">No other God can cross or make it void;</l>
    <l n="136">And he affirms, that one the most annoy'd</l>
    <l n="137">With woes and toils of all those men that fought</l>
    <l n="138">For Priam's city, and to end hath brought</l>
    <l n="139">Nine years in the contention, is with thee.</l>
    <l n="140">For in the tenth year, when roy victory<anchor xml:id="n5.140_ref"/></l>
    <l n="141">Was won to give the Greeks the spoil of Troy,</l>
    <l n="141">Return they did profess, but not enjoy,</l>
    <l n="142">Since Pallas they incens'd, and she the waves</l>
    <l n="143">By all the winds' power, that blew ope their graves.</l>
    <l n="144">And there they rested. Only this poor one</l>
    <l n="145">This coast both winds and waves have cast upon;</l>
    <l n="146">Whom now forthwith he wills thee to dismiss,</l>
    <l n="147">Affirming that th' unaltered Destinies<anchor xml:id="n5.147_ref"/></l>
    <l n="148">Not only have decreed he shall not die</l>

    <note target="#n5.131_ref"><mentioned>Lackey</mentioned>—go on foot, be a footman. The word is common, and may be found even in Milton, and Dryden. Teut. lacken, to run.</note>
    <note target="#n5.140_ref"><mentioned>Roy</mentioned>—royal. I do not remember to have met with the word thus used. Roy for king was not uncommon. See NARES.</note>
    <note target="#n5.147_ref"><mentioned>Unaltered</mentioned>—unalterable.</note>

    <pb n="115" facs="#177"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="149">Apart his friends, but of necessity</l>
    <l n="150">Enjoy their sights before those fatal hours,</l>
    <l n="151">His country earth reach, and erected towers."</l>
    <l n="152">This struck a love-check'd horror through her powers,</l>
    <l n="153">When, naming him, she this reply did give :</l>
    <l n="154">"Insatiate are ye Gods, past all that live,</l>
    <l n="155">In all things you affect; which still converts</l>
    <l n="156">Your powers to envies. It afflicts your hearts,</l>
    <l n="157">That any Goddess should, as you obtain</l>
    <l n="158">The use of earthly dames, enjoy the men,</l>
    <l n="159">And most in open marriage. So ye far'd,</l>
    <l n="160">When the delicious-finger'd Morning shar'd</l>
    <l n="161">Orion's bed; you easy-living States</l>
    <l n="162">Could never satisfy your emulous hates,</l>
    <l n="163">Till in Ortygia the precise-liv'd Dame,</l>
    <l n="164">Gold-throned Diana, on him rudely came,</l>
    <l n="165">And with her swift shafts slew him. And such pains,</l>
    <l n="166">When rich-hair'd Ceres pleas'd to give the reins</l>
    <l n="167">To her affections, and the grace did yield</l>
    <l n="168">Of love and bed amidst a three-cropp'd field,</l>
    <l n="169">To her Iasion, he paid angry Jove,</l>
    <l n="170">Who lost no long time notice of their love,</l>
    <l n="171">But with a glowing lightning was his death.</l>
    <l n="172">And now your envies labour underneath</l>
    <l n="173">A mortal's choice of mine; whose life I took</l>
    <l n="174">To liberal safety, when his ship Jove strook,</l>
    <l n="175">With red-hot flashes, piece-meal in the seas,</l>
    <l n="176">And all his friends and soldiers succourless</l>
    <l n="177">Perish'd but he. Him, cast upon this coast</l>
    <l n="178">With blasts and billows, I, in life given lost,</l>
    <l n="179">Preserv'd alone, lov'd, nourish'd, and did vow</l>
    <l n="180">To make him deathless, and yet never grow</l>

    <pb n="116" facs="#178"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="181">Crooked, or worn with age, his whole life long.</l>
    <l n="182">But since no reason may be made so strong</l>
    <l n="183">To strive with Jove's will, or to make it vain,</l>
    <l n="184">No not if all the other Gods should strain</l>
    <l n="185">Their powers against it, let his will be law,</l>
    <l n="186">So he afford him fit means to withdraw,</l>
    <l n="187">As he commands him, to the raging main.</l>
    <l n="188">But means from me he never shall obtain,</l>
    <l n="189">For my means yield nor men, nor ship, nor oars,</l>
    <l n="190">To set him off from my so envied shores.</l>
    <l n="191">But if my counsel and good will can aid</l>
    <l n="192">His safe pass home, my best shall be assay'd."</l>
    <l n="193">"Vouchsafe it so," said heaven's ambassador,</l>
    <l n="194">"And deign it quickly. By all means abhor</l>
    <l n="195">T' incense Jove's wrath against thee, that with grace</l>
    <l n="196">He may hereafter all thy wish embrace."</l>
    <l n="197">Thus took the Argus-killing God his wings.</l>
    <l n="198">And since the reverend Nymph these awful things</l>
    <l n="199">Receiv'd from Jove, she to Ulysses went;</l>
    <l n="200">Whom she ashore found, drown'd in discontent,</l>
    <l n="201">His eyes kept never dry he did so mourn,</l>
    <l n="202">And waste his dear age for his wish'd return;</l>
    <l n="203">Which still without the cause he used to do,</l>
    <l n="204">Because he could not please the Goddess so.</l>
    <l n="205">At night yet, forc'd, together took their rest,</l>
    <l n="206">The willing Goddess and th' unwilling Guest;</l>
    <l n="207">But he all day in rocks, and on the shore,</l>
    <l n="208">The vex'd sea view'd, and did his fate deplore.</l>
    <l n="209">Him, now, the Goddess coming near bespake:</l>
    <l n="210">"Unhappy man, no more discomfort take</l>
    <l n="211">For my constraint of thee, nor waste thine age,</l>
    <l n="212">I now will passing freely disengage</l>

    <pb n="117" facs="#179"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="213">Thy irksome stay here. Come then, fell thee wood,</l>
    <l n="214">And build a ship, to save thee from the flood.</l>
    <l n="215">I'll furnish thee with fresh wave, bread, and wine</l>
    <l n="216">Ruddy and sweet, that will the piner pine,<anchor xml:id="n5.217_ref"/></l>
    <l n="217">Put garments on thee, give thee winds foreright,</l>
    <l n="218">That every way thy home-bent appetite</l>
    <l n="219">May safe attain to it; if so it please</l>
    <l n="220">At all parts all the heaven-housed Deities,</l>
    <l n="221">That more in power are, more in skill, than I,</l>
    <l n="222">And more can judge what fits humanity."</l>
    <l n="223">He stood amaz'd at this strange change in her,</l>
    <l n="224">And said: "O Goddess! Thy intents prefer</l>
    <l n="225">Some other project than my parting hence,</l>
    <l n="226">Commanding things of too high consequence</l>
    <l n="227">For my performance, that myself should build</l>
    <l n="228">A ship of power, my home-assays to shield</l>
    <l n="229">Against the great sea of such dread to pass;</l>
    <l n="230">Which not the best built ship that ever was</l>
    <l n="231">Will pass exulting, when such winds, as Jove</l>
    <l n="232">Can thunder up, their trims and tacklings prove.</l>
    <l n="233">But could I build one, I would ne'er aboard,</l>
    <l n="234">Thy will opposed, nor, won, without thy word,</l>
    <l n="235">Given in the great oath of the Gods to me,</l>
    <l n="236">Not to beguile me in the least degree."</l>
    <l n="237">The Goddess smiled, held hard his hand, and said:</l>
    <l n="238">"O y' are a shrewd one, and so habited</l>
    <l n="239">In taking heed thou know'st not what it is</l>
    <l n="240">To be unwary, nor use words amiss.</l>
    <l n="241">How hast thou charm'd me, were I ne'er so sly!</l>
    <l n="242">Let earth know then, and heaven, so broad, so high,</l>
    <l n="243">And th' under-sunk waves of th' infernal stream,</l>

    <note target="#n5.217_ref"><mentioned>The piner</mentioned>—Hunger.—CHAPMAN.</note>

    <pb n="118" facs="#180"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="244">(Which is an oath, as terribly supreme,</l>
    <l n="245">As any God swears) that I had no thought</l>
    <l n="246">But stood with what I spake, nor would have wrought,</l>
    <l n="247">Nor counsell'd, any act against thy good;</l>
    <l n="248">But ever diligently weigh'd, and stood</l>
    <l n="249">On those points in persuading thee, that I</l>
    <l n="250">Would use myself in such extremity.</l>
    <l n="251">For my mind simple is, and innocent,</l>
    <l n="252">Not given by cruel sleights to circumvent,</l>
    <l n="253">Nor bear I in my breast a heart of steel,</l>
    <l n="254">But with the sufferer willing suffrance feel."</l>
    <l n="255">This said, the Grace of Goddesses led home,</l>
    <l n="256">He track'd her steps; and, to the cavern come,</l>
    <l n="257">In that rich throne, whence Mercury arose,</l>
    <l n="258">He sat. The Nymph herself did then appose,</l>
    <l n="259">For food and beverage, to him all best meat</l>
    <l n="260">And drink, that mortals used to taste and eat.</l>
    <l n="261">Then sat she opposite, and for her feast</l>
    <l n="262">Was nectar and ambrosia address'd</l>
    <l n="263">By handmaids to her. Both, what was prepar'd,</l>
    <l n="264">Did freely fall to. Having fitly far'd,</l>
    <l n="265">The Nymph Calypso this discourse began :</l>
    <l n="266">"Jove-bred Ulysses! Many-witted man!</l>
    <l n="267">Still is thy home so wish'd? So soon, away?</l>
    <l n="268">Be still of cheer, for all the worst I say.</l>
    <l n="269">But, if thy soul knew what a sum of woes,</l>
    <l n="270">For thee to cast up, thy stern Fates impose,</l>
    <l n="271">Ere to thy country earth thy hopes attain,</l>
    <l n="272">Undoubtedly thy choice would here remain,</l>
    <l n="273">Keep house with me, and be a liver ever.</l>
    <l n="274">Which, methinks, should thy house and thee dissever,</l>
    <l n="275">Though for thy wife there thou art set on fire,</l>

    <pb n="119" facs="#181"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="276">And all thy days are spent in her desire;</l>
    <l n="277">And though it be no boast in me to say</l>
    <l n="278">In form and mind I match her every way.</l>
    <l n="279">Nor can it fit a mortal dame's compare,</l>
    <l n="280">T' affect those terms with us that deathless are."</l>
    <l n="281">The great-in-counsels made her this reply:</l>
    <l n="282">"Renown'd, and to be reverenced, Deity!</l>
    <l n="283">Let it not move thee, that so much I vow</l>
    <l n="284">My comforts to my wife; though well I know</l>
    <l n="285">All cause myself why wise Penelope</l>
    <l n="286">In wit is far inferior to thee,</l>
    <l n="287">In feature, stature, all the parts of show,</l>
    <l n="288">She being a mortal, an immortal thou,</l>
    <l n="289">Old ever growing, and yet never old.</l>
    <l n="290">Yet her desire shall all my days see told,</l>
    <l n="291">Adding the sight of my returning day,</l>
    <l n="292">And natural home. If any God shall lay</l>
    <l n="293">His hand upon me as I pass the seas,</l>
    <l n="294">I'll bear the worst of what his hand shall please,</l>
    <l n="295">As having given me such a mind as shall</l>
    <l n="296">The more still rise the more his hand lets fall.</l>
    <l n="297">In wars and waves my sufferings were not small.</l>
    <l n="298">I now have suffer'd much, as much before,</l>
    <l n="299">Hereafter let as much result, and more."</l>
    <l n="300">This said, the sun set, and earth shadows gave;</l>
    <l n="301">When these two (in an in-room of the cave,</l>
    <l n="302">Left to themselves) left love no rites undone.</l>
    <l n="303">The early Morn up, up he rose, put on</l>
    <l n="304">His in and out weed. She herself enchaces</l>
    <l n="305">Amidst a white robe, full of all the Graces,</l>
    <l n="306">Ample, and pleated thick like fishy scales;</l>
    <l n="307">A golden girdle then her waist impales;</l>

    <pb n="120" facs="#182"/>
    <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

    <l n="308">Her head a veil decks; and abroad they come.</l>
    <l n="309">And now began Ulysses to go home.</l>
    <l n="310">A great axe first she gave, that two ways cut,</l>
    <l n="311">In which a fair well-polish'd helm was put,</l>
    <l n="312">That from an olive bough receiv'd his frame.</l>
    <l n="313">A plainer then. Then led she, till they came<anchor xml:id="n5.313_ref"/></l>
    <l n="314">To lofty woods that did the isle confine.</l>
    <l n="315">The fir tree, poplar, and heaven-scaling pine,</l>
    <l n="316">Had there their offspring. Of which, those that were</l>
    <l n="317">Of driest matter, and grew longest there,</l>
    <l n="318">He choos'd for lighter sail. This place thus shown,</l>
    <l n="319">The Nymph turn'd home. He fell to felling down,</l>
    <l n="320">And twenty trees he stoop'd in little space,</l>
    <l n="321">Plain'd, used his plumb, did all with artful grace.</l>
    <l n="322">In mean time did Calypso wimbles bring.<anchor xml:id="n5.322_ref"/></l>
    <l n="323">He bor'd, closed, nail'd, and order'd every thing,</l>
    <l n="324">And took how much a ship-wright will allow</l>
    <l n="325">A ship of burden (one that best doth know</l>
    <l n="326">What fits his art) so large a keel he cast,</l>
    <l n="327">Wrought up her decks, and hatches, side-boards, mast,</l>
    <l n="328">With willow watlings arm'd her to resist</l>
    <l n="329">The billows outrage, added all she miss'd,<anchor xml:id="n5.329_ref"/></l>
    <l n="330">Sail-yards, and stern for guide. The Nymph then brought</l>
    <l n="331">Linen for sails, which with dispatch he wrought,</l>
    <l n="332">Gables, and halsters, tacklings. All the frame<anchor xml:id="n5.332_ref_1"/><anchor xml:id="n5.332_ref_2"/></l>
    <l n="333">In four days' space to full perfection came.</l>

    <note target="#n5.313_ref"><mentioned>Plainer</mentioned>—i. e. a plane, that which makes plain, smooth.</note>
    <note target="#n5.322_ref"><mentioned>Wimbles</mentioned>—gimlets, boring tools.</note>
    <note target="#n5.329_ref"><mentioned>Miss'd</mentioned>—wanted, required.</note>
    <note target="#n5.332_ref_1"><mentioned>Gables and halsters</mentioned>—cables and hawsers.</note>
    <note target="#n5.332_ref_2">This four days' work (you will say) is too much for one man: and Pliny affirms, that Hiero (a king of Sicily) in five-and-forty days built two hundred and twenty ships, rigged them, and put to sea with them.—CHAPMAN.</note>

    <pb n="121" facs="#183"/>
    <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

    <l n="334">The fifth day, they dismiss'd him from the shore,</l>
    <l n="335">Weeds neat, and odorous, gave him, victuals store,</l>
    <l n="336">Wine, and strong waters, and a prosp'rous wind,</l>
    <l n="337">To which, Ulysses, fit-to-be-divin'd,</l>
    <l n="338">His sails expos'd, and hoised. Off he gat;</l>
    <l n="339">And cheerful was he. At the stern he sat,</l>
    <l n="340">And steer'd right artfully. Nor sleep could seize</l>
    <l n="341">His eye-lids. He beheld the Pleiades;</l>
    <l n="342">The Bear, surnam'd the Wain, that round doth move</l>
    <l n="343">About Orion, and keeps still above</l>
    <l n="344">The billowy ocean; the slow-setting star</l>
    <l n="345">Bootes call'd, by some the waggoner.</l>
    <l n="346">Calypso warn'd him he his course should steer</l>
    <l n="347">Still to his left hand. Seventeen days did clear</l>
    <l n="348">The cloudy night's command in his moist way,</l>
    <l n="349">And by the eighteenth light he might display<anchor xml:id="n5.349_ref"/></l>
    <l n="350">The shady hills of the Phæacian shore,</l>
    <l n="351">For which, as to his next abode, he bore.</l>
    <l n="352">The country did a pretty figure yield,</l>
    <l n="353">And look'd from off the dark seas like a shield.</l>
    <l n="354">Imperious Neptune, making his retreat</l>
    <l n="355">From th' Æthiopian earth, and taking seat</l>
    <l n="356">Upon the mountains of the Solymi,</l>
    <l n="357">From thence, far off discovering, did descry</l>
    <l n="358">Ulysses his fields ploughing. All on fire</l>
    <l n="359">The sight straight set his heart, and made desire</l>
    <l n="360">Of wreak run over, it did boil so high.</l>
    <l n="361">When, his head nodding, " O impiety,"</l>
    <l n="362">He cried out, "now the Gods' inconstancy</l>
    <l n="363">Is most apparent, altering their designs</l>

    <note target="#n5.349_ref"><mentioned>Display</mentioned>—see, view.</note>

  <pb n="122"/>

  <l n="364">Since I the Æthiops saw, and here confines<anchor xml:id="n5.364_ref"/></l>
        <l n="365">To this Ulysses' fate his misery.</l>
        <l n="366">The great mark, on which all his hopes rely,</l>
        <l n="367">Lies in Phæacia. But I hope he shall</l>
        <l n="368">Feel woe at height, ere that dead calm befall."</l>
        <l n="369">This said; he, begging, gather'd clouds from land,<anchor xml:id="n5.369_ref"/></l>
        <l n="370">Frighted the seas up, snatch'd into his hand</l>
        <l n="371">His horrid trident, and aloft did toss,</l>
        <l n="372">Of all the winds, all storms he could engross,</l>
        <l n="373">All earth took into sea with clouds, grim Night</l>
        <l n="374">Fell tumbling headlong from the cope of light,</l>
        <l n="375">The East and South winds justled in the air,</l>
        <l n="376">The violent Zephyr, and North making-fair,</l>
        <l n="377">Rolled up the waves before them. And then bent</l>
        <l n="378">Ulysses' knees, then all his spirit was spent.</l>
        <l n="379">In which despair, he thus spake: "Woe is me!</l>
        <l n="380">What was I born to, man of misery!</l>
        <l n="381">Fear tells me now, that, all the Goddess said,</l>
        <l n="382">Truth's self will author, that Fate would he paid</l>
        <l n="383">Grief's whole sum due from me, at sea, before</l>
        <l n="384">I reach'd the dear touch of my country's shore.</l>
        <l n="385">With what clouds Jove heaven's heighten'd forehead binds!</l>
        <l n="386">How tyrannize the wraths of all the winds!</l>
        <l n="387">How all the tops he bottoms with the deeps,</l>
        <l n="388">And in the bottoms all the tops he steeps!</l>
        <l n="389">Thus dreadful is the presence of our death.</l>
        <l n="390">Thrice four times blest were they that sunk beneath</l>
        <l n="391">Their fates at Troy, and did to nought contend</l>
        <l n="392">But to renown Atrides with their end!</l>

        <note target="#n5.364_ref"><mentioned>Confines</mentioned>—puts an end to.</note>
        <note target="#n5.369_ref">Συναγείρω—Mendicando colligo.—CHAPMAN.</note>

        <pb n="123" facs="#185"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="393">I would to God, my hour of death and fate</l>
        <l n="394">That day had held the power to terminate,</l>
        <l n="395">When showers of darts my life bore undepress'd</l>
        <l n="396">About divine Æacides deceased!</l>
        <l n="397">Then had I been allotted to have died,</l>
        <l n="398">By all the Greeks with funerals glorified,</l>
        <l n="399">(Whence death, encouraging good life, had grown)</l>
        <l n="400">Where now I die, by no man mourn'd nor known."</l>
        <l n="401">This spoke, a huge wave took him by the head,</l>
        <l n="402">And hurl'd him o'er board; ship and all it laid</l>
        <l n="403">Inverted quite amidst the waves, but he</l>
        <l n="404">Far off from her sprawl'd, strow'd about the sea,</l>
        <l n="405">His stern still holding broken off, his mast</l>
        <l n="406">Burst in the midst, so horrible a blast</l>
        <l n="407">Of mix'd winds struck it. Sails and sail-yards fell</l>
        <l n="408">Amongst the billows; and himself did dwell</l>
        <l n="409">A long time under water, nor could get</l>
        <l n="140">In haste his head out, wave with wave so met</l>
        <l n="411">In his depression; and his garments too,</l>
        <l n="412">Given by Calypso, gave him much to do,</l>
        <l n="413">Hind'ring his swimming; yet he left not so</l>
        <l n="414">His drenched vessel, for the overthrow</l>
        <l n="415">Of her nor him, but gat at length again,</l>
        <l n="416">Wrestling with Neptune, hold of her; and then</l>
        <l n="417">Sat in her bulk, insulting over death,</l>
        <l n="418">Which, with the salt stream press'd to stop his breath,<anchor xml:id="n5.418_ref"/></l>
        <l n="419">He 'scap'd, and gave the sea again to give</l>
        <l n="420">To other men. His ship so striv'd to live,</l>
        <l n="421">Floating at randon, cuff'd from wave to wave.<anchor xml:id="n5.421_ref"/></l>
        <l n="422">As you have seen the North wind when he drave</l>

        <note target="#n5.418_ref"><mentioned>Prest</mentioned>—ready.</note>
        <note target="#n5.421_ref"><mentioned>Randon</mentioned>—the old and etymological spelling.</note>

        <pb n="124" facs="#186"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="423">In autumn heaps of thorn-fed Grasshoppers</l>
        <l n="424">Hither and thither, one heap this way bears,</l>
        <l n="425">Another that, and makes them often meet</l>
        <l n="426">In his confus'd gales; so Ulysses' fleet</l>
        <l n="427">The winds hurl'd up and down; now Boreas</l>
        <l n="428">Toss'd it to Notus, Notus gave it pass</l>
        <l n="429">To Eurus, Eurus Zephyr made it pursue</l>
        <l n="430">The horrid tennis. This sport call'd the view</l>
        <l n="431">Of Cadmus' daughter, with the narrow heel,</l>
        <l n="432">Ino Leucothea, that first did feel</l>
        <l n="433">A mortal dame's desires, and had a tongue,</l>
        <l n="434">But now had th' honour to be nam'd among</l>
        <l n="435">The marine Godheads. She with pity saw</l>
        <l n="436">Ulysses justled thus from flaw to flaw,</l>
        <l n="437">And, like a cormorant in form and flight,</l>
        <l n="438">Rose from a whirl-pool, on the ship did light,</l>
        <l n="439">And thus bespake him: "Why is Neptune thus</l>
        <l n="440">In thy pursuit extremely furious,</l>
        <l n="441">Oppressing thee with such a world of ill,</l>
        <l n="442">Even to thy death? He must not serve his will,</l>
        <l n="443">Though 'tis his study. Let me then advise</l>
        <l n="444">As my thoughts serve; thou shalt not be unwise</l>
        <l n="445">To leave thy weeds and ship to the commands</l>
        <l n="446">Of these rude winds, and work out with thy hands</l>
        <l n="447">Pass to Phæacia, where thy austere Fate</l>
        <l n="448">Is to pursue thee with no more such hate.</l>
        <l n="449">Take here this tablet, with this riband strung,</l>
        <l n="450">And see it still about thy bosom hung;</l>
        <l n="451">By whose eternal virtue never fear</l>
        <l n="452">To suffer thus again, nor perish here.</l>
        <l n="453">But when thou touchest with thy hand the shore,</l>
        <l n="454">Then take it from thy neck, nor wear it more,</l>

        <pb n="125" facs="#187"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="455">But cast it far off from the continent,</l>
        <l n="456">And then thy person far ashore present."</l>
        <l n="457">Thus gave she him the tablet; and again,</l>
        <l n="458">Turn'd to a cormorant, dived, past sight, the main.</l>
        <l n="459">Patient Ulysses sigh'd at this, and stuck</l>
        <l n="460">In the conceit of such fair-spoken luck,</l>
        <l n="461">And said: "Alas! I must suspect even this,</l>
        <l n="462">Lest any other of the Deities</l>
        <l n="463">Add sleight to Neptune's force, to counsel me</l>
        <l n="464">To leave my vessel, and so far off see</l>
        <l n="465">The shore I aim at. Not with thoughts too clear</l>
        <l n="466">Will I obey her, but to me appear</l>
        <l n="467">These counsels best: As long as I perceive</l>
        <l n="468">My ship not quite dissolv'd, I will not leave</l>
        <l n="469">The help she may afford me, but abide,</l>
        <l n="470">And suffer all woes till the worst be tried.</l>
        <l n="471">When she is split, I'll swim. No miracle can,</l>
        <l n="472">Past near and clear means, move a knowing man."</l>
        <l n="473">While this discourse employ'd him, Neptune raised</l>
        <l n="474">A huge, a high, and horrid sea, that seized</l>
        <l n="475">Him and his ship, and toss'd them through the lake.</l>
        <l n="476">As when the violent winds together take</l>
        <l n="477">Heaps of dry chaff, and hurl them every way;</l>
        <l n="478">So his long wood-stack Neptune strook astray.</l>
        <l n="479">Then did Ulysses mount on rib, perforce,</l>
        <l n="480">Like to a rider of a running horse,</l>
        <l n="481">To stay himself a time, while he might shift</l>
        <l n="482">His drenched weeds, that were Calypso's gift.</l>
        <l n="483">When putting straight Leucothea's amulet</l>
        <l n="484">About his neck, he all his forces set</l>
        <l n="485">To swim, and cast him prostrate to the seas.</l>
        <l n="486">When powerful Neptune saw the ruthless prease</l>

        <pb n="126" facs="#188"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="487">Of perils siege him thus, he mov'd his head,</l>
        <l n="488">And this betwixt him and his heart he said:</l>
        <l n="489">" So, now feel ills enow, and struggle so,</l>
        <l n="490">Till to your Jove-lov'd islanders you row.</l>
        <l n="491">But my mind says, you will not so avoid</l>
        <l n="492">This last task too, but be with suffrance cloy'd."</l>
        <l n="493">This said, his rich-man's horse he mov'd, and reach'd</l>
        <l n="494">His house at Ægas. But Minerva fetch'd</l>
        <l n="495">The winds from sea, and all their ways but one</l>
        <l n="496">Barr'd to their passage; the bleak North alone</l>
        <l n="497">She set to blow, the rest she charg'd to keep</l>
        <l n="498">Their rages in, and bind themselves in sleep.</l>
        <l n="499">But Boreas still flew high to break the seas,</l>
        <l n="500">Till Jove-bred Ithacus the more with ease</l>
        <l n="501">The navigation-skill'd Phæacian states</l>
        <l n="502">Might make his refuge, Death and angry Fates</l>
        <l n="503">At length escaping. Two nights, yet, and days</l>
        <l n="504">He spent in wrestling with the sable seas;</l>
        <l n="505">In which space, often did his heart propose</l>
        <l n="506">Death to his eyes. But when Aurora rose,</l>
        <l n="507">And threw the third light from her orient hair,</l>
        <l n="508">The winds grew calm, and clear was all the air,</l>
        <l n="509">Not one breath stirring. Then he might descry,</l>
        <l n="510">Rais'd by the high seas, clear, the land was nigh.</l>
        <l n="511">And then, look how to good sons that esteem</l>
        <l n="512">Their father's life dear, (after pains extreme,</l>
        <l n="513">Felt in some sickness, that hath held him long</l>
        <l n="514">Down to his bed, and with affections strong</l>
        <l n="515">Wasted his body, made his life his load,</l>
        <l n="516">As being inflicted by some angry God)</l>
        <l n="517">When on their prayers they see descend at length</l>
        <l n="518">Health from the heavens, clad all in spirit and strength,</l>

        <pb n="127" facs="#189"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="519">The sight is precious; so, since here should end</l>
        <l n="520">Ulysses' toils, which therein should extend</l>
        <l n="521">Health to his country, held to him his sire,</l>
        <l n="522">And on which long for him disease did tire,</l>
        <l n="523">And then, besides, for his own sake to see</l>
        <l n="524">The shores, the woods so near, such joy had he,</l>
        <l n="525">As those good sons for their recover'd sire.</l>
        <l n="526">Then labour'd feet and all parts to aspire</l>
        <l n="527">To that wish'd continent; which when as near</l>
        <l n="528">He came, as Clamour might inform an ear,</l>
        <l n="529">He heard a sound beat from the sea-bred rocks,</l>
        <l n="530">Against which gave a huge sea horrid shocks,</l>
        <l n="531">That belch'd upon the firm land weeds and foam,</l>
        <l n="532">With which were all things hid there, where no room</l>
        <l n="533">Of fit capacity was for any port,</l>
        <l n="534">Nor from the sea for any man's resort,</l>
        <l n="535">The shores, the rocks, the cliffs, so prominent were.</l>
        <l n="536">"O," said Ulysses then, " now Jupiter</l>
        <l n="537">Hath given me sight of an unhoped for shore,</l>
        <l n="538">Though I have wrought these seas so long, so sore.</l>
        <l n="539">Of rest yet no place shows the slend'rest prints,</l>
        <l n="540">The rugged shore so bristled is with flints,</l>
        <l n="541">Against which every way the waves so flock,</l>
        <l n="542">And all the shore shows as one eminent rock,</l>
        <l n="543">So near which 'tis so deep, that not a sand</l>
        <l n="544">Is there for any tired foot to stand,</l>
        <l n="545">Nor fly his death-fast following miseries,</l>
        <l n="546">Lest, if he land, upon him fore-right flies</l>
        <l n="547">A churlish wave, to crush him 'gainst a cliff,</l>
        <l n="548">Worse than vain rend'ring all his landing strife.</l>
        <l n="549">And should I swim to seek a haven elsewhere,</l>
        <l n="550">Or land less way-beat, I may justly fear</l>

        <pb n="128" facs="#190"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="551">I shall be taken with a gale again,</l>
        <l n="552">And cast a huge way off into the main;</l>
        <l n="553">And there the great Earth-shaker (having seen</l>
        <l n="554">My so near landing, and again his spleen</l>
        <l n="555">Forcing me to him) will some whale send out,</l>
        <l n="556">(Of which a horrid number here about,</l>
        <l n="557">His Amphitrite breeds) to swallow me.</l>
        <l n="558">I well have prov'd, with what malignity</l>
        <l n="559">He treads my steps. While this discourse he held,<anchor xml:id="n5.559_ref"/></l>
        <l n="560">A curs'd surge 'gainst a cutting rock impell'd</l>
        <l n="561">His naked body, which it gash'd and tore,</l>
        <l n="562">And had his bones broke, if but one sea more</l>
        <l n="563">Had cast him on it. But She prompted him,</l>
        <l n="564">That never fail'd, and bade him no more swim</l>
        <l n="565">Still off and on, but boldly force the shore,</l>
        <l n="566">And hug the rock that him so rudely tore;</l>
        <l n="567">Which he with both hands sigh'd and clasp'd, till past</l>
        <l n="568">The billow's rage was; when 'scap'd, back so fast</l>
        <l n="569">The rock repuls'd it, that it reft his hold,</l>
        <l n="570">Sucking him from it, and far back he rolled.</l>
        <l n="571">And as the polypus that (forc'd from home</l>
        <l n="572">Amidst the soft sea, and near rough land come</l>
        <l n="573">For shelter 'gainst the storms that beat on her</l>
        <l n="574">At open sea, as she abroad doth err)</l>
        <l n="575">A deal of gravel, and sharp little stones,</l>
        <l n="576">Needfully gathers in her hollow bones;</l>
        <l n="577">So he forc'd hither by the sharper ill,</l>
        <l n="578">Shunning the smoother, where he best hop'd, still</l>
        <l n="579">The worst succeeded; for the cruel friend,</l>
        <l n="580">To which he cling'd for succour, off did rend</l>
        <l n="581">From his broad hands the soaken flesh so sore,</l>
        <l n="582">That off he fell, and could sustain no more.</l>

        <note target="#n5.559_ref"><mentioned>Pallas</mentioned>.</note>

        <pb n="129" facs="#191"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="583">Quite under water fell he; and, past fate,</l>
        <l n="584">Hapless Ulysses there had lost the state</l>
        <l n="585">He held in life, if, still the grey-eyed Maid</l>
        <l n="586">His wisdom prompting, he had not assay'd</l>
        <l n="587">Another course, and ceas'd t' attempt that shore,</l>
        <l n="588">Swimming, and casting round his eye t' explore</l>
        <l n="589">Some other shelter. Then the mouth he found</l>
        <l n="590">Of fair Callicoe's flood, whose shores were crown'd<anchor xml:id="n5.590_ref"/></l>
        <l n="591">With most apt succours; rocks so smooth they seem'd</l>
        <l n="592">Polish'd of purpose; land that quite redeem'd</l>
        <l n="593">With breathless coverts th' others' blasted shores.</l>
        <l n="594">The flood he knew, and thus in heart implores:</l>
        <l n="595">" King of this river, hear! Whatever name</l>
        <l n="596">Makes thee invok'd, to thee I humbly frame</l>
        <l n="597">My flight from Neptune's furies. Reverend is</l>
        <l n="598">To all the ever-living Deities</l>
        <l n="599">What erring man soever seeks their aid.</l>
        <l n="600">To thy both flood and knees a man dismay'd</l>
        <l n="601">With varied suff'rance suues.</l>
        <l n="602">Yield then some rest</l>
        <l n="603">To him that is thy suppliant profess'd."</l>
        <l n="604">This, though but spoke in thought, the Godhead heard,</l>
        <l n="605">Her current straight stay'd, and her thick waves clear'd</l>
        <l n="606">Before him, smooth'd her waters, and, just where</l>
        <l n="607">He pray'd half-drown'd, entirely saved him there.</l>
        <l n="608">Then forth he came, his both knees falt'ring, both</l>
        <l n="609">His strong hands hanging down, and all with froth</l>
        <l n="610">His cheeks and nosthrils flowing, voice and breath</l>
        <l n="611">Spent to all use, and down he sunk to death.</l>
        <l n="612">The sea had soak'd his heart through; all his veins</l>

        <note target="#n5.590_ref">Callicoe's flood.—The original is simply ποταμοῖο κατὰ στόμα καλλιρόοιο, at the mouth of a fair-flowing river. I presume Chapman meant the epithet for the name of the river, calling it Callirrhoe, not Callicoe, as it is printed in the folio.</note>

        <pb n="130" facs="#192"/>
        <fw rend="center">THE FIFTH BOOK</fw>

        <l n="613">His toils had rack'd t' a labouring woman's pains.<anchor xml:id="n5.613_ref"/></l>
        <l n="614">Dead weary was he. But when breath did find</l>
        <l n="615">A pass reciprocal, and in his mind</l>
        <l n="616">His spirit was recollected, up he rose,</l>
        <l n="617">And from his neck did th' amulet unloose,</l>
        <l n="618">That Ino gave him; which he hurl'd from him</l>
        <l n="619">To sea. It sounding fell, and back did swim</l>
        <l n="620">With th' ebbing waters, till it straight arriv'd</l>
        <l n="621">Where Ino's fair hand it again receiv'd.</l>
        <l n="622">Then kiss'd he th' humble earth; and on he goes,</l>
        <l n="623">Till bulrushes show'd place for his repose,</l>
        <l n="624">Where laid, he sigh'd, and thus said to his soul:</l>
        <l n="625">"O me, what strange perplexities control</l>
        <l n="626">The whole skill of thy powers in this event?</l>
        <l n="627">What feel I? If till care-nurse night be spent</l>
        <l n="628">I watch amidst the flood, the sea's chill breath,</l>
        <l n="629">And vegetant dews, I fear will be my death,</l>
        <l n="630">So low brought with my labours. Towards day</l>
        <l n="631">A passing sharp air ever breathes at sea.</l>
        <l n="632">If I the pitch of this next mountain scale,</l>
        <l n="633">And shady wood, and in some thicket fall</l>
        <l n="634">Into the hands of Sleep, though there the cold</l>
        <l n="635">May well be check'd, and healthful slumbers hold</l>
        <l n="636">Her sweet hand on my powers, all care allay'd,</l>
        <l n="637">Yet there will beasts devour me. Best appaid</l>
        <l n="638">Doth that course make me yet; for there, some strife,</l>
        <l n="639">Strength, and my spirit, may make me make for life;</l>
        <l n="640">Which, though impair'd, may yet be fresh applied,</l>
        <l n="641">Where peril possible of escape is tried.</l>
        <l n="642">But he that fights with heaven, or with the sea,</l>

        <note target="#n5.613_ref">Ωδεε οἱ ὠδίνω, à partu doleo.—CHAPMAN. It is hardly necessary to observe that Chapman's fanciful derivation is wrong, ᾠδεε being the imperfect of οἰδέω, tumeo.</note>

        <pb n="131" facs="#193"/>
        <fw rend="center">OF HOMER'S ODYSSEYS.</fw>

        <l n="643">To indiscretion adds impiety."</l>
        <l n="644">Thus to the woods he hasted; which he found</l>
        <l n="645">Not far from sea, but on far-seeing ground,</l>
        <l n="646">Where two twin underwoods he enter'd on,</l>
        <l n="647">With olive-trees and oil-trees overgrown;</l>
        <l n="648">Through which the moist force of the loud-voiced wind</l>
        <l n="649">Did never beat, nor ever Phœbus shin'd,</l>
        <l n="650">Nor shower beat through, they grew so one in one,</l>
        <l n="651">And had, by turns, their power t' exclude the sun.</l>
        <l n="652">Here enter'd our Ulysses; and a bed</l>
        <l n="653">Of leaves huge, and of huge abundance, spread</l>
        <l n="654">With all his speed. Large he made it, for there</l>
        <l n="655">For two or three men ample coverings were,</l>
        <l n="656">Such as might shield them from the winter's worst,<anchor xml:id="n5.656_ref"/></l>
        <l n="657">Though steel it breath'd, and blew as it would burst.</l>
        <l n="658">Patient Ulysses joy'd, that ever day</l>
        <l n="659">Show'd such a shelter. In the midst he lay,</l>
        <l n="660">Store of leaves heaping high on every side.</l>
        <l n="661">And as in some out-field a man doth hide</l>
        <l n="662">A kindled brand, to keep the seed of fire,</l>
        <l n="663">No neighbour dwelling near, and his desire</l>
        <l n="664">Serv'd with self store, he else would ask of none,</l>
        <l n="665">But of his fore-spent sparks rakes th' ashes on;</l>
        <l n="666">So this out-place Ulysses thus receives,</l>
        <l n="667">And thus nak'd virtue's seed lies hid in leaves.</l>
        <l n="668">Yet Pallas made him sleep as soon as men</l>
        <l n="669">Whom delicacies all their flatteries deign,</l>
        <l n="170">And all that all his labours could comprise</l>
        <l n="671">Quickly concluded in his closed eyes.</l>

        <note target="#n5.656_ref">A metaphorical hyperbole, expressing the winter's extremity of sharpness.—CHAPMAN.</note>
  </div>

</div>
   </div>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>