<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <pb n="410"/>
        <head>HYMN TO CERES.</head>
        <head>TRANSLATED BY RICHARD HOLE, LL.B.</head>
        <argument>
          <p>Proserpine being carried off by Pluto, Ceres proceeds to seek her. Having learned from Hecate and the Sun what had befallen her, she forsakes heaven, and, assuming the form of a woman, wanders through the earth till she comes to the house of Celeus at Eleusis, where she is engaged as a nurse for the infant son of Celeus. Purposing to make the child immortal, she places him every night secretly in the midst of the fire, in order to burn away the corruptible part of his nature; but, being one night surprised by his mother in the act, she declares her intentions frustrated. Celeus, to pacify the goddess, builds a temple to her. Meanwhile, her absence from heaven has affected the Earth with sterility, but she refuses to return, even after repeated requests from Jupiter, until Pluto is ordered to restore Proserpine; Pluto obeys, but, as he has given her a pomegranate seed to eat, she cannot be wholly divorced from him, and Ceres is obliged to be satisfied that Proserpine shall pass two-thirds of the year with her, and one-third with her husband. The Eleusinian Mysteries are instituted.</p>
        </argument>
        <l n="1">CERES, to thee belongs the votive lay,</l>
        <l n="2">Whose locks in radiance round thy temples play;</l>
        <pb n="411"/>
        <l n="3">And Proserpine, whom, distant from thy sight,</l>
        <l n="4">Fierce Pluto bore to realms of endless night.</l>
        <l n="5">For thus decreed the God, whose piercing eyes</l>
        <l n="6">Trace every act, whose thunder shakes the skies,</l>
        <l n="7">That she, whose hands the golden sickle bear,</l>
        <l n="8">And choicest product of the circling year,</l>
        <l n="9">Rich fruits, and fragrant-breathing flowers, should know</l>
        <l n="10">The tender conflicts of maternal woe.</l>
        <l n="11">In Nysia's vale, with nymphs a lovely train,</l>
        <l n="12">Sprung from the hoary father of the main,</l>
        <l n="13">Fair Proserpine consum'd the fleeting hours</l>
        <l n="14">In pleasing sports, and pluck'd the gaudy flowers.</l>
        <l n="15">Around them wide the flamy crocus glows,</l>
        <l n="16">Thro' leaves of verdure blooms the opening rose;</l>
        <l n="17">The hyacinth declines his fragrant head,</l>
        <l n="18">And purple violets deck th' enamell'd mead.</l>
        <l n="19">The fair Narcissus far above the rest,</l>
        <l n="20">By magic form'd, in beauty rose confess'd.</l>
        <l n="21">So Jove, t' ensnare the virgin's thoughtless mind,</l>
        <l n="22">And please the ruler of the shades, design'd.</l>
        <l n="23">He caus'd it from the opening earth to rise,</l>
        <l n="24">Sweet to the scent, alluring to the eyes.</l>
        <l n="25">Never did mortal or celestial power</l>
        <l n="26">Behold such vivid tints adorn a flower.</l>
        <l n="27">From the deep root an hundred branches sprung,</l>
        <l n="28">And to the winds ambrosial odours flung;</l>
        <l n="29">Which, lightly wafted on the wings of air,</l>
        <l n="30">The gladden'd earth, and heaven's wide circuit, share.</l>
        <l n="31">The joy-dispensing fragrance spreads around,</l>
        <l n="32">And ocean's briny swell with smiles is crown'd.</l>
        <l n="33">Pleas'd at the sight, nor deeming danger nigh,</l>
        <l n="34">The fair beheld it with desiring eye:</l>
        <l n="35">Her eager hand she stretch'd to seize the flower,</l>
        <l n="36">(Beauteous illusion of th' ethereal power!)</l>
        <l n="37">When, dreadful to behold, the rocking ground</l>
        <l n="38">Disparted—widely yawn'd a gulf profound!—</l>
        <l n="39">Forth-rushing from the black abyss, arose</l>
        <l n="40">The gloomy monarch of the realm of woes,</l>
        <l n="41">Pluto, from Saturn sprung. The trembling maid</l>
        <l n="42">He seiz'd, and to his golden car convey'd.</l>
        <l n="43">Borne by immortal steeds the chariot flies:</l>
        <l n="44">And thus she pours her supplicating cries:</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Proserpine</speaker>
          <l n="45">'Assist, protect me, thou who reign'st above,</l>
          <l n="46">'Supreme and best of Gods, paternal Jove!'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="47">But ah! in vain the hapless virgin rears</l>
        <l n="48">Her wild complaint: nor god nor mortal hears!</l>
        <pb n="412"/>
        <l n="49">Not to the white-arm'd nymphs with beauty crown'd,</l>
        <l n="50">Her lov'd companions, reach'd the mournful sound.</l>
        <l n="51">Pale Hecate, who in the cell of night</l>
        <l n="52">Muses on youthful pleasure's rapid flight;</l>
        <l n="53">And bright Hyperion's son, who decks the skies</l>
        <l n="54">With splendour, only heard the virgin's cries</l>
        <l n="55">Invoke the father of th' ethereal powers.</l>
        <l n="56">But he, at distance from their airy bowers,</l>
        <l n="57">Sits in his hallow'd fane; his votaries hears,</l>
        <l n="58">Accepts their offerings, and rewards their prayers.</l>
        <l n="59">While hell's dread ruler in his car convey'd</l>
        <l n="60">To realms of darkness the reluctant maid.</l>
        <l n="61">Long as she view'd the star-bespangled skies,</l>
        <l n="62">And ocean's many-teeming waters rise;</l>
        <l n="63">While earth's gay verdure fled not from her view,</l>
        <l n="64">Nor Phœbus yet his cheerful light withdrew;</l>
        <l n="65">So long the ray of hope illum'd her breast,</l>
        <l n="66">Nor sunk her soul, undaunted tho' distress'd.</l>
        <l n="67">Her mother still she thought would meet her sight,</l>
        <l n="68">And friendly powers who dwelt in realms of light.</l>
        <l n="69">E'en ocean's depth resounded to her cry,</l>
        <l n="70">And lofty mountains towering to the sky!</l>
        <l n="71">At length, the shrieks of woe her mother hears:</l>
        <l n="72">Her heavenly breast the shaft of anguish tears.</l>
        <l n="73">The blooming wreath she from her brow unbinds;</l>
        <l n="74">Rends her bright locks, and gives them to the winds:</l>
        <l n="75">Then (mournful emblem of her inward woes!)</l>
        <l n="76">A sable veil athwart her shoulders throws.</l>
        <l n="77">As some fond bird her ravish'd young deplores,</l>
        <l n="78">And every secret shade in vain explores;</l>
        <l n="79">To seek the fair she flies o'er sea and land,</l>
        <l n="80">The burning torches waving in her hand.</l>
        <l n="81">Nor gods, nor men, the author of her woes</l>
        <l n="82">Unfold: no birds of omen'd flight disclose.</l>
        <l n="83">Nine tedious days in vain the queen ador'd</l>
        <l n="84">The various regions of the earth explor'd;</l>
        <l n="85">Nor did she taste, while she her course pursued,</l>
        <l n="86">The balmy nectar, or ambrosial food;</l>
        <l n="87">Nor ever in the cool translucent wave,</l>
        <l n="88">Toil's sweet relief, her form of beauty lave.</l>
        <l n="89">On the tenth morn, as, chasing night's dull gloom,</l>
        <l n="90">Aurora's beams the purpled east illume,</l>
        <l n="91">Pale Hecate before her view appear'd;</l>
        <l n="92">Her hand the faintly-gleaming taper rear'd,</l>
        <pb n="413"/>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Hecate</speaker>
          <l n="93">And thus began; 'Oh thou! to whom we owe</l>
          <l n="94">'Those joys, the season's circling flight bestow;</l>
          <l n="95">'What god, what mortal dar'd the impious deed,</l>
          <l n="96">'That makes a heavenly breast with sorrow bleed?</l>
          <l n="97">'I heard thy daughter's voice implore relief;</l>
          <l n="98">'Unknown to me the author of her grief—'<ref n="413.1">1</ref></l>
        </sp>
        <gap extent="* * * * *"/>
        <l n="99">She ceas'd; nor did the goddess make reply,</l>
        <l n="100">But sudden wav'd the flaming torch on high,</l>
        <l n="101">And sought the ruler of the day; whose sight</l>
        <l n="102">From the pure regions of unclouded light</l>
        <l n="103">All actions views. Before his car they came;</l>
        <l n="104">The burning car, and horses breathing flame,</l>
        <l n="105">Stopp'd sudden. Ceres thus;</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Ceres</speaker>
          <l n="105a">'Oh Phœbus hear!</l>
          <l n="106">'My fame, my ancient dignity revere!</l>
          <l n="107">'If e'er my blessings gave thy soul delight,</l>
          <l n="108">'Those blessings now by friendship's act requite.</l>
          <l n="109">'A daughter late was mine of beauteous form-</l>
          <l n="110">'(Sweet tender plant, uprooted by a storm!)</l>
          <l n="111">'Distant I heard her loud-lamenting cries;</l>
          <l n="112">'But fate severe denied her to my eyes.</l>
          <l n="113">'Oh thou! who, crown'd with ether's purest light,</l>
          <l n="114">'Thro' earth and ocean dart'st thy boundless sight,</l>
          <l n="115">'Tell me what god, what mortal, has convey'd</l>
          <l n="116">'Reluctant from these arms my darling maid?'</l>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Phoebus</speaker>
          <l n="117">'Daughter of Rhea!' he replied, 'I hear</l>
          <l n="118">'With grief thy wrongs, and dignity revere.</l>
          <l n="119">'Blame not th' ethereal race: from heaven's dread king,</l>
          <l n="120">'Who dwells mid' black'ning clouds, thy sorrows spring.</l>
          <l n="121">'Pluto, by his decree, the virgin bore</l>
          <l n="122">'Where, darkly frowning on th' infernal shore,</l>
          <l n="123">'His lofty palace stands. No more repine;</l>
          <l n="124">'No cause for anguish, nor for shame, is thine.</l>
          <l n="125">'He, brother to the god who rules on high,</l>
          <l n="126">'Now hails her empress of the lower sky:</l>
          <l n="127">'For Saturn's awful race superior reign</l>
          <l n="128">'O'er heaven, o'er hell, and earth-encircling main.'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="129">He said; and then (his course no more delay'd)</l>
        <l n="130">Spoke to his fiery steeds: his steeds obey'd.</l>
        <l n="131">Whirl'd rapid onwards thro' th' illumin'd skies,</l>
        <l n="132">The flame-rob'd chariot kindles as it flies:</l>
        <l n="133">Swift, as when rushing thro' the blaze of day,</l>
        <l n="134">Darts the fierce eagle on his distant prey.</l>
        <note n="413.1">Some part of Hecate's speech appears to have been lost. She relates nothing more to Ceres than what she knew before; and yet, from what follows, one would suppose that her information had conveyed to the goddess some additional cause for grief and vexation. Hole.</note>
        <pb n="414"/>
        <l n="135">But deeper anguish rends the mother's soul,</l>
        <l n="136">And thoughts of vengeance in her bosom roll;</l>
        <l n="137">She shuns th' imperious power who rules on high,</l>
        <l n="138">And quits th' immortal synod of the sky.</l>
        <l n="139">Then, furious from Olympus' airy height</l>
        <l n="140">To earth precipitates her rapid flight.</l>
        <l n="141">There, mingling with the race of man, she shares</l>
        <l n="142">Their various toils; consum'd with grief appears</l>
        <l n="143">Her beauteous form; unknown from shore to shore</l>
        <l n="144">She roves; till Celeus' hospitable door</l>
        <l n="145">Receives her steps. He in Eleusis reign'd,</l>
        <l n="146">Where still her rites and honours are maintain'd.</l>
        <l n="147">Beside a path, while o'er her drooping head</l>
        <l n="148">His grateful shade the verdant olive spread,</l>
        <l n="149">As by her feet Parthenius' waters flow,</l>
        <l n="150">She sits, a pallid spectacle of woe.</l>
        <l n="151">Her faded cheeks no more with beauty bloom'd,</l>
        <l n="152">But now the form of wrinkled age assum'd.</l>
        <l n="153">She seem'd like those whom each attractive grace</l>
        <l n="154">Forsakes, when time with wrinkles marks the face;</l>
        <l n="155">From whom the Cyprian power indignant flies,</l>
        <l n="156">Her gifts refuses, and her charms denies,</l>
        <l n="157">Who, in some regal dome, by fate severe,</l>
        <l n="158">Are doom'd to nurse, and serve another's heir.</l>
        <l n="159">Four gentle nymphs, light-moving o'er the plain,</l>
        <l n="160">Approach; four brazen urns their arms sustain:</l>
        <l n="161">Great Celeus was their sire: he bade them bring</l>
        <l n="162">The limpid water from Parthenius' spring.</l>
        <l n="163">Lovely they seem'd as heaven's immortal powers:</l>
        <l n="164">Youth's purple light, and beauty's opening flowers</l>
        <l n="165">Glow'd on their cheeks: Callidice the fair,</l>
        <l n="166">And meek Clausidice with pensive air;</l>
        <l n="167">Then Demo, and Callithoe's riper grace</l>
        <l n="168">Appear'd, the eldest of the lovely race.</l>
        <l n="169">They hail the power unknown: (for mortal eyes</l>
        <l n="170">How hard to penetrate a god's disguise!)</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Nymphs</speaker>
          <l n="171">'Who, and whence art thou, Dame! whose brow appears</l>
          <l n="172">'Mark'd by the traces of revolving years?</l>
          <l n="173">'Why dost thou shun yon peopled town? in grief</l>
          <l n="174">'Why lonely sit?—there thou wilt find relief:</l>
          <l n="175">'There, matrons like thyself, who long the load</l>
          <l n="176">'Of life have borne, and traced its rugged road,</l>
          <l n="177">'Employ'd in labours, such as best engage</l>
          <l n="178">'The pleas'd attention of declining age,</l>
          <l n="179">'With tender maids, thy sorrows shall condole,</l>
          <l n="180">'And acts of friendship cheer thy drooping soul!'</l>
        </sp>
        <pb n="415"/>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Ceres</speaker>
          <l n="181">'Hail nymphs unknown!' the goddess thus rejoin'd,</l>
          <l n="182">'Accept the tribute of a grateful mind.</l>
          <l n="183">'Would you the story of my sorrows know,</l>
          <l n="184">'Attend to no fictitious tale of woe.</l>
          <l n="185">'Reluctant from the Cretan coast I came;</l>
          <l n="186">'Dear native land! and Doris is my name.</l>
          <l n="187">'To ruffians' force who plough the wat'ry way,</l>
          <l n="188">'I fell an helpless, unresisting prey.</l>
          <l n="189">'The bark bounds swiftly o'er the liquid main,</l>
          <l n="190">'And soon the coast of Thoricus<ref n="415.1">1</ref> we gain.</l>
          <l n="191">'The vessel safely moor'd, a female band</l>
          <l n="192">'Prepare the banquet on the neighb'ring strand;</l>
          <l n="193">'Whilst wide around us eve's grey vapours rise,</l>
          <l n="194">'And her dim shades roll slowly thro' the skies.</l>
          <l n="195">'But, deeply-musing on my woes, I pine,</l>
          <l n="196">'Nor share the feast, nor taste the cheerful wine.</l>
          <l n="197">'When thro' the sky night's deeper gloom was spread,</l>
          <l n="198">'Unnotic'd, trembling o'er the beach I fled.</l>
          <l n="199">'The spoiler's lust of gold I rendered vain;</l>
          <l n="200">'Unransom'd, thus escap'd the galling chain</l>
          <l n="201">'Of servitude, long time from shore to shore</l>
          <l n="202">'I wander'd; various toils and perils bore.</l>
          <l n="203">'To me e'en now unknown, ere you unfold,</l>
          <l n="204">'The land I tread, the people I behold.</l>
          <l n="205">'To you, ye virgins! may th' ethereal powers.</l>
          <l n="206">'Who o'er Olympus dwell in airy bowers,</l>
          <l n="207">'Shed choicest favours! may your consorts prove</l>
          <l n="208">'Of lovely form, deserving of your love!</l>
          <l n="209">'And be your children with such beauty blest,</l>
          <l n="210">'As hope can image in a parent's breast!</l>
          <l n="211">'Then, gentle maids, in pity to my woes,</l>
          <l n="212">'How best I can obtain relief, disclose,</l>
          <l n="213">'In yonder town with pleasure I'll engage</l>
          <l n="214">'In tasks best suited to my feeble age.</l>
          <l n="215">'Well-skill'd in household toils, to please my lord</l>
          <l n="216">'The couch I'll spread, and crown the festive board;</l>
          <l n="217">'Or should a child be trusted to my care,</l>
          <l n="218">'These arms shall nurse him, and these knees shall bear.'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="219">She ceas'd. The loveliest of a lovely line,</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Callidice</speaker>
          <l n="220">Callidice, replied; 'No more repine!</l>
          <l n="221">'But know, whate'er th' immortal gods ordain,</l>
          <l n="222">'It is our part to suffer, not complain:</l>
          <l n="223">'Enough for us that justice rules their mind,</l>
          <l n="224">'Whose wisdom, like their power, is unconfin’d.</l>
          <l n="225">'The chiefs, who here supreme dominion hold,</l>
          <l n="226">'Be it my task, O stranger! to unfold:</l>
          <l n="227">'Thro' whom, Eleusis hostile rage defies;</l>
        </sp>
        <note n="415.1">A town and demus in Attica.</note>
        <pb n="416"/>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Callidice</speaker>
          <l n="228">'Beneath whose care yon guardian ramparts rise.</l>
          <l n="229">'From whom protecting law derives its force,</l>
          <l n="230">'And awful justice holds her steady course:</l>
          <l n="231">'Triptolemus, of deep-revolving mind,</l>
          <l n="232">'Diocles noble, Polyxenus kind;</l>
          <l n="233">'With every milder grace Eumolpus crown'd,</l>
          <l n="234">'And stately Dolichus in arms renown'd.</l>
          <l n="235">'Superior to the rest, o'er these domains,</l>
          <l n="236">'Our honour'd sire, the mighty Celeus, reigns.</l>
          <l n="237">'Each chief a lovely consort boasts, who guides</l>
          <l n="238">'Domestic labours, and at home presides:</l>
          <l n="239">'Not one of them who would thy suit reject,</l>
          <l n="240">'But soothe thy sorrows, and thy age respect:</l>
          <l n="241">'For sure, thou seem'st of more than mortal race,</l>
          <l n="242">'Tho' time with wrinkles marks thy pallid face.</l>
          <l n="243">'But if thou here wilt rest, without delay</l>
          <l n="244">'We'll to our mother's ears thy tale convey.</l>
          <l n="245">'If she approves, accept a welcome there:</l>
          <l n="246">'An only child, an unexpected heir,</l>
          <l n="247">'Born to his parents in declining age,</l>
          <l n="248">'Our darling pleasure, will thy cares engage.</l>
          <l n="249">'Shouldst thou preserve him (kindly thus employ'd)</l>
          <l n="250">'Till ripening manhood make thy labours void,</l>
          <l n="251">'Such gifts hereafter he'll on thee bestow,</l>
          <l n="252">'As those will envy most, who best shall know.'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="253">The virgin ceas'd; nor aught the goddess said,</l>
        <l n="254">But bow'd submissive her assenting head.</l>
        <l n="255">The liquid crystal fills their polish'd urns:</l>
        <l n="256">Each nymph exulting to the town returns.</l>
        <l n="257">Arriv'd at Celeus' dome, they quick disclose</l>
        <l n="258">The stranger's humble suit, and tale of woes</l>
        <l n="259">To Metanira:<ref n="416.1">1</ref> pleas'd at the request,</l>
        <l n="260">Maternal fondness glowing in her breast,</l>
        <l n="261">She bids them to the matron thus declare,</l>
        <l n="262">That ample treasures should reward her care.</l>
        <l n="263">Like the kine's lowing race, that sportive bound</l>
        <l n="264">Along the plain with flowery verdure crown'd;</l>
        <l n="265">Or the sleek fawn, when he at first perceives</l>
        <l n="266">Spring's genial warmth, and crops the budding leaves;</l>
        <l n="267">Thus joyful thro' the beaten road they pass'd,</l>
        <l n="268">With robes collected to promote their haste.</l>
        <l n="269">Their tresses, like the crocus' flamy hue,</l>
        <l n="270">In waving radiance round their shoulders flew.</l>
        <l n="271">Now to the place, where sate the heavenly dame</l>
        <l n="272">Beside the murmuring stream, the virgins came.</l>
        <note n="416.1">The wife of Celeus.</note>
        <pb n="417"/>
        <l n="273">Their mother's suit they urge, nor she denies;</l>
        <l n="274">While thoughts of sorrow in her bosom rise,</l>
        <l n="275">Wrapt in the sable veil her course she bends;</l>
        <l n="276">The robe dark-flowing to her feet descends.</l>
        <l n="277">Soon they approach to Celeus' stately gate;</l>
        <l n="278">Within the lofty hall the mother<ref n="417.1">1</ref> sate</l>
        <l n="279">Beside the threshold; frequent to her breast</l>
        <l n="280">The child, the darling of her soul, she press'd.</l>
        <l n="281">Each nymph to greet her much-lov'd parent flies,</l>
        <l n="282">While Ceres distant stands in humble guise.</l>
        <l n="283">Lo! suddenly, before their wond'ring sight,</l>
        <l n="284">Her form increasing, to the temple's height</l>
        <l n="285">Ascends; her head with circling rays is crown'd,</l>
        <l n="286">And wide th' ethereal splendour spreads around!</l>
        <l n="287">Awe, veneration, seiz'd the mother's breast,</l>
        <l n="288">And pallid fear was on her cheeks impress'd:</l>
        <l n="289">Upstarting from her couch she'd fain resign</l>
        <l n="290">The seat resplendent to her guest divine:</l>
        <l n="291">With looks unwilling she the suit denies,</l>
        <l n="292">And fixes on the ground her radiant eyes.</l>
        <l n="293">But kind Iambe with a modest mien</l>
        <l n="294">A seat provided for the seasons' queen:</l>
        <l n="295">A lambkin's snowy fleece she o'er it spread;</l>
        <l n="296">Still, deeply-musing, nought the goddess said,</l>
        <l n="297">But round her head the dusky mantle drew,</l>
        <l n="298">To hide her deep-felt anguish from their view.</l>
        <gap extent="* * * * *"/><ref n="417.2">2</ref>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Metanira</speaker>
          <l n="299">'Be it thy care to nurse this lovely boy,</l>
          <l n="300">'Child of my age, an unexpected joy</l>
          <l n="301">'By favouring gods bestow'd !-should, thro' thy cares,</l>
          <l n="302">'My Demophon arrive at manhood's years;</l>
          <l n="303">'Others shall at thy happier state repine,</l>
          <l n="304">'Such high rewards, such treasure shall be thine!'</l>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Ceres</speaker>
          <l n="305">'Oh woman! favour'd by the powers of heaven,</l>
          <l n="306">'To whom the gods this beauteous child have given,’</l>
          <l n="307">Ceres replied, 'I take with joy thy heir:</l>
          <l n="308">'No nurse unskill'd receives him to her care:</l>
          <l n="309">'Nor magic spell, nor roots of mighty power,</l>
          <l n="310">'From earth's dark bosom torn at midnight hour,</l>
          <l n="311">'Shall hurt thy offspring; to defeat each charm,</l>
          <l n="312">'And herb malignant of its power disarm,</l>
          <l n="313">'Full well I know.'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="314">She said, and to her breast</l>
        <l n="315">The infant clasp'd, and tenderly caress'd.</l>
        <note n="417.1">Metanira.</note>
        <note n="417.2">Several verses are lost; and some other passages are defective.</note>
        <pb n="418"/>
        <l n="316">Thus Ceres nurs'd the child. Exulting joy</l>
        <l n="317">Reign'd in his parents' hearts. Mean while the boy</l>
        <l n="318">Grew like an offspring of ethereal race;</l>
        <l n="319">Health crown'd his frame, and beauty deck'd his face.</l>
        <l n="320">No mortal food he ate: the queen ador'd</l>
        <l n="321">Around him oft ambrosial odours pour'd;</l>
        <l n="322">Oft as the child was on her bosom laid,</l>
        <l n="323">She heavenly influence to his soul convey'd.</l>
        <l n="324">At night, to purge from earthly dross his frame,</l>
        <l n="325">She kindled on the earth th' annealing flame;</l>
        <l n="326">And, like a brand, unmark'd by human view,</l>
        <l n="327">Amid the fire wide-blazing frequent threw</l>
        <l n="328">Th' unconscious child: his parents wond'ring trace</l>
        <l n="329">Something divine, a more than mortal grace</l>
        <l n="330">Shine in his form; and she design'd the boy,</l>
        <l n="331">To chance superior, and to time's annoy,</l>
        <l n="332">Crown'd with unceasing joys in heaven should reign:</l>
        <l n="333">Those thoughts a mother's rashness render'd vain!</l>
        <l n="334">One fatal night, neglectful of repose,</l>
        <l n="335">Her couch forsaking, Metanira rose;</l>
        <l n="336">And from her secret stand beheld the flame</l>
        <l n="337">Receive the infant. Terror shakes her frame!</l>
        <l n="338">She shrieks in agony; she smites her thighs;</l>
        <l n="339">And thus she pours her loud-lamenting cries:</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Metanira</speaker>
          <l n="340">'Oh Demophon, my child! this stranger guest,</l>
          <l n="341">'What causeless rage, what frenzy has possess'd?</l>
          <l n="342">'Consuming flames around thy body roll,</l>
          <l n="343">'And anguish rends thy mother's tortur'd soul!'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="344">Wrath seiz'd the goddess; her immortal hands</l>
        <l n="345">Sudden she plung'd amid the fiery brands;</l>
        <l n="346">And full before th' afflicted mother's view,</l>
        <l n="347">On the cold floor the blameless infant threw,</l>
        <l n="348">And furious thus began:</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Ceres</speaker>
          <l n="349">'Oh mortals vain!</l>
          <l n="350">'Whose folly counteracts what gods ordain!</l>
          <l n="351">'Who lost in error's maze, will never know</l>
          <l n="352">'Approaching blessings from impending woe!</l>
          <l n="353">'Long, for the rashness that thy soul possess'd,</l>
          <l n="354">'Shall keen reflection agonize thy breast.</l>
          <l n="355">'For, by that oath which binds the powers supreme</l>
          <l n="356">'I swear! by sable Styx, infernal stream!</l>
          <l n="357">'Else had thy son in youth's perpetual prime</l>
          <l n="358">'Shar'd heavenly joys, and mock'd the rage of time.</l>
          <l n="359">'But now 'tis past! from fate he cannot fly!-</l>
          <l n="360">'Man's common lot is his-he breathes to die!-</l>
          <pb n="419"/>
          <l n="361">'Fame shall attend his steps, and bright renown</l>
          <l n="362">'With wreaths unfading shall his temples crown.</l>
          <l n="363">'In future times, torn by discordant rage,</l>
          <l n="364">'Eleusis' sons commutual war shall wage;</l>
          <l n="365">'Then Demophon'</l>
          <gap extent="* * * * *"/>
          <l n="366">'Know then that Ceres, from whose bounty flow</l>
          <l n="367">'Those blessings the revolving years bestow,</l>
          <l n="368">'Who, both from gods and man's frail race demands</l>
          <l n="369">'Her honours due, before thy presence stands.</l>
          <l n="370">'Away, and let Eleusis' sons unite,</l>
          <l n="371">'Where steep Callichorus' projecting height</l>
          <l n="372">'Frowns o'er the plain, a stately fane to rear:</l>
          <l n="373">'Her awful rites its goddess shall declare.</l>
          <l n="374">'There with pure hearts upon the hallow'd shrine</l>
          <l n="375">'Your victims slay, and soothe a power divine!'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="376">This said; the front of age so late assum'd</l>
        <l n="377">Dissolv'd; her face with charms celestial bloom'd.</l>
        <l n="378">The sacred vesture that around her flew,</l>
        <l n="379">Thro' the wide air ambrosial odours threw;</l>
        <l n="380">Her lovely form with sudden radiance glow'd;</l>
        <l n="381">Her golden locks in wreaths of splendour flow'd.</l>
        <l n="382">Thro' the dark palace stream'd a flood of light,</l>
        <l n="383">As cloud-engender'd fires illume the night</l>
        <l n="384">With dazzling blaze. Then swiftly from their view,</l>
        <l n="385">Urg'd by indignant rage, the goddess flew.</l>
        <l n="386">In Metanira's breast amazement reign'd:</l>
        <l n="387">Silent she stood; nor long her knees sustain'd</l>
        <l n="388">Their tottering weight; she sunk in grief profound;</l>
        <l n="389">The child neglected, shrieking on the ground</l>
        <l n="390">Beside her lay: his agonizing cries</l>
        <l n="391">The sisters hear, and from their couches rise:</l>
        <l n="392">They snatch him from the floor; the fire suppress'd</l>
        <l n="393">One lights anew; one fondly to her breast</l>
        <l n="394">The infant folds; by filial duty sway'd,</l>
        <l n="395">Another hastes to Metanira's aid.</l>
        <l n="396">And now they gather'd round th' afflicted child,</l>
        <l n="397">And bath'd his beauteous form with dust defil'd:</l>
        <l n="398">With broken sobs he ceas'd not to complain;</l>
        <l n="399">A different nurse he sought, but sought in vain.</l>
        <l n="400">To soothe the goddess' rage, with awe impress'd,</l>
        <l n="401">In deep consult they pass'd the hours of rest;</l>
        <l n="402">Till night her dreary shadows roll'd away,</l>
        <l n="403">And bright Aurora brought the cheerful day:</l>
        <l n="404">Then, as she bade, around whose brow divine,</l>
        <l n="405">The blooming flowers, a lovely wreath, entwine,</l>
        <pb n="420"/>
        <l n="406">They, to the ruler of Eleusis' state</l>
        <l n="407">The wonders of th' eventful night relate.</l>
        <l n="408">The sages of the land conven'd, his will</l>
        <l n="409">He thus unfolds; 'that on th' impending hill</l>
        <l n="410">'Of steep Callichorus, to the bright-hair'd power</l>
        <l n="411">'An altar rise, and stately temple tower.'</l>
        <l n="412">Gladly the chiefs assent: with busy care</l>
        <l n="413">The people soon the splendid fabric rear.</l>
        <l n="414">A power superior aids their warm desire;</l>
        <l n="415">They hail the omen, and with joy retire.</l>
        <l n="416">There Ceres, distant from the powers divine,</l>
        <l n="417">Sits deeply-musing in her hallow'd shrine.</l>
        <l n="418">The eager wish to view her daughter's face,</l>
        <l n="419">Again to fold her with a fond embrace,</l>
        <l n="420">Consumes her beauteous form; alternate roll</l>
        <l n="421">The tides of grief and vengeance in her soul.</l>
        <l n="422">She to the earth her genial power denies:</l>
        <l n="423">The corn unfruitful in its bosom lies:</l>
        <l n="424">The oxen draw the crooked plough in vain;</l>
        <l n="425">No waving verdure decks the blasted plain:</l>
        <l n="426">Pale famine spreads around: each mortal breast</l>
        <l n="427">Is sunk with woe, and by despair possess'd.</l>
        <l n="428">One common fate had now involv'd them all,</l>
        <l n="429">And the blest gods who in th' aerial hall</l>
        <l n="430">Of high Olympus reign, by man ador'd,</l>
        <l n="431">Their votaries' vows, and offerings had deplor'd:</l>
        <l n="432">But Jove revolving on the ills design'd</l>
        <l n="433">By Ceres;-to appease her wrathful mind,</l>
        <l n="434">Sends the bright goddess of the splendid bow,</l>
        <l n="435">Whose gold-bespangled wings with lustre glow,</l>
        <l n="436">Thro' yielding air with matchless speed she flew;</l>
        <l n="437">Eleusis' temple rose before her view.</l>
        <l n="438">There, while rich incense wafted fragrance round,</l>
        <l n="439">Clad in her sable veil the queen she found,</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Iris</speaker>
          <l n="440">And thus began: 'The ruler of the sky</l>
          <l n="441">'Calls thee to meet th' assembled gods on high:</l>
          <l n="442">'Oh haste! with them celestial pleasures prove;</l>
          <l n="443">'Nor fruitless be the words that come from Jove!'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="444">Iris in vain her soothing words address'd;</l>
        <l n="445">The goddess yields not to her kind request:</l>
        <l n="446">In vain, at his command who sways the skies,</l>
        <l n="447">Th' immortals sue; she hears and she denies:</l>
        <l n="448">Their proffer'd honours and their gifts disdains,</l>
        <l n="449">And in her breast relentless vengeance reigns.</l>
        <l n="450">Firmly resolv'd where high Olympus towers</l>
        <l n="451">She ne'er would mingle with th' ethereal powers,</l>
        <l n="452">Nor fruitful earth's productive force renew,</l>
        <pb n="421"/>
        <l n="453">Till her lov'd daughter met her longing view.</l>
        <l n="454">When the dread power whose thunder shakes the skies,</l>
        <l n="455">From whose keen sight no act unnoticed lies,</l>
        <l n="456">Heard her determin'd will; he gave command</l>
        <l n="457">To Maia's son, who bears the golden wand,</l>
        <l n="458">That straight to Erebus he wing his way,</l>
        <l n="459">And woo the god, whom shadowy forms obey,</l>
        <l n="460">With words persuasive; that his queen ador'd</l>
        <l n="461">In Stygian realms, might be to heaven restor'd,</l>
        <l n="462">And, mingling with the powers celestial; ease</l>
        <l n="463">Her mother's anxious soul, and wrath appease.</l>
        <l n="464">Hermes obeys, and from the realms of day</l>
        <l n="465">To Tartarus directs his rapid way;</l>
        <l n="466">There, in the centre of the earth profound,</l>
        <l n="467">The monarch of th' infernal realms he found</l>
        <l n="468">High-thron'd in gloomy state; beside her lord</l>
        <l n="469">Fair Proserpine her mother's loss deplor'd,</l>
        <l n="470">Who, deep-revolving in her troubled mind,</l>
        <l n="471">Dire vengeance 'gainst th' ethereal race design'd.</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Hermes</speaker>
          <l n="472">Hermes began; 'Oh thou! whose awful head</l>
          <l n="473">'Is crown'd with sable locks, to whom the dead</l>
          <l n="474">'Submissive reverence pay, the sire of gods</l>
          <l n="475">'Great Jove decrees, that from these dark abodes,</l>
          <l n="476">'By me, thy consort, crown'd with beauty's charms,</l>
          <l n="477">'Should be to heaven restor'd, and Ceres' arms.</l>
          <l n="478">'For know, such vengeful thoughts her soul inspire,</l>
          <l n="479">'That e'en the immortal gods must feel her ire.</l>
          <l n="480">'No golden harvests now the plains adorn,</l>
          <l n="481">'In earth she hides the life-sustaining corn,</l>
          <l n="482">'And man must fall; to those who rule the skies</l>
          <l n="483">'No honours shall be paid, no prayers arise.</l>
          <l n="484">'Far, far from them, with rage-enkindled heart,</l>
          <l n="485">'She in her lofty temple sits apart,</l>
          <l n="486">'Rear'd by Eleusis to her power divine,</l>
          <l n="487">'Where clouds of incense roll around her shrine.'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="488">The gloomy monarch Jove's commands obey'd;</l>
        <l n="489">Reluctant smiles his dark-bent brows display'd:</l>
        <l n="490">And thus his blooming consort he address'd;</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Pluto</speaker>
          <l n="491">'Go Proserpine! let pleasure sway thy breast;</l>
          <l n="492">'No more let memory recal the past,</l>
          <l n="493">'But to thy mother's fond embraces haste.</l>
          <l n="494">'Tis fruitless, nay, tis folly to complain-</l>
          <l n="495">'Nor I a husband that deserves disdain-</l>
          <l n="496">'Brother to Jove supreme!-Hence then, my fair!</l>
          <l n="497">'And soon again to Pluto's arms repair.</l>
          <pb n="422"/>
          <l n="498">'Honour to thee the heavenly powers shall pay;</l>
          <l n="499">'Thee shall the shadowy forms of hell obey;</l>
          <l n="500">'And those, who ne'er on earth invok'd thy aid,</l>
          <l n="501">'Nor victims slew, nor rich oblations paid,</l>
          <l n="502">'By thee condemn'd, shall prove eternal pains</l>
          <l n="503">'In the dark realms where endless horror reigns.'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="504">He said; and sudden from her seat arose</l>
        <l n="505">His lovely bride; her heart with transport glows;</l>
        <l n="506">Then Pluto fear'd, lest from the realms above,</l>
        <l n="507">And Ceres, object of her filial love,</l>
        <l n="508">She'd ne'er return; and fraudulent decreed</l>
        <l n="509">The fair should taste the rich pomegranate's seed-</l>
        <l n="510">A fatal pledge! The ruler of the dead</l>
        <l n="511">Then to their view his sable coursers led;</l>
        <l n="512">And yok'd them to the splendid car; his bride</l>
        <l n="513">Assum'd the seat, with Hermes by her side,</l>
        <l n="514">The god, whose fury to th' infernal plains</l>
        <l n="515">Hurl'd hapless Argus;-firm he grasp'd the reins,</l>
        <l n="516">And wav'd the lash; the steeds impetuous flew;</l>
        <l n="517">The realms of darkness vanish'd from their view;</l>
        <l n="518">Onward they rush, impatient of delay,</l>
        <l n="519">Nor seas, nor rapid streams impede their way:</l>
        <l n="520">Nor tow'ring heights, which dark'ning clouds surround;</l>
        <l n="521">Nor low-sunk vales with verdant herbage crown'd.</l>
        <l n="522">With steady ardour, unabated force,</l>
        <l n="523">Through depth of air they urge their rapid course;</l>
        <l n="524">Till Ceres' sacred temple they behold,</l>
        <l n="525">Where clouds of incense round her altar roll'd.</l>
        <l n="526">Soon as the goddess view'd her daughter's face,</l>
        <l n="527">With eager speed she rush'd to her embrace.</l>
        <l n="528">Thus when the hind her long-lost fawn espies,</l>
        <l n="529">In transport from the mountain's brow she flies.</l>
        <gap extent="* * * * *"/>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Ceres</speaker>
          <l n="530">'Thou here with Ceres, daughter of my love,</l>
          <l n="531">'Shalt stay, high-honour'd by the powers above:</l>
          <l n="532">'But if thou aught in Pluto's drear abode</l>
          <l n="533">'Hast ate, thou must retrace the gloomy road;</l>
          <l n="534">'And with th' infernal god his sceptre share</l>
          <l n="535">'One tedious third of the revolving year:</l>
          <l n="536">'The rest shalt thou partake with heavenly powers;</l>
          <l n="537">'And when with herbage green, and blooming flowers</l>
          <l n="538">'Spring decks the earth, thou shalt ascend the skies,</l>
          <l n="539">'A joy to mortal and celestial eyes.'</l>
        </sp>
        <gap extent="* * * * *"/>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Ceres</speaker>
          <l n="540">'Say, by what art thy unsuspecting mind</l>
          <l n="541">'The God deceiv'd?'</l>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Proserpine</speaker>
          <l n="541a">Thus Proserpine rejoin'd:</l>
          <pb n="423"/>
          <l n="542">'When the wing'd herald of the powers above</l>
          <l n="543">'Came with the mandate of all-ruling Jove,</l>
          <l n="544">'Again to bear me to th' ethereal skies,</l>
          <l n="545">'And give me to thy long-desiring eyes,</l>
          <l n="546">'That thus thy vengeful rage might be suppress'd,</l>
          <l n="547">'My heart with transport bounded in my breast.</l>
          <l n="548">'But then, so hell's imperious lord decreed,</l>
          <l n="549">'I ate reluctant the pernicious seed.<ref n="423.1">1</ref></l>
          <l n="550">'Joyful I wander'd through the verdant plain,</l>
          <l n="551">'Leucippe, Phæno, Rhodia in my train:</l>
          <l n="552">'With them Electra, Ianira stray'd,</l>
          <l n="553">'And Rhodope in beauty's charms array'd:</l>
          <l n="554">'Ocyroe too was there of roseate hue;</l>
          <l n="555">'Her golden locks around Chryseis flew:</l>
          <l n="556">'Calypso's charming form, Urania's grace,</l>
          <l n="557">'And Galaxaure's love-inspiring face;</l>
          <l n="558">'Pallas, who bids the rage of battle glow,</l>
          <l n="559">'And chaste Diana with her sounding bow.</l>
          <l n="560">'In pleasing sports the fleeting hours we wear,</l>
          <l n="561">'And pluck the blushing honours of the year.</l>
          <l n="562">'Lilies and hyacinths the air perfume;</l>
          <l n="563">'The crocus glows, th' expanding roses bloom:</l>
          <l n="564">'But lovelier far I view with joyful eyes</l>
          <l n="565">'The fair Narcissus from the earth arise.</l>
          <l n="566">'This wondrous flower, the meadow's blooming pride,</l>
          <l n="567">'I rush'd to seize. The rent earth opening wide</l>
          <l n="568">'A dreary gulf disclos'd: from thence appear'd</l>
          <l n="569">'The mighty king in Tartarus rever'd,</l>
          <l n="570">'And bore me to his golden car; in vain</l>
          <l n="571">'I weep, resist, and to the gods complain.</l>
          <l n="572">'Swift flies his chariot to the realms below,</l>
          <l n="573">'And still my bosom bleeds at former woe!'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="574">With mutual joy they now sweet converse hold,</l>
        <l n="575">And now each other in their arms enfold;</l>
        <l n="576">And, all the live-long day, the transports prove</l>
        <l n="577">That flow from filial and maternal love.</l>
        <note n="423.1">Here appears to be an omission, unless the speech of Proserpine has been transposed through some mistake. It should probably have begun with the following line: Joyful I wander'd through the Nysian plain; and after that which now concludes the speech, should follow the account of Mercury's coming to her in the palace of Plnto, with which it now begins. As it stands at present, Proserpine concludes her narrative with telling Ceres that she is still sorrowful; and the lines that immediately follow describe their mutual joy at meeting with each other. Hole.</note>
        <pb n="424"/>
        <l n="578">No thoughts of vengeance Ceres' soul infest:</l>
        <l n="579">But harmony and pleasure rule her breast.</l>
        <l n="580">Soon Hecate approach'd, and hail'd the fair,</l>
        <l n="581">A splendid fillet bound her flowing hair:</l>
        <l n="582">To Proserpine her breast with friendship glow'd,</l>
        <l n="583">And all her acts a kind attention show'd.<ref n="424.1">1</ref></l>
        <l n="584">And now th' all-seeing god, whose thunders shake</l>
        <l n="585">Th' aerial regions, thus to Rhea spake:</l>
        <l n="586">(Around whose form her robes in darkness flew;</l>
        <l n="587">From whom her birth the queen of seasons drew):</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Jove</speaker>
          <l n="588">'Let Ceres hasten to th' ethereal plain,</l>
          <l n="589">'And every honour she desires, obtain.</l>
          <l n="590">'Her Proserpine, with heavenly powers, shall share</l>
          <l n="591">'In joy two parts of the revolving year,</l>
          <l n="592">'The rest in realms of night.'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="592a">The Thunderer said:</l>
        <l n="593">The willing goddess his commands obey'd;</l>
        <l n="594">And from Olympus' cloud-encircled height</l>
        <l n="595">Bends to Callichorus her lofty flight:</l>
        <l n="596">O'er the drear region desolation frown'd,</l>
        <l n="597">So late with fruits and waving verdure crown'd.</l>
        <l n="598">But soon the earth its wonted power regains;</l>
        <l n="599">Again the harvest clothes th' extended plains;</l>
        <l n="600">Increasing ploughshares turn the grateful soil,</l>
        <l n="601">And weighty sheaves reward the lab'rers' toil.</l>
        <l n="602">Thro' air's ungenial void the goddess bends</l>
        <l n="603">Her flight sublime, and now on earth descends.</l>
        <l n="604">Each kindred power to hail the other flies,</l>
        <l n="605">Joy rules their hearts, and sparkles in their eyes.</l>
        <l n="606">At length sage Rhea, round whose awful head</l>
        <l n="607">The wreath of splendour glow'd, to Ceres said:</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Rhea</speaker>
          <l n="608">'Jove calls my daughter to th' ethereal plain;</l>
          <l n="609">'Such honours as thy soul desires, obtain.</l>
          <l n="610">'He wills two parts of the revolving year,</l>
          <l n="611">'Thy Proserpine shall heavenly pleasure share;</l>
          <l n="612">'The rest in realms of night. His sacred nod</l>
          <l n="613">'Confirm'd the promise of the all-ruling god.</l>
          <l n="614">'Haste then: no more oppose with wrathful mind</l>
          <l n="615">'Heaven's mighty lord 'mid dark'ning clouds enshrin'd:</l>
          <l n="616">'But thy kind influence to the earth impart,</l>
          <l n="617">'And with thy blessings cheer man's drooping heart.'</l>
        </sp>
        <l n="618">The power, whose brow the flowery wreath entwines,</l>
        <l n="619">Obeys her word; her anger she resigns.</l>
        <note n="424.1">Matthæi very justly supposes these four verses to be spurious, or out of place. Hecate, as Hole observes, is "introduced very needlessly."</note>
        <pb n="425"/>
        <l n="620">Th' extended plains with fruits and flowers are crown'd,</l>
        <l n="621">And plenty reigns, and nature smiles around.</l>
        <l n="622">Then to the chiefs, who o'er Eleusis sway'd,</l>
        <l n="623">Whose righteous laws the grateful realm obey'd,</l>
        <l n="624">Eumolpus, and Triptolemus the sage,</l>
        <l n="625">Diocles skill'd to tame the courser's rage,</l>
        <l n="626">Kind Polyxenus, and the king who reign'd</l>
        <l n="627">Supreme, great Celeus, she her rites explain'd;</l>
        <l n="628">Those sacred mysteries, for the vulgar ear</l>
        <l n="629">Unmeet; and known, most impious to declare!</l>
        <l n="630">Oh! let due reverence for the gods restrain</l>
        <l n="631">Discourses rash, and check inquiries vain!</l>
        <l n="632">Thrice happy he among the favour'd few,</l>
        <l n="633">To whom 'tis given those glorious rites to view!</l>
        <l n="634">A fate far different the rejected share;</l>
        <l n="635">Unblest, unworthy her protecting care,</l>
        <l n="636">They'll perish: and with chains of darkness bound,</l>
        <l n="637">Be plung'd for ever in the gulf profound!</l>
        <l n="638">Her laws establish'd, to the realms of light</l>
        <l n="639">With Proserpine she wings her towering flight:</l>
        <l n="640">The sacred powers assume their seat on high,</l>
        <l n="641">Beside the god, whose thunders shake the sky.</l>
        <l n="642">Happy, thrice happy he of human race,</l>
        <l n="643">Who proves deserving their benignant grace!</l>
        <l n="644">Plutus, who from his unexhausted stores</l>
        <l n="645">To favour'd mortals boundless treasure pours,</l>
        <l n="646">Th' auspicious Deities to him shall send;</l>
        <l n="647">And prosperous fortune shall his steps attend.</l>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Bard</speaker>
          <l n="648">'And now, O Ceres! at thy hallow'd shrine</l>
          <l n="649">'Submissive bow the Eleusinian line:</l>
          <l n="650">'Antron's dark rocks re-echo with thy praise,</l>
          <l n="651">'And sea-surrounded Paros thee obeys.</l>
          <l n="652">'Goddess! thro' whom the season's circling flight</l>
          <l n="653">'Successive blessings pours, and new delight;</l>
          <l n="654">'And thou, O lovely Proserpine, reward</l>
          <l n="655">'With honour'd age and tranquil joys the bard</l>
          <l n="656">'Who sings your acts; and soon his voice he'll raise,</l>
          <l n="657">'And other strains shall celebrate your praise.'</l>
        </sp>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
