<TEI>
    <text>
        <body>
<pb n="469" facs="#555"/>
<head>HYMN TO VENUS.</head>
<head>TRANSLATED BY GEORGE CHAPMAN.</head>
<argument>
<p>The power and influence of Venus. Jupiter, indignant at her haughtiness,
resolves that she shall experience humiliation, and accordingly inspires
her with an irresistible passion for the mortal Anchises. Account of
her union with him. Prediction of the fame which Æneas, the offspring
of their love, is to enjoy.</p>
</argument>
<l n="1">THE force, O muse, and functions, now unfold,</l>
<l n="2">Of Cyprian Venus, grac'd with mines of gold:</l>
<l n="3">Who, even in deities, lights love's sweet desire;</l>
<l n="4">And all death's kinds of men, makes kiss her fire;</l>
<l n="5">All air's wing'd nation; all the belluine;</l>
<l n="6">That or the earth feeds, or the seas confine.</l>
<l n="7">To all which appertain the love and care</l>
<l n="8">Of well-crown'd Venus' works. Yet three there are,</l>
<l n="9">Whose minds she neither can deceive nor move;</l>
<l n="10">Pallas, the seed of Ægis-bearing-Jove,</l>
<l n="11">Who still lives indevirginate; her eyes</l>
<l n="12">Being blue, and sparkling like the freezing skies;</l>
<l n="13">Whom all the gold of Venus never can</l>
<l n="14">Tempt to affect her facts, with God or man:</l>
<l n="15">She, loving strife, and Mars his working banes</l>
<l n="16">Pitch'd fields and fights, and famous artizans,</l>
<l n="17">Taught earthy men first all the arts that are;</l>
<l n="18">Chariots, and all the frames vehicular,</l>
<l n="19">Chiefly with brass arm'd, and adorn'd for war:</l>
<l n="20">Where Venus only soft-skinn'd wenches fills</l>
<l n="21">With wanton house-works, and suggests those skills</l>
<l n="22">Still to their studies. Who Diana neither,</l>
<l n="23">That bears the golden distaff, and together</l>
<pb n="470" facs="#556"/>
<l n="24">Calls horns, and halloos, and the cries of hounds,</l>
<l n="25">And owns the epithet of loving-sounds,</l>
<l n="26">For their sakes springing from such sprightly sports,</l>
<l n="27">Can catch with her kind lures. But still resorts</l>
<l n="28">To wild-beasts, slaughters, accents far-off heard</l>
<l n="29">Of harps and dances, and of woods unshear'd,</l>
<l n="30">The sacred shades she loves; yet likes as well</l>
<l n="31">Cities where good men and their offspring dwell.</l>
<l n="32">The third, whom her kind passions nothing please,</l>
<l n="33">Is virgin Vesta; whom Saturnides</l>
<l n="34">Made reverend with his counsels; when his sire,</l>
<l n="35">That adverse counsels agitates, life's fire</l>
<l n="36">Had kindled in her, being his last begot:</l>
<l n="37">Whom Neptune woo'd to knit with him the knot</l>
<l n="38">Of honour'd nuptials; and Apollo too;</l>
<l n="39">Which with much vehemence she refus'd to do,</l>
<l n="40">And stern repulses put upon them both:</l>
<l n="41">Adding to all her vows the god's great oath,</l>
<l n="42">And touching Jove's chin, which must consummate</l>
<l n="43">All vows so bound, that she would hold her state;</l>
<l n="44">And be th' invincible maid of deities</l>
<l n="45">Through all her days' dates. For Saturnides</l>
<l n="46">Gave her a fair gift in her nuptials' stead,</l>
<l n="47">To sit in midst of his house and be fed</l>
<l n="48">With all the free and richest feast of heaven;</l>
<l n="49">In all the temples of the gods being given</l>
<l n="50">The prize of honour. Not a mortal man,</l>
<l n="51">That either of the pow'rs Olympian</l>
<l n="52">His half-birth having, may be said to be</l>
<l n="53">A mortal of the gods, or else that he</l>
<l n="54">(Deities' wills doing) is of deity,</l>
<l n="55">But gives her honour of the amplest kind.<ref n="470.1">1</ref></l>
<l n="56">Of all these three can Venus not a mind</l>
<l n="57">Deceive, or set on forces to reflect.<ref n="470.2">2</ref></l>
<l n="58">Of all pow'rs else yet, not a sex, nor sect,</l>
<l n="59">Flies Venus; either of the blessed gods,</l>
<l n="60">Or men confin'd in mortal periods.</l>
<l n="61">But even the mind of Jove she doth seduce,</l>
<l n="62">That chides with thunder so her lawless use</l>
<l n="63">In human creatures; and by lot is given</l>
<l n="64">Of all, most honour, both in earth and heaven.</l>
<note n="470.1">There is not a single mortal, (even though he may be either the son of a deity, or may seem, by piously doing the will of the gods, to partake of the divine nature,) that does not pay ample honours to Vesta.</note>
<note n="470.2">Venus cannot apply sufficient force to reflect them, or turn them back or away from their own course.</note>
<pb n="471" facs="#557"/>
<l n="65">And yet even his all-wise and mighty mind,</l>
<l n="66">She, when she lists, can forge affects to blind,</l>
<l n="67">And mix with mortal dames his deity:</l>
<l n="68">Conceal'd, at all parts, from the jealous eye</l>
<l n="69">Of Juno, who was both his sister born,</l>
<l n="70">And made his wife; whom beauty did adorn</l>
<l n="71">Past all the bevy of immortal dames,</l>
<l n="72">And whose so chiefly-glorified flames</l>
<l n="73">Cross-counsel'd Saturn got; and Rhæa bore;</l>
<l n="74">And Jove's pure counsels (being conqueror)</l>
<l n="75">His wife made of his sister. Ay, and more,</l>
<l n="76">Cast such an amorous fire into her mind</l>
<l n="77">As made her (like him) with the mortal kind</l>
<l n="78">Meet in unmeet bed; using utmost haste,</l>
<l n="79">Lest she should know that he liv'd so unchaste,</l>
<l n="80">Before herself felt that fault in her heart,</l>
<l n="81">And gave her tongue too just edge of desert</l>
<l n="82">To tax his lightness. With this end, beside,</l>
<l n="83">Lest laughter-studying Venus should deride</l>
<l n="84">The gods more than the goddesses; and say</l>
<l n="85">That she the gods commix'd in amorous play</l>
<l n="86">With mortal dames; begetting mortal seed</l>
<l n="87">T' immortal sires, and not make goddesses breed</l>
<l n="88">The like with mortal fathers :-but t' acquite</l>
<l n="89">Both gods and goddesses of her despite,</l>
<l n="90">Jove took (even in herself) on him her pow'r;</l>
<l n="91">And made her with a mortal paramour</l>
<l n="92">Use as deform'd a mixture as the rest,</l>
<l n="93">Kindling a kind affection in her breast</l>
<l n="94">To god-like-limb'd Anchises, as he kept,</l>
<l n="95">On Ida's-top-on-top-to-heavens-pole heap'd,</l>
<l n="96">Amongst the many fountains there, his herd;</l>
<l n="97">For after his brave person had appear'd</l>
<l n="98">To her bright eye, her heart flew all on fire;</l>
<l n="99">And (to amaze) she burn'd in his desire,</l>
<l n="100">Flew straight to Cyprus, to her odorous fane</l>
<l n="101">And altars, that the people Paphian</l>
<l n="102">Advanc'd to her. Where, soon as enter'd, she</l>
<l n="103">The shining gates shut; and the Graces three</l>
<l n="104">Wash'd, and with oils of everlasting scent</l>
<l n="105">Bath'd, as became, her deathless lineament.</l>
<l n="106">Then her ambrosian mantle she assum'd,</l>
<l n="107">With rich and odoriferous airs perfum'd;</l>
<l n="108">Which being put on, and all her trims beside</l>
<l n="109">Fair, and with all allurements amplified,</l>
<l n="110">The all-of-gold-made-laughter-loving dame</l>
<pb n="472" facs="#558"/>
<l n="111">Left odorous Cyprus; and for Troy became</l>
<l n="112">A swift contendress, her pass cutting all</l>
<l n="113">Along the clouds; and made her instant fall</l>
<l n="114">On fountful Ida, that her mother-breasts</l>
<l n="115">Gives to the preyful brood of savage beasts.</l>
<l n="116">And through the hill she went the ready way</l>
<l n="117">T' Anchises' oxstall, where did fawn and play,</l>
<l n="118">About her blessed feet, wolves grisly-grey;</l>
<l n="119">Terrible lions; many a mankind<ref n="472.1">1</ref> bear;</l>
<l n="120">And leopards swift, insatiate of red deer.</l>
<l n="121">Whose sight so pleas'd, that, ever as she past,</l>
<l n="122">Through every beast a kindly love she cast;</l>
<l n="123">That in their dens-obscur'd with shadows deep,</l>
<l n="124">Made all, distinguish'd in kind couples, sleep.</l>
<l n="125">And now she reach'd the rich pavilion</l>
<l n="126">Of the hero, in whom the heavens had shown</l>
<l n="127">A fair and goodly composition;</l>
<l n="128">And whom she in his oxstall found, alone;</l>
<l n="129">His oxen feeding in fat pastures by,</l>
<l n="130">He walking up and down, sounds clear and high</l>
<l n="131">From his harp striking. Then, before him, she</l>
<l n="132">Stood like a virgin, that invincibly</l>
<l n="133">Had borne her beauties; yet alluringly</l>
<l n="134">Bearing her person, lest his ravish'd eye</l>
<l n="135">Should chance t' affect him with a stupid fear.</l>
<l n="136">Anchises seeing her, all his senses were</l>
<l n="137">With wonder stricken; and high-taken heeds</l>
<l n="138">Both of her form, brave stature, and rich weeds.</l>
<l n="139">For, for a veil, she shin'd in an attire</l>
<l n="140">That cast a radiance past the ray of fire.</l>
<l n="141">Beneath which, wore she girt to her a gown</l>
<l n="142">Wrought all with growing-rose-buds, reaching down</l>
<l n="143">T' her slender smalls, which buskins did divine;<ref n="472.2">2</ref></l>
<l n="144">Such as taught Thetis' silver feet to shine.</l>
<l n="145">Her soft white neck rich carcanets embrac'd,</l>
<l n="146">Bright, and with gold in all variety grac'd;</l>
<l n="147">That to her breasts let down, lay there and shone,</l>
<l n="148">As at her joyful full the rising moon.</l>
<l n="149">Her sight show'd miracles. Anchises' heart</l>
<l n="150">Love took into his hand, and made him part<ref n="472.3">3</ref></l>
<l n="151">With these high salutations:</l>
<sp><speaker>Anchises</speaker>
<l n="151a">'Joy, (O queen !)</l>
<l n="152">'Whoever of the blest thy beauties been</l>
<note n="472.1">Resembling man, by walking on his hinder legs. Shakespeare has "A mankind witch."</note>
<note n="472.2">Buskins indicated the shape of them.</note>
<note n="472.3">Part with, deliver, utter.</note>
<pb n="473" facs="#559"/>
<l n="153">'That light these entries: or the deity</l>
<l n="154">'That darts affecteth;<ref n="473.1">1</ref> or that gave the eye</l>
<l n="155">'Of heaven his heat and lustre ;<ref n="473.2">2</ref> or that moves</l>
<l n="156">The hearts of all, with all-commanding loves;</l>
<l n="157">'Or generous Themis; or the blue-ey'd maid;</l>
<l n="158">'Or of the Graces any, that are laid</l>
<l n="159">'With all the gods in comparable scales,</l>
<l n="160">'And whom fame up to immortality calls;</l>
<l n="161">'Or any of the nymphs, that unshorn groves,</l>
<l n="162">'Or that this fair hill-habitation loves,</l>
<l n="163">'Or valleys flowing with earth's fattest goods;</l>
<l n="164">'Or fountains, pouring forth eternal floods.</l>
<l n="165">'Say, which of all thou art, that in some place</l>
<l n="166">'Of circular prospect, for thine eyes' dear grace,</l>
<l n="167">'I may an altar build, and to thy pow'rs</l>
<l n="168">'Make sacred all the year's devoted hours,</l>
<l n="169">'With consecrations sweet and opulent.</l>
<l n="170">'Assur'd whereof, be thy benign mind bent</l>
<l n="171">'To these wish'd blessings of me, give me parts</l>
<l n="172">'Of chief attraction in Trojan hearts.</l>
<l n="173">'And after, give me the refulgency</l>
<l n="174">Of most renown'd and rich posterity;</l>
<l n="175">'Long, and free life, and heaven's sweet light as long;</l>
<l n="176">'The people's blessings, and a health so strong,</l>
<l n="177">'That no disease it let my life engage,</l>
<l n="178">'Till th' utmost limit of a human age.'</l></sp>
<l n="179">To this, Jove's seed this answer gave again:</l>
<sp><speaker>Venus</speaker>
<l n="180">'Anchises! happiest of the human strain;</l>
<l n="181">'I am no goddess: why a thrall to death</l>
<l n="182">'Think'st thou like those that immortality breathe?</l>
<l n="183">'A woman brought me forth: my father's name</l>
<l n="184">'Was Otreus, (if ever his high fame</l>
<l n="185">'Thine ears have witness'd,) for he govern'd all</l>
<l n="186">'The Phrygian state; whose every town a wall</l>
<l n="187">'Impregnable embrac'd. Your tongue, you hear,</l>
<l n="188">'I speak so well that in my natural sphere</l>
<l n="189">'(As I pretend) it must have taken prime.</l>
<l n="190">'A woman likewise, of the Trojan clime,</l>
<l n="191">'Took of me, in her house, the nurse's care</l>
<l n="192">'From my dear mother's bosom, and thus are</l>
<l n="193">'My words of equal accent with your own.</l>
<l n="194">'How here I come to make the reason known,</l>
<l n="195">'Argicides, that bears the golden rod,</l>
<l n="196">'Transferr'd me forcibly from my abode</l>
<l n="197">'Made with the maiden train of her that joys</l>
<l n="198">'In golden shafts; and loves so well the noise</l>
<note n="473.1">Diana.</note>
<note n="473.2">Latona, mother of Apollo.</note>
<pb n="474" facs="#560"/>
<l n="199">'Of hounds and hunters, (heaven's pure-living pow'r,)</l>
<l n="200">'Where many a nymph and maid of mighty dow'r</l>
<l n="201">Chaste sports employ'd. All circled with a crown</l>
<l n="202">'Of infinite multitude, to see so shown</l>
<l n="203">'Our maiden pastimes. Yet from all the fair</l>
<l n="204">Of this so forceful concourse, up in air</l>
<l n="205">'The golden-rod-sustaining Argus guide,<ref n="474.1">1</ref></l>
<l n="206">'Rap'd me in sight of all, and made me ride</l>
<l n="207">'Along the clouds with him, enforcing me</l>
<l n="208">'Through many a labour of mortality;</l>
<l n="209">'Through many an unbuilt region and a rude,</l>
<l n="210">Where savage beasts devour'd preys warm and crude;</l>
<l n="211">'And would not let my fears take one foot's tread</l>
<l n="212">'On her by whom are all lives comforted;</l>
<l n="213">'But said, my maiden state must grace the bed</l>
<l n="214">'Of king Anchises, and bring forth to thee</l>
<l n="215">'Issue as fair as of divine degree.</l>
<l n="216">'Which said, and showing me thy moving grace,</l>
<l n="217">'Away flew he up to th' immortal race.</l>
<l n="218">'And thus came I to thee: necessity,</l>
<l n="219">'With her steel strings, compelling me t' apply</l>
<l n="220">'To her high pow'r my will. But you must I</l>
<l n="221">'Implore by Jove, and all the reverence due</l>
<l n="222">'To your dear parents; who (in bearing you)</l>
<l n="223">'Can bear no mean sail; lead me home to them</l>
<l n="224">'An untouch'd maid: being brought up in th' extreme</l>
<l n="225">Of much too cold simplicity, to know</l>
<l n="226">'The fiery cunnings that in Venus glow.</l>
<l n="227">'Show me to them then, and thy brothers born;</l>
<l n="228">'I shall appear none that parts disadorn,</l>
<l n="229">'But such as well may serve a brother's wife;</l>
<l n="230">'And show them now, even to my future life</l>
<l n="231">'If such or no my present will extend.</l>
<l n="232">'To horse-bred-vary'ng Phrygia likewise send</l>
<l n="233">'T' inform my sire and mother of my state,</l>
<l n="234">'That live, for me, extreme disconsolate;</l>
<l n="235">'Who gold enough, and well-woven weeds will give:</l>
<l n="236">'All whose rich gifts in my amends receive.</l>
<l n="237">'All this perform'd, add celebration then</l>
<l n="238">'Of honour'd nuptials, that by god and men</l>
<l n="239">'Are held in reverence.'</l></sp>
<l n="239a">All this while she said,</l>
<l n="240">Into his bosom, jointly, she convey'd</l>
<l n="241">The fires of love, when, all enamour'd, he</l>
<l n="242">In these terms answer'd:</l>
<sp><speaker>Anchises</speaker>
    <l n="242a">'If mortality</l>
<l n="243">Confine thy fortunes, and a woman were</l>
<l n="244">Mother to those attractions that appear</l>
<note n="474.1">A typographical corruption, apparently, for "Argicide."</note>
<pb n="475" facs="#561"/>
<l n="245">'In thy admired form; thy great father given</l>
<l n="246">'High name of Otreus, and the spy of heaven</l>
<l n="247">(Immortal Mercury) th' enforceful cause</l>
<l n="248">'That made thee lose the prize of that applause</l>
<l n="249">That modesty immaculate virgins gives:</l>
<l n="250">My wife thou shalt be call'd through both our lives.</l>
<l n="251">'Nor, shall the pow'rs of men nor gods withhold</l>
<l n="252">'My fiery resolution, to enfold</l>
<l n="253">'Thy bosom in mine arms; which here I vow</l>
<l n="254">'To firm performance, past delay, and now.</l>
<l n="255">'Nor, should Apollo with his silver bow</l>
<l n="256">Shoot me to instant death, would I forbear</l>
<l n="257">'To do a deed so full of cause so dear.</l>
<l n="258">'For with a heaven-sweet woman I will lie,</l>
<l n="259">'Though straight I stoop the house of Dis, and die.'</l></sp>
<l n="260">This said, he took her hand, and she took way</l>
<l n="261">With him; her bright eyes casting round; whose stay</l>
<l n="262">She stuck upon a bed, that was before</l>
<l n="263">Made for the king, and wealthy coverings wore.</l>
<l n="264">On which bears' hides and big-voic'd lions' lay,</l>
<l n="265">Whose preyful lives the king had made his prey,</l>
<l n="266">Hunting th' Idalian hills. This bed, when they</l>
<l n="267">Had both ascended, first he took from her</l>
<l n="268">The fiery weed, that was her utmost wear.</l>
<l n="269">Unbutton'd her next rosy robe, and loos'd</l>
<l n="270">The girdle that her slender waist enclos'd;</l>
<l n="271">Unlac'd her buskins; all her jewel'ry</l>
<l n="272">Took from her neck and breasts, and all laid by</l>
<l n="273">Upon a golden-studded chair of state.</l>
<l n="274">Th' amaze of all which being remov'd, even fate</l>
<l n="275">And council of the equal gods gave way</l>
<l n="276">To this, that with a deathless goddess lay</l>
<l n="277">A deathful man: since, what his love assum'd,</l>
<l n="278">Not with his conscious knowledge was presum'd.</l>
<l n="279">Now, when the shepherds and the herdsmen all</l>
<l n="280">Turn'd from their flow'ry pasture to their stall,</l>
<l n="281">With all their oxen; fat, and frolic sheep;</l>
<l n="282">Venus into Anchises cast a sleep,</l>
<l n="283">Sweet and profound; while with her own hands now</l>
<l n="284">With her rich weeds she did herself endow;</l>
<l n="285">But so distinguish'd, that he clear might know</l>
<l n="286">His happy glories; then (to her desire</l>
<l n="287">Her heavenly person, put in trimms entire)</l>
<l n="288">She by the bed stood of the well-built stall,</l>
<l n="289">Advanc'd her head to state celestial;</l>
<l n="290">And in her cheeks arose the radiant hue</l>
<l n="291">Of rich-crown'd Venus to apparent view.</l>
<pb n="476" facs="#562"/>
<l n="292">And then she rous'd him from his rest, and said,</l>

<sp><speaker>Venus</speaker>
<l n="293">'Up, my Dardanides, forsake thy bed.</l>
<l n="294">'What pleasure, late employ'd, lets humour steep</l>
<l n="295">Thy lids in this inexcitable sleep?</l>
<l n="296">'Wake, and now say, if I appear to thee</l>
<l n="297">'Like her that first thine eyes conceited me.'</l></sp>
<l n="298">This started him from sleep, though deep and dear,</l>
<l n="299">And, passing promptly, he enjoy'd his ear.</l>
<l n="300">But when his eye saw Venus' neck and eyes,</l>
<l n="301">Whose beauties could not bear the counterprise</l>
<l n="302">Of any other, down his own eyes fell;</l>
<l n="303">Which pallid fear did from her view repel,</l>
<l n="304">And made him, with a main respect beside,</l>
<l n="305">Turn his whole person from her state, and hide</l>
<l n="306">(With his rich weed appos'd) his royal face;</l>
<l n="307">These wing'd words using:</l>
<sp><speaker>Anchises</speaker>
    <l n="307a">'When, at first, thy grace</l>
<l n="308">Mine eyes gave entertainment, well I knew</l>
<l n="309">'Thy state was deified: but thou told'st not true;</l>
<l n="310">'And therefore let me pray thee (by thy love</l>
<l n="311">'Borne to thy father, Ægis-bearing Jove)</l>
<l n="312">That thou wilt never let me live to be</l>
<l n="313">'An abject, after so divine degree</l>
<l n="314">'Taken in fortune; but take ruth on me.</l>
<l n="315">'For any man that with a goddess lies,</l>
<l n="316">'Of interest in immortalities,</l>
<l n="317">'Is never long liv'd.'</l></sp>
<l n="317a">She replied,</l>
 <sp><speaker>Venus</speaker><l n="317b">'Forbear</l>
<l n="318">'(O happiest of mortal men) this fear,</l>
<l n="319">'And rest assur'd, that not for me, at least,</l>
<l n="320">'Thy least ills fear fits; no, nor for the rest</l>
<l n="321">'Of all the blessed, for thou art their friend;</l>
<l n="322">'And so far from sustaining instant end,</l>
<l n="323">'That to thy long-enlarg'd life there shall spring</l>
<l n="324">'Amongst the Trojans a dear son, and king,</l>
<l n="325">'To whom shall many a son, and son's son rise</l>
<l n="326">'In everlasting great posterities.</l>
<l n="327">'His name Æneas; therein keeping life</l>
<l n="328">'For ever, in my much-conceited grief,</l>
<l n="329">That I, immortal, fell into the bed</l>
<l n="330">'Of one whose blood mortality must shed.</l>
<l n="331">'But rest thou comforted, and all the race</l>
<l n="332">'That Troy shall propagate in this high grace;</l>
<l n="333">'That, past all races else, the gods stand near</l>
<l n="334">Your glorious nation, for the forms ye bear,</l>
<l n="335">'And natures so ingenuous and sincere.</l>
<l n="336">'For which, the great in counsels, Jupiter,</l>
<l n="337">'Your gold-lock'd Ganymedes did transfer</l>
<pb n="477" facs="#563"/>
<l n="338">'In rapture far from men's depressed fates,</l>
<l n="339">'To make him consort with our deified states,</l>
<l n="340">'And scale the tops of the Saturnian skies;</l>
<l n="341">'He was so mere a marvel in their eyes.</l>
<l n="342">And therefore from a bowl of gold he fills</l>
<l n="343">'Red nectar, that the rude distension kills</l>
<l n="344">'Of winds that in your human stomachs breed.</l>
<l n="345">'But then did languor on the liver feed</l>
<l n="346">'Of Tros his father, that was king of Troy:</l>
<l n="347">'And ever did his memory employ</l>
<l n="348">'With loss of his dear beauty so bereaven,</l>
<l n="349">Though with a sacred whirlwind rapt to heaven.</l>
<l n="350">'But Jove, in pity of him, saw him given</l>
<l n="351">'Good compensation, sending by heaven's spy</l>
<l n="352">'White-swift-hoof'd horse, that immortality</l>
<l n="353">'Had made firm spirited; and had, beside,</l>
<l n="354">'Hermes to see his embassy supplied</l>
<l n="355">'With this vow'd bounty,<ref n="477.1">1</ref> (using all at large</l>
<l n="356">That his unalter'd counsels gave in charge,)</l>
<l n="357">That he himself should immortality breathe,</l>
<l n="358">'Expert of age and woe, as well as death.</l>
<l n="359">'This embassy express'd, he mourn'd no more,</l>
<l n="360">'But up with all his inmost mind he bore;</l>
<l n="361">Joying that he, upon his swift-hoof'd horse,</l>
<l n="362">'Should be sustain'd in an eternal course.</l>
<l n="363">'So did the golden-thron'd Aurora raise</l>
<l n="364">'Into her lap, another that the praise</l>
<l n="365">Of an immortal fashion had in fame,</l>
<l n="366">'And of your nation bore the noble name;</l>
<l n="367">'(His title Tithon) who not pleas'd with her,</l>
<l n="368">'As she his lovely person did transfer,</l>
<l n="369">To satisfy him, she bade ask of Jove,</l>
<l n="370">'The gift of an immortal for her love.</l>
<l n="371">'Jove gave, and bound it with his bowed brow,</l>
<l n="372">'Performing to the utmost point his vow.</l>
<l n="373">'Fool that she was, that would her love engage,</l>
<l n="374">'And not as long ask from the bane of age</l>
<l n="375">The sweet exemption, and youth's endless flow'r:</l>
<l n="376">'Of which as long as both the grace and pow'r</l>
<l n="377">'His person entertain'd, she lov'd the man,</l>
<l n="378">'And (at the fluents of the ocean</l>
<l n="379">'Near Earth's extreme bounds) dwelt with him; but when</l>
<l n="380">'(According to the course of aged men)</l>
<l n="381">On his fair head, and honourable beard,</l>
<l n="382">'His first grey hairs to her light eyes appear'd;</l>
<note n="477.1">To see this promise of bounty added to his message.</note>
<pb n="478" facs="#564"/>
<l n="383">'She left his bed, yet gave him still for food</l>
<l n="384">'The gods' ambrosia, and attire as good.</l>
<l n="385">'Till even the hate of age came on so fast</l>
<l n="386">That not a lineament of his was grac'd</l>
<l n="387">With power of motion, nor did still sustain</l>
<l n="388">'(Much less the vigour had, t' advance a vein)</l>
<l n="389">The virtue lost in each exhausted limb,</l>
<l n="390">That at his wish before would answer him;</l>
<l n="391">'All pow'rs so quite decay'd, that when he spake</l>
<l n="392">'His voice no perceptible accent brake:</l>
<l n="393">'Her counsel then thought best to strive no more,</l>
<l n="394">'But lay him in his bed and lock his door.</l>
<l n="395">'Such an immortal would not I wish thee,</l>
<l n="396">'T' extend all days so to eternity.</l>
<l n="397">'But if, as now, thou couldst perform thy course</l>
<l n="398">'In grace of form, and all corporeal force,</l>
<l n="399">To an eternal date; thou then shouldst bear</l>
<l n="400">'My husband's worthy name, and not a tear</l>
<l n="401">'Should I need rain, for thy deserts declin'd,</l>
<l n="402">'From my all-clouded bitterness of mind.</l>
<l n="403">'But now the stern storm of relentless age</l>
<l n="404">'Will quickly circle thee, that waits t' engage</l>
<l n="405">'All men alike, even loathsomeness and bane</l>
<l n="406">'Attending with it every human wane;</l>
<l n="407">'Which even the gods hate. Such a penance lies</l>
<l n="408">'Impos'd on flesh and blood's infirmities,</l>
<l n="409">'Which I myself must taste in great degree,</l>
<l n="410">'And date as endless, for consorting thee.</l>
<l n="411">'All the immortals with my opprobry</l>
<l n="412">'Are full by this time; on their hearts so lie</l>
<l n="413">'(Even to the sting of fear) my cunnings us'd,</l>
<l n="414">'And wiving conversations infus'd</l>
<l n="415">'Into the bosoms of the best of them</l>
<l n="416">'With women, that the frail and mortal stream</l>
<l n="417">'Doth daily ravish. All this long since done;</l>
<l n="418">'Which now no more, but with effusion</l>
<l n="419">Of tears, I must in heaven so much as name;</l>
<l n="420">'I have so forfeited, in this, my fame;</l>
<l n="421">'And am impos'd pain of so great a kind</l>
<l n="422">'For so much erring from a goddess' mind.</l>
<l n="423">'For I have put beneath my girdle here</l>
<l n="424">'A son, whose sire the human mortal sphere</l>
<l n="425">Gives circumscription. But when first the light</l>
<l n="426">His eyes shall comfort, nymphs that haunt the height</l>
<l n="427">Of hills, and breasts have of most deep receipt,</l>
<l n="428">'Shall be his nurses; who inhabit now</l>
<l n="429">'A hill of so vast and divine a brow,</l>
<pb n="479" facs="#565"/>
<l n="430">'As man nor god can come at their retreats:</l>
<l n="431">'Who live long lives and eat immortal meats,</l>
<l n="432">'And with immortals in the exercise</l>
<l n="433">'Of comely dances dare contend; and rise</l>
<l n="434">'Into high question which deserves the prize.</l>
<l n="435">'The light Sileni mix in love with these</l>
<l n="436">'And, of all spies the prince, Argicides;</l>
<l n="437">'In well-trimm'd caves their secret meetings made.</l>
<l n="438">'And with the lives of these doth life invade</l>
<l n="439">'Or odorous fir trees, or high-foreheaded oaks,</l>
<l n="440">'Together taking their begetting strokes;</l>
<l n="441">'And have their lives and deaths of equal dates,</l>
<l n="442">'Trees bearing lovely and delightsome states,</l>
<l n="443">'Whom Earth first feeds, that men initiates.</l>
<l n="444">'On her high hills she doth their states sustain,</l>
<l n="445">'And they their own heights raise as high again.</l>
<l n="446">'Their growths together made, nymphs call their groves</l>
<l n="447">'Vow'd to th' immortals services and loves;</l>
<l n="448">'Which men's steels therefore touch not, but let grow.</l>
<l n="449">'But when wise Fates times for their fadings know,</l>
<l n="450">'The fair trees still before their fair nymphs die,</l>
<l n="451">'The bark about them grown corrupt and dry,</l>
<l n="452">'And, all their boughs fall'n, yield to Earth her right;</l>
<l n="453">'And, then the nymphs' lives leave the lovely light.</l>
<l n="454">'And these nymphs, in their caves, shall nurse my son,</l>
<l n="455">'Whom (when in him youth's first grace is begun)</l>
<l n="456">'The nymphs, his nurses, shall present to thee,</l>
<l n="457">'And shew thee what a birth thou hast by me.</l>
<l n="458">'And, sure as now I tell thee all these things,</l>
<l n="459">When Earth hath cloth'd her plants in five fair springs,</l>
<l n="460">'Myself will make return to this retreat,</l>
<l n="461">'And bring that flow'r of thy enamour'd heat;</l>
<l n="462">'Whom when thou then seest, joy shall fire thine eyes:</l>
<l n="463">'He shall so well present the deities.</l>
<l n="464">'And then into thine own care take thy son</l>
<l n="465">'From his calm seat to windy Ilion,</l>
<l n="466">Where, if strict question be upon the past,</l>
<l n="467">'Asking what mother bore beneath her waist</l>
<l n="468">'So dear a son; answer, as I afford</l>
<l n="469">'Fit admonition, nor forget a word;</l>
<l n="470">They say a nymph, call'd Calucopides,</l>
<l n="471">That is with others, an inhabitress</l>
<l n="472">'On this thy wood-crown'd hill, acknowledges</l>
<l n="473">That she his life gave. But if thou declare</l>
<l n="474">'The secret's truth, and art so mad to dare</l>
<l n="475">'(In glory of thy fortunes) to approve</l>
<l n="476">That rich-crown'd Venus mix'd with thee in love;</l>
<pb n="480" facs="#566"/>
<l n="477">'Jove, fir'd with my aspersion so dispread,</l>
<l n="478">'Will, with a wreakful lightning, dart thee dead.</l>
<l n="479">'All now is told thee; comprehend it all.</l>
<l n="480">'Be master of thyself, and do not call</l>
<l n="481">'My name in question; but with reverence vow</l>
<l n="482">'To deities' angers all the awe ye owe.'</l></sp>
<l n="483">This said, she reach'd heaven, where airs ever flow,</l>
<l n="484">And so, O goddess, ever honour'd be,</l>
<l n="485">In thy so odorous Cyprian emperie;</l>
<l n="486">My muse, affecting first thy fame to raise,</l>
<l n="487">Shall make transcension now to others' praise.</l>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
