<text><body><div type="introduction"><head>PREFACE.</head><p>
<cit><quote rend="blockquote">We have learned that the books of Apollodorus are found in ancient Italian manuscripts written in such a way that, if those manuscripts are compared with the editions, we would scarcely consider this writer to resemble himself.</quote>
<bibl>G. Hermann, Preface to the Homeric Hymns, p. XLV.</bibl></cit>

It is good, as a favorable omen, to begin with this statement of a most distinguished man; for, however this knowledge reached him, the remarkable insight, in which he otherwise excelled, also seems to have served him well here, after I discovered in the Vatican Library the manuscript I am now about to publish. For, six years ago, after I had happily traveled through Greece, I settled in Rome to investigate the Greek mythographers, laboring intensely on certain works of Palaephatus, so much so that I was almost on the verge of abandoning this entire subject.

Behold, then, a little book in a rather poor state was delivered into my hands by a “Vatican Angel”—for thus all servants in Italy are called—who claimed it contained “poetic fables and certain grammatical material taken from Eustathius, without beginning or end”, as the catalog described. I immediately recognized that the first part of this codex contained excerpts from Apollodorus’ Library, which had escaped both Janus Parrhasius nearly four centuries ago and, in our time, Angelo Mai. At the same time, it became clear to me that these texts were derived from a far better archetype than all the codices of the libraries.

Therefore, I began to compare this epitome with the text of Apollodorus, and day by day I admired more the excellence of the codex, by means of which it was possible to correct no small part of the almost innumerable corruptions that pollute the library’s text.

The value of these excerpts first became fully evident when I noticed that the epitomator, in his copy, preserved intact that portion of the Library which we had long lamented as having been lost due to the ravages of time. For, in the middle of folio 36, after recounting the slaying of Sinis, where our Library abruptly ends, the excerptor, without the slightest hesitation, proceeds to Theseus’ next labor and describes the remainder of this hero’s life up to the end of folio 38.

Next, advancing to the progeny of Tantalus, and after mentioning Tantalus and Broteas, he gives a more detailed account of the fate of Pelops and his sons, eventually reaching the beginnings of the Trojan War. This history, which continues up to Menelaus’ return, fills nine complete folios (40–49). Now, since it seemed worthwhile in itself to bring to light a new narrative of Trojan matters, the reliability and authority of these excerpts was further enhanced by my observation that they closely align with Proclus’ excerpts from the cyclic poems—something I briefly discussed in my commentary published in Musei Rhenani, Vol. XLI (pp. 134–150).

Thus, upon returning home, I had a double task to fulfill: the first was to publish the words of the epitome, restored through the preserved portion of the Library and my collation efforts. The errors inherent in such a work could scarcely be avoided, and for this, I owe immense gratitude to August Mau, who, with his customary diligence, meticulously compared the text I had reconstructed with the Vatican codex.

In this text, I have corrected only those errors attributable to the scribes of the excerpts so that the genuine form of the epitome, as it was once derived from Apollodorus, might emerge. In the apparatus, I have included all instances where the epitome offers a better reading than the Library or where corruption appears in both sources, adding diacritical marks wherever a definitive judgment was possible. In this way, anyone—without even consulting an edition of the mythographer—can easily perceive the critical relationship between our Vatican manuscript and the codices of Apollodorus.

Indeed, we bring significant benefit to the text of the Library; for in 250 places, our epitome provides a superior reading compared to the codices of the Library, from which nearly 110 new emendations stand out.

In the new excerpts, I relegated to the bottom of the page only the most troublesome scribal errors from the text, preferring to record the rest of my emendations separately. Moreover, I have appended the fragments and testimonies of Apollodorus that exist elsewhere, so that what survives of the lost part of the Library may be found gathered together in one view.

I have added more extensive annotations to the apparatus, in which, beyond explaining individual passages, I have taken care to elucidate Apollodorus’ style and the condition of the other codices I collated. This serves to prepare the way, so to speak, for the edition of the Library I am working on. Much of this material has already been made public on a fitting occasion in my Commentationes Ribbeckianae (On the Interpolations in Apollodorus’ Library, pp. 133–151).

I was then led, prompted by the observation I mentioned above, to undertake a more ambitious effort: namely, to investigate the sources of the Library. You can recognize how slippery and difficult this work is from the fact that the epitomator, apart from one mention of the Little Iliad, never cites his sources. Often, however, the nature of the narratives was such that, even if the author’s name was not clear, the period or poetic tradition became evident; and in such cases, I often chose to stop with a description rather than indulge in empty conjecture.

To achieve greater certainty, I collected every available testimony and version of the fables from all possible sources and compared them with the words of the epitome. This often enabled me to uncover the mythographer’s source. In doing so, it was unavoidable to investigate more closely the history of individual fables. However, while surveying this vast cycle of mythical history, I could not devote as much attention to each myth as would someone whose aim is to catalog the various versions of a single story.

Above all, I could not pursue, nor indeed in this city even attempt, to gather together everything that scholars have ever written about the individual fables and, particularly, about the monuments I occasionally cited. Therefore, if some deeper traces of fables may have escaped me, or if a conjecture of mine has already been published elsewhere in print, I beg forgiveness from those who are more devoted to the study of literature than I am.

I freely admit, moreover, that many of the conclusions I have proposed have not attained the degree of certainty I had hoped for. No one who has entered the arena of mythological studies will be unaware that such difficulties cannot be entirely avoided in a question so fraught with intricacies. Yet, with these commentaries, to which I have not without reason added the title Curae (Studies), I am confident that I have laid some foundation upon which scholars more learned and perceptive than I may build splendid edifices. If they do so, I will rejoice greatly.

For I have, first of all, established that Apollodorus, in his treatment of Trojan matters, made use of a fuller epitome of the cyclic poems—one which was later abridged and excerpted in various ways, eventually finding its way into Proclus’ Chrestomathy and into the preface of the Homeric scholia. Thus, whereas scholars have long labored to reconstruct, from the meager remains, any image of the lost poems, the unexpected use of the Vatican codex now significantly increases our knowledge of the Cypria, the Aethiopis, the Little Iliad, the Iliupersis (Sack of Troy), and the Nostoi (Returns). It has even been possible to conjecture that Stesichorus’ Persis has, in some part, been preserved.

Furthermore, Apollodorus—something others had already suspected—incorporated many tragic plots, likely derived through Asclepiades, into his widely circulated narratives. With the help of these accounts, I have demonstrated through numerous examples that the dramas of Sophocles and Euripides, in particular, can be reconstructed more accurately.

Finally, he seems to have drawn other selected fables, especially those of the Alexandrian poets, perhaps from the works of Philostephanus.

However, let us return from the investigation of sources to an explanation of the condition of the Vatican epitome itself. The so-called Library of Apollodorus was not only read frequently by students but also by grammarians, and was transcribed countless times. This is evident both from the numerous corruptions and interpolations present in all manuscripts, and from the frequent testimonies of later scholia. Were this not the case, one might rightly wonder why, from the earlier compendia of mythical history—sources from which Apollodorus himself derived much of his learning—not even the names of their authors have been preserved to our time.

That this work retained its authority up to the Byzantine period is attested by Tzetzes, who, especially in his commentary on Lycophron’s Alexandra, quotes no author more frequently than Apollodorus.

A certain interpolator <pb n="ix"/> illustrated Zenobius’ proverbs with Apollodorean fables, and around the 14th century, Ioannes Pediasimus, the chartophylax of Bulgaria, transcribed the Labors of Heracles—both of them working with a better archetype than that from which our extant manuscripts are derived.

Thus, when the rebirth of literary studies saw Greek authors returning to Italy, as if exiles from distant lands, Apollodorus was among their number. Yet even at that time, the consensus of the manuscripts shows that the text was already in poor condition and mutilated at the end. Among the crowd of manuscripts, only the Parisinus 4 (no. 2722) stands out slightly.

One might have expected that the scholars of that era would have embraced with great joy this handbook of mythological learning, something they could scarcely have found more useful or convenient. Yet Apollodorus seems to have pleased them less, his style being simple and dry, adorned with neither the elegance of rhetorical flourishes nor the charm of allegorical explanations. As a result, the number of manuscripts is not very large: to the fourteen manuscripts cataloged by Westermann, as far as I know, only two manuscripts in Turin, occasionally cited by Eberhard (in Jahresbericht über die Fortschritte der Altertumswissenschaft, II, p. 1315), and the Barberinus (I. no. 122) can be added. The latter is the most recent and worst of them all, which is why, having just discovered it, I immediately cast it aside.

The kind of authors who caused our mythographer to fall into oblivion will be clear to anyone who has examined the multitude of manuscripts of Palaephatus, Cornutus, and Pediasimus scattered throughout the libraries of Italy.

From four Italian manuscripts, the first edition of Apollodorus was produced by Aegius in Rome in 1555. However, all our modern editions (with the exception of Karl Müller’s, who was the first to use the Parisinus manuscript) have been constructed based on the apparatus compiled long ago by Heyne. It is therefore all the more praiseworthy how well that most learned man, who never laid eyes on a manuscript of Apollodorus himself, served our author. Yet I am equally surprised that neither Bekker nor Hercher considered it worthwhile to revisit the manuscripts. Thus, it frequently happens that I have found in the manuscripts what had already been adopted from scholars’ emendations into our editions, as I explained in note I 1.4 (pp. 79 ff.). However, since all these matters pertain to minor details, not even a complete <pb n="x"/>collation of all manuscripts would yield much gain; rather, all hope rests on the Vatican manuscript, which, as we shall see, does not fail us.

The Vatican manuscript 950, a parchment codex in small octavo format, was written at the end of the 14th century. It now bears the title: “Poetic fables and certain grammatical material from Eustathius, without beginning or end.” Older signatures “N 60” and “SPM sar” have been erased, and the current designation Vat. 950 was added. It consists of 112 folios, but between folios 20 and 21, one folio is missing, between folios 49 and 50, three folios have been cut out, and several more at the end are also missing.

Folio 1, in poor condition, begins with the words:
κασσιέπεια γὰρ ἡ κηφέως γυνή (Library II.4.3.2),
and continues with the story of Perseus, omitting the words from §6: παραγενόμενος — Δίκτυν βασιλέα (“he arrived at Dictys the king”). It proceeds up to §7: ἀθηνᾶ δὲ λαβοῦσα τὴν κεφαλὴν τῆς Γοργόνης ἐν μέσῃ ἀσπίδι (“Athena, taking the head of the Gorgon, placed it in the center of her shield”).

Without any break or title, starting from line 19 on the first page, follows the epitome from Apollodorus’ Library, which I now edit, continuing until the end of folio 49.

At the beginning of folio 50, we read:
Τοσοῦτον ὡς ἐν ταλάρῳ καὶ λίκνῳ αὐτὸν περιστρεφόμενον ἤτοι κουνείω δίκην βρεφυλλίων καθεύδειν, εἰς τέττιγα μετέβαλεν.

These words come from Tzetzes’ commentary on Lycophron v.18. Excerpts from these scholia and from the Chiliads fill the remaining part of the codex.



I was not the first to turn my attention to this manuscript. Already at the beginning of the 16th century, Ianus Parrhasius inspected it, as evidenced by the few words he transcribed from folio 39,<note n="x.1">Ianus Parrhasius (1470–1522), in his book De rebus per epistolam quaesitis (edited by Henricus Stephanus, 1567, p. 20), included the following passage in a letter addressed to Paulus Veiens:

“The one who compiled historical accounts writes as follows: Βροτέας κυνηγὸς ὢν τὴν Ἄρτεμιν οὐκ ἐτίμα·
ἔλεγε δὲ ὡς οὐδ᾽ ὑπὸ πυρός τι πάθοι· ἐμμανὴς οὖν γενόμενος ἔβαλεν
εἰς πῦρ ἑαυτόν (“Broteas, being a hunter, did not honor Artemis; he said that not even fire could harm him. Then, having gone mad, he threw himself into the fire and perished”). (Epistle VIII).

Now, since we know that Parrhasius was an avid lover of books, purchasing numerous and precious manuscripts throughout Italy, one can easily conjecture that our Vatican manuscript was among those in his possession. (See Andresii’s Prodromus to Anecdota Graeca et Latina from the manuscripts of the Royal Library of Naples, 1816, p. XXX ff., and Ianelli’s De vita et scriptis Auli Iani Parrhasii, 1844, p. VII ff. and 157 ff.).

However, Parrhasius, at his death, bequeathed his books to Antonio Seripandi. Antonio’s brother, Hieronymus, placed all these books in the Bibliotheca Carbonaria in Naples, from where they were transferred to the Bourbon Library in 1779.

It is also worth noting what Ianelli remarks (ibid., p. 158):
“When, anxious and in haste, he departed from Rome, it may well have happened that many books he had loaned to friends were either not sought after or not returned.”

Parrhasius had been summoned to Rome in 1513 by Pope Leo X, where he remained until the beginning of 1520 (Ianelli, p. 100 ff.).

Thus, whatever conclusions one may draw about Ianus Parrhasius, it is clear that excerpts from Apollodorus’ Library already existed in Rome at that time.</note> which Gerhard <pb n="xi"/> (in Mus. Rhenanum, VIII, p. 132) unsuccessfully tried to trace.

Later, Angelo Mai thoroughly examined the codex and correctly noted what appears in the middle of folio 69:
ἐκ τῶν διὰ στίχων ἱστορικοῦ βιβλίου τοῦ τζέτζου (“from the line-by-line historical book of Tzetzes”). His marginal annotation reads: “These are excerpts taken from Tzetzes’ Chiliads to the end of the codex. A. M.”

From there, Mai proceeded to study the Chiliads and added notes in the margins of several pages, identifying passages copied by the epitomator:
	•	folio 65: Tzetzes Chiliads I, History 32. A. M.
	•	folio 68: Tzetzes Chiliads III, 96. A. M.
	•	folio 112: Tzetzes Chiliads VII, History 142. A. M.

However, Mai mistakenly believed that the entire codex, from beginning to end, was filled with excerpts from Tzetzes. As a result, this treasure remained hidden in the archives of the renowned library until our time.

I was not the first to turn my attention to this manuscript. At the beginning of the 16th century, Ianus Parrhasius had already examined it, as evidenced by the few words he transcribed from folio 39. Gerhard (Mus. Rhenanum VIII, p. 132) searched in vain to determine where Parrhasius had found them. Later, Angelo Mai carefully investigated the codex and correctly observed the passage in the middle of folio 69: ἐκ τῶν διὰ στίχων ἱστορικοῦ βιβλίου τοῦ Τζέτζου (“from the line-by-line historical book of Tzetzes”), as indicated by his marginal note: “These are excerpts taken from Tzetzes’ Chiliads to the end of the codex. A. M.”

Mai then examined the Chiliads and added references in the margins of several pages identifying passages copied by the epitomator:
	•	Folio 65: Tzetzes Chiliads I, History 32. A. M.
	•	Folio 68: Tzetzes Chiliads III, 96. A. M.
	•	Folio 112: Tzetzes Chiliads VII, History 142. A. M.

However, Mai mistakenly believed that the entire book, from beginning to end, was filled with excerpts from Tzetzes. Thus, this treasure remained hidden in the archives of the renowned library until our time.

The age in which the anonymous author undertook the labor of compiling this epitome cannot be determined by any testimony. But it can be stated with certainty that the Vatican manuscript was not written in the author’s own hand. For there are numerous corruptions foreign to Apollodorus’ codices—so crude that they can only be attributed to the ignorance of scribes (cf. note I 9.1.1). This suggests that the excerpts were copied several times.




And we are led to the same conclusion by the excellence of the manuscript, which, as I have previously explained, far surpasses the archetype from which all other codices are derived. Therefore, it seems very probable that this work also owes its existence to the efforts of the Byzantine grammarians, who, even in the 12th century, are known to have possessed the complete text of the Library.

It is well established that Alexius I, at the beginning of that same century, sought to restore the study of antiquity, founding a school <pb n="xii"/> which may well have been the intended audience for such selections. However, it may even be possible to trace this epitome as far back as the time of Photius or to the 10th century, during which Emperor Constantine Porphyrogenitus devoted immense efforts to compiling selections from the treasures of Greek writers. For it is scarcely credible that within only a few years 250 corruptions could have crept into the text of just thirty-five small folios.

Whoever the author of these excerpts may have been, he certainly did not waste his effort. By preserving a remarkably good and significantly expanded version of the Library, he has ensured its survival for our memory.


In the correction of the printed proofs, my most esteemed friend Franciscus Poland of Dresden assisted me with great diligence, for which, especially in the revision of the Curarum Mythographarum, I gratefully acknowledge my immense debt to him.

Out of pious remembrance, I have dedicated this book, such as it is, to the name of my late uncle, Aemilius Kuhn, who passed away ten years ago. Those who are well-versed in these studies know how greatly he contributed to the understanding of Roman and Greek antiquities. I alone know the noble example of virtue and genuine labor he left for me to emulate.

Written in Dresden at the end of the year 1890.

Richard Wagner.
</p></div></body></text>