<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="eng">The Iliad</title>
            <author>Homer</author>
            <editor>George Chapman</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Initial text generation from OCR and primary TEI XML encoding by</resp>
               <name>Gemini 3.5</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>about 320 p.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">New TEI XML edition started from OCR-generated text under the supervision of Gregory Crane.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Homer</author>
                  <title>Homer's Iliad</title>
                  <title type="sub">translated by George Chapman ; with an introduction by Henry Morley</title>
                  <editor>George Chapman</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>G. Routledge</publisher>
                     <date>1884</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="page">320 p.</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="cm">
                     <height>19</height>
                  </biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>           
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="line" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
               replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']//tei:l[@n='$2'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Line</p>
            </cRefPattern>
            <cRefPattern n="book" matchPattern="(\w+)"
               replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <refState delim="." unit="book"/>
            <refState unit="card"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <refState unit="book" delim="."/>
            <refState unit="line"/>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2026-07-10" who="Gemini 3.5">Initial file creation, OCR text generation, and basic EpiDoc TEI header tagging under Gregory Crane's supervision.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.chapman1611morley1887-eng2" xml:id="book1">
            <pb n="9"/>
            <head>HOMER'S ILIAD.</head>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
               <head>BOOK I.</head>
               
               <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="arg1">
                  <head>ARGUMENT.</head>
                  <l n="1">Apollo's priest to the Argive fleet doth bring</l>
                  <l n="2">Gifts for his daughter, prisoner to the king;</l>
                  <l n="3">For which her tendered freedom he entreats;</l>
                  <l n="4">But, being dismissed with contumelious threats,</l>
                  <l n="5">At Phœbus' hands, by vengeful prayer, he seeks</l>
                  <l n="6">To have a plague inflicted on the Greeks.</l>
                  <l n="7">Which had, Achilles doth a council cite,</l>
                  <l n="8">Emboldening Calchas, in the king's despite,</l>
                  <l n="9">To tell the truth why they were punished so.</l>
                  <l n="10">From hence their fierce and deadly strife did grow.</l>
                  <l n="11">For wrong in which Æacides so raves,</l>
                  <l n="12">That goddess Thetis, from her throne of waves</l>
                  <l n="13">Ascending heaven, of Jove assistance won,</l>
                  <l n="14">To plague the Greeks by absence of her son,</l>
                  <l n="15">And make the general himself repent</l>
                  <l n="16">To wrong so much his army's ornament.</l>
                  <l n="17">This found by Juno, she with Jove contends;</l>
                  <l n="18">Till Vulcan, with heaven's cup, the quarrel ends.</l>
               </div>
               
               <div type="textpart" subtype="argument" n="arg2">
                  <head>ANOTHER ARGUMENT.</head>
                  <l n="1">Alpha the prayer of Chryses sings :</l>
                  <l n="2">The army's plague: the strife of kings.</l>
               </div>
               
               <div type="textpart" subtype="lines" n="body">
                  <l n="1">ACHILLES' baneful wrath resound, O Goddess, that imposed</l>
                  <l n="2">Infinite sorrows on the Greeks, and many brave souls losed</l>
                  <l n="3">From breasts heroic; sent them far to that invisible cave</l>
                  <l n="4">That no light comforts; and their limbs to dogs and vultures gave :</l>
                  <l n="5">To all which Jove's will gave effect; from whom first strife begun</l>
                  <l n="6">Betwixt Atrides, king of men, and Thetis' godlike son.</l>
                  <l n="7">What god gave Eris their command, and oped that fighting vein ?</l>
                  <l n="8">Jove's and Latona's son; who, fired againt the king of men</l>
                  <l n="9">For contumely shown his priest, infectious sickness sent</l>
                  <l n="10">To plague the army, and to death by troops the soldiers went.</l>
                  <l n="11">Occasioned thus: Chryses, the priest, came to the fleet to buy,</l>
                  <l n="12">For presents of unvalued price, his daughter's liberty;</l>
                  <l n="13">The golden sceptre and the crown of Phœbus in his hands</l>
                  <l n="14">Proposing; and made suit to all, but most to the commands</l>
                  <pb n="10"/>
                  <l n="15">Of both the Atrides, who most ruled. "Great Atreus' sons," said he,</l>
                  <l n="16">"And all ye well-greaved Greeks, the gods, whose habitations be</l>
                  <l n="17">In heavenly houses, grace your powers with Priam's razed town,</l>
                  <l n="18">And grant ye happy conduct home! To win which wished renown</l>
                  <l n="19">Of Jove, by honouring his son, far-shooting Phœbus deign</l>
                  <l n="20">For these fit presents to dissolve the ransomable chain</l>
                  <l n="21">Of my loved daughter's servitude." The Greeks entirely gave</l>
                  <l n="22">Glad acclamations, for sign that their desires would have</l>
                  <l n="23">The grave priest reverenced, and his gifts of so much price embraced.</l>
                  <l n="24">The general yet bore no such mind, but viciously disgraced</l>
                  <l n="25">With violent terms the priest, and said :—" Dotard! avoid our fleet,</l>
                  <l n="26">Where lingering be not found by me, nor thy returning feet</l>
                  <l n="27">Let ever visit us again, lest nor thy godhead's crown,</l>
                  <l n="28">Nor sceptre, save thee! Her thou seekest I still will hold mine own</l>
                  <l n="29">Till age deflower her. In our court Argos, far transferred</l>
                  <l n="30">From her loved country, she shall ply her web, and see prepared</l>
                  <l n="31">With all fit ornaments my bed. Incense me then no more,</l>
                  <l n="32">But, if thou wilt be safe, begone." This said, the sea-beat shore,</l>
                  <l n="33">Obeying his high will, the priest trod off with haste and fear;</l>
                  <l n="34">And walking silent, till he left far off his enemies' ear,</l>
                  <l n="35">Phœbus, fair-haired Latona's son, he stirred up with a vow,</l>
                  <l n="36">To this stern purpose : "Hear, thou God that bear'st the silver bow,</l>
                  <l n="37">That Chrysa guard'st, rul'st Tenedos with strong hand, and the round</l>
                  <l n="38">Of Cilla most divine dost walk! O Smintheus! if crowned</l>
                  <l n="39">With thankful offerings thy rich fane I ever saw, or fired</l>
                  <l n="40">Fat thighs of oxen and of goats to thee, this grace desired</l>
                  <l n="41">Vouchsafe to me: pains for my tears let these rude Greeks repay,</l>
                  <l n="42">Forced with thy arrows." Thus he prayed, and Phœbus heard him pray,</l>
                  <l n="43">And, vexed at heart, down from the tops of steep heaven stooped; his bow</l>
                  <l n="44">And quiver covered round, his hands did on his shoulders throw;</l>
                  <l n="45">And of the angry Deity the arrows as he moved</l>
                  <l n="46">Rattled about him. Like the night he ranged the host, and roved</l>
                  <l n="47">(Apart the fleet set) terribly; with his hard-loosing hand</l>
                  <l n="48">His silver bow twanged; and his shafts did first the mules command</l>
                  <l n="49">And swift hounds; then the Greeks themselves his deadly arrows shot,</l>
                  <l n="50">The fires of death went never out; nine days his shafts flew hot</l>
                  <l n="51">About the army; and the tenth, Achilles called a court of all the Greeks;</l>
                  <l n="52">heaven's white-armed Queen (who, everywhere cut short,</l>
                  <l n="53">Beholding her loved Greeks, by death) suggested it; and he</l>
                  <l n="54">(All met in one) arose, and said: "Atrides, now I see</l>
                  <l n="55">We must be wandering again, flight must be still our stay,</l>
                  <l n="56">If flight can save us now, at once sickness and battle lay</l>
                  <l n="57">Such strong hand on us. Let us ask some prophet, priest, or prove</l>
                  <l n="58">Some dream-interpreter (for dreams are often sent from Jove)</l>
                  <l n="59">Why Phœbus is so much incensed; if unperformed vows</l>
                  <l n="60">He blames in us, or hecatombs; and if these knees he bows</l>
                  <l n="61">To death may yield his graves no more, but offering all supply</l>
                  <pb n="11"/>
                  <l n="62">Of savours burnt from lambs and goats, avert his fervent eye,</l>
                  <l n="63">And turn his temperate." Thus he sat, and then stood up to them</l>
                  <l n="64">Calchas, surnamed Thestorides, of augurs the supreme;</l>
                  <l n="65">He knew things present, past, to come, and ruled the equipage</l>
                  <l n="66">Of the Argive fleet to Ilion, for his prophetic rage</l>
                  <l n="67">Given by Apollo; who, well seen in the ill they felt, proposed</l>
                  <l n="68">This to Achilles: "Jove's beloved, would thy charge see disclosed</l>
                  <l n="69">The secret of Apollo's wrath? then covenant and take oath</l>
                  <l n="70">To my discovery, that, with words and powerful actions both,</l>
                  <l n="71">Thy strength will guard the truth in me; because I well conceive</l>
                  <l n="72">That he whose empire governs all, whom all the Grecians give</l>
                  <l n="73">Confirined obedience, will be moved; and then you know the state</l>
                  <l n="74">Of him that moves him. When a king hath once marked for his hate</l>
                  <l n="75">A man inferior, though that day his wrath seems to digest</l>
                  <l n="76">The offence he takes, yet evermore he rakes up in his breast</l>
                  <l n="77">Brands of quick anger, till revenge hath quenched to his desire</l>
                  <l n="78">The fire reserved. Tell me, then, if whatsoever ire</l>
                  <l n="79">Suggests in hurt of me to him, thy valour will prevent?"</l>
                  <l n="80">Achilles answered: "All thou knowest speak, and be confident;</l>
                  <l n="81">For by Apollo, Jove's beloved (to whom performing vows,</l>
                  <l n="82">O Calchas, for the state of Greece, thy spirit prophetic shows</l>
                  <l n="83">Skills that direct us) not a man of all these Grecians here,</l>
                  <l n="84">I living, and enjoying the light shot through this flowery sphere,</l>
                  <l n="85">Shall touch thee with offensive hands: though Agamemnon be</l>
                  <l n="86">The man in question, that doth boast the mightiest empery</l>
                  <l n="87">Of all our army." Then took heart the prophet, unreproved,</l>
                  <l n="88">And said: "They are not unpaid vows, nor hecatombs, that moved</l>
                  <l n="89">The God against us; his offence is for his priest impaired</l>
                  <l n="90">By Agamemnon, that refused the present he preferred,</l>
                  <l n="91">And kept his daughter. This is cause why heaven's Far-darter darts</l>
                  <l n="92">These plagues amongst us; and this still will empty in our hearts</l>
                  <l n="93">His deathful quiver, uncontained till to her loved sire</l>
                  <l n="94">The black-eyed damsel be resigned; no rédemptory hire</l>
                  <l n="95">Took for her freedom, —not a gift, but all the ransom quit,</l>
                  <l n="96">And she conveyed, with sacrifice, till her enfranchised feet</l>
                  <l n="97">Tread Chrysa under; then the God, so pleased perhaps we may</l>
                  <l n="98">Move to remission." Thus, he sate; and up, the great in sway,</l>
                  <l n="99">Heroic Agamemnon rose, eagerly bearing all;</l>
                  <l n="100">His mind's seat overcast with fumes; an anger general</l>
                  <l n="101">Filled all his faculties; his eyes sparkled like kindling fire,</l>
                  <l n="102">Which sternly cast upon the priest, thus vented he his ire :</l>
                  <l n="103">"Prophet of ill; for never good came from thee towards me</l>
                  <l n="104">Not to a word's worth; evermore thou took'st delight to be</l>
                  <l n="105">Offensive in thy auguries, which thou continuest still,</l>
                  <l n="106">Now casting thy prophetic gall, and vouching all our ill,</l>
                  <l n="107">Shot from Apollo, is imposed since I refused the price</l>
                  <l n="108">Of fair Chryseis' liberty; which would in no worth rise</l>
                  <l n="109">To my rate of herself, which moves my vows to have her home,</l>
                  <l n="110">Past Clytemnestra loving her, that graced my nuptial room</l>
                  <l n="111">With her virginity and flower. Nor ask her merits less</l>
                  <l n="112">For person, disposition, wit, and skill in housewiferies.</l>
                  <pb n="12"/>
                  <l n="113">And yet, for all this, she shall go, if more conducible</l>
                  <l n="114">That course be than her holding here. I rather wish the weal</l>
                  <l n="115">Of my loved army than the death. Provide yet instantly</l>
                  <l n="116">Supply for her, that I alone of all our royalty</l>
                  <l n="117">Lose not my winnings. 'Tis not fit. Ye see all I lose mine</l>
                  <l n="118">Forced by another, see as well some other may resign</l>
                  <l n="119">His prize to me." To this replied the swift-foot, god-like son</l>
                  <l n="120">Of Thetis, thus: "King of us all, in all ambition</l>
                  <l n="121">Most covetous of all that breathe, why should the great-souled Greeks</l>
                  <l n="122">Supply thy lost prize out of theirs? Nor what thy avarice seeks</l>
                  <l n="123">Our common treasury can find; so little it doth guard</l>
                  <l n="124">Of what our razed town yielded us; of all which most is shared,</l>
                  <l n="125">And given our soldiers; which again to take into our hands</l>
                  <l n="126">Were igominious and base. Now then, since God commands,</l>
                  <l n="127">Part with thy most loved prize to him; not any one of us</l>
                  <l n="128">Exacts it of thee, yet we all, all loss thou sufferest thus,</l>
                  <l n="129">Will treble, quadruple, in gain, when Jupiter bestows</l>
                  <l n="130">The sack of well-walled Troy on us; which by his word he owes."</l>
                  <l n="131">"Do not deceive yourself with wit," he answered, "god-like man,</l>
                  <l n="132">Though your good name may colour it; 'tis not your swift foot can</l>
                  <l n="133">Outrun me here; nor shall the gloss, set on it with the God,</l>
                  <l n="134">Persuade me to my wrong. Wouldst thou maintain in sure abode</l>
                  <l n="135">Thine own prize, and slight me of mine? Resolve this: if our friends,</l>
                  <l n="136">As fits in equity my worth, will right me with amends,</l>
                  <l n="137">So rest it; otherwise, myself will enter personally</l>
                  <l n="138">On thy prize, that of Ithacus, or Ajax, for supply;</l>
                  <l n="139">Let him on whom I enter rage. But come, we'll order these</l>
                  <l n="140">Hereafter, and in other place. Now put to sacred seas</l>
                  <l n="141">Our black sail; in it rowers put, in it fit sacrifice;</l>
                  <l n="142">And to these I will make ascend my so much envied prize,</l>
                  <l n="143">Bright-cheeked Chryseis. For conduct of all which, we must choose</l>
                  <l n="144">A chief out of our counsellors. Thy service we must use,</l>
                  <l n="145">Idomeneus; Ajax, thine; or thine, wise Ithacus;</l>
                  <l n="146">Or thine, thou terriblest of men, thou son of Peleus,</l>
                  <l n="147">Which fittest were, that thou might'st see these holy acts performed</l>
                  <l n="148">For which thy cunning zeal sopleads ; and he, whose bowthus stormed</l>
                  <l n="149">For our offences, may be calmed." Achilles, with a frown,</l>
                  <l n="150">Thus answered: "O thou impudent! of no good but thine own</l>
                  <l n="151">Ever respectful, but of that with all craft covetous,</l>
                  <l n="152">With what heart can a man attempt a service dangerous,</l>
                  <l n="153">Or at thy voice be spirited to fly upon a foe,</l>
                  <l n="154">Thy mind thus wretched? For myself, I was not injured so</l>
                  <l n="155">By any Trojan, that my powers should bid them any blows;</l>
                  <l n="156">In nothing bear they blame of me; Phthia, whose bosom flows</l>
                  <l n="157">With corn and people, never felt impair of her increase</l>
                  <l n="158">By their invasion; hills enow, and far-resounding seas,</l>
                  <l n="159">Pour out their shades and deeps between; but thee, thou frontless man,</l>
                  <l n="160">We follow, and thy triumphs make with bonfires of our bane ;</l>
                  <l n="161">Thine, and thy brother's, vengeance sought, thou dog's eyes, of this Troy</l>
                  <l n="162">By our exposed lives; whose deserts thou neither dost employ</l>
                  <pb n="13"/>
                  <l n="163">With honour nor with care. And now, thou threat'st to force from me</l>
                  <l n="164">The fruit of my sweat, which the Greeks gave all; and though it be,</l>
                  <l n="165">Compared with thy part, then snatched up, nothing; nor ever is</l>
                  <l n="166">At any sacked town; but of fight, the fetcher in of this,</l>
                  <l n="167">My hands have most share; in whose toils when I have emptied me</l>
                  <l n="168">Of all my forces, my amends in liberality,</l>
                  <l n="169">Though it be little, I accept, and turn pleased to my tent;</l>
                  <l n="170">And yet that little thou esteem'st too great a continent</l>
                  <l n="171">In thy incontinent avarice. For Phthia therefore now</l>
                  <l n="172">My course is; since 'tis better far than here to endure that thou</l>
                  <l n="173">Should'st still be ravishing my right, draw my whole treasure dry,</l>
                  <l n="174">And add dishonour." He replied: "If thy heart serve thee, flee;</l>
                  <l n="175">Stay not for my cause; other here will aid and honour me;</l>
                  <l n="176">If not, yet Jove I know is sure; that counsellor is he</l>
                  <l n="177">That I depend on. As for thee, of all our Jove-kept kings</l>
                  <l n="178">Thou still art most mine enemy; strifes, battles, bloody things,</l>
                  <l n="179">Make thy blood-feasts still. But if strength, that these moods build upon,</l>
                  <l n="180">Flow in thy nerves, God gave thee it; and so 'tis not thine own,</l>
                  <l n="181">But in his hands still. What then lifts thy pride in this so high?</l>
                  <l n="182">Home with thy fleet, and Myrmidons; use there their empery;</l>
                  <l n="183">Command not here. I weigh thee not, nor mean to magnify</l>
                  <l n="184">Thy rough-hewn rages, but, instead, I thus far threaten thee :</l>
                  <l n="185">Since Phœbus needs will force from me Chryseis, she shall go ;</l>
                  <l n="186">My ships and friends shall waft her home; but I will imitate so</l>
                  <l n="187">His pleasure, that mine own shall take, in person, from thy tent</l>
                  <l n="188">Bright-cheeked Briseis; and so tell thy strength how eminent</l>
                  <l n="189">My power is, being compared with thine; all other making fear</l>
                  <l n="190">To vaunt equality with me, or in this proud kind bear</l>
                  <l n="191">Their beards against me." Thetis's son at this stood vexed, his heart</l>
                  <l n="192">Bristled his bosom, and two ways drew his discursive part;</l>
                  <l n="193">If, from his thigh his sharp sword drawn, he should make room about</l>
                  <l n="194">Atrides' person slaughtering him, or sit his anger out,</l>
                  <l n="195">And curb his spirit. While these thoughts strived in his blood and mind,</l>
                  <l n="196">And he his sword drew, down froin heaven Athenia stooped, and shined</l>
                  <l n="197">About his temples, being sent by the ivory-wristed Queen</l>
                  <l n="198">Saturnia, who out of her heart had ever loving been</l>
                  <l n="199">And careful for the good of both. She stood behind, and took</l>
                  <l n="200">Achilles by the yellow curls, and only gave her look</l>
                  <l n="201">To him; appearance not a man of all the rest could see.</l>
                  <l n="202">He turning back his eye, amaze strook every faculty;</l>
                  <l n="203">Yet straight he knew her by her eyes, so terrible they were,</l>
                  <l n="204">Sparkling with ardour, and thus spake : "Thou seed of Jupiter,</l>
                  <l n="205">Why comest thou? To behold his pride that boasts our empery?</l>
                  <l n="206">Then witness with it my revenge, and see that insolence die</l>
                  <l n="207">That lives to wrong me." She replied: "I come from heaven to see</l>
                  <l n="208">Thine anger settled, if thy soul will use her sovereignty</l>
                  <l n="209">In fit reflection. I am sent from Juno, whose affects</l>
                  <l n="210">Stand heartily inclined to both, Come, give us both respects,</l>
                  <pb n="14"/>
                  <l n="211">And cease contention; draw no sword; use words, and such as may</l>
                  <l n="212">Be bitter to his pride, but just; for trust in what I say,</l>
                  <l n="213">A time shall come, when, thrice the worth of that he forceth now,</l>
                  <l n="214">He shall propose for recompense of these wrongs; therefore throw</l>
                  <l n="215">Reins on thy passions, and serve us." He answered: "Though my heart</l>
                  <l n="216">Burn in just anger, yet my soul must conquer the angry part,</l>
                  <l n="217">And yield you conquest. Who subdues his earthy part for heaven,</l>
                  <l n="218">Heaven to his prayers subdues his wish." This said, her charge was given</l>
                  <l n="219">Fit honour; in his silver hilt he held his able hand,</l>
                  <l n="220">And forced his broad sword up; and up to heaven did re-ascend</l>
                  <l n="221">Minerva, who, in Jove's high roof that bears the rough shield, took</l>
                  <l n="222">Her place with other deities. She gone, again forsook</l>
                  <l n="223">Patience his passion, and no more his silence could confine his wine,</l>
                  <l n="224">His wrath, that this broad language gave: "Thou ever steeped in wine,</l>
                  <l n="225">Dog's face, with heart but of a hart, that nor in the open eye</l>
                  <l n="226">Of fight dar'st thrust into a prease, nor with our noblest lie</l>
                  <l n="227">In secret ambush! These works seem too full of death for thee;</l>
                  <l n="228">'Tis safer far in the open host to dare an injury</l>
                  <l n="229">To any crosser of thy lust. Thou subject-eating king !</l>
                  <l n="230">Base spirits thou govern'st, or this wrong had been the last foul thing</l>
                  <l n="231">Thou ever author'dst; yet I vow, and by a great oath swear,</l>
                  <l n="232">Even by this sceptre, that, as this never again shall bear</l>
                  <l n="233">Green leaves or branches, nor increase with any growth his size,</l>
                  <l n="234">Nor did since first it left the hills, and had his faculties</l>
                  <l n="235">And ornaments bereft with iron; which now to other end</l>
                  <l n="236">Judges of Greece bear, and their laws, received from Jove, defend</l>
                  <l n="237">(For which my oath to thee is great); so, whensoever need</l>
                  <l n="238">Shall burn with thirst of me thy host, no prayers shall ever breed</l>
                  <l n="239">Affection in me to their aid, though well-deserved woes</l>
                  <l n="240">Afflict thee for them, when to death man-slaughtering Hector throws</l>
                  <l n="241">Whole troops of them, and thou torment'st thy vexed mind with conceit</l>
                  <l n="242">Of thy rude rage now, and his wrong that most deserved the right</l>
                  <l n="243">Of all thy army." Thus, he threw his sceptre against the ground,</l>
                  <l n="244">With golden studs stuck, and took seat. Atrides' breast was drowned</l>
                  <l n="245">In rising choler. Up to both sweet-spoken Nestor stood,</l>
                  <l n="246">The cunning Pylian orator, whose tongue poured forth a flood</l>
                  <l n="247">Of more-than-honey-sweet discourse; two ages were increased</l>
                  <l n="248">Of divers-languaged men, all born in his time and deceased</l>
                  <l n="249">In sacred Pylos, where he reigned amongst the third aged men,</l>
                  <l n="250">He, well-seen in the world, advised, and thus expressed it then :</l>
                  <l n="251">"O Gods! Our Greek earth will be drowned in just tears; rapeful Troy,</l>
                  <l n="252">Her king, and all his sons, will make as just a mock, and joy,</l>
                  <l n="253">Of these disjunctions; if of you, that all our host excel</l>
                  <l n="254">In counsel and in skill of fight, they hear this. Come, repel</l>
                  <l n="255">These young men's passions. Ye are not both, put both your years in one</l>
                  <l n="256">So old as I. I lived long since, and was companion</l>
                  <l n="257">With men superior to you both, who yet would ever hear</l>
                  <l n="258">My counsels with respect. Mine eyes yet never witness were,</l>
                  <pb n="15"/>
                  <l n="259">Nor ever will be, of such men as then delighted them :</l>
                  <l n="260">Pirithous, Exadius, and god-like Polypheme,</l>
                  <l n="261">Cæneus, and Dryas prince of men, Ægean Theseus,</l>
                  <l n="262">A man like heaven's immortals formed; all, all most vigorous,</l>
                  <l n="263">Of all men that even those days bred; most vigorous men, and fought with beasts most vigorous,</l>
                  <l n="264">mountain beasts (for men in strength were nought</l>
                  <l n="265">Matched with their forces) fought with them, and bravely fought them down.</l>
                  <l n="266">Yet even with these men I conversed, being called to the renown</l>
                  <l n="267">Of their societies, by their suits from Pylos far, to fight</l>
                  <l n="268">In the Asian kingdom; and I fought, to a degree of might</l>
                  <l n="269">That helped even their mights, against such as no man now would dare</l>
                  <l n="270">To meet in conflict; yet even these my counsels still would hear,</l>
                  <l n="271">And with obedience crown my words. Give you such palm to them;</l>
                  <l n="272">'Tis better than to wreath your wrath. Atrides, give not stream</l>
                  <l n="273">To all thy power, nor force his prise, but yield her still his own,</l>
                  <l n="274">As all men else do. Nor do thou encounter with thy crown,</l>
                  <l n="275">Great son of Peleus, since no king that ever Jove allowed</l>
                  <l n="276">Grace of a sceptre equals him. Suppose thy nerves endowed</l>
                  <l n="277">With strength superior, and thy birth a very goddess gave,</l>
                  <l n="278">Yet he of force is mightier, since what his own nerves have</l>
                  <l n="279">Is amplified with just command of many other. King of men,</l>
                  <l n="280">Command thou then thyself; and I with my prayers will obtain</l>
                  <l n="281">Grace of Achilles to subdue his fury; whose parts are</l>
                  <l n="282">Worth our entreaty, being chief check to all our ill in war."</l>
                  <l n="283">"All this, good father," said the king, " is comely and good right;</l>
                  <l n="284">But this man breaks all such bonds; he affects, past all men, height;</l>
                  <l n="285">All would in his power hold, all make his subjects, give to all</l>
                  <l n="286">His hot will for a temperate law; all which he never shall</l>
                  <l n="287">Persuade at my hands. If the gods have given him the great style</l>
                  <l n="288">Of ablest soldier, made they that his licence to revile</l>
                  <l n="289">Men with vile language?" Thetis' son prevented him, and said :</l>
                  <l n="290">"Fearful and vile I might be thought, if the exactions laid</l>
                  <l n="291">By all means on me I should bear. Others command to this,</l>
                  <l n="292">Thou shalt not me; or if thou dost, far my free spirit is</l>
                  <l n="293">From serving thy command. Besides, this I affirm (afford</l>
                  <l n="294">Impression of it in thy soul) I will not use my sword</l>
                  <l n="295">On thee or any for a wench, unjustly though thou takest the thing thou gavest;</l>
                  <l n="296">but all things else that in my ship thou makest</l>
                  <l n="297">Greedy survey of, do not touch without my leave; or do, —</l>
                  <l n="298">Add that act's wrong to this, that these may see that outrage too, —</l>
                  <l n="299">And then comes my part; then be sure thy blood upon my lance</l>
                  <l n="300">Shall flow in vengeance." These high terms these two at variance</l>
                  <l n="301">Used to each other; left their seats; and after them arose the whole court.</l>
                  <l n="302">To his tents and ships, with friends and soldiers, goes</l>
                  <l n="303">Angry Achilles. Atreus' son the swift ship launched, and put</l>
                  <l n="304">Within it twenty chosen rowers, within it likewise shut</l>
                  <l n="305">The hecatomb to appease the God; then caused to come aboard</l>
                  <l n="306">Fair-cheeked Chryseis; for the chief, he in whom Pallas poured</l>
                  <l n="307">Her store of counsels, Ithacus, aboard went last; and then</l>
                  <pb n="16"/>
                  <l n="308">The moist ways of the sea they sailed. And now the king of men</l>
                  <l n="309">Bade all the host to sacrifice. They sacrificed and cast</l>
                  <l n="310">The offal of all to the deeps; the angry God they grace</l>
                  <l n="311">With perfect hecatombs; some bulls, some goats, along the shore</l>
                  <l n="312">Of the unfruitful sea, inflamed. To heaven the thick fumes bore</l>
                  <l n="313">Enwrapped savours. Thus, though all the politic king made show</l>
                  <l n="314">Respects to heaven, yet he himself all that time did pursue</l>
                  <l n="315">His own affections; the late jar, in which he thundered threats</l>
                  <l n="316">Against Achilles, still he fed, and his affections' heats</l>
                  <l n="317">Thus vented to Talthybius, and grave Eurybates</l>
                  <l n="318">Heralds, and ministers of trust, to all his messages.</l>
                  <l n="319">"Haste to Achilles' tent; where take Briseis' hand, and bring</l>
                  <l n="320">Her beauties to us. If he fail to yield her, say your king</l>
                  <l n="321">Will come himself, with multitudes that shall the horribler</l>
                  <l n="322">Make both his presence, and your charge, that so he dares defer."</l>
                  <l n="323">This said, he sent them with a charge of hard condition.</l>
                  <l n="324">They went unwillingly, and trod the fruitless sea's shore; soon</l>
                  <l n="325">They reached the navy and the tents, in which the quarter lay</l>
                  <l n="326">Of all the Myrmidons, and found the chief Chief in their sway</l>
                  <l n="327">Set at his black bark in his tent. Nor was Achilles glad</l>
                  <l n="328">To see their presence; nor themselves in any glory had their message;</l>
                  <l n="329">but with reverence stood, and feared the offended king,</l>
                  <l n="330">Asked not the dame, nor spake a word. He yet, well knowing the thing</l>
                  <l n="331">That caused their coming, graced them thus: "Heralds, ye men that bear</l>
                  <l n="332">The messages of men and gods, ye are welcome, come ye near.</l>
                  <l n="333">I nothing blame you, but your king 'tis be he, I know, doth send</l>
                  <l n="334">You for Briseis; she is his. Patroclus, honoured friend,</l>
                  <l n="335">Bring forth the damsel, and these men let lead her to their lord.</l>
                  <l n="336">But, heralds, be you witnesses before the most adored,</l>
                  <l n="337">Before us mortals, and before your most ungentle king,</l>
                  <l n="338">Of what I suffer, that, if war ever hereafter bring</l>
                  <l n="339">My aid in question, to avert any severest bane</l>
                  <l n="340">It brings on others, I am 'scused to keep mine aid in wane,</l>
                  <l n="341">Since they mine honour. But your king, in tempting mischief, raves,</l>
                  <l n="342">Nor sees at once by present present things the future ; how like waves</l>
                  <l n="343">Ills follow ills; injustices being never so secure</l>
                  <l n="344">In present times, but after-plagues even then are seen as sure;</l>
                  <l n="345">Which yet he sees not, and so soothes his present lust, which checked</l>
                  <l n="346">Would check plagues future; and he might, in succouring right, protect</l>
                  <l n="347">Such as fight for his right at fleet. They still in safety fight</l>
                  <l n="348">That fight still justly." This speech used, Patroclus did the rite</l>
                  <l n="349">His friend commanded, and brought forth Briseis from her tent,</l>
                  <l n="350">Gave her the heralds, and away to the Achive ships they went.</l>
                  <l n="351">She sad, and scarce for grief could go. Her love all friends forsook,</l>
                  <l n="352">And wept for anger. To the shore of the old sea he betook</l>
                  <l n="353">Himself alone, and casting forth upon the purple sea</l>
                  <l n="354">His wet eyes, and his hands to heaven advancing, this sad plea</l>
                  <l n="355">Made to his mother: "Mother! since you brought me forth to breathe</l>
                  <l n="356">So short a life, Olympius had good right to bequeath</l>
                  <pb n="17"/>
                  <l n="357">My short life honour; yet that right he doth in no degree,</l>
                  <l n="358">But lets Atrides do me shame, and force that prize from me</l>
                  <l n="359">That all the Greeks gave." This with tears he uttered, and she heard,</l>
                  <l n="360">Set with her old sire in his deeps, and instantly appeared</l>
                  <l n="361">Up from the grey sea like a cloud, sate by his side, and said :</l>
                  <l n="362">"Why weeps my son? What grieves thee? Speak, conceal not what hath laid</l>
                  <l n="363">Such hard hand on thee, let both know." He, sighing like a storm,</l>
                  <l n="364">Replied: "Thou dost know. Why should I things known again inform?</l>
                  <l n="365">We marched to Thebes, the sacred town of King Eëtion,</l>
                  <l n="366">Sacked it, and brought to fleet the spoil, which every valiant son</l>
                  <l n="367">Of Greece indifferently shared. Atrides had for share</l>
                  <l n="368">Fair-cheeked Chryseis. After which, his priest, that shoots so far,</l>
                  <l n="369">Chryses, the fair Chryseis' sire, arrived at th' Achive fleet,</l>
                  <l n="370">With infinite ransom, to redeem the dear imprisoned feet</l>
                  <l n="371">Of his fair daughter. In his hands he held Apollo's crown,</l>
                  <l n="372">And golden sceptre; making suit to every Grecian son,</l>
                  <l n="373">But most the sons of Atreus, the others' orderers,</l>
                  <l n="374">Yet they least heard him; all the rest received with reverend ears</l>
                  <l n="375">The motion, both the priest and gifts gracing, and holding worth</l>
                  <l n="376">His wished acceptance. Atreus' son yet (vexed) commanded forth</l>
                  <l n="377">With rude terms Phœbus' reverend priest; who, angry, made retreat,</l>
                  <l n="378">And prayed to Phœbus, in whose grace he standing passing great</l>
                  <l n="379">Got his petition. The God an ill shaft sent abroad</l>
                  <l n="380">That tumbled down the Greeks in heaps. The host had no abode</l>
                  <l n="381">That was not visited. We asked a prophet that well knew</l>
                  <l n="382">The cause of all; and from his lips Apollo's prophecies flew,</l>
                  <l n="383">Telling his anger. First myself exhorted to appease</l>
                  <l n="384">The angered God, which Atreus' son did at the heart displease;</l>
                  <l n="385">And up he stood, used threats, performed. The black-eyed Greeks sent home</l>
                  <l n="386">Chryseis to her sire, and gave his God a hecatomb.</l>
                  <l n="387">Then, for Briseis, to my tents Atrides' heralds came,</l>
                  <l n="388">And took her that the Greeks gave all. If then thy powers can frame</l>
                  <l n="389">Wreak for thy son, afford it. Scale Olympus, and implore</l>
                  <l n="390">Jove (if by either word or fact thou ever didst restore</l>
                  <l n="391">Joy to his grieved heart) now to help. I oft have heard thee vaunt</l>
                  <l n="392">In court of Peleus, that alone thy hand was conversant</l>
                  <l n="393">In rescue from a cruel spoil the black cloud-gathering Jove,</l>
                  <l n="394">Whom other Godheads would have bound (the Power whose pace doth move</l>
                  <l n="395">The round earth, heaven's great Queen, and Pallas); to whose bands</l>
                  <l n="396">Thou cam'st with rescue, bringing up him with the hundred hands</l>
                  <l n="397">To great Olympus, whom the Gods call Briareus, men</l>
                  <l n="398">Ægæon, who his sire surpassed, and was as strong again,</l>
                  <l n="399">And in that grace sat glad by Jove. Th' immortals stood dismayed</l>
                  <l n="400">At his ascension, and gave free passage to his aid.</l>
                  <l n="401">Of all this tell Jove; kneel to him, embrace his knee, and pray,</l>
                  <l n="402">If Troy's aid he will ever deign, that now their forces may</l>
                  <l n="403">Beat home the Greeks to fleet and sea; embruing their retreat</l>
                  <l n="404">In slaughter; their pains paying the wreak of their proud sovereign's heat;</l>
                  <pb n="12"/>
                  <l n="405">And that far-ruling king may know from his poor soldier's harms</l>
                  <l n="406">His own harm falls; his own and all in mine, his best in arms."</l>
                  <l n="407">Her answer she poured out in tears: "O me, my son," said she,</l>
                  <l n="408">"Why brought I up thy being at all, that brought thee forth to be</l>
                  <l n="409">Sad subject of so hard a fate? O would to heaven, that since</l>
                  <l n="410">Thy fate is little, and not long, thou might'st without offence</l>
                  <l n="411">And tears perform it! But to live thrall to so stern a fate</l>
                  <l n="412">As grants thee least life, and that least so most unfortunate,</l>
                  <l n="413">Grieves me to have given thee any life. But what thou wishest now,</l>
                  <l n="414">If Jove will grant, I'll up and ask; Olympus crowned with snow</l>
                  <l n="415">I'li climb; but sit thou fast at fleet, renounce all war, and feed</l>
                  <l n="416">Thy heart with wrath, and hope of wreak; till which come, thou shalt need</l>
                  <l n="417">A little patience. Jupiter went yesterday to feast</l>
                  <l n="418">Amongst the blameless Æthiops, in th' ocean's deepened breast,</l>
                  <l n="419">All Gods attending him; the twelfth, high heaven again he sees,</l>
                  <l n="420">And then his brass-paved court I'll scale, cling to his powerful knees,</l>
                  <l n="421">And doubt not but to win thy wish." Thus, made she her remove,</l>
                  <l n="422">And left wrath tyring on her son for his enforced love.</l>
                  <l n="423">Ulysses, with the hecatomb, arrived at Chrysa's shore;</l>
                  <l n="424">And when amidst the haven't deep mouth they came to use the oar,</l>
                  <l n="425">They straight struck sail, then rolled them up, and on the hatches threw;</l>
                  <l n="426">The top-mast to the kelsine then with halyards down they drew;</l>
                  <l n="427">Then brought the ship to port with oars; then forked anchor cast;</l>
                  <l n="428">And, against the violence of storm, for drifting made her fast.</l>
                  <l n="429">All come ashore, they all exposed the holy hecatomb</l>
                  <l n="430">To angry Phœbus, and, with it, Chryseis welcomed home ;</l>
                  <l n="431">Whom to her sire, wise Ithacus, that did at the altar stand,</l>
                  <l n="432">For honour, led, and, speaking thus, resigned her to his hand :</l>
                  <l n="433">"Chryseis, the mighty king of men, great Agamemnon sends</l>
                  <l n="434">Thy loved seed by my hands to thine; and to thy God commends</l>
                  <l n="435">A hecatomb, which my charge is to sacrifice, and seek</l>
                  <l n="436">Our much-sigh-mixed woe his recure, invoked by every Greek."</l>
                  <l n="437">Thus he resigned her, and her sire received her highly joyed.</l>
                  <l n="438">About the well-built altar, then, they orderly employed</l>
                  <l n="439">The sacred offering, washed their hands, took salt cakes; and the priest,</l>
                  <l n="440">With hands held up to heaven, thus prayed: "O thou that all things seest,</l>
                  <l n="441">Fautour of Chrysa, whose fair hand doth guardfully dispose</l>
                  <l n="442">Celestial Cilla, governing in all power Tenedos,</l>
                  <l n="443">O hear thy priest, and as thy hand, in free grace to my prayers,</l>
                  <l n="444">Shot fervent plague-shafts through the Greeks, now hearten their affairs</l>
                  <l n="445">With health renewed, and quite remove th'infection from their blood."</l>
                  <l n="446">He prayed; and to his prayers again the God propitious stood.</l>
                  <l n="447">All, after prayer, cast on salt cakes, drew back, killed, flayed the beeves,</l>
                  <l n="448">Cut out and dubbed with fat their thighs, fair dressed with doubled leaves,</l>
                  <l n="449">And on them all the sweetbreads pricked. The priest, with small sere wood,</l>
                  <l n="450">Did sacrifice, poured on red wine; by whom the young men stood,</l>
                  <l n="451">And turned, in five ranks, spits. On which (the legs enough) they eat</l>
                  <pb n="19"/>
                  <l n="452">The inwards; then in giggots cut the other fit for meat,</l>
                  <l n="453">And put to fire; which roasted well they drew. The labour done,</l>
                  <l n="454">They served the feast in that fed all to satisfaction.</l>
                  <l n="455">Desire of meat and wine thus quenched, the youths crowned cups of wine,</l>
                  <l n="456">Drunk off, and filled again to all. That day was held divine,</l>
                  <l n="457">And spent in pæans to the Sun, who heard with pleased ear;</l>
                  <l n="458">When whose bright chariot stooped to sea, and twilight hid the clear,</l>
                  <l n="459">All soundly on their cables slept, even till the night was worn.</l>
                  <l n="460">And when the Lady of the light, the rosy-fingered Morn,</l>
                  <l n="461">Rose from the hills, all fresh arose, and to the camp retired.</l>
                  <l n="462">Apollo with a fore-right wind their swelling bark inspired.</l>
                  <l n="463">The top-mast hoisted, milk-white sails on his round breast they put,</l>
                  <l n="464">The mizens strooted with the gale, the ship her course did cut</l>
                  <l n="465">So swiftly that the parted waves against her ribs did roar;</l>
                  <l n="466">Which, coming to the camp, they drew aloft the sandy shore;</l>
                  <l n="467">Where, laid on stocks, each soldier kept his quarter as before.</l>
                  <l n="468">But Peleus' son, swift-foot Achilles, at his swift ships sate</l>
                  <l n="469">Burning in wrath, nor ever came to councils of estate</l>
                  <l n="470">That make men honoured, never trod the fierce embattled field,</l>
                  <l n="471">But kept close, and his loved heart pined, what fight and cries could yield</l>
                  <l n="472">Thirsting at all parts to the host. And now, since first he told</l>
                  <l n="473">His wrongs to Thetis, twelve fair morns their ensigns did unfold,</l>
                  <l n="474">And then the ever-living Gods mounted Olympus, Jove</l>
                  <l n="475">First in ascension. Thetis then remembered well to move</l>
                  <l n="476">Achilles' motion, rose from sea, and, by the morn's first light</l>
                  <l n="477">The great heaven and Olympus climbed; where, in supremest height</l>
                  <l n="478">Of all that many-headed hill, she saw the far-seen son</l>
                  <l n="479">Of Saturn, set from all the rest, in his free seat alone.</l>
                  <l n="480">Before whom, on her own knees fall'n, the knees of Jupiter</l>
                  <l n="481">Her left hand held, her right his chin, and thus she did prefer</l>
                  <l n="482">Her son's petition: "Father Jove! If ever I have stood</l>
                  <l n="483">Aidful to thee in word or work, with this implored good</l>
                  <l n="484">Requite my aid, renown my son, since in so short a race</l>
                  <l n="485">(Past others) thou confin'st his life. An insolent disgrace</l>
                  <l n="486">Is done him by the king of men; he forced from him a prize</l>
                  <l n="487">Won with his sword. But thou, O Jove, that art most strong, most wise,</l>
                  <l n="488">Honour my son for my sake; add strength to the Trojans' side</l>
                  <l n="489">By his side's weakness in his want; and see Troy amplified</l>
                  <l n="490">In conquest, so much and so long, till Greece may give again</l>
                  <l n="491">The glory reft him, and the more illustrate the free reign</l>
                  <l n="492">Of his wronged honour." Jove at this sate silent; not a word</l>
                  <l n="493">In long space passed him. Thetis still hung on his knee, implored</l>
                  <l n="494">The second time his help, and said: "Grant or deny my suit,</l>
                  <l n="495">Be free in what thou dost; I know thou canst not sit thus mute</l>
                  <l n="496">For fear of any; speak, deny, that so I may be sure</l>
                  <l n="497">Of all heaven's Goddesses, 'tis I that only must endure</l>
                  <l n="498">Dishonour by thee." Jupiter, the great cloud-gatherer, grieved</l>
                  <l n="499">With thought of what a world of griefs this suit asked, being achieved,</l>
                  <l n="500">Swelled, sighed, and answered : "Works of death thou urgest. O at this</l>
                  <l n="501">Juno will storm, and all my powers inflame with contumelies,</l>
                  <pb n="20"/>
                  <l n="502">Ever she wrangles, charging me in ear of all the Gods</l>
                  <l n="503">That I am partial still, that I add the displeasing odds</l>
                  <l n="504">Of my aid to the Ilians. Begone then, lest she see;</l>
                  <l n="505">Leave thy request to my care; yet, that trust may hearten thee</l>
                  <l n="506">With thy desire's grant, and my power to give it act approve</l>
                  <l n="507">How vain her strife is, to thy prayer my eminent head shall move;</l>
                  <l n="508">Which is the great sign of my will with all th' immortal states;</l>
                  <l n="509">Irrevocable; never fails; never without the rates</l>
                  <l n="510">Of all powers else; when my head bows, all heads bow with it still</l>
                  <l n="511">As their first mover; and gives power to any work I will."</l>
                  <l n="512">He said; and his black eyebrows bent; above his deathless head</l>
                  <l n="513">The ambrosian curls flowed; great heaven shook; and both were severed;</l>
                  <l n="514">Their counsels broken. To the depths of Neptune's kingdom dived</l>
                  <l n="515">Thetis from heaven's height; Jove arose, and all the Gods received</l>
                  <l n="516">(All rising from their thrones) their sire, attending to his court.</l>
                  <l n="517">None sate when he rose, none delayed the furnishing his port</l>
                  <l n="518">Till he came near, all met with him, and brought him to his throne.</l>
                  <l n="519">Nor sate great Juno ignorant, when she beheld alone</l>
                  <l n="520">Old Nereus' silver-footed seed with Jove, that she had brought</l>
                  <l n="521">Counsels to heaven; and straight her tongue had teeth in it, that wrought</l>
                  <l n="522">This sharp invective : "Who was that (thou craftiest counsellor</l>
                  <l n="523">Of all the Gods) that so apart some secret did implore?</l>
                  <l n="524">Ever, apart from me, thou lovest to counsel and decree</l>
                  <l n="525">Things of more close trust than thou think'st are fit t' impart to me.</l>
                  <l n="526">Whatever thou determin'st, I must ever be denied</l>
                  <l n="527">The knowledge of it by thy will." To her speech thus replied</l>
                  <l n="528">The Father both of men and Gods : "Have never hope to know</l>
                  <l n="529">My whole intentions, though my wife; it fits not, nor would show</l>
                  <l n="530">Well to thine own thoughts: but what fits thy woman's ear to hear,</l>
                  <l n="531">Woman, nor man, nor God, shall know before it grace thine ear.</l>
                  <l n="532">Yet, what apart from men and Gods I please to know, forbear</l>
                  <l n="533">T' examine or inquire of that." She with the cow's fair eyes,</l>
                  <l n="534">Respected Juno, this returned: "Austere king of the skies,</l>
                  <l n="535">What hast thou uttered? When did I before this time inquire</l>
                  <l n="536">Or sift thy counsels? Passing close you are still. Your desire</l>
                  <l n="537">Is served with such care, that I fear you can scarce vouch the deed</l>
                  <l n="538">That makes it public; being seduced by this old sea-god's seed,</l>
                  <l n="539">That could so early use her knces, embracing thine. I doubt</l>
                  <l n="540">The late act of thy bowed head was for the working out</l>
                  <l n="541">Of some boon she asked; that her son thy partial hand would please</l>
                  <l n="542">With plaguing others." "Wretch!" said he, "thy subtle jealousies</l>
                  <l n="543">Are still exploring; my designs can never 'scape thine eye,</l>
                  <l n="544">Which yet thou never canst prevent. Thy curiosity</l>
                  <l n="545">Makes thee less cared for at my hands, and horrible the end</l>
                  <l n="546">Shall make thy humour. If it be what thy suspects intend,</l>
                  <l n="547">What then? 'Tis my free will it should; to which let way be given</l>
                  <l n="548">With silence. Curb your tongue in time, lest all the Gods in heaven</l>
                  <l n="549">Too few be and too weak to help thy punished insolence,</l>
                  <l n="550">When my inaccessible hands shall fall on thee." The sense</l>
                  <pb n="21"/>
                  <l n="551">Of this high threatening made her fear, and silent she sate down,</l>
                  <l n="552">Humbling her great heart. All the Gods in court of Jove did frown</l>
                  <l n="553">At this offence given; amongst whom heaven's famous artizan,</l>
                  <l n="554">Ephaistus, in his mother's care this comely speech began :</l>
                  <l n="555">"Believe it, these words will breed wounds beyond our powers to bear,</l>
                  <l n="556">If thus for mortals ye fall out. Ye make a tumult here</l>
                  <l n="557">That spoils our banquet. Evermore worst matters put down best.</l>
                  <l n="558">But, mother, though yourself be wise, yet let your son request</l>
                  <l n="559">His wisdom audience. Give good terms to our loved father Jove,</l>
                  <l n="560">For fear he take offence again, and our kind banquet prove</l>
                  <l n="561">A wrathful battle. If he will, the heavenly Light'ner can</l>
                  <l n="562">Take you and toss you from your throne, his power Olympian</l>
                  <l n="563">Is so surpassing. Soften then with gentle speech his spleen,</l>
                  <l n="564">And drink to him; I know his heart will quickly down again."</l>
                  <l n="565">This said, arising from his throne, in his loved mother's hand</l>
                  <l n="566">He put the double-handed cup, and said: "Come, do not stand</l>
                  <l n="567">On these cross humours, suffer, bear, though your great bosom grieve,</l>
                  <l n="568">And lest blows force you, all my aid not able to relieve</l>
                  <l n="569">Your hard condition, though these eyes behold it, and this heart</l>
                  <l n="570">Sorrow to think it. 'Tis a task too dangerous to take part</l>
                  <l n="571">Against Olympius. I myself the proof of this still feel.</l>
                  <l n="572">When other Gods would fain have helped, he took me by the heel,</l>
                  <l n="573">And hurled me out of heaven. All day I was in falling down;</l>
                  <l n="574">At length in Lemnos I struck earth. The likewise-falling sun</l>
                  <l n="575">And I, together, set; my life almost set too; yet there</l>
                  <l n="576">The Sintii cheered and took me up." This did to laughter cheer</l>
                  <l n="577">White-wristed Juno, who now took the cup of him and smiled.</l>
                  <l n="578">The sweet peace-making draught went round, and lame Ephaistus filled</l>
                  <l n="579">Nectar to all the other Gods. A laughter never left</l>
                  <l n="580">Shook all the blessed deities, to see the lame so deft</l>
                  <l n="581">At that cup service. All that day, even till the sun went down,</l>
                  <l n="582">They banqueted, and had such cheer as did their wishes crown.</l>
                  <l n="583">Nor had they music less divine; Apollo there did touch</l>
                  <l n="584">His most sweet harp, to which, with voice, the Muses pleased as much.</l>
                  <l n="585">But when the sun's fair light was set, each Godhead to his house</l>
                  <l n="586">Addressed for sleep, where every one, with art most curious,</l>
                  <l n="587">By heaven's great both-foot-halting God a several roof had built.</l>
                  <l n="588">Even he to sleep went, by whose hand heaven is with lightning gilt,</l>
                  <l n="589">High Jove, where he had used to rest when sweet sleep seized his eyes:</l>
                  <l n="590">By him the golden-throned Queen slept, the Queen of Deities.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>