<tei><text><body>
<head>Scholia in Apollonium Rhodium vetera
Berolini : Weidmann, 1935</head>

<p n="1">
<s n="1">Henry Keil, who in 1854 was the first to undertake the reconstruction of the scholia on the <title>Argonautica</title> of Apollonius Rhodius not from the first edition but from manuscripts, <quote>was convinced that the Laurentian Codex XXXII 9 was the sole source of all these scholia and that no other book had preserved their memory to our time</quote>.</s>
<s n="2">After other scholars, Ludwig Deicke opposed him, arguing in a dissertation published in Göttingen in 1901 (<title>De seboliis in Apollonium Rhodium quaestiones selectae</title> 5–19) with strong evidence that neither the Florentine nor the Parisian scholia could have been derived directly from the Laurentian Codex.</s>
<s n="3">Thus, it had become customary that anyone wishing to study an Apollonian scholion thoroughly would consult three books: Keil's edition of the Laurentian Codex, the Parisian scholia published by Schaefer in 1815, and the Florentine scholia first printed in 1496 and repeatedly corrected and reissued, mainly by Henri Estienne.</s>
<s n="4">Scholars and students of ancient literature rightly demanded a new edition of these scholia, which would examine the relationships among all extant manuscripts and be based on the best of them.</s>
<s n="5">For this reason, Deicke, supported by a grant from the Göttingen Society of Letters, traveled to Italy in the winter of 1901–1902 to study all Apollonian manuscripts preserved in the libraries of that country.</s>
<s n="6">After completing this work, he realized that not three but four types of scholia had come down to us: in addition to the Laurentian, Florentine, and Parisian types, there was a shorter type found in many manuscripts, which we shall call the Ambrosian.</s>
<s n="7">To study the Laurentian type as accurately as possible, he reexamined the marginal scholia of Codex XXXII 9, largely ignoring the glosses; he was the first to identify and fully compare Codices Laur. XXX 11 and Vat. Pal. 150 as witnesses of the Florentine type. He attributed the new Ambrosian type to Codices Vat. Pal. 280, Ambr. B 98 sup.,

<pb n="VIII"/>

Ven. Marc. 480, Vat. Urb. 146, and Vat. 36, though he was content to examine only the first. Regarding the Parisian type, he relied on Schaefer's edition.</s>
<s n="8">Upon returning home, he worked on the scholia of the second book of Apollonius, apparently as an example, combining those four types.</s>
<s n="9">This makes it clear that Deicke was firmly convinced that the four types he had established were independent of one another, each standing on its own.</s>
</p>


<p n="2">
<s n="10">It is deeply regrettable that Deicke was not fated to complete the work he had so diligently and successfully begun.</s>
<s n="11">Overwhelmed by his scholastic duties, he was forced to continually postpone the edition of the scholia, until, having taken up arms when war broke out, he met an honorable death for his country on November 11, 1914.</s>
<s n="12">In the autumn of 1920, Deicke's heirs, with the recommendation of Ulrich von Wilamowitz-Moellendorff, allowed me to continue the work he had begun and to bring it to completion.</s>
<s n="13">The materials I received included not only the aforementioned collations and prepared scholia of the second book but also notes on the scholia of several Italian manuscripts, glosses from the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> transcribed from Richard Reitzenstein's copies in 1899 in Strasbourg, indexes of various matters and glosses found in the scholia, and many conjectures pertaining both to the edition of the scholia and to his Göttingen dissertation.</s>
<s n="14">Upon reviewing these materials, I saw that much remained for me to gather and examine personally.</s>
<s n="15">Manuscripts preserved outside Italy had not yet been examined, nor had there been sufficient investigation into how witnesses of the same type or different types of scholia were interconnected.</s>
<s n="16">Therefore, I first set out to locate all surviving manuscripts in libraries and then to compare a sample from each codex to judge their relationships.</s>
<s n="17">While I undertook the first task alone, I greatly benefited in the second from frequent correspondence with Hermann Fraenkel, who was preparing a new edition of Apollonius' poem, and from his extensive dissertation (<title>Die Handschriften der Argonautika des Apollonios von Rhodos</title>, Gött. Ges. d. Wiss. 1929, 164–194),
<pb n="IX"/>
 insofar as was possible.</s> <s n="18">Having devoted myself to these studies, I realized that not only would I need to examine manuscripts neglected by Deicke, but I would also have to reexamine the Laurentian Codex, which Deicke had profitably revisited.</s>
<s n="19">Moreover, I needed to study other bodies of scholia, writings of grammarians and mythographers, and many lexica to search for parallel passages in the scholia.</s>
<s n="20">In particular, I reexamined the copies of the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> transcribed under Reitzenstein's direction, now preserved in the Royal Danish Academy in Copenhagen, as they could be considered a sufficiently ancient Apollonian manuscript and were referenced in Deicke's notes.</s>
<s n="21">As a result, I was able to personally verify the glosses transcribed from the <title>Etymologicum</title> and all the variant readings I had seen with my own eyes.</s>
</p>

<p n="3">
<s n="22">Since I have already discussed at length in my 1952 publication (<title>Die Überlieferung der Scholien zu Apollonios von Rhodos</title>, Gött. Ges. d. Wiss. 3. Folge Nr. 1) the manuscripts, the different types of scholia, the affinities of books and types, the archetype, the scholia transmitted outside the Apollonian books, and the oldest commentaries, I will cut this discussion short here.</s>
</p>

<p n="4">
<s n="23">Before addressing specific topics, I must first express my gratitude to the heirs of Ludwig Deicke, who granted me access to the materials he left behind; to the Göttingen Society of Sciences, which generously provided the means for me to visit Italian libraries; to the Society for the Promotion of Research in Germany, whose funding made the printing of this book possible; to the directors of the Berlin Institute for Classical Studies, who entrusted me with the copy of Keil's edition annotated by Ulrich von Wilamowitz-Moellendorff; and to the many librarians who, with great kindness, allowed me to either view the manuscripts themselves, receive photographic reproductions, or gain detailed information about specific passages.</s>
<s n="24">I am equally indebted to the scholars who kindly assisted me in completing this work: Franz Specht, a friend who supported me with both advice and effort; Eduard Fraenkel and Otto Regenbogen, who, with the agreement of the publisher dedicated to classical studies, included this edition in the Weidmannian Series;

<pb n="X"/>

 and finally, Hermann Fraenkel of Göttingen, who not only carefully read the proofs, applying his keen intellect to correct several corrupt passages, but also guided me to sound judgment in many difficult and obscure places, whether by supporting or challenging my interpretations.</s>
<s n="25">It is unfortunate, however, that Otto Regenbogen, who had fruitfully reviewed the first and second quires despite the tediousness of correcting proofs, was later compelled to abandon the project due to other obligations.</s>
</p>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="I">
<head>I. THE ANCIENT FORM OF THE SCHOLIA IN THE APOLLONIAN BOOKS</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="1">
<head>On the Laurentian Codex and Its Derivatives</head>
<p n="5">
<s n="26">Among the witnesses of the scholia, the most outstanding in terms of both antiquity and quality is the famous Laurentian Codex XXXII 9, dating to the early 11th century, designated as L.</s>
<s n="27">It contains on folios 190–264 the <title>Argonautica</title> of Apollonius along with many scholia, glosses, and variant readings. The prolegomena A, Bab, Ab, and C follow the text in this order.</s>
<s n="28">After Henry Keil, it was collated by Deicke and Wendel.</s></p>
<note n="X.1">
<p n="6">
<s n="29">Let it suffice to demonstrate with a few examples that neither Deicke nor I spent our time collating in vain.</s>
<s n="30">Deicke was the first to notice these words omitted by Keil in the codex:
I 1265/72b ἑλώδεις καὶ πηλώδεις ἄμεινον δὲ τοὺς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(swampy and muddy, better for them)</foreign>,
II 58/39a ἀντὶ τοῦ μέγας <foreign xml:lang="eng">(instead of "great")</foreign>,
ἔστι δὲ ἀπὸ ὀρθῆς τῆς Τυφωεύς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(it comes from the straight line of Typhoeus)</foreign>,
III 37 δι᾽ ἑνὸς ρ τὰ τοιαῦτα <foreign xml:lang="eng">(through one, such things)</foreign>,
854/59b τὸ δὲ ἄνθος — κρόκῳ <foreign xml:lang="eng">(but the flower—saffron)</foreign>,
IV 82:[31] καὶ τοῦ στήθους -- πλευρῶν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(and of the chest—the ribs)</foreign>.</s>
<s n="31">He also determined that the following were missing, which Keil had incorrectly retained from the Stephanus edition: 375, 28 ἀπὸ τοῦ λέχους <foreign xml:lang="eng">(from the bed)</foreign>,
378,3 ταύτῃ — τὸ ἔθνος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(in this way—the people)</foreign>,
388, 34 παρασχεδὸν ἀντὶ τοῦ ἐγγύς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(nearby instead of close)</foreign>,
406, 19 ἢ τὰ τέλη <foreign xml:lang="eng">(or the ends)</foreign>,
407,1 θέσφατα — λέγει <foreign xml:lang="eng">(he says oracles)</foreign>,
407,32 πρόσθε τὸ πρότερον δηλοῖ <foreign xml:lang="eng">(before, it signifies earlier)</foreign>.</s>
<s n="32">Among the individual corrections made by Deicke, I will highlight the following:
I 1320 τὰς γενικὰς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(the general)</foreign> instead of τὸν γενικὸν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(the generic)</foreign>,
558 ἀφήκασιν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(they have released)</foreign> instead of ἀφῆκαν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(they released)</foreign>,
879/83 ταῦτα δ᾽ ἂν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(these would)</foreign> instead of ταῦτα δὲ <foreign xml:lang="eng">(but these)</foreign>,
1015/17a ἐξ οὗ <foreign xml:lang="eng">(from which)</foreign> instead of ἑξῆς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(successively)</foreign>.</s>
</p>
<p n="7">
<s n="33">I investigated fewer omitted words than Deicke, but I was able to add examples, such as: B b (534, 4) εἰ <foreign xml:lang="eng">(if)</foreign> before μὴ <foreign xml:lang="eng">(not)</foreign>, 1207b αὐτὸν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(him)</foreign> after κατηνέχθαι <foreign xml:lang="eng">(brought down)</foreign>, IV 214/15 ὡς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(as)</foreign> before οὐκ <foreign xml:lang="eng">(not)</foreign>.</s>
<s n="34">In many cases, I was the first to discover the correct reading, such as: B b (533, 34) φρύττουσα <foreign xml:lang="eng">(roasting)</foreign> instead of φρύγγουσα <foreign xml:lang="eng">(quivering)</foreign>, ἀναιρεθείη <foreign xml:lang="eng">(should be taken up)</foreign> instead of ἀναιρεσθείη <foreign xml:lang="eng">(was taken up)</foreign>, φύσειεν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(let it grow)</foreign> instead of φύσειν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to grow)</foreign>.</s>
</p>
</note>
<p n="8">

<s n="35">The Parisian Codex 2846 from the 15th century most closely resembles the Laurentian Codex L with regard to the scholia, although the scholia are entirely absent from I 498 to IV 1090 in the Parisian Codex.</s>
<s n="36">The prolegomena, as in L, end in the same way.</s>
<s n="37">The codices Comensis I 4, 10, and the British Museum's Harleian Codex 5621 from the 15th century are closely related to the Parisian Codex. They include the text and numerous glosses, neglecting all but the scholia, and the prolegomena A, Ab, Bab, Bb without the catalog of the Argonauts.</s>
<s n="38">These twin codices, while agreeing in some respects with the Parisian Codex and differing from the Laurentian Codex in others, sometimes agree with each other where they diverge from the Parisian Codex and align with the Laurentian Codex. This suggests that they were copied from the same older book that provided the scholia to the Parisian Codex.</s>
<s n="39">This older book, in my judgment, is somewhat older than the three mentioned codices and can be demonstrated to have originated from the Laurentian Codex itself.</s>
<s n="40">Since I have read only the prolegomena and scholia on I 1–322 in the Comensis Codex but have thoroughly collated the entire Harleian Codex, which I will designate as H, I will rely primarily on the latter.</s>
<s n="41">H preserves nearly all the scholia or portions of scholia that are misordered in L, leaving them in incorrect places, such as I 769/73 τὸ δὲ δεῖσεν κτλ. after 763/642, II 21 after 22/232, 1282a after b.</s>
<s n="42">Annotations found between the text and marginal scholia in L are placed in some cases alongside the scholia (e.g., II 836, 888, IV 282/91d) and in others inserted into the context of the scholia with added lemmata (e.g., II 889, 895, 901, 1031a, III 77b, 97/99a, 166, 167). Occasionally, even

<pb n="XII"/>

interlinear glosses from Codex L, though largely ignored, are transferred either to the margin (e.g., III 298, 785, 1145, IV 1299a, 1314, 1315, 1367) or to the scholia context (e.g., II 322/23d, III 342b).</s>
<s n="43">It is not surprising that the scribe, following such a method, sometimes inserted intramarginal or interlinear notes in incorrect places, such as the interpretation of the word ἀπήντησεν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(he/she/it met)</foreign> at II. 1219/21a after 1231/41a, at III 1/5e before the argument, and at III 72 after 73. Above all, the dependency of Codex H on Codex L is confirmed by these two observations.</s>

<s n="44">For instance, if the scholia I 760/62a4–d in H follow scholium I 726/27 with many scholia interspersed, it seems to me that this occurred because, in L, due to a lack of space, they were written in the lower margin of the preceding page near verse 726.</s>

<s n="45">Furthermore, the condition of Codex L clearly explains why the scholia III 917/18–971 are missing in H. These scholia are found in L on folio 236r, which was later filled with verses III 923–962 to such an extent that the scholia in the inner margin were easily overlooked.</s>
<s n="46">Given these circumstances, I am convinced that the common exemplar of the Parisian, Comensis, and Harleian manuscripts originates from the Laurentian Codex, which has been preserved to our times.</s>
<s n="47">The Harleian Codex and the Comensis Codex not only corrected and refined many corrupted or obscure passages from the Laurentian Codex — a common practice among Byzantine and Renaissance scholars — but also added a few interpretations from another source, especially at the beginning of the scholia.</s>
<s n="48">Significant additions are found in the prolegomenon chapter Ba, where the words καὶ Ἀλκιδίκης appear after Τυρὼ ἡ Σαλμωνέως, and in the scholium on I 199/201b containing extremely rare mythographical information not found elsewhere.</s>
<s n="49">The source of these additions remains unknown.</s>
<note n="XII.1">
<s n="50">I no longer believe they were derived from the Guelferbytanus Codex (contrary to W 10), since the significant readings of the Guelferbytanus scholia are absent from the Harleian Codex except for one prolegomenon passage mentioned above.</s>
<s n="51">Therefore, following Paul Maas (Byz. Zs. 32, 1932, 346), I now prefer to deduce the words καὶ Ἀλκιδίκης and the scholium on I 199/201b from some mythographic work (cf. Apoll. Bibl. I 90 regarding Alcidice).</s>
</note>
</p></div>

<pb n="XIII"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="2">
<head>On the Codices G and S</head>
<p n="9">
<s n="52">Next in importance after the Laurentian Codex are the small remnants of scholia found in the Guelferbytanus Codex 10.2 Aug. 4o, from the 14th century, designated G.</s>
<s n="53">It contains the same prolegomena arranged in the same order as L, as well as a few interlinear glosses and scholia written in two colors.</s>
<s n="54">While the black scholia were copied from some etymological work or the Suda lexicon, the red scholia and glosses seem to be derived from an Apollonian Codex closely related to L.</s>
<s n="55">The Argonauts’ catalog proves it differs from L, as only G provides the names Φάληρος Ἄλκωνος and Ἴφιτος Ναυβόλου in their proper places separated by a long interval.</s>
<s n="56">It is unfortunate that no more than thirty ancient scholia are preserved in G, and these are often very compressed.</s>
</p>

<p n="10">
<s n="57">The red scholia and glosses of Codex G largely correspond to the rarer notes found in the Laurentian Codex XXXII 16 from the 14th century on folios 190v–231v, written either in narrow margins or between the lines of text in very small script.</s>
<s n="58">This codex, which we will designate as S (Sm, Sg), must depend on the same older exemplar as G.</s>
<s n="59">I was the first to collate the scholia and glosses of both codices.</s>
<s n="60">Together, these findings significantly enhance our understanding of their textual lineage.</s>
</p>
</div></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section">
<head>II. ON THE MORE RECENT FORMS OF THE SCHOLIA</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection">
<head>1. The Ambrosian Recension</head>
<p n="11">
<s n="61">Far more than the Comensis and Harleian codices, seven 15th-century codices differ from the Laurentian Codex (L), led by the Ambrosian Codex B 98 sup., designated by the siglum A.</s>
<s n="62">While the Comensis and Harleian codices omitted more scholia at the beginning and very few later, and retained scholia with minimal changes, the author of the recension I call Ambrosian severely reduced and condensed the entire corpus, giving it an entirely different appearance.</s>
<s n="63">This recension particularly eliminated scholia and parts of scholia that discussed myths treated in various ways by different writers, focusing almost exclusively on clarifying the poet's own meaning.</s>
<s n="64">However, as was typical of a learned grammarian of a much later age,
<pb n="XIV"/>
 the author did not simply abridge the ancient scholia but also refined many passages and added several new explanations, both of content and language.</s>
<s n="65">Nevertheless, in my commentary (28–33), I believe I have convincingly demonstrated with substantial evidence that not a single reading in Codex A prevents us from concluding that the entire recension ultimately depends on the Laurentian Codex. Since Deicke carefully collated the Vatican Codex Pal. 280, which was copied from the Ambrosian recension, I deemed it sufficient to review only the passages in A that differ from L.</s>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection">
<head>The Parisian Recension</head>
<p n="12">
<s n="66">The second more recent type of scholia, which we have become accustomed to calling Parisian since the first edition appeared in 1815, was disseminated in far more manuscripts than the Ambrosian recension. This recension has reached us in two forms: complete and abridged.</s>
<s n="67">While the complete corpus of scholia is transmitted without the poet's text in some books, selected scholia accompanied by glosses are found inserted into the text in others.</s>
<s n="68">Some codices contain only the complete scholia, others the text with selected scholia, and still others are structured so that the complete scholia follow a text adorned with a few scholia.</s>
<s n="69">Both forms of the Parisian scholia must derive from the same exemplar, which appears to have contained the poet's text alongside the complete scholia.</s>
</p>
<p n="13">
<s n="70">The most significant witnesses to the Parisian recension are: 1. The Vienna Codex Philological 81 (N.) from the 15th century, which contains the complete scholia and is designated by the siglum V.</s>
<s n="71">I collated books II–IV in their entirety and all passages in Book I about which I had any doubts. 2. The Brussels Codex 18170, written in 1489, which provides the poet's text along with selected scholia and glosses. I collated the entire codex and designated it with the letter B. 3. The Parisian Codex 2727 from the 16th century, in which the poet's text with glosses and selected scholia precedes the complete scholia.</s>
<s n="72">I collated all notes from the first part, designated by the siglum Pa, and from the second part (P), which G. H. Schaefer published using a transcript by David Ruhnkenius, I collated all of Book I and, from Books II–IV, only the passages where I had determined that Codex V differed from Schaefer's edition.</s>
</p>
<pb n="XV"/>
<p n="14">
<s n="73">The author of the Parisian recension revised the ancient corpus of scholia, which we know chiefly from Codex L, so thoroughly in all its parts that scarcely a single scholion was left unchanged.</s>
<s n="74">His primary aim was always to render the transmitted statements in a more elegant form, to eliminate difficulties either of content or language, and to express everything clearly and openly.</s>
<s n="75">To achieve this, he omitted or altered corrupt or problematic passages, merged duplicate scholia into one, and removed scholia that he deemed superfluous.</s>
<s n="76">The Parisian author did not merely modify the ancient scholia but also dared to explicitly criticize the earlier interpreters where he disagreed (e.g., I 414, 879/83e, IV 131/35c). Finally, he added numerous entirely new interpretations of his own accord to the older scholia, which included references to well-known poets and lighter explanations of grammatical and linguistic matters.</s>
</p>

<p n="15">
<s n="77">Given these revisions, the critical question is whether the exemplar from which the Parisian recension originated was distinct from Codex L or not.</s>
<s n="78">This question is extremely difficult to answer, as almost all the better readings in the Parisian scholia compared to the Laurentian ones could, if one wishes, be attributed to the conjectures of the learned editor.</s>
<s n="79">However, in my commentary (45–51), I believe I have necessarily demonstrated that a significant number of passages could only have come from a manuscript different from L.</s>
<s n="80">

A few important examples may be cited:</s>
<list>
<item><bibl>I 475</bibl>: Ἀπόλλωνι (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to Apollo)</foreign> : πολλῶν (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of many)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>I 1345</bibl>: πολίσαι (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to settle)</foreign> : ποιῆσαι (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to make)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>II 159/60a</bibl>: τριμερῆ (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(threefold)</foreign> : θυμηδῆ (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(joyful)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>II 279a</bibl>: ὕστερον (P; cf. <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title>) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(later)</foreign> : ὑπό τινων (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(by some)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>II 941/422</bibl>: Ἄμαστρις (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Amastris)</foreign> : Δάματρις (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Dametris)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>III 535b</bibl>: Θεσσαλίας (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of Thessaly)</foreign> : πεσσαλίς (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(a pestle)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>III 1090b</bibl>: κληθῆναι (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to be called)</foreign> : καῆναι (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to burn)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>IV arg.</bibl>: πόντον (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(sea)</foreign> : ποταμόν (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(river)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>IV 277/78a</bibl>: ἀπότονοι (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(unstrung, slackened)</foreign> : ἀπὸ γάρ (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(for from)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>IV 1615/16b</bibl>: κυρίως (P; cf. *Etymologicum Genuinum*) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(properly)</foreign> : καί (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(and)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>IV 1630</bibl>: ἢ παρὰ τὸ αὐλίζεεθαι ὅ ἐστι κοιμᾶσεθαι (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(or from *aulizesthai*, which means "to rest")</foreign> : ἄδηλον δέ, πότερον τὸ αὐλίζεσεθαι κεῖται ἐπὶ τοῦ κοιμᾶσθαι (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(it is unclear whether *aulizesethai* refers to resting)</foreign>. <s n="81">These statements, once preserved solely by P, appear to have been an added gloss.</s></item>
</list>
</p>

<p n="16">
<s n="82">The ancient manuscript that served as the foundation for the Parisian recension seems to have survived on the island of Crete until relatively recent times, as nearly all copies of this recension can be shown to have originated from there.</s>
<pb n="XVI"/>
<s n="83">The precise date when this recension was created cannot be determined, but there is no reason to doubt that it was produced shortly before the surviving manuscripts, which are primarily assigned to the fourth quarter of the 15th century.</s>
</p>

<p n="17">
<s n="84">The Parisian recension aimed to provide scholars with a comprehensive and polished commentary, a goal very different from that of the Ambrosian recension, which seems to have been intended more for beginners.</s>
<s n="85">However, it is unsurprising that the two recensions agree in some individual passages, as both sought to purify the transmitted text of errors and make it easier to read and understand. Consider, for example, these significant cases:</s>
<list>
<item><bibl>I 216/17a</bibl>: θράκης (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of Thrace)</foreign> : Ἀττικῆς (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of Attica)</foreign>; from which Ἀστικῆς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of Asty, Attica)</foreign> was correctly inferred by Holstenius.</item>
<item><bibl>I 788/89b</bibl>: σιτεῖσθαι (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to eat)</foreign> : σιτᾶσθαι (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to eat, alternate form)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>I 1132</bibl>: χερμάδια (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(stones)</foreign> : χερμαδίους (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(stone fragments)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>I 1134/39a</bibl>: κτυποῦντες (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(striking)</foreign> : κομποῦντες (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(boasting)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>I 1184</bibl>: ὥστε (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(so that)</foreign> : ὥς (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(as)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>I 1265/72a</bibl>: ταῖς βουσί (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to the cattle)</foreign> : ταῖς λογάσι (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to the chosen [corrupt])</foreign> τῶν βοῶν <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of the oxen)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>II 112/15</bibl>: ἐντοσθίων (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of entrails)</foreign> : ἐντοσθιδίων (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of small entrails)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>II 235</bibl>: ὁμόθεν (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(from the same place)</foreign> in a well-known verse of Euripides : νόμον (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(law)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>II 611/12</bibl>: ἡμᾶς (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(us)</foreign> : ὑμάς (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(you)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>III 187</bibl>: ἀπὸ τοῦ (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(from that)</foreign> : αὐτὸ τό (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(the very thing; more difficult but correct)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>III 200a</bibl>: τὰς ἐρημίας Ἑκὰς τότε (P; Ἑκάς as a proper name linked with ἐρημίας) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(the wildernesses of Hecas)</foreign> : τὰς ἐρημίας ἑκάστοτε (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(the wildernesses each time; correct)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>III 997/1004a</bibl>: γῆμεν (P) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to marry)</foreign> : γήμας (L) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(having married)</foreign>.</item>
<item><bibl>IV arg.</bibl>: τὴν Μήδειαν (P; necessary supplement) <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Medea)</foreign> : omitted (L).</item>
</list>
<s n="86">However, as hundreds of instances demonstrate where the Ambrosian and Parisian recensions diverge, do not assume that similar or matching passages necessarily come from a common exemplar.</s>
</p>

<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection">
<head>Florentine Recension</head>
<p n="18">
<s n="87">The third recension of scholia is the one printed in Florence in 1496 by Laurentius de Alopa under the supervision of Janus Lascaris. It is designated by the siglum F. In my commentary (18–21), I demonstrated with very strong arguments that this first edition originated from Codex Laurentianus XXXI τι and fragments of scholia propagated through other manuscripts.</s>
<s n="88">It can also be firmly established that Janus Lascaris derived his scholia from two manuscripts: one belonging to the Laurentian type and the other to the complete Parisian type. The critical question, however, is whether the Codex L itself should be considered the exemplar of the Laurentian type
<pb n="XVII"/>

used by Lascaris.</s>
<s n="89">In my opinion, there is no reason to doubt that Codex L provided the Laurentian scholia for Lascaris, provided we assume that the highly learned editor emended the transmitted text with excellent conjectures.</s>
<s n="90">If this were not the case, it would be quite surprising, since Codex L, brought from Constantinople to Italy in 1423 at the command of Niccolò Niccoli of Florence, remained either in the library of the Monastery of San Marco or the private library of the Medici family in Florence after its first owner's death. It is well known that Lascaris made extensive use of this particular library.</s>
<s n="91">Moreover, we have seen above that other scholars of nearly the same period, such as the authors of the Parisian 2846, Comensis, Harleian, and Ambrosian codices, were also familiar with this ancient codex.</s>
<s n="92">Finally, it should be noted that Lascaris also consulted a manuscript similar to the GS codices (Fraenkel 188, W 25), from which he may have drawn one or two variant readings (cf. Maas, Byz. Zs. 32, 1932, 346).</s>
</p>
</div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
<head>III. ON THE ARCHETYPAL MANUSCRIPT</head>
<p n="19">
<s n="93">Codex L, the parent of the GS codices, and the lost exemplar of the Parisian recension appear to trace back to a single archetypal manuscript, as evidenced by the numerous common errors and lacunae in the Laurentian, Parisian, and Guelferbytanus scholia. This archetypal manuscript seems to have resembled the Laurentian Codex very closely, as a comparison of the derived manuscripts demonstrates that its text was equipped not only with marginal scholia but also with interlinear glosses and variant readings.</s>
<s n="94">As Merkel correctly observed (LVIsqq.), the lemmata of the scholia correspond to the variant readings added to the text, indicating that the archetypal manuscript drew from two sources: one supplying the poet’s text and the other providing scholia and textual variants.</s>
<s n="95">However, before it was copied, this exemplar appears to have lost two folios: the first containing the argument of Book I and the second containing lines I 321 with their scholia.</s>
<s n="96">As a result, both the scholia and variant readings for these eighty verses are absent in the preserved manuscripts.</s>
</p>

<pb n="XVIII"/>

<p n="20">
<s n="97">The corpus of scholia incorporated into the archetypal manuscript was drawn from three earlier commentaries, as indicated by this subscription in the Laurentian Codex: παράκειται τὰ σχόλια. ἐκ τῶν Λουκίλλου Ταρραίου καὶ Σοφοκλείου καὶ Θέωνος. The first of these authors is Theon, son of Artemidorus, who is known to have been a contemporary of Augustus.</s>
<s n="98">Lucillus of Tarrha and Sophocleus are to be placed in the second century AD, with the latter belonging to its late period.</s>
<s n="99">The compiler of this scholia corpus appears to have used the edition of Lucillus as a foundation, incorporating nearly the entire commentary of Sophocleus into the margin. From the commentary of Theon, which Sophocleus had already partially integrated (albeit in abridged form), only the most significant portions were included.</s>
<s n="100">We do not know when this unknown grammarian lived, but it is highly likely that he worked in late antiquity, around the 5th century AD, transferring Apollonius’ epic poem along with the scholia from papyrus scrolls into a parchment codex for the first time.</s>
<s n="101">This original codex served as the exemplar for the archetypal manuscript, which, as we have seen, provided the scholia to the Laurentian-like manuscript. However, the manuscript from which the scholia were drawn, having already lost two folios before it was copied, appears to have been somewhat older. It should be dated to at least the 9th century.</s>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
<head>IV. ON SCHOLIA TRANSMITTED OUTSIDE THE APOLLONIAN BOOKS</head>

<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="1">
<head>On Eustathius and Tzetzes</head>

<p n="21">
<s n="102">Although it must be assumed with certainty that 12th-century writers read Apollonius' <title>Argonautica</title> along with the scholia, traces of these scholia in their works are exceedingly rare. Eustathius is found twice incorporating Apollonian scholia into his Homeric commentaries: at 344, 18, where the explanation of the term κίτυβος appears to derive from scholia II 98/100ab, and at 711, 42, which refers to scholium IV 175b.</s>
<s n="103">In his commentary on Dionysius Periegetes at v. 1134, he defines the terms ῥόμβος, ῥύμβος, and ῥυμβών almost identically to the scholia at I 1134/39b and IV 143/44a.
<pb n="XIX"/>
The scholia used by Eustathius seem to have been very similar to those in the Laurentian Codex, perhaps slightly more extensive (e.g., Hom. 711, 42: ἀχαιινέη ἔλαφος, περὶ ἧν πολλὰ πονοῦνται οἱ ἐξηγηταί).</s>
</p>

<p n="22">
<s n="104">John Tzetzes, in his commentary on Lycophron, excerpted many details from the Apollonian scholia to lend an air of erudition to his work but rarely transcribed entire scholia, as seen, for example, on p. 35, 10–14 Sch., where he discusses Scylla, referring to scholium IV 825/31a.</s>
<s n="105">He also briefly touched on Apollonian scholia in his <title>Chiliads</title>.</s>
<s n="106">The Apollonius manuscript that Tzetzes used seems to have been very close to Codex L.</s>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="2">
<head>On the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title></head>

<p n="23">
<s n="107">Deicke (22sqq.) convincingly demonstrated, following earlier scholars, that the author of the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> had incorporated many Apollonian scholia into his glosses.</s>
<s n="108">Richard Reitzenstein granted him permission to examine the transcriptions of the best manuscripts, Vatican 1818 (A) and Laurentian Marciani 304 (B), which Reitzenstein had partly prepared himself and partly had prepared for his own use. I was able to review and augment the Apollonian glosses transcribed by Deicke, as these transcriptions, which Reitzenstein had deposited at the Royal Danish Academy in Copenhagen, were sent to Göttingen in 1930 for use by Fraenkel and myself.</s>
</p>
<p n="24">
<s n="109">The Apollonian glosses in the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> are explicitly confirmed to have been derived from scholia by the grammarian himself, as evidenced by notes such as these or similar ones, which he either appended or prefixed to some of them: οὕτως εὗρον εἰς τὰ σχόλια τῶν Ἀργοναυτικῶν τοῦ Ἀπολλωνίου, Ἀπολλώνιος ὁ τὰ Ἀργοναυτικά, σχόλια <foreign xml:lang="eng">(thus I found in the scholia on the <title>Argonautica</title> of Apollonius, Apollonius the one of the <title>Argonautica</title>, scholia)</foreign>.</s>
<s n="110">Many glosses of this kind closely align with the scholia transmitted in Apollonian manuscripts, though they are often either more complete or more concise, and almost all are altered to varying degrees in terms of form.</s>
<s n="111">While it must be conceded that the author of the <title>Etymologicum</title> sometimes transcribed the scholia carelessly, expanded or abridged them at will, or modified them in other ways, there can be no doubt that he found many discrepancies in his exemplar compared to those known to us.</s>
<s n="112">Indeed, the scholia in this exemplar contained not only explanations of individual words and phrases of the poet but also numerous items
<pb n="XX"/>
of great significance, some of which are wholly or partially missing from the Apollonian manuscripts, such as these fragments of lost poets and writers:
Antimachus on Σείριος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Sirius)</foreign> and Σήσαμοι <foreign xml:lang="eng">(sesame)</foreign>,
Archilochus on στύπος ἀμπέλου <foreign xml:lang="eng">(the trunk of a vine)</foreign>,
Callimachus on Ἅλυς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Halys)</foreign> and χύτλα <foreign xml:lang="eng">(small vessels)</foreign>,
Eratosthenes on αὐτόγυον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(self-sprung)</foreign>,
Herodian on Πλειστοῖο <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of Pleistos)</foreign>,
Phylarchus on Βόσπορος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Bosphorus)</foreign>,
Pindar on Πλειάδες <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Pleiades)</foreign>,
Sophocles on ὀπίζεσθαι <foreign xml:lang="eng">(to revere)</foreign>,
Stesimbrotus on Ἰδαῖοι Δάκτυλοι <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Idaean Dactyls)</foreign>.
</s>
<s n="113">In fact, glosses in the <title>Etymologicum</title> are found that evidently derive from scholia otherwise completely lost.:</s> <s n="114">Examples of this type include:</s>
<list>
<item>Ἄθως <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Athos, referring to I 601)</foreign>,</item>
<item>ἄκαινα <foreign xml:lang="eng">(a spike, III 1323)</foreign>,</item>
<item>ἀμεύεσμος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(diminishment, IV 297)</foreign>,</item>
<item>Ἄμυκος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Amycus, II 1)</foreign>,</item>
<item>Ἀμφιφορίητς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Amphiphoretic, IV 1770)</foreign>,</item>
<item>ἀρείων <foreign xml:lang="eng">(better, II 77)</foreign>,</item>
<item>Ἀργώ <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Argo, I 4)</foreign>,</item>
<item>Ἠερία <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Eeria, IV 267)</foreign>,</item>
<item>Θεραπναῖον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Therapnaion, II 163)</foreign>,</item>
<item>Ἰτωνίς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Itonis, I 551)</foreign>,</item>
<item>Ὄσση <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Ossa, I 1598)</foreign>,</item>
<item>πήχυιον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(a cubit-length, I 579)</foreign>,</item>
<item>σκολιὸν πόρον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(crooked path, II 549)</foreign>,</item>
<item>and Χυτῷ λιμένι <foreign xml:lang="eng">(at the harbor of Chytos, I 987)</foreign>.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p n="25">
<s n="115">The Apollonian manuscript used by the author of the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title>, though broadly consistent with the archetypal manuscript, was nevertheless somewhat more complete.</s>
<s n="116">This is not surprising, since the archetypal manuscript is attributed to around the 10th century, while this manuscript must be older, as the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> is believed to have originated in the 9th century.</s>
<s n="117">This aligns with the fact that the major lacuna present in the archetype, which we saw afflicted the manuscript with scholia, is not found in this codex. For example, the gloss πήχυιον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(a cubit-length)</foreign> mentioned above pertains to verse I 379, which is known to have been written on the lost folio of that exemplar.</s>
<s n="118">Given this, it must be asked whether the Apollonian manuscript used by the author of the <title>Etymologicum</title> already contained the scholia corpus composed from the commentaries of three authors or only one or two of these commentaries.</s>
<s n="119">Since the <title>Etymologicum</title>, at the entry Ἑλάρα <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Helara)</foreign>, as well as the scholia at I 760/62bc, presents two explanations of the same topic side by side with the term ἄλλως <foreign xml:lang="eng">(otherwise, i.e., "found elsewhere")</foreign> and cites Lucillus' commentary under the same name Ταρραίος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(of Tarrha)</foreign> that the scholia consistently use, there can be little doubt that the glosses in the <title>Etymologicum</title> were derived from a manuscript containing the corpus of the three authors.</s>
<s n="120">Although this manuscript must be regarded as the oldest surviving witness to the corpus, its content had been so revised by a learned Byzantine scholar that every caution must be exercised by anyone attempting to reconstruct the truly ancient form of the scholia based on it.</s>
</p></div>
<pb n="XXI"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="1">
<head>On Orus and Methodius</head>

<p n="26">
<s n="121">Of the three commentaries from which a learned individual in approximately the 5th century is thought to have compiled the scholia corpus transmitted in the Apollonian books, only Sophocles' commentary is mentioned outside the corpus and its derivatives.</s>
<s n="122">Stephanus of Byzantium, whose abridged lexicon of ethnic terms has come down to us, explicitly states that three glosses, closely aligning with the Apollonian scholia, were taken from Sophocles' commentary: cf. v. Ἄβαρνος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Abarna)</foreign> with scholia I 932/33a, v. Γενήτης <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Genetes)</foreign> with scholia II 377/80, and v. Κάναστρον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Kanastron)</foreign> with scholia I 598/99. It is therefore beyond doubt that many other glosses, which align with the known scholia, also originated from this same commentary.</s>
<s n="123">These include: </s>
<list>
<item>v. Ἀκμονία <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Akmoneia)</foreign> — scholia II 992</item>
<item>v. Ἀμαραντλοί <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Amarantloi)</foreign> — scholia II 399/401a</item>
<item>v. Γυρτών <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Gyrton)</foreign> — scholia I 57/642</item>
<item>v. Δοίαντος πεδίον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(the plain of Doias)</foreign> — scholia II 988</item>
<item>v. Ἐρυθῖνοι <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Erythinoi)</foreign> — scholia II 941/42a</item>
<item>v. Κτιμένη <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Ktimenê)</foreign> — scholia I 67/68b</item>
<item>v. Κύταια <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Kytaiä)</foreign> — scholia II 399/4012</item>
<item>v. Παρνασσός <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Parnassos)</foreign> — scholia II 705/11g</item>
<item>v. Ταίναος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Tainaros)</foreign> — scholia I 101/04b, </item>
<item>v. Φλιοῦς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Phlius)</foreign> — scholia I 115. </item>
</list>
<s n="124">Since Stephanus' usage of Sophocles' commentary often proves to be richer than the scholia, there is no reason to hesitate in attributing to it glosses pertaining to passages in Apollonius' works that today are wholly or largely absent from the manuscripts.</s>
<s n="125">Such glosses seem to include: Ἀβαντίς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Abantis)</foreign> and Ἀμαντία <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Amantia)</foreign> (cf. scholia IV 1174/75b), Ἀνάφη <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Anaphe)</foreign> and Μεμβλίαρος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Membliaros)</foreign> (cf. scholia IV 1711), Ἀργανθών <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Arganthos)</foreign> (cf. scholia I 1177/78b), and Αὔλιον ἄντρον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Aulion cave)</foreign> under AUM (cf. scholia II 904/10.2).</s>
</p>

<p n="27">
<s n="126">We must now ask whether Stephanus himself handled Sophocles' commentary or received the excerpts from another author.</s>
<s n="127">To resolve this question, it is highly significant that the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> gloss Ἄμαντες <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Amantes)</foreign>, which—like Stephanus' glosses Ἀβαντίς <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Abantis)</foreign> and Ἀμαντία <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Amantia)</foreign>—appears to have come from the more complete scholia at IV 1174/75b, is derived from the book <title>On Ethnics</title> by Orus the grammarian.</s>
<s n="128">It is therefore highly probable that Stephanus owed all the Apollonian glosses
<pb n="XXII"/>
from Sophocles' commentary to Orus as an intermediary, who is known to have been heavily excerpted by him.</s> <s n="129">Conversely, it can be asserted with certainty that the other Apollonian glosses drawn by the author of the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> from Orus' book (cf. v. Ἀγαυέα <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Agavea)</foreign> — scholia IV 175b, v. Αἰγαῖον πέλαγος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Aegean Sea)</foreign> — scholia I 851, v. Μίλητος <foreign xml:lang="eng">(Miletos)</foreign> — scholia I 185/882) ultimately trace back to Sophocles' commentary.</s>
</p>

<p n="28">
<s n="130">Besides Orus, a grammarian whom I assign to the 5th century, another source that seems to have transmitted some Apollonian glosses to the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> is Methodius, whose lost great lexicon is believed to have been the primary source for the letter A in the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title>.</s>
<s n="131">The following Apollonian glosses in the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> are thought to derive from Methodius' lexicon: duόpnrov <foreign xml:lang="eng">(double-edged)</foreign> — ἀμήρυτον <foreign xml:lang="eng">(uncut)</foreign> — scholia II 221, ἀνταία <foreign xml:lang="eng">(face-to-face)</foreign> — scholia I 1141/48a, ἀλκαία <foreign xml:lang="eng">(strong)</foreign> — scholia IV 1615/16h, ἀίγδην <foreign xml:lang="eng">(continuously)</foreign> — scholia II 826.</s>
<s n="132">It is not certain which commentary Methodius used, but since he is likely to have been nearly contemporary with Orus, it seems highly probable that he also relied on Sophocles' commentary.</s>
</p>
</div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="5">
<head>V. ON THE METHOD AND PRINCIPLES OF THIS EDITION</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="1">
<head>On the Method of the Edition</head>

<p n="29">
<s n="133">In undertaking a new edition of the ancient scholia on Apollonius, I deliberately excluded the recensions from the Byzantine and Renaissance periods.</s>
<s n="134">Thus, I based the text primarily on Codex L, using Codex G for the prolegomena and occasionally incorporating readings from Codices G and S in other places.</s>
<s n="135">I disregarded the Parisian scholia where the ancient exemplar they revised appeared to agree with L. However, when the Parisian scholia seemed to stem from a reading divergent from L, I adopted that reading from the exemplar, even if the Laurentian reading was often inferior and sometimes seemed to be merely conjectural.</s>
<s n="136">Overall, I used the Parisian scholia as transmitted in Codex P; where Codex V differs, I included the readings of both manuscripts. On rarer occasions, I found it necessary to draw on the shorter scholia of Codices B and Pe; one significant scholium (II 222/24b) is preserved only in these.</s>
<s n="137">I ignored the interlinear glosses of Codices B and P?.</s>
<s n="138">I included selected conjectures from the manuscripts derived from the Laurentian Codex (such as A, H, and the first printed edition, F), but I preferred to err on the side of inclusion rather than exclusion. I included not only conjectures that I consider correct or especially noteworthy but also those that appear to have originated from a more ancient exemplar shared by two or three manuscripts.</s>
<s n="139">I accepted additions from these manuscripts except for the trivial Ambrosian glosses.</s>
</p>

<p n="30">
<s n="140">I included all interpretations from Codex L, encompassing not only the scholia proper (L) but also interlinear glosses (L8) and marginal notes lacking lemmata (1.3). I also retained a few interlinear and marginal glosses from the 13th, 14th, and 15th centuries, as they seem to replace faded ancient glosses (Lgr and Lmr). I reproduced the scholia lemmata, which are essential for restoring the poet’s words, with such precision that even letters omitted for brevity and supplied by editors are carefully noted.</s>
<s n="141">This care is not superfluous, as demonstrated by scholium IV 973, where Keil misexpanded an abbreviation, reading ὀρειχάλκοιο φασίν instead of ὀρειχάλκοιο φα<add>εινοῦ</add>. Where the order of the scholia was disordered, I restored it to follow the poet's text, indicating the traditional order in the apparatus.</s>
<s n="142">If a scribe or corrector had already corrected an error by adding letters or numbers, I did not record it. I added interlinear glosses related to textual variants, except where they involved only individual letters or very short segments.</s>
<s n="143">This approach is useful, as it is sometimes unclear whether a word should be considered a gloss or a textual variant, such as IV 564/66b Λιγυρνίδες, 603/06b ἐφήμεναι, 627/34b πόντον, and 1115 ἐφημοσύνῃσιν. While I strove to document Codex L as meticulously as possible, I deliberately ignored orthographic matters where the true reading is not in doubt.</s>
<s n="144">For example, I did not note cases where ἢ was written for ε, as in τυγχάνην (388, 19 K.), παρασύρην (437, 27 K.), and συμπάσχην (470, 32 K.); or where n was replaced with ι, as in τῆς (371, 6 K.), Ἀρητιάδη (412, 15 K.), and Νύμφης (424, 7 K.); or where ω was written for ο, as in τὸν (= τῶν, 378, 10 K.), or τὸ (= τῷ, 384, 15 K.). Nor did I note the consistent omission of iota adscript (e.g., τῶ, Ἅρπυαι Ἅδης)
<pb n="XXIV"/>

 or trivial errors such as repeated words or omitted articles.</s>
<s n="145">I applied the same care to the few ancient scholia and glosses from Codices G and S.</s>
</p>

<p n="31">
<s n="146">Regarding the scholia transmitted outside the Apollonian books, I transcribed verbatim all passages from Stephanus of Byzantium and the <title>Etymologicum Genuinum</title> that are evidently derived from the corpus of the three authors or from Sophocles' commentary. Even where the scholia preserved in the <title>Etymologicum</title> had been altered at the discretion of a Byzantine scholar, I recorded them accurately.</s>
<s n="147">Additionally, I included the ancient scholia brought to light by Albert Wifstrand (Ramos 30, 1932, 2–6) from Berlin Papyrus 13415 (dating to the 1st or 2nd century AD); cf. scholia II 1075, 1099, 1103, and 1127. I also added numerous other passages derived from the scholia that are so similar to them as to aid in their correction, supplementation, explanation, or better understanding.</s>
<s n="148">While I ensured verbatim transcription for the former, I only referenced the latter by title. I acknowledge that my selection in compiling these passages was not entirely consistent, sometimes including more and sometimes fewer.</s>
</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="1">
<head>On the Approach of the Edition</head>

<p n="32">
<s n="149">Since the archetypal manuscript was often corrupt, incomplete, or disordered in various places, the art of conjecture frequently needed to be employed. As scholars from antiquity to the present have abundantly engaged in this practice, I did not consider it necessary to include all their findings in the apparatus.</s>
<s n="150">However, where a certain passage seemed to me corrupt and unresolved, I provided a more detailed account of the efforts of scholars. In all conjectures included, I endeavored to credit the original proposer, specifying the title of their work precisely.</s>
<s n="151">Whenever possible, I gave preference to handwritten manuscripts over modern conjectures. I discovered five conjectures in Deicke’s notes and seventy-two unpublished ones in an example of Keil’s edition, which I had the privilege of examining in September 1932, with permission from the directors of the Berlin Institute for the Promotion of Antiquity Studies, where it had been handled by Wilamowitz.</s>
<s n="152">For eight passages where Wilamowitz’s conjectures coincided with those I had independently recorded long ago, I attributed both our names.</s>
<s n="153">Finally, I have already mentioned above (p. X) the significant contributions Hermann Fraenkel made to improving the corrupt passages.</s>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="subsection" n="1">
<head>On the Principles of the Edition</head>

<p n="33">
<s n="154">Since the ancient scholia are generally contained in Codex L and the lost exemplar of the Parisian scholia, I deemed it unnecessary to assign any siglum to those parts and fragments found both in the margin of Codex L and in the fuller Parisian scholia (P). However, do not assume that the Parisian scholia always agree verbatim with the Laurentian ones if no differences are noted in the apparatus, as I have only included those variant readings that could reasonably be traced back to the ancient exemplar.</s>
<s n="155">When it was necessary to reference Codex P in the apparatus, I distinguished three forms of citation, illustrated by these examples:
1. χαλιμίας L : χαλίδας P. In Codex P, the word χαλίδας is recorded in this exact form.
2. ἐντοσθιδίων L : ἐντοσθίων (P). Codex P, having altered the entire phrase, reads τὰ ἐντόσθια, suggesting that the original exemplar might have contained ἐντοσθίων.
3. αὐτοῦ F : αὐτόν L : aliter P. Codex P rephrased and reworked the ancient scholium so extensively that it is unclear whether the exemplar offered αὐτοῦ, αὐτόν, or something else entirely.</s>
<s n="156">On the other hand, for any scholium found only in another manuscript, either solely or in combination with other sources, or in L interlinear glosses (Lg) or marginal notes (Lm), I included the sigla of the witnesses at the end.</s>
</p>

<p n="34">
<s n="157">For all scholia preserved in Codex L, I prefixed lemmata drawn from the same codex without noting differences from other manuscripts. Most of the scholia proper, with few exceptions, retain the same wording as in the body of the codex scholia.</s>
<s n="158">For those annotations in the codex that lack lemmata (Lg and Lm), I supplied phrases taken from the poet’s text, enclosed in slanted brackets.</s>
<s n="159">If Codex P included the same gloss with an added lemma among the scholia, I indicated its correspondence to the same poetical phrase in the Parisian scholia by omitting the brackets but nonetheless transcribed the lemma from Codex L.</s>
</p>
<p n="35">
<s n="160">In determining the order of the scholia, I strictly adhered to the poet’s text.

 </s>
<pb n="XXVI"/>

<s n="161">For scholia that interpret multiple verses, I prefixed the numbers of both the first and last verse to reduce the reader’s effort.</s>
<s n="162">I distinguished different scholia pertaining to the same verses by adding letters.</s>
<s n="163">I ignored the order of the Parisian scholia.</s>
</p>

<p n="36">
<s n="164">Since the interlinear glosses, which are closely connected to many marginal notes, were mostly extracted from the complete scholia, I chose not to include them as separate entries.</s>
<s n="165">Instead, I placed those glosses that appear to have been derived from transmitted scholia in the apparatus.</s>
</p>

<p n="37">
<s n="166">I organized the critical apparatus so that I always repeated the words accepted into the text along with the sigla of the witnesses before presenting the variant readings from other manuscripts.</s>
<s n="167">This ensures that there can never be any doubt about the source of the accepted text.</s>
<s n="168">However, when a conjecture has been accepted into the text, the transmitted reading—if it appears identically in all the manuscripts that preserve the scholium—is presented without the sigla of the manuscripts.</s>
<s n="169">To illustrate with examples:
1. τ. sch. II 177 θυνίαι W : Βιθυνίαι. This indicates that in manuscripts L and P, which contain the scholium, the reading Βιθυνίαι is found.
2. sch. II 70/742 διεκκλινόμενος F : διακλ-. This indicates that Codex L, the sole witness to this scholium, provides the form διακλινόμενος. Conversely, if I chose to record a conjecture that is uncertain or, in my judgment, to be rejected, it seemed unnecessary to repeat the words accepted from the manuscripts.</s>
</p>

<p n="38">
<s n="170">Written in Halle, Saxony, in the month of March, 1935.</s>
</p>

<p n="39">
<s n="171">Charles Wendel.</s>
</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
<head>CONSPECTUS OF SCHOLARS</head>

<p n="40">
<s n="172">The following individuals are cited by name only:

<item>
<term>Deicke</term> = Ludovicus Deicke, mentioned in handwritten notes; see pp. VIII, XXIV.
</item>

<item>
<term>Deicke cum numero paginae</term> = The same, as referenced in his Göttingen dissertation; see p. VII.
</item>

<item>
<term>Fr.</term> = Hermannus Fraenkel; see pp. X, XXV.
</item>

<item>
<term>Hoelzlin</term> = <title>Ap. Rh. Argonauticorum Libri IV</title> translated into Latin by Jeremias Hoelzlin... Lugduni Batavorum, 1641. This work includes, in addition to many excellent conjectures by Hoelzlin, the observations of Lucae Holstenius (vol. II, pp. 363–368).
</item>

<item>
<term>K</term> = <title>Scholia Vetera</title> from the Laurentian Codex, edited by Henricus Keil (<title>Ap. Rh. Argonautica</title>, edited with critical apparatus and introduction by R. Merkel, Leipzig, 1854, pp. 299–562).
</item>

<item>
<term>R</term> = Otto Regenbogen; see p. X.
</item>

<item>
<term>Schaefer</term> = <title>Ap. Rh. Argonautica</title>, edited from the text and with the notes of Rich. Fr. Phil. Brunckius, revised and corrected edition, Vol. 2, Leipzig, 1813. Part 1, pp. 1–340: <title>Scholia Vetera in Ap. Rh.</title> from the Parisian Codex 2727, edited by Godofredus Henricus Schaefer.
</item>

<item>
<term>Steph.</term> = <title>Ap. Rh. Argonauticon Libri IV</title>. Ancient scholia on the same books, edited with annotations by Henricus Stephanus, Paris, 1574.
</item>

<item>
<term>W</term> = Charles Wendel in this edition.
</item>

<item>
<term>W cum numero paginae</term> = The same, in his commentary on the transmission of the scholia; see p. IX.
</item>

<item>
<term>Wellauer</term> = <title>Ap. Rh. Argonautica</title>, based on the manuscripts and earlier editions, with expanded and emended scholia, edited by A. Wellauer, Leipzig, 1828.
</item>

<item>
<term>Wil.</term> = Udalricus von Wilamowitz-Moellendorff.
</item>

<item>
<term>Wil. ad l.</term> = The same, in his copy of Keil’s edition; see pp. IX, XXIV.
</item>
</s>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
<head>CONSPECTUS SIGNORUM</head>
<p n="41">

<list>
<head>Sigla of Manuscripts</head>

<item><term>A</term> = Ambrosianus B 98 sup.; see pp. XIII, XVI, XXII.</item>
<item><term>B</term> = Bruxellensis 18170; see pp. XIV, XXII.</item>
<item><term>F</term> = First printed edition, Florence, published by Laurentius de Alopa in 1496, edited by Janus Lascaris; see pp. XVI, XXII.</item>
<item><term>G</term> = Guelferbytanus 10. 2. Aug. 49; see pp. XIII, XXIV.</item>
<item><term>H</term> = Harleianus 5621; see pp. XI, XXII.</item>
<item><term>L</term> = Laurentianus XXXII 9; see pp. X, XXIII.</item>
<item><term>P</term> = Parisini 2727, posterior part; see pp. XIV, XXII.</item>
<item><term>Pa</term> = Parisini 2727, anterior part; see pp. XIV, XXII.</item>
<item><term>S</term> = Laurentianus XXXII τό; see pp. XIII, XXIV.</item>
<item><term>V</term> = Viennensis philol. 81 N.; see pp. XIV, XXII.</item>
</list>

<list>
<head>Signs Appended to Manuscript Sigla</head>

<item><term>x1, x2</term> = Scholium repeated in the same manuscript.</item>
<item><term>xg</term> = Interlinear gloss.</item>
<item><term>xm</term> = Note written in the margin outside the scholium column.</item>
<item><term>xr</term> = Note written by a later hand.</item>
<item><term>(x)</term> = Reading from a manuscript not given in all its details; see p. XXV.</item>
</list>

<list>
<head>Other Symbols</head>

<item><gap/> = Lacuna determined by conjecture.</item>
<item>†† = Corrupt words.</item>
<item><add></add> = Words added by conjecture.</item>
<item><del></del> = Words to be deleted.</item>
</list>
</div></div>
</body></text></tei>
