<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Extract from Diary Regarding Visits to John Adams</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Encoded for structural and linguistic analysis.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Digitized scan of a historical diary extract regarding John Adams.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter">
        <pb n="66"/>
        <head>VISITS TO JOHN ADAMS.</head>
        <milestone unit="separator"/>
        <p>
          <hi rend="dropcap">D</hi>URING the last five years of the life of <persName>John
          Adams</persName> I enjoyed the privilege of constant
          intercourse with him during the summer months.
          Several times a week I went to his house, where I
          frequently read aloud to him or acted as his amanu-
          ensis. I shall give some gleanings from his conver-
          sations, as I find them recorded in my journals.
        </p>
        <p>
          <quote>
            <date when="1820-09-06">September 6, 1820.</date> — <persName>Judge Winston</persName> and <persName>Major
            Sommerville</persName>, gentlemen from the South, drove out
            this morning and stayed with us some time. Then
            we all went up to call upon <persName role="president">President Adams</persName>. His
            visitors asked him his opinion of <persName>Patrick Henry</persName>, and
            whether he was not the greatest orator he had ever
            heard. His reply was : <quote>No, gentlemen. Much of
            <persName>Wirt</persName>'s life of him<note type="citation">William Wirt, <title>Sketches of the Life and Character of Patrick Henry</title> (1817)</note> is a romance. Why, I have heard
            that gentleman's father <stage>[pointing to one who was
            present]</stage> speak in a strain of eloquence to which <persName>Pat-
            rick Henry</persName> could never pretend.</quote> He paused, and
            then added, <quote>You know Virginian geese are always
            swans.</quote> Notwithstanding these remarks, the gentle-
            men seemed very much pleased with their visit.
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>
          In a letter addressed to <persName>Mr. Wirt</persName> himself, and
          bearing date <date when="1818-01-05">January 5, 1818</date>, I find that <persName>Mr. Adams</persName>'s
          <pb n="67"/>
          testimony is the same. The passage is characteris-
          tic enough for quotation. He writes: <quote><persName>James Otis</persName>
          electrified the town of <placeName>Boston</placeName>, the Province of <placeName>Massa-
          chusetts Bay</placeName>, and the whole continent more than
          <persName>Patrick Henry</persName> ever did in the whole course of his
          life. If we must have panegyrics and hyperboles,
          I must say that if <persName>Mr. Henry</persName> was <persName>Demosthenes</persName> and
          <persName>Mr. Richard Henry Lee</persName> was <persName>Cicero</persName>, <persName>James Otis</persName> was
          <persName>Isaiah</persName> and <persName>Ezekiel</persName> united.</quote>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="diary_entry">
        Josiah Quincy, Figures of the past from the leaves of old journals (Bosto 1910)
        <pb n="74"/>
        <p>
          I now turn back to 1822, and make my concluding
          extract from the diary of October 30. 
          <quote>
            Visited the President in the morning; and, after writing a letter
            to <persName>Mathew Carey</persName> from his dictation, conversed with
            him on several literary subjects. Speaking of <persName>Cicero</persName>'s
            treatise <title>De Senectute</title>, he said that he read it every
            year. He declared <persName>Cato</persName> was quite a Christian in
            feeling when he says, 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:lang="la">Si quis deus mihi largiatur,
              ut ex hac ætate repuerascam et in cunis vagiam, valde
              recusem : nec verò velim, quasi decurso spatio, ad car-
              ceres a calce revocari.</quote>
              <ref target="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi053:83">Cicero, De Senectute 83</ref>
              <note type="translation" xml:lang="en">If some god should grant me that from this age I might become a child again and cry in the cradle, I would strongly refuse; nor would I truly wish, as if the race were run, to be called back from the finish line to the starting barriers.</note>
            </cit>
            The President recommended
            <persName>Cicero</persName> and <persName>Pliny</persName> as models of literary style, and a
            letter written to <persName>Lord Mansfield</persName> by — the name I can-
            not recall. He thought <persName>Lord Bolingbroke</persName>'s <title>Patriot
            King</title> was serviceable to public speakers. I do not
            admire <persName>Bolingbroke</persName> as much as he does; probably
            from want of taste. I read to him the last part
            <pb n="75"/>
            <fw type="header">VISITS TO JOHN ADAMS. 75</fw>
            of the <title>Senectute</title>, where the orator combats the idea
            that the near approach of death is an evil. When
            I reached the passage where <persName>Cicero</persName> anticipates his
            reunion with those he had known and his meeting
            with those of whom he had read<note type="citation"><ref target="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi053:84">Cicero, De Senectute 84–85</ref></note>, the old gentleman
            became much excited and exclaimed: <quote>That is just
            as I feel. Nothing would tempt me to go back. I
            agree with my old friend, <persName>Dr. Franklin</persName>, who used to
            say on this subject, <quote>We are all invited to a great
            entertainment. Your carriage comes first to the door;
            but we shall all meet there.</quote></quote> Who would think such
            an old age a burden, honored in this world and hop-
            ing soon to depart for a better, where he believes he
            shall meet not only the friends he has lost, but all
            the great and good who have gone before him?
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p>
          This last extract fairly represents the prevailing
          mood of mind of <persName>John Adams</persName> during his closing
          years.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>