<div type="annotations" subtype="Nero_Claudius_Caesar">
    <div type="notes" n="5">
        <note n="a">
            <p>THESE foure factions or crewes that ran with Chariots for the prise, were distinguished by foure colors of cloth, or liveries, and therupon called by their names, Alba, i. White, Veneta, watchet or light blew, Præsina, i. greene, and Rosea, i. Rose coloured or read. Unto which were added by Domitian Aurata and Purpurea, i. Gold coloured or yellow, and purple. The former foure Sidonius Apollinaris hath comprised in his Hendecasyllabes, thus:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Micant colores,</l>
                <l>Albus cum veneto, virens rubensque.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>Then shine these crewes and make a gallant shew<br/>In white, in blew, in greene and roset hew.</p>
            <p>Proportionate they are unto the foure seasons of the yeare: white, to the Autumne or end of Sommer, Watchet to the winter, Greene to the spring, and Red to sommer, or as some would have it to the foure Elements.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Physicians have observed three kinds of dropsie. The first is Ascites, wherein the belly doth swell with much water gathered betweene the inner skin or rine of the belly, and the cawle which lappeth the guts, and some wind withall, so named of ἀσκὸς in Greeke, i. A bottle, because in turning of the bodie to a side, the water is perceived to shog in the womb, like as liquor in a bottle halfe full, when it is shaken. The second, Tympanites, wherein the belly is hoven up with wind especially, and some water among. Whereby it will sound like a taber or drum, if one tamper upon it, and thereof it was so called. The third Leucophlegmatias, anasarca, Hyposarca, in Latin Intercus, or Aqua intercutem, in the proper signification<note place="foot" n="1">For Cornelius Celsus attributeth this name to all the kindes.</note>, when the bodie all over is puffed up with water and wind running betweene the fell and the flesh. And thereof as should seeme, died this Domitius.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="6">
        <note n="a">
            <p>To wit, the ninth day after he was borne, on which they used to name their sonnes. And as this day was called Nominalia, so there was a goddesse forsooth, president of this complement and ceremonies, whom they named Nundina.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="7">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The manner was, during these solemnities in the Albane mount, (where the chiefe magistrates were present) to leave for Provost of the Citie, some principall young Gentleman of the Nobilitie, before whom sitting judicially, causes of no great importance should be brought.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="11">
        <note n="a">
            <p>These youthfull sports Iuvenalia, or Iuvenales ludi, were first instituted by this Nero, privately in houses or gardens, and orchards. Wherein, of all degrees, ages and sexes they daunced and revelled.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="12">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The fabulous reports of Ladie Pasiphæ wife to King Minos, how she was enamoured of a Bull, as also of Icarus the sonne of Dædalus, who would needs attempt to flie in the ayre, be well enough knowen to them that are but meanely seene in Poetrie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Iuxca cubiculum eius decidit. By Cubiculum, he meaneth heere, a royall seat raised on high within that quarter of the Theater called Orchestra, under a rich Tent or Canopie, where Emperors were wont to sit when they beheld such solemnities. These Pavillions were called in Greeke οὐρανισκοὶ κωνώπεα in some sort resembling bed-chambers.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>So named because they that wrestled, ran, or otherwise exercised, were naked, like as the place itselfe of such exercises thereupon tooke the name Gymnasium.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="16">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Full and formall suppers, whereto men were invited, and at which the guestes sate orderly marshalled according to their worth place, and were called cænæ rectæ, and after this manner in other Princes daies were their favorites feasted. In steed hereof came in Sportula, i. allowances given unto them, eyther in money, or cates, in recompence of their ordinarie salutations and attendance.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>As there were sundrie factions or crewes favourizing this or that colour of the Chariotters, so were there likewise of Actours and players, whereupon many roiots, outrages, Fraies and murthers were committed.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="17">
        <note n="a">
            <p>It should seeme, that for the pleading and triall of causes, such Tribunal seats, pues, benches and barrs, were erected at first, for the present occasion, and taken downe againe by certaine persons, who gathered therfore a rent of those that went to law.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="18">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Divers Kings of Pontus were named Polemones as of Ægypt Ptolemæi, whereupon the realme Pontus, is by Vopiscus called Polemonius, like as the Alpes Cottiæ of Cottius.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="19">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Many had attempted this beside him but all their cost and labour came to nought: οὕτως χαλεπὸν ἀνθρώπῳ τὰ θεῖα βιάσασθαι.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="20">
        <note n="a">
            <p>τῆς λανθανούσης μουσικῆς οὐδεῖς λόγος.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>In respect of a former fleet, that was wont to come before, and bring newes of the second laden with marchandise and under saile. Therefore those ships were called naves Tabellaria. Seneca.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Bombos, resembling either the buzzing and humming noise of Bees, or the sound of trumpets.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Imbrices, much after the manner of that rattling, which a sodaine shewre makes upon the tiles of an house, or the sound that crest tiles or gutter tiles may make.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Testas, to expresse the crashing of potsheards or earthen pots, clattering one against another.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>Insignes pinguissima coma. In which sense we read of pingues togæ and Lacerna. Yet some understand thereby λιπαροπλοκάμους, i. whose lokes and faix were so slicke and glib with sweet oyles, that they shone againe.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="21">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For, so would he have it to be called. And Thraseas Pætus was judicially convented, and deeply charged, because he had never offred sacrifice for that heavenly voice of his. Tacit.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Who was with child by her owne brother Macareus, whereupon her father Æolus caused the childe new borne to be cast before hungrie dogs and sent a sword to his daughter to kill her selfe with.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>In revenge of his father Agamemnons death, by her murdered, whereupon he fell into a furious kinde of deepe melancholie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Who unwitting killed his owne father Laius, and as ignorantly wedded his owne mother Iocasta.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>By putting on a garment next his skinne, envenomed with the poison of Nessus the Centaure, and so sent unto him as a token, from his wife Deianira.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="24">
        <note n="a">
            <p>It may be it was thought, that he then acted Edipus or Creon or some other King, and therefore carried in his hand a regall staffe or Sceptre. Yet some interprete this of a Lawrel rod or braunch, such as Actors held in their hands while they sung.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>For, at Olimpia, were Games also of Criers, striving who could cry lowdest, for the prize.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>These were called Hieronica, as one would say, sacred victories, to witt at the solemne games in Greece, Nemea, Pythia, Istmia, and Olimpia.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="25">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Five thousand were there of these Gallants, as Xiphilinus writeth, ready to applaud him when he chaunted.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="26">
        <note n="a">
            <p>He meaneth eyther a peruke and cap of counterfait haire, Κόμας περιθέτους, Dioni thereby disguising himselfe: the same that in Caligula he termeth Capillamentum, or else some hood covering his head all save the eyes. Julius Capitolinus calleth it Cucullionem, wherewith the Emperour Verus played such parts by night, in imitation of Caligula and Nero.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Quintana was a Gate or Street rather in the Roman Campe, wherein was usually kept, Forum rerum utensilium, in resemblance whereof, he termed a certaine place in his house Quintana, in which he made sale of such wares and commodities, as he had gotten together by rifling and robbing.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>It appeareth by Tacitus, that this was Julius Montanus, who, albeit he had not sitten in counsell as Senator, yet was Laticlavius, and wore the Senators Robe. Such Gentlemen were called Iuvenes secundi ordinis, in distinction of those of the Imperiall bloud, or otherwise neere allied unto the Emperour.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="27">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The manner was in old time to imploy the day in businesses, and therein to take no liberall meales, putting off the full refection, and cherishing of the bodie untill night. Convivia de die, argued Intemperance, much more then feasting from noone to midnight.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Ambubaiarum. These tooke their name (as most expositors have conjectured), Quod circa Baias versarentur. Yet some learned men of later time fetch the same from this Syriacke word Anbubaicæ, as if such were Syrian women, who being otherwise naughtie packes and callots, gat their living also by playing upon certaine instruments of musike, which they brought with them out of their native countrey.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Copas imitantium. Although Copæ, properly be such women as keepe victualling houses, readie not onely to entertaine, but also to invite and call in guestes, yet because these commonly are verie bold and unshamefaced, this terme goeth indifferently for strumpets and curtesans. For seldome shall a man see an impudent woman that is not withall incontinent, so inseparably is modestie joyned with Chastitie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>The corrupt text in this place hath given occasion of much obscuritie, and ministred matter enough for Criticks to worke upon, while some read Mellita, others Myrtitrichila. By which are ment certaine sweat junkets, as daintie wafers, etc.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>This may be thought incredible, that banqueting conceits at one sitting should cost so much, and the aspersion of rose-water or other odoriferous liquors arise to more. Where is to be noted the observation of some, who for ab Syrtio rosaria read aspersio rosaria, that is to say, the artificiall besprinkling and aromatizing (as I may so say) of banqueting rowmes, out of spouts and pipes, conveying odoriferous waters and oyles, going under the name of Rosaria. Which spouts, if they were made of silver or gold, (as we read they were at the feast of Otho, when he gave Nero entertainment) might soone amount to that somme. To say nothing of the costly compound distilled waters, or extracts and oyles, themselves, drawen out of most pretious simples and spices.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="28">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Him he called, as other Authors write, Sabbina and Poppӕа, after the name of his wife deceased.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="29">
        <note n="a">
            <p>In other writers he is named Pythagoras, so that it should seeme he caried two names.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="30">
        <note n="a">
            <p>A great Magician, whom he intertained thus royally, because he would have learned magicke of him. See Plinie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Whereas Augustus when he played at this game, ventured no more, than for everie Talus, which were foure in all, a single denier. For it should seeme that the game of Tali heere mentioned, was Pleistobolinda, i. who could throw most with four Tali, whether the same were cockall bones in deed, or made of gold, silver or Ivorie, with foure sides, everie one representing a chaunce, an Ace or unitie and sise, a trey and quatre, opposite, one unto the other. For they wanted deux and cinque, which the Tessera Cubus, or Die carying six faces, hath.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>It is evident hereby, as also out of that verse of Juvenal, Ut læti phaleris omnes et torquibus omnes, that these Phalere were not Trappings and furniture belonging to horses, but some other ornaments, wherewith footmen and horsemen both were trimly decked.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="33">
        <note n="a">
            <p>In this verbe Morari, there is couched a double sense, which gives the grace unto this pleasant scoffe. For, being a meere Latin word, and having the first sillable by nature short, it signifieth, to stay or to make long abode: and taking it thus, Nero might be thought to imply thus much, that Claudius was now departed out of the companie of mortall men, and raunged among the heavenly wights. But take the same word, as Nero spake it, derived of μῶρος in Greeke, which signifyeth, A foole, and hath the first syllable long, it importeth, that Claudius played the foole no longer here in the world among men. Read the little pamphlet of Seneca entituled ἀποκολοκήντωσις, if ye would see Claudius depainted in his colours, and in a fooles coat: which he, as it may appeare, composed of purpose to gratifie Nero in that humour of his.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The Greekes call this Κανστραν οι τύβον. And the Romans in honour of their Princes, were wont to compasse the same all about with a wall of flint, or other durable stone, as marble.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="34">
        <note n="a">
            <p>It may be it was in the same forme, that Justinus Martyr citeth out of Orpheus: θύρας δ᾽ ἐπίθεσθε βεβήλος. Fortes opponite profanis. Which Virgil in some sort hath expressed thus: Procul este profani. And Claudian after him: Gressus removete profani.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="37">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The like example is reported by Vopiscus in Aurelianus, who tooke wonderfull delight in a mightie Eater<note place="foot" n="2">Phagone.</note>, that in one day before his owne table, devoured a wild bore full and whole, an hundred loaves of bread, a wether mutton, and a pig.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="38">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This Iambicke verse, as Dion writeth, was rife also in Tiberius Cæsars mouth.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Albeit this word, Insula, beside the common signification of an Iland, is taken for an house standing entire by it selfe, a part from other, yet in this Author I observe that it is put els where for other houses also and tenements let out to tenants by the owners and Landlords, who are called Domini Insularum. And even in this acception, it may well goe in this place.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>This toure Horace describeth, Carm. lib. 3, Od. 19, in these words, Molem propinquam nubibus arduis, etc.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="39">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which number ariseth to ten thousand a moneth. A mortalitie nothing comparable to that which as Eusebius reporteth, reigned at Rome in the daies of Vespasian, in which there died of the pestilence ten thousand a day, nor to that in Constantinople, when many daies, there were likewise ten thousand dead bodies caried forth. Procop. lib. 2, de bello persico.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Such a rumor in deed ran rife, but untruly. Tacitus.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Orestes to revenge his father Agamemnons death wrought by Clytemnestra his mother and Ægysthus the adulterer, murdered her.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Alcmæon sonne of Amphiaraus and Eriphyle, killed her, bycause shee had contrived his fathers death.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Æneas caried his old father Anchises upon his shoulders out of the fyre of Troy when it burned. Here is to be noted the duple sense of the verbe [Sustulit] in one and the same Latin verse: for in the former place, it signifieth to Kill, or make away, as Nero did his mother, in the later, to take up and cary, as Æneas did his father. This yeeldeth an elegant grace in Latin, and cannot so well be expressed in English.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>Apollo was surnamed Pæan of παίειν in Greek, which signifieth to strike, or of παύειν, to ease and allay paine, as being a God, that both sendeth diseases, and also cureth them. But commonly the Romaines terme him so, in this latter and better sense. He is styled likewise Hecatebeletes in Greek, which is as much, as shooting or wounding from afarr. In these abstruse significations and obscure termes therefore this Epigram implyeth thus much: That whiles Nero in the habit of Apollo plaieth upon the harpe. and would seeme to be a milde and gratious Prince: the Parthian King with bow and arrowes representing Apollo likewise, endaungered the Empire of Rome, and all, through the supine negligence of Nero geven to his Musick and other vanities excessively.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="g">
            <p>This is ment by that huge house of Neroes building, and hath a reference to that desolate estate of Rome, when it was sacked and fyred by the French, after the imfortunate battaile of Allia, what time the Romaines were in consultation to abandon the Cittie and departe to Veii, there to inhabite.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="h">
            <p>It seemeth that Nero in his Poeme entituled Troica, had used to chaunt of Nauplius the father of Palamedes, who abid many calamities himselfe, and in revenge of his sonnes death, wrought much mischiefe to others. The Cynicke therefore, noteth Nero for his singing, as also for abusing his owne good parts in perpetrating all wickednesse, or else for mispending his treasure so dissolutely.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="i">
            <p>῎Εῤῥωσο δὴ καὶ ὑγίαινε, οὔτε λέγειν οὔτε ἀκούειν, ἀγαθὸν, οὐ γὰρ προσίοντες ἄλλοις, οὔτε μέλλοντές τι πράττειν, ταῦτα λέγουσιν ἄνθρωποι, ἀλλὰ ἀπαλαττόμενοι ἀλλήλων, καὶ πρὸς ἄπνον τρεπόμενοι. Artemidor. lib. 1, cap. ult.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="j">
            <p>By Orcus, or Pluto, taken for the God of Hell or the Grave, is understood death, in this place, readie to seize upon the Senatours, whose overthrow Nero had intended. Now, well knowne it is, that the manner was then, among the Romans, as at this day with us, to cary forth their dead with the feet forward.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="40">
        <note n="a">
            <p>It should seeme, this answere was delivered in these words:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Εξηκοστὸν ἔτος τρισκαιδέκατόντε φυλάττου.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>Of sixtieth yeare (I doe thee reed)<br/>And thirteenth more, see thou take heed.</p>
            <p>Whereby Apollo (for his oblique aunswers rightly of the Greeks termed Loxias) or the Divell himselfe, whether you will, playing with him in a two-fold and ambiguous construction, (as his manner was) deluded him. For whiles he rested secure, dreaming still of the 73 yeare, which he supposed was meant of his owne age, and which he was farre short of, he fell into the hands of Galba, a man indeede of those yeares.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="45">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Rome was wont to be served of corne from Alexandrea in Ægypt, in the time of dearth especially, when Cicilie, otherwise reckoned Horreum populi Romani, i. the people of Romes Garner, was not able to furnish them. Now, when in steede of corne long expected, there arrived certaine saile from thence fraught with dust and sand for the sports of his gallants: no mervaile if all the discontentment and heart-burning of the people conceived against Cornmongers and such as made gaine by the scarcitie of graine, redounded upon Nero and his Courtiers.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Νῦν γὰρ ἐστ᾽ ἀγών. The end of some Trimetre or Senarie Iambicke verse in a Tragedie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Νῦν δεῖ ἐλαύνειν ἢ ἕλκειν,  . Now 'tis high time to drive or draw. In both which Empreses, by a most tart and bitter Sarcasmus, is taxed his excessive love of Charioting.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>The speech of the people, or of his mother, who could not reclayme him.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>As a Paricide or Killer of Parents, etc., whose judgement was to be sowed quicke within a lether budge, etc.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>There is not only an Homonyme in the word [Gallos] signifying the French Nation, and the crowing cocks, but an Amphibolie also in the sentence: whereby it may be understood, eyther that Nero with his chaunting, had awakened the French, who began now to revolt, as not able any longer to endure his songs: or that the French awakened him, to bestirre himselfe and looke better about him as if they were the Cockes indeed, to raise him out of his drowsie securitie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="g">
            <p>The ambiguitie of this word [Vindex], implieth both a private chastiser of servants for their faults, and also C. Julius Vindex, a revenger of publicke injuries, and a maintainer of the common libertie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="h">
            <p>Who now had taken Armes against Nero.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="46">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Auspicia, albeit they properly do signifie presaging tokens delivered by birds: yet the sequence and circumstance of this passage, lead us rather to some other uncouth prodigies and straunge sightes.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Nero was semblably distained, in another kinde: as having murdered his Father Claudius<note place="foot" n="1">Who adopted him.</note>, his mother Agrippina, and his two wives Octavia and Poppæa.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="47">
        <note n="a">
            <p>A cælatura carminum Homeri. Which if wee straine a little, may be Englished thus, for the workmanship and engraving upon them, out of Homers verses. Alluding to that standing massie cup of Nestors, described by Homer in the eleventh of his Ilias.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>An halfe verse out of Virgil, 12 Æneid. The words of Turnus unto his sister Juturna.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Although there were divers Præfecturæ in Ægypt, called Nomi, as one would say, Shires or Divisions, as appeareth in Plinie, 5 lib. cap. 9. Yet by this place is to be understood the Presidencie over all Ægypt, which by the institution of Augustus, was ordinarily conferred upon some Gentlemen of Rome. By which, it appeareth, he would play at small game rather than sit out.</p>
        </note>
    </div>
</div>