<text>
  <div type="notes" n="20">
        <note>
            <p>τῆς λανθανούσης μουσικῆς οὐδεῖς λόγος. [cite: 59]</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>In respect of a former fleet, that was wont to come before, and bring newes of the second laden with marchandise and under saile. [cite: 60] Therefore those ships were called naves Tabellaria. Seneca. [cite: 61]</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>Bombos, resembling either the buzzing and humming noise of Bees, or the sound of trumpets. [cite: 62]</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>Imbrices, much after the manner of that rattling, which a sodaine shewre makes upon the tiles of an house, or the sound that crest tiles or gutter tiles may make. [cite: 63]</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>Testas, to expresse the crashing of potsheards or earthen pots, clattering one against another. [cite: 64]</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>Insignes pinguissima coma. In which sense we read of pingues togæ and Lacerna. Yet some understand thereby λιπαροπλοκάμους, i. [cite: 65] whose lokes and faix were so slicke and glib with sweet oyles, that they shone againe. [cite: 66]</p>
        </note>
    </div>
  <div type="chapter" n="21">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Esteeming so highly as he did of singing, he solemnized at Rome also againe the foresaid games called Neroneum before the day and time by order appointed<note type="numerical" n="6">Every fifth yeares.</note>. And when all the people called upon him for his celestial voice<note type="alphabetical" n="a">For, so would he have it to be called. And Thraseas Pætus was judicially convented, and deeply charged, because he had never offred sacrifice for that heavenly voice of his. Tacit.</note>, he made answere: That he verily would do them that pleasure (being so willing and desirous as they were to heare him): but it should be in his Hortyards. Howbeit, when the corps de guarde of the (Pretorian) Souldiers which at that time kept watch and ward seconded the praiers of the common people, willingly he promised to fulfill their minds out of hand in the very place; and without any farther delay caused his owne name to be written in the roll of other professed minstrels and singers to the harpe. Thus having put his lot into the pitcher with the rest, hee entred the stage when his turne came: and withall the Capitaines of the Guard supporting his harpe: after them the tribunes militarie, and close unto them his most inwarde friendes and Minions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Now when hee had taken up his standing, and ended his Proæme, he gave publike notice and pronounced by the voice of Cluvius Rufus, (no meaner man than of Consuls degree) that he would sing and act the storie of Niobe<note type="numerical" n="1">Wife of Amphion King of Thebes, who priding herself in her faire issewe 6 sonnes and as manie daughters durst compare with Latona, and prefer herselfe before her, who had but 2, Apollo and Diana. Whereupon they two, to wreke their mothers injurie, shot all the said children to death. Wherewith the mother halfe franticke for sorrow, was turned into a stone.</note>: and so continued hee well neere unto the tenth houre of the day<note type="numerical" n="2">Foure of the clocke after noone.</note>: which done he differred the Musicke Coronet due for the present victorie, and the residue of the games, unto the next yeare following; and all because he might have occasion oftener to chaunt.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="115"/> Hee sung moreover, disguised, Tragædies of the worthies and gods: of noble Ladies likewise in olde time and of goddesses, having their visards<note type="numerical" n="5">Or Masques.</note> framed and made to the likenesse of his own face and of some woman whom hee loved. Among the rest he chanted the tale of Canace travailing in child-birth<note type="alphabetical" n="b"><p>Who was with child by her owne brother Macareus, whereupon her father Æolus caused the childe new borne to be cast before hungrie dogs and sent a sword to his daughter to kill her selfe with.</p></note>: of Orestes who killed his own Mother<note type="alphabetical" n="c">In revenge of his father Agamemnons death, by her murdered, whereupon he fell into a furious kinde of deepe melancholie.</note>: of Edipus that plucked out his own eyes<note type="alphabetical" n="d">Who unwitting killed his owne father Laius, and as ignorantly wedded his owne mother Iocasta.</note>, and of Hercules enraged<note type="alphabetical" n="e">By putting on a garment next his skinne, envenomed with the poison of Nessus the Centaure, and so sent unto him as a token, from his wife Deianira.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="22">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Exceedingly given hee was of a boy to delight in horse-manship, and with the love of charioting mightily inflamed : and very much would he be talking (forbidden though he were) of the Circeian games. And one time as hee was making mone, and bewailing among his skoole-fellowes, the hard fortune of a chariot driver, one of the greene-coate faction, drawen and dragged by his steedes<note type="numerical" n="1">Or sore wounded and bruised with the wheeles running over him. See Plin. Nat. Hist. lib. 28 cap. 17.</note>, being chidden therefore by his schoole-master, he had a lye ready, and said that he spake of Hector<note type="numerical" n="2">Who was likewise, Raptatus Bigis as Virgil writeth.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="116"/> Soone after himselfe also would needs make one and be seene oftentimes to play the Chariotier. And when he had tryed what hee could doe, and performed, as it were, his first Actes in (private) hortyardes among verie slaves and the base commons, he proceeded to shew himselfe in the greatest Cirque in all mens eyes, appointing a certaine freed man of his to put out a white linnen cloth<note type="numerical" n="3">Mappam. To give the warning peece or token to start.</note> for a signall, from the place where Magistrates are wont to doe it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Those Cities and states where solemne gamings of musicke are usually held, had brought up a custome to sende all the Coronets of harpe-players unto him. This he accepted so kindly, that he not onely admitted at the very first to his presence the Embassadors who brought the same, but also placed them among his familiar guestes at the table. And being requested by some of them to sing at supper time, and highly praised with <pb n="117"/> excessive applause, he came out with this speech, That Græcians were the onely skilfull Hearers, and the men alone worthie of his studies. Neither would he deferre his journey thither but embarqued incontinently.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="23">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>After this, he went to all the games of prise, one after another: for even those that usually are celebrated at most remote and distant times he commanded to be reduced all into one yeare, and some of them also to be iterated<note type="numerical" n="3">Solemnized twice in the same yeare.</note>. At Olympia likewise hee caused, (contrarie to the manner and custome of that place) a game of musick to be held. And that he might not whiles he was thus busied, be called away or withdrawen by any meanes: when his freed-man Helius advertised him that the Citie affaires required his presence, he wrote backe unto him in these words, Howsoever your counsell to me, and your willing desire is, that I should returne with all speede: yet ought you to advise me rather and wish, that I may returne worthie of my selfe, that is to say, of Nero.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>All the while hee was singing, lawefull it was not for anye person to depart out of the Theatre, were the cause never so necessarie. Whereupon reported it is, that some great bellied women falling into travaile were delivered upon the very skaffolds : yea and many men besides, wearie of tedious hearing and praysing him, when the towne gates were shut, eyther by stealth leapt downe from the walles, or counterfeiting themselves dead were caried forth as corses to bee buried. But how timorously, with what thought and anguish of minde, with what æmulation of his concurrents and feare of the Umpiers, hee strove for the Mastery, it is almost incredible.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="118"/> His manner was to deale with his adversaries, as if they had beene but his equals and of the same condition: to ly in the wind for to catch advantage: to defame them under hand: otherwhiles to raile at them and give them hard words when he met them: yea and to corrupt with bribes<note type="numerical" n="1">Thereby to make them relent and not to do their best.</note> and giftes such as excelled in skill and cunning.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="24">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>During the time that hee strove for to winne any prise, so strictely obeyed hee the lawes of the game, that hee never durst once spit and reach up fleame: and the very swet of his forehead hee wiped away with his arme onely<note type="numerical" n="2">Or sleeve and not with anie handkercheife.</note>. Moreover in the acting of a Tragædie, when he had quickly taken up his staffe<note type="alphabetical" n="a">It may be thought, that he then acted Edipus or Creon or some other King, and therefore carried in his hand a regall staffe or Sceptre. Yet some interprete this of a Lawrel rod or braunch, such as Actors held in their hands while they sung.</note> againe, which he happened to let fall, being much dismaied and in great feare, least for that delinquent he should be put from the stage: by no meanes tooke he heart againe, until an under actor or prompter standing by sware an oth that it was not espied, for the shouts and acclamations of the people that were about him. Now, whensoever he wan the victorie, he used to pronounce himselfe victour. For which cause, he contended also in every place for the Criers coronet<note type="numerical" n="4">Due to him that had the lowdest voice.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="b">For, at Olimpia, were Games also of Criers, striving who could cry lowdest, for the prize. These were called Hieronica, as one would say, sacred victories, to witt at the solemne games in Greece, Nemea, Pythia, Istmia, and Olimpia.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="119"/> Furthermore, he ran with chariots for the best game in many places, and at the Olympicke solemnities with one that had a teeme of tenne steedes, notwithstanding he had in a certaine Poeme of his, reproved King Mithridates for the same. But being once shaken and hoisted out of his Chariot and set therein againe, howbeit not able to hold out, he desisted and gave over, before he had runne the race through. Yet was he crowned neverthelesse.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="25">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Beeing returned out of Greece hee entred Naples, mounted upon a Chariot drawne with white horses, through a breach in the wals made of purpose, (as the manner of all victors in those sacred games is). Semblably rode he into Antium, and from thence into Albanum and so forward into Rome. But he entred Rome in the very same Chariot, wherein sometime Augustus had rode in triumph, clad in a purple cloke<note type="numerical" n="1">Or Mantell.</note>, and the same garnished with starres embrodered in golde: wearing upon his head the Olympicke Coronet<note type="numerical" n="2">Made of the wilde Olive branches.</note>, and bearing in his right hand the Pythisk<note type="numerical" n="3">Of Lawrell.</note>...  not without a traine also of Applauders, following his Chariot, after the manner of those that ride ovant in petie Triumph<note type="alphabetical" n="a">Five thousand were there of these Gallants, as Xiphilinus writeth, ready to applaud him when he chaunted.</note> setting up a note, and crying with a lowde voice, That they were Augustians, and the souldiers of his triumph.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="120"/> As for the sacred Coronets and guirlands aforesayde, he bestowed them in his owne bed-chamber round about his beds: likewise his owne statues pourtraied in the habit of an harper<note type="numerical" n="1">Or Minstrell.</note>, and with that marke stamped he his money. And after all this, so far was he from letting slacke and remitting one jote his ardent studie of Musick, that for the preservation of his voice, he would never make speech unto his souldiers but by messages, or else having another to pronounce the same for him, when he was present himselfe: neither did he ought in earnest or mirth, without his Phonascus by, a governour of his voice, to put him in minde for to spare his wind and hold his handkercheife to his mouth. Unto many men he either offered his friendship or denounced enmitie, according as every one praised him more or lesse.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="26">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His unruly wildnesse, unbridled lust, wastfull riotousnesse, avarice and cruelty, he practised verely at first, by leasure closely, as the trickes of youthfull folly: yet so, as even then no man might doubt, that they were the inbred vices of nature, and not the errors of young age. No sooner was it twi-light and the evening shut in but presently he would catch up a capsa<note type="alphabetical" n="a">He meaneth eyther a peruke and cap of counterfait haire, Κόμας περιθέτους, Dioni thereby disguising himselfe: the same that in Caligula he termeth Capillamentum, or else some hood covering his head all save the eyes. Julius Capitolinus calleth it Cucullionem, wherewith the Emperour Verus played such parts by night, in imitation of Caligula and Nero.</note> on his head, and so disguised, goe into tavernes and victualling houses, and range sporting about the streetes, howbeit not without shrewd turnes and mischiefe. For he used to fall upon those that came late from supper and knocke them soundly; yea and if they struggled with him and made resistance, to wound them and drowne them in the sinkes and bogs: to breake into petie shops also, and rifle them: for he had set up in his house at home a faire<note type="alphabetical" n="b">Quintana was a Gate or Street rather in the Roman Campe, wherein was usually kept, Forum rerum utensilium, in resemblance whereof, he termed a certaine place in his house Quintana, in which he made sale of such wares and commodities, as he had gotten together by rifling and robbing.</note>, there to receive the price of the bootie which hee had gotten, and so was sold to who would give most and bid best for it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="121"/> But many a time at such brawles and skufflings aforesaied, he endangered his eyes, yea and his life too; being once beaten well neere to death by a certaine young gentleman of Senatours degree<note type="alphabetical" n="c">It appeareth by Tacitus, that this was Julius Montanus, who, albeit he had not sitten in counsell as Senator, yet was Laticlavius, and wore the Senators Robe. Such Gentlemen were called Iuvenes secundi ordinis, in distinction of those of the Imperiall bloud, or otherwise neere allied unto the Emperour.</note>, whose wife he had misused with uncleane handling. Whereupon, never after durst he goe abroad into the streets at that time of the night, without his Tribunes following him a farre off and secretly. In the day time also, being closely caried in a chaire into the Theater, he would be present in person, and out of the upper part of the proscene<note type="numerical" n="1">Where he might directly sit and looke downe upon the stage.</note> looking downe give a signall to the seditious factions of players, and animated them. Now when they were come once to plaine battell, and fought with stones and peeces of broken seats, himselfe flung many among the people, and with one brake the head of a Prætor.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="27">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>But as his vices grewe by little and little to get head, he laide aside these wilde trickes by way of sport and in secret : and without all care of concealing and dissimuling the matter, broke out openly to greater outrages.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>His meales hee drewe out at length<note type="alphabetical" n="a">The manner was in old time to imploy the day in businesses, and therein to take no liberall meales, putting off the full refection, and cherishing of the bodie untill night. Convivia de die, argued Intemperance, much more then feasting from noone to midnight.</note>: eating and drinking from noone to midnight, foveting and cherishing himselfe oftentimes in hote baines, and in sommer season in bathes cooled with snowe. His suppers hee tooke divers times abroade also in publike place, to wit, in the Naumachia<note type="numerical" n="5">A broad place, wherein a Naval fight had sometime been exhibited. Read Tacit. annal lib. 15.</note> shut up and enclosed, or else in the Mars field, where hee was served and attended upon by all the common Queanes of the Citie, and stinking strumpets of the stewes<note type="alphabetical" n="b">Ambubaiarum. These tooke their name (as most expositors have conjectured), Quod circa Baias versarentur. Yet some learned men of later time fetch the same from this Syriacke word Anbubaicæ, as if such were Syrian women, who being otherwise naughtie packes and callots, gat their living also by playing upon certaine instruments of musike, which they brought with them out of their native countrey. Copas imitantium. Although Copæ, properly be such women as keepe victualling houses, readie not onely to entertaine, but also to invite and call in guestes, yet because these commonly are verie bold and unshamefaced, this terme goeth indifferently for strumpets and curtesans. For seldome shall a man see an impudent woman that is not withall incontinent, so inseparably is modestie joyned with Chastitie.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="122"/> His manner was also to give warning unto his familiar friends, and bid him selfe to supper: and one of them it cost in sweet meats<note type="alphabetical" n="c">The corrupt text in this place hath given occasion of much obscuritie, and ministred matter enough for Criticks to worke upon, while some read Mellita, others Myrtitrichila. By which are ment certaine sweat junkets, as daintie wafers, etc.</note> 4 millians<note type="numerical" n="1">Quadragies HS.</note> of sesterces<note type="alphabetical" n="d">This may be thought incredible, that banqueting conceits at one sitting should cost so much, and the aspersion of rose-water or other odoriferous liquors arise to more. Where is to be noted the observation of some, who for ab Syrtio rosaria read aspersio rosaria, that is to say, the artificiall besprinkling and aromatizing (as I may so say) of banqueting rowmes, out of spouts and pipes, conveying odoriferous waters and oyles, going under the name of Rosaria. Which spouts, if they were made of silver or gold, (as we read they were at the feast of Otho, when he gave Nero entertainment) might soone amount to that somme. To say nothing of the costly compound distilled waters, or extracts and oyles, themselves, drawen out of most pretious simples and spices.</note>: and another a good deale more in rose water and odoriferous oyles.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="28">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Over and besides the unnaturall abusing of boyes free-borne, and the keeping of mens wives as his concubines, he forced also and defloured Rubria, a vestale Virgin. Acte a freed woman he went very neere to have wedded as his lawefull wife<note type="numerical" n="2">Which had beene a great disparagement.</note>, suborning certaine men who had beene Consuls, to sweare and forsweare that shee was borne of King Attalus his royal bloud. A boy there was named Sporus<note type="alphabetical" n="a">Him he called, as other Authors write, Sabbina and Poppæa, after the name of his wife deceased.</note>, whose Genitories he cut out, and assayed therby to transforme him into the nature of a woman. Him he caused to be brought unto him as a bride, with a dowry, in a fine (yellow) veile, after the solemne maner of mariage, not without a great traine and much pompe: whom he maintained as his wife. Touching which Sporus, a pretie and merrie conceited speech of a certaine person is still currant, That it had been speeded well with the world, if Domitius his father had wedded such a wife.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>This Sporus, trimmed and set out with the abiliments of the Empresses, he caried about with him in his owne litter, both through the streets and markets of all Corporations in Greece, and also at Rome, in the Sigillaria<note type="numerical" n="3">A street in Rome where such wares were to be sold.</note>, kissing him other-whiles as they rode together. For, that he had a lust to ly with his owne mother, and was frighted from it by some depraving backe-friendes of hers; for feare, least the proude and insolent dame might by this kind of favour grow too mightie, no man ever made doubt: especially after that he had entertained among his concubines a certaine strumpet, most like in all points unto Agrippina.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="29">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>As for his owne body, certes, he forfeited the honour thereof, prostituting it to bee abused so farreforth, as having defiled in-manner all the parts of it, at the last, he devised a kind (as it were) of sport and game: that being covered all over in a wilde beastes skin, hee should be let loose forth of a cage<note type="numerical" n="1">Or grate. I wish that both Suetonius and Dio had in this place and such like been altogether silent.</note> and then give the assault upon the privities of men and women both as they stood tyed fast to a stake: and when he had shewed his rage to the full, be killed, forsooth by Doriphorus<note type="alphabetical" n="a">In other writers he is named Pythagoras, so that it should seeme he caried two names.</note> his freed-man, unto <pb n="123"/> whom him selfe also was wedded like as Sporus unto him: insomuch as hee counterfeited the noise and cries of maidens, when they bee forced and suffer devirgination<note type="numerical" n="2">Confessed of themselves and their owne accord.</note>. I have heard of divers that he was fully perswaded, No man nor woman was honest, or in any part of their bodies pure and cleane: but cloaked their uncleannesse onely, and craftily hid it. And therefore to such as freely confessed unto him their obscene filthinesse, he forgave all other faults and iniquities whatsoever.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="30">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The fruite of richesse and use of money, he tooke to be nothing else but lavish expense: thinking them to be very base niggards and mechanicall pinch-pennies, that kept any account or reckoning what they spent and layde out: but those onely right noble and brave gallants, who unthriftily wasted and confounded all. Neither praised hee or admired he his uncle C. Caligula for any thing so much as this, that in so short a time hee had spent downe to the bare pomeall that huge masse of wealth, which Tiberius left behind him. Knowing therefore no meane nor end of prodigalitie, he dealt and spent upon his favorites most excessive summes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Hee allowed unto Tiridates<note type="alphabetical" n="a">A great Magician, whom he intertained thus royally, because he would have learned magicke of him. See Plinie.</note> (a thing almost incredible) 800000 Sesterces, day by day, for his expenses, and at his departure bestowed upon him not so little as one hundred milians. Unto Menecrates the harper and Spicillus the fencer he gave the livelode and houses of men that had triumphed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="124"/> No garments did hee on his backe twice: at hazard when he played, he ventured no lesse than 400000 sesterces at a cast, upon every point or pricke of the chaunce<note type="numerical" n="1">Quadringenis Sestertiis. Take Sestertium here in the newter gender, of which 400000 make of our money about 3125 pound, which in four cast he might hap to loose.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="b">Whereas Augustus when he played at this game, ventured no more, than for everie Talus, which were foure in all, a single denier. For it should seeme that the game of Tali heere mentioned, was Pleistobolinda, i. who could throw most with four Tali, whether the same were cockall bones in deed, or made of gold, silver or Ivorie, with foure sides, everie one representing a chaunce, an Ace or unitie and sise, a trey and quatre, opposite, one unto the other. For they wanted deux and cinque, which the Tessera Cubus, or Die carying six faces, hath.</note> Hee fished with a golden net<note type="numerical" n="2">Aurato rete. Orosius saith more expresly, retibus aureis.</note> (drawen and knit) with cords twisted of purple and crimsen silke in graine. He never ordinarily journed with fewer than a thousand caroches drawen with mules. His mules were shod with silver. His mulitiers arraied in fine (red) Canusme cloth: and attended he was with a multitude of Mazaces and Curreurs gaily set out with their bracelets and riche Phalers<note type="alphabetical" n="d">It is evident hereby, as also out of that verse of Juvenal, Ut læti phaleris omnes et torquibus omnes, that these Phaleræ were not Trappings and furniture belonging to horses, but some other ornaments, wherewith footmen and horsemen both were trimly decked.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="31">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In no one thing was hee more wastefull and prodigall then in building. Hee made an house, that reached from the Palatium to the Esquiliæ: which at first he called his Transitorie: but when it had been consumed with fire and was reedefied hee named his golden ædifice. As touching the large compasse and receit, the rich furniture and setting out thereof, it may suffice to relate thus much. The porch was of such an heigth as therein might stand upright the geant-like image representing his owne person, an hundred and twentie foote high. So large was this house, as that it conteined three galleries of a mile a peece in length<note type="numerical" n="6">Porticus triplices milliarias. If a man expound it thus: Galleries with three rows of pillers, a mile long, it wold be more consonant to the truth I suppose.</note>. Semblably, a standing poole like unto a sea, and the same enclosed round about with buildings in forme of Cities. It received moreover, rurall tractes, medowes, vinyards, pastures, and woods, replenished with a multitude of tame and wilde beastes of all kindes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="125"/> In all other parts thereof, all was laide over with golde, garnished with precious stones and shels of pearle<note type="numerical" n="1">Mother of pearle.</note>. As for the parlours, framed they were with enbowed roufs, seeled with frets of Ivorie, devided into panils, which might turne about and let fall downe floures, and out of pipes shed forth sweet oiles from aloft. But of al these parlours and banqueting roomes, the principall and fairest was made rounde, to turne about continually both day and night, in manner of the World<note type="numerical" n="2">Or heaven.</note>. The baines within this house were continually supplied with salt water from the Sea, and rowghish water from the springs of Albula. This edifice thus finished, when hee came to dedicate and consecrate, hee liked it so well, that he commended it thus far forth, as to say, He now at length began to live like a man.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Furthermore, hee began a poole<note type="numerical" n="4">Piscinam.</note> reaching from Misenum to the Meere<note type="numerical" n="5">(Or lake.)</note> Avernus, cloystered and roofed all over, into which he might turne all the hote waters that were in the bathes of Baiæ. Likewise hee went about a Fosse or ditch, from the said Avernus unto Ostia, thereby to travell by water in shippes, and yet never be on the sea: in length 160 miles: and so broade, as five galleys with three bankes of Ores a peece, might passe in front one by another. For the performance of these workes, hee gave order, That all prisoners round about from every place should be convayed into Italie; and that no person convict of any wicked act, should in other manner bee condemned, but to these workes.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="32">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>To these outragious expenses, beside the trust and confidence he had in the revenewes of the Empire, put forward hee was upon a certaine unexpected hope also that he <pb n="126"/> conceived, of finding a world of wealth. And that by the intelligence given unto him of a Romane Knight, who assured him, that the rich treasure and old store of silver and gold both, which Queene Dido flying out of Tyros caried away with her, lay buried in Affricke within most huge and vaste caves: and might bee gotten out with a little labour.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>But when this hope failed him, and came to nothing, being altogether destitute and behind hand, so as he was hardly able to yeeld full pay unto the Souldiers, and exhibit the benefits due unto the olde servitours, he bent his mind to promoting of false imputations, to pilling also and polling. Before hee first established this order, That out of the goods of freed-men deceased, insteede of the one halfe, hee should exact five parts of sixe, if without good cause they bare the name of any family into which himselfe was engraffed<note type="numerical" n="1">Namely the Claudian or Julian.</note>. Afterwards, that their wils should be forfaite and confiscate, who were unthankeful to the Prince<note type="numerical" n="1">Remembred him not in their wils and made him not an heyre.</note>. Also, that the Lawyers who drew and wrot such wils, should not scape fine and punishment. Furthermore, that all words and deedes, whereby there was any waight to bee gotten by the law, should bee brought within the compasse of high Treason. Hee called in also the rewards and donatives, which he had given unto any Cities.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>And whereas hee had prohibited the use of the Amethist<note type="numerical" n="2">Or violet in graine.</note> and purple colours, he suborned one of purpose under hand to sell upon a market day<note type="numerical" n="3">Or faire.</note> some few ounces therof, and so shut up the shoppes of all the Marchants and occupiers therabouts. More then so, having espied once as he was singing a dame of the citie in the stage<note type="numerical" n="4">Among the beholders.</note> arrayed in purple, he pointed at her (as it is verily thought), and shewed her to his Procurators: who presently haled her downe, and stript her, not of her garment onely, but also of her goods and lands.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p><pb n="127"/> To conclude, he robbed the Temples of many giftes and oblations: the Images likewise therein made of golde or silver he melted into a masse: and among the rest, even those of the Tutelar gods<note type="numerical" n="3">Apollo, Neptune, Jupiter, Juno, Minerva.</note> (of Rome) : which soone after Galba restored and erected againe in their places.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="33">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>As touching his Parricides and murders hee began them first with Claudius: of whose death although he were not principall author, yet he was privie and accessarie thereto. Neither dissimuled he so much, as who afterwards was wont by a Greek by-word, to praise mushromes, (in which kinde of meat Claudius had taken his bane), as the foode of the gods<note type="numerical" n="5">θεῶν βρῶμα, alluding to the deification after his death.</note>. For, in scoffing wise he would say of him that hee had left now moraria<note type="alphabetical" n="a">In this verbe Morari, there is couched a double sense, which gives the grace unto this pleasant scoffe. For, being a meere Latin word, and having the first sillable by nature short, it signifieth, to stay or to make long abode: and taking it thus, Nero might be thought to imply thus much, that Claudius was now departed out of the companie of mortall men, and raunged among the heavenly wights. But take the same word, as Nero spake it, derived of μῶρος in Greeke, which signifyeth, A foole, and hath the first syllable long, it importeth, that Claudius played the foole no longer here in the world among men. Read the little pamphlet of Seneca entituled ἀποκολοκήντωσις, if ye would see Claudius depainted in his colours, and in a fooles coat: which he, as it may appeare, composed of purpose to gratifie Nero in that humour of his.</note> anie longer among mortall men, using the first sillable of the sayd word long. Many a time also he threw out many by-words and invectives against him, blaming his folly and cruelty: for hee would say, that he left off among men morari, staying upon the first sillable. Finally, he neglected the place of his funerall fire<note type="alphabetical" n="b">The Greekes call this Κανστραν οι τύβον. And the Romans in honour of their Princes, were wont to compasse the same all about with a wall of flint, or other durable stone, as marble.</note>: suffering it to be empaled<note type="numerical" n="7">As the manner was for certaine daies before the ashes and reliques were gathered up.</note>, but with sleight stuffe and low railes of timber.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>As for Britannicus, not so much for envie that he had a sweeter and better voice than himselfe, as for feare least sometime or other hee should bee preferred before him in the good grace and favour of the people, in the respect of his fathers memorie, he attempted to make him away by poison. This poison, Nero had received at the hands of one Locusta, a finder out of divers receipts, and a witnesse deposing against him. <pb n="128"/> Now when shee alleaged for her excuse that she gave him the lesse dose<note type="numerical" n="1">In quantitie.</note>, thereby to colour and cloke the odious fact... 'Why! then belike,' quoth he, 'I am affraide of the lawe Julia<note type="numerical" n="2">De Veneficiis. For her former practise of poisoning, by which she stoode condemned.</note>.' And so hee forced her before his face in his owne bed-chamber to compound and seeth a poison that should be most quicke and of present operation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Which done, he tryed it upon a kidde: and when the beast lingred 5 howres before it died, he caused the said potion to be boiled againe, and many times put his owne thereto. Then he offred it to a pigge; and seeeing it die presently upon the taking thereof, he commaunded it should be brought into the dining chamber, and given unto Britannicus as he sate at supper. No sooner had he tasted it but hee fell downe dead. Nero made no more adoe, but lying then as hee did, told the guestes, It was the falling sicknesse, wherewith he useth to bee caught. But the morrow after, he buried him in all hast, with meane and base obsequies, and in an outragious storme of raine. Unto this Locusta, for her paines, he gave a pardon and franke seidge<note type="numerical" n="4">Lands by patent without rent.</note> in the countrey: yea, and put unto her for to be taught, certaine schollars.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="34">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His owne mother, for looking narrowly into him, and examining his words and deedes somewhat streightly: for seeming also to correct and reforme the same, hee stomaked so much, that oftentimes he strained and wrung her with odious and bitter words: yea, and brought her to that passe, that shee was faine to depart his house, and retire into a private <pb n="129"/> place of her owne. Thus, for an amendment, he added one disgrace more unto another, withdrawing from her all honour, withdrawing the guarde of Souldiers, and the watch of Germans from her attendance. Furthermore, he forbad her his own company, and thrust her out of the Palatium. Passing from these indignities, he left no meanes unassayed to vexe and disquiet her: suborning some, who whiles she lay in Rome should daily trouble her with sutes and actions: and when she was retired for her rest into the country, other, who coasting as they went both by land and sea, should abuse her with reviling tauntes, and skoffing reproches. Pretending that he was about to resigne up the Empire and depart to Rhodes<note type="numerical" n="1">As if she were the cause therof.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>But beeing terrified with her threats and violent shrewdnesse, hee determined to kill and dispatch her at once. Having attempted it with poison thrice, and perceiving that she was defenced with preservatives, he provided a bed-chamber for her, with so ticklish an arched roufe over her head, as beeing easily unjoincted, the frame thereof might fall in peeces in the night, and light upon her as she lay a sleepe. When this designe was bewrayed and defeated by the complices that were privie thereto, he devised a pinnace that should be easily undone and floted, that either by the shipwracke, or by the fall of the cabbine aloft she might quickly perish. And so, making a semblance of a Love-day and reconciliation, hee sent for her by most sweet and kinde Letters, training her unto Baiæ, there to celebrate with him the solemnity of the Quinquatrian<note type="numerical" n="3">A feast in the honour of Minerva, beginning five daies before the Ides of March, i. the 11 of March.</note>. And having given order before hand to certaine Maisters of Gallies for to split the Foist<note type="numerical" n="4">Or Pinnace.</note> wherein she was embarqued (as if by chaunce they had runne against her), he put unto her the other abovesaid made with joints and vices, and protracted the <pb n="130"/> time of his feast until it was late in the night. Then at her returne unto Bauli, in liew of her owne which was broken, he offred her the said peecemeale barke, accompanied her (to the water side<note type="numerical" n="1">Or to the staires.</note>) and at the parting also kissed her paps.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The rest of that night he watched, with great trembling and feare, waiting for the event of his enterprise. But when he understood that all went crosse, and that she was escaped to land by swimming, being at his wits end and to seeke what he should doe, upon the sodaine comming of Lucius Agerinus her freed-man, by whom she sent him word with great joy, that she was both alive and safe, he slily conveied a skeane into the hand of the said Agerinus: and immediately catching him with the maner (as if he had beene suborned and hired by her to assassinate him) caused the said Agerinus to be apprehended and bound with chaines: and withall, his mother aforesaid, to be murdred, that he might give it out, she had made her selfe away, for that her treachery was detected.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Hereunto are added matters of a more hideous and feareful nature, by the report of men upon their credit: namely, that he came to see his mother when she was dead: that he felt and handled all the parts of her naked bodie: that he found fault with some, and commended others: and taking a thirst upon it, dranke his liquor. Yet could he not either for the present or ever after, endure the worme and sting of conscience for this foule fact, but confesse many a time, that haunted and harried he was with the apparition of his mothers ghost: tormented also with the scourges and burning torches of the Furies. Which was the cause that with a sacrifice made by the direction of Magicians, he obeied and called up her spright, and humbly besought her to release him of his paines. Verily as hee travailed through Greece, at the sacred Eleusine ceremonies<note type="alphabetical" n="a">It may be it was in the same forme, that Justinus Martyr citeth out of Orpheus: θύρας δ᾽ ἐπίθεσθε βεβήλος. Fortes opponite profanis. Which Virgil in some sort hath expressed thus: Procul este profani. And Claudian after him: Gressus removete profani.</note>... he durst not be present, when the cryer made a publike proclamation, That all wicked and ungodly persons should depart from thence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>To this parricidy of his mother, he adjoyned also the murder of his aunt<note type="numerical" n="4">Domitia by his fathers side.</note>. <pb n="131"/> For, finding her sore sicke in her bed, and feeling her pulse, when she as old folkes are wont to doe, soothingly flattered him, and saied, Let me once see the day that I may receive the mosse growing upon your chin<note type="numerical" n="1">i. your first beard downe.</note>, and then I care not if I die: he turning unto those that stood by, with a mocke, saied he would cause it to be taken off streight waies: and so commaunded the Physicians to give her a purgative more than ordinary. For, even before she was through dead, he laide sure hold of her goods, and suppressed her last wil that nothing might escape his clutches.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="35">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Besides Octavia, he maried afterwards two wives: to wit, Poppæa Sabina the daughter of one who had beene Questor, and the wedded wife before of a romane Knight : then, Statilia Messallina, neice<note type="numerical" n="8">In the right line of descent.</note> in the third degree removed of Taurus, twice Consul, who had once triumphed. For to have and enjoy her, he murdred her husband Atticus Vestinus then Consul, even during the time of that honorable Magistracie. Soone wearie he was of Octaviæ's companie and forsooke her bed. And when some friends reproved him for it he made answere, that the jewels els and ornaments only of a wife ought to content her.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Soon after, when he had assayed many times (but in vaine) to strangle her, he put her away, pretending she was barraine.  But when the people misliked this divorse, and forbare not to raile upon him for it, he proceeded, even to confine and banish her quite. In the end he murdred her, under a colourable imputation of divers adulteries, charged upon her so impudently and falsely, that when al generally who were by torture examined upon the point, stood stoutly to the very last in deniall, he suborned and brought in Anicetus<note type="numerical" n="10">Who had brought him up in his childhood.</note> his own Pædagogue against her, who should slander himselfe with her and confesse that by a wile he had abused her bodie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The twelfth day after the said divorcement of Octavia, he espoused and maried the aforesaid dame Poppæa, whom he loved intirely; and yet even her also he killed with a kicke<note type="numerical" n="1">Or spurne.</note> of his heele, for that, being big with child and sickly withall, she had reviled him and given him shrewd words, for comming home so late one night, after his running with chariots. By her he had a daughter named Claudia Augusta, whom he buried when she was a very infant.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>There was no kinde of affinitie and consanguinity were it never so neere, but it felt the waight of his deadly hand. Antonia, the daughter of Claudius, refusing after the death of Poppæa to bee his wife, he slew, under a pretense as if she went about to conspire against him and to alter the state. Semblably, he killed all the rest, that were either allied unto him or of his kinred. Among whom was A. Plautius a young gentleman... against whom he offered force by way of unaturall pollution, before he put him to death... </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>His Preceptor and Schoole-master Seneca he compelled to dye: albeit he had sworne unto him very devoutely, oftentimes making sute to depart the Courte, and yeelding up all his wealth into his handes, That he had no cause to suspect him: for he would rather lose his owne life then doe him anie hurt. Unto Burrhus, Captaine (of the guarde) he promised a medicine to heale his swollen throat<note type="numerical" n="1">A squinancie.</note>, and sent him the rank poison Toxicum for it. Free men of his own, that were rich and olde, whose favor, helpe and advise had been the chiefe meanes of his advancement to the Empire, he tooke away by poyson, partly mixt in their meates, and partly in their drinke.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </text>