<div type="chapter" n="1">
  <div type="section" n="1">
    <p>TITUS, surnamed as his Father was, Vespasianus... was borne... neere unto the Septizonium<note type="alphabetical" n="a">A PLACE in Rome so called of a building there, which stood upon seven courses of Columnes or Pillars, arising all round and higher every one than other, in manner of so many circles or girdles.</note>, within a poore ill-favoured house... </p>
  </div>
  <div type="section" n="2">
    <p>His Education hee had in the Court together with Britannicus... At which time verily, men say, that a Fortune-teller<note type="numerical" n="2">Metoposcopum.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="b">He meaneth not a Physiognomer, who hath taken upon him by inspection of eyes, forehead, face, etc., to tell ones nature and disposition: such an one as Zopyrus was, who noted Socrates for to be by naturall inclination a wanton lover of women: but a fortune teller, by looking on the forehead onely. Such as in these daies, by the art of Palmestrie, for-sooth, can assure folke, how long they shall live, and what not. If they do but see lines in the palmes of their hands, or by feaxe in the forehead, will say, how many wives a man shall have, etc. As vaine as those, who by counting the letters of the husband and the wives name, will confidently pronounce, whether of them shall burie the other. </note>... affirmed most constantly, that... Titus... should surely bee Emperour.</p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="chapter" n="3">
  <div type="section" n="1">
    <p>...as appeareth by a number of his images and titles<note type="alphabetical" n="a">By titles in this place, and many others of Suetonius, are to be understood inscriptions, testifying for what considerations such Statues were erected. Such also were usually set up at publicke executions, to shew the offences and causes why any suffered. A thing usuall among the Romanes in their government, in what Province so ever, as may appeare by that which stood upon the Crosse of our Saviour Christ. </note> to them annexed, throughout both Provinces.</p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="chapter" n="4">
  <div type="section" n="3">
    <p>...as he consecrated at Memphis the Ox Apis, he wore a Diademe<note type="alphabetical" n="a">That is to say a white band or ribband: such as the Royall Diademe at first was. </note>: which he did in deed according to the custome and rites of the auncient religion there.</p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="chapter" n="6">
  <div type="section" n="3">
    <p>...and built the Baines hard-by, with great expedition<note type="numerical" n="2">Celeriter.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="a">Of these Baines, with what speede and celerity they were finished, Martialis writeth thus: <quote>Hic ubi miramur velocia munera, Thermas.</quote> </note>, he exhibited a Spectacle of Sword-fencers...</p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="chapter" n="8">
  <div type="section" n="2">
    <p>...the Ornaments<note type="numerical" n="1">As their armour, weapons, etc.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="a">Dooing them thus much credit in the eyes of the world, as to give the allowance and approbation, or otherwise, of the weapons wherewith they should fight. For, in this sense may Ornaments be taken: the rather, because some copies have Ferramenta. Or this place may be understood of other furniture, as well as armes, wherwith they should come appointed into the listes. </note> of the Champions that were to fight, presented unto him, hee reached unto them for to view and peruse.</p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="chapter" n="9">
  <div type="section" n="1">
    <p>...by occasion, that as hee sacrificed, the beast brake loose and gat away: as also because in faire and cleare weather it had thundered<note type="alphabetical" n="a">This hath beene observed in all ages, to fore-runne the death of some Prince. Thus, before the end of Julius Cæsar, as Virgil writeth: 
    <quote><l>Non alias lato occiderunt plura sereno</l> <l>Fulgura, etc.</l></quote> 
    Horace likewise: 
    <quote><l>Per purum sonantes</l> <l>Egit equos volucremque currum.</l></quote> 
    Our owne Chronicles also exemplifie no lesse. To say nothing of the fresh resemblance of that, which happened with us three yeares since, in July. </note>.</p>
  </div>
</div>

<div type="chapter" n="10">
  <div type="section" n="1">
    <p>He departed this world<note type="alphabetical" n="a">Some write, and Tzetzes by name, that hee was poysoned with eating of Sea-hares. </note>, in the very same Country-house wherein his father died before him...</p>
  </div>
</div>