<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Historie of Nero Claudius Caesar</title>
        <author>C. Suetonius Tranquillus</author>
        <editor>Philemon Holland (Translator)</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Encoded for TEI XML</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Transcribed from PDF source files of Philemon Holland's 1898 edition.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
     <pb n="98"/>
      <head>THE HISTORIE OF NERO CLAUDIUS CÆSAR</head>
 
<div type="chapter" n="1">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>OUT of the Domitian stocke and name, there sprung two famous families, to wit, the Calumi and the Enobarbi. These Ænobarbi have for the first Author of their originall, and surname likewise, L. Domitius: whome, as he returned in times past homeward out of the countrey, two yong men twinnes<note type="numerical" n="1">Castor and Pollux resembling two yong men.</note>, carying with them a venerable presence and countenance more then ordinary, encountred, by report, and commanded to relate unto the Senate and People of Rome, newes, of that victorie whereof as yet they stood in doubt: and for the better assurance of their divine majestie stroke his cheekes so, as that therewith they made the hayre<note type="numerical" n="2">Capillum, i. Pilum. Gellius.</note> of blacke, redd<note type="numerical" n="3">Or ruddy.</note>, and like in colour to brasse<note type="numerical" n="4">Or Copper.</note>. Which marke and badges continued also in his posterity; and most of them have such red beardes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Moreover, having borne seven Consulships, triumphed likewise and beene Censors twice, and therwith bin chosen into the ranke of the Patritii, they remained al in the same surname. Neither were they knowen by any other forenames than Cneus and Lucius: and the same in variety worth the noting and observation: one while continuing either of the sayd names in three persons together: otherwhiles changing alternatively one after another in every descent. For, we have heard say, that the first, second and <pb n="99"/> third of these Ænobarbi were forenamed Lucii: and againe, the three next following them in order were Cnei. All the rest no otherwise then by turnes one after another had their forenames, first Lucii and then Cnei. That many persons of this house descended should be knowen, I suppose it very pertinent and materiall: whereby it may the better appeare, that Nero degenerated from the Vertues of his Auncestors so, as yet he caried away and resembled the vices of them all, as infused into him and inbred by nature.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="2">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>To fetch the beginning therefore of this our discourse somewhat farther of, his great Grandfathers Grandfather<note type="numerical" n="1">Atavus eius, his Grandfather 4 degrees of.</note> Cn. Domitius, beeing in his Tribunate much offended at the Pontifies<note type="numerical" n="2">High Priests.</note>, for electing any other but himselfe into his fathers place, transferred the right and power of subrogating priests in the roome of those that were deceassed, from their Colledges to the bodie of the people. But in his Consulship having vanquished the Allobroges and the Arverni, he rode through his province<note type="numerical" n="3">Gallia Narbonensis.</note> mounted upon an Elephant, whiles the whole multitude of his souldiours attended upon him in a traine after the manner of a solemne triumph.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>This Domitius it was, whom Licinius Crassus the oratour in a certaine declamation sayd, It was no mervaile he had a brasen beard whose face was made of Iron, and heart of lead. His sonne being Pretour was the man, who as Cæsar<note type="numerical" n="4">Jul. Cæsar Dictator.</note> went out of his Consulship (thought Auspicia<note type="numerical" n="5">Approbation of the gods.</note> and the lawes) convented him before the Senate to be by them examined, tried and censured. Afterwards when he was Consull he attempted to fetch him backe, Lord Generall as he was of an armie, from his forces in Gaule: and being by the adverse faction<note type="numerical" n="6">The Pompeians.</note> nominated his successour in that province, was in the beginning of the civil warre taken prisoner before Corfininum:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>from whence being dismissed and set at libertie, after he had by his comming to the Massilians streightly <pb n="100"/> beleagured, much strengthened them, sodainely he forsooke them: and in the end, at the battaile of Pharsalia lost his life: a man not very constant and resolute, but with all of a fell and savage nature. Being driven to utter despaire, he was so much afraid of death, which for feare he had desired, that after a drawght of poyson hee repented the taking thereof and cast it up againe; yea and enfranchised his Phisitian, who wittingly and of purpose had so tempered it that it might do him no great harme. And what time as Cn. Pompeius put to question what should be done to those Neuters that stood indifferent and sticked to no part: he alone opined, That they were to be reckoned enemies and proceeded against accordingly.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="3">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Hee left behind him a sonne, worthy without question, to be preferred before all others of his name and linage. This man being among those that were privie to Cæsars death, and of that conspiracy, standing condemned (though guiltlesse) by the law Pædia<note type="numerical" n="1">Which Q. Pædius made against the murderers of Cæsar.</note>, when he had betaken himselfe to Cassius and Brutus his neere kinsfolke, after the end of them both, held stil in his hand the fleet committed before time to his charge, yea and augmented the same: neither yeelded he it up to M. Antonius before his owne side was every where quite overthrowen: which he then did of his owne accord; and so, as that Antonius took himselfe highly beholden unto him therfore.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>He only also of all those who by vertue of the like law stood condemned, being restored into his native countrey, went through the most honorable offices of state: soone after likewise, when civil dissension was kindled againe and renewed, being in quality of Lieutenant to the said Antonie, what time the soveraigne Empire was offered unto him by those who were ashamed of Cleopatra, not daring to accept thereof nor yet to refuse it resolutely, by occasion of sodaine sicknesse wherewith he was surprised, went and sided with Augustus, and within few dayes after departed this life: being himselfe also noted <pb n="101"/> with some infamie: for, Antonie gave it commonly forth, That for the love of one Servilia Nais whom he kept, he fled to Augustus side.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="4">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>From him came that Domitius, who soone after had the name abroade to have beene the chapman of Augustus goods and substance left by his wil and testament<note type="numerical" n="1">Dicis causa, i. by an imaginarie bargaine of sale to have bought them to the behoofe and use of the heyre.</note>: a man no lesse renowmed in his youth for good skill in ruling of Chariots and running with them a race, as afterwards for the triumphant ornaments achieved by the Germaine warre; but arrogant of spirit, wastefull in expence, and therewith cruel. When he was Ædile he forced L. Plancus that had beene Censor<note type="numerical" n="2">Censorium, not Censorem.</note>, to give him the way. Bearing the honorable offices of Preture and Consulate, hee produced upon the stage to acte a Comicall and wanton Enterlude, the gentlemen and dames of Rome. He exhibited baiting of wilde beastes both in the cirque and also in every quarter of the City, yea and a shew of sword-fight: but with so great cruelty, that Augustus was compelled of necessitie to restraine him by an edict, since that no secret warning nor admonition at his hands would prevaile.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="5">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Of Antonia the elder, hee begat the father of Nero: an impe in all the parts of his life ungracious and detestable. For accompanying Caius Cæsar<note type="numerical" n="3">Sonne of M. Agrippa and Julia, adopted by Augustus.</note> in his youth into the East-parts, where he killed a freed-man of his owne, because he refused to quaffe as much as he was commanded, being discharged therfore out of the cohort of his friends, he led his life never a whit more modestly: but both within a village standing upon the street Appia, sodainely put his horses to gallop, and not unwittingly rode over a little child and trode him to death and also at Rome in the midst of the Forum plucked a Romane gentlemans eye out of his head, for chiding him somewhat over boldly.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="102"/> So false and perfidious beside, that he defrauded not onely the bankers and money changers of the prices of such commodities as they had bought up, but also when he was Pretour put the runners with Chariots besides the prises of their victories. For which prankes, reproved he was merily even by his owne sister (Lepida) and upon complaint made by the Masters of the foure factions<note type="alphabetical" n="a"><p>THESE foure factions or crewes that ran with Chariots for the prise, were distinguished by foure colors of cloth, or liveries, and therupon called by their names, Alba, i. White, Veneta, watchet or light blew, Præsina, i. greene, and Rosea, i. Rose coloured or read. Unto which were added by Domitian Aurata and Purpurea, i. Gold coloured or yellow, and purple. The former foure Sidonius Apollinaris hath comprised in his Hendecasyllabes, thus:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Micant colores,</l>
                <l>Albus cum veneto, virens rubensque.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>Then shine these crewes and make a gallant shew</p>
            <quote>
                <l>In white, in blew, in greene and roset hew.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>Proportionate they are unto the foure seasons of the yeare: white, to the Autumne or end of Sommer, Watchet to the winter, Greene to the spring, and Red to sommer, or as some would have it to the foure Elements.</p></note> hee enacted, That from thence-forth ever after, the said prises should be presently payed. Being accused likewise for treason to the State and many adulteries, as also for incest committed with his sister Lepida a little before the decease of Tiberius, yet escaped he the danger of Law by the alteration of the times, and died at Pyrgæ of the Dropsie<note type="numerical" n="1">Morbo aquæ intercutis: that kind of dropsy wherein water runneth between the fell and the flesh all the bodie over, Leucophlegmatias in Greeke.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="b"><p>Physicians have observed three kinds of dropsie. The first is Ascites, wherein the belly doth swell with much water gathered betweene the inner skin or rine of the belly, and the cawle which lappeth the guts, and some wind withall, so named of ἀσκὸς in Greeke, i. A bottle, because in turning of the bodie to a side, the water is perceived to shog in the womb, like as liquor in a bottle halfe full, when it is shaken. The second, Tympanites, wherein the belly is hoven up with wind especially, and some water among. Whereby it will sound like a taber or drum, if one tamper upon it, and thereof it was so called. The third Leucophlegmatias, anasarca, Hyposarca, in Latin Intercus, or Aqua intercutem, in the proper signification<note place="foot" n="1">For Cornelius Celsus attributeth this name to all the kindes.</note>, when the bodie all over is puffed up with water and wind running betweene the fell and the flesh. And thereof as should seeme, died this Domitius.</p></note>, when Agrippina daughter to Germanicus had brought him a sonne named Nero.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="6">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>This Nero was borne at Antium, nine moneths after that Tiberius departed this world, eighteene daies before the Kalends of Januarie, just as the Sunne was newly risen, so as his beames light<note type="numerical" n="2">Or shone. Dio sayth, hee was compassed with the sunne beames: and yet no sunne appeared above the Horizon.</note> well neere upon him before they could touch the earth. As touching his Horoscope<note type="numerical" n="4">Or Nativitie.</note>, many men straightwaies gave many guesses and conjectures of fearefull events. And even a very word that his father Domitius spake, was taken to be a presaging osse. For when his friends by way of gratulation wished him joy of his sonne new born, he said, That of himselfe and Agrippina there could nothing come into the world but accursed, detestable and to the hurt of the weale publick.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Of the same future infortunity there appeared an evident signe upon his naming day<note type="alphabetical" n="a"><p>To wit, the ninth day after he was borne, on which they used to name their sonnes. And as this day was called Nominalia, so there was a goddesse forsooth, president of this complement and ceremonies, whom they named Nundina.</p></note>: for Caius Cæsar (Caligula) when his sister (Agrippina) requested him to give the Infant what name<note type="numerical" n="5">Forename.</note> he would, looking wistly on Claudius his Unkle, (by whom afterwards being Emperour (the child) was adopted), said he gave him his name. Neither spake hee this in earnest, but merily in boord: and Agrippina scorned and rejected it, for that as <pb n="103"/> then, Claudius went for a foole, and one of the laughing stocks of the Court.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>At three yeeres of age he became fatherlesse: and being his fathers heire but of one third part, yet could not he touch so much as that, full and whole, by reason of Caius his coheire, who had seized upon and caught up before-hand all the goods: and for that his mother also was soone after confined and packt away, he being in manner destitute of all helpe and very needy, was fostered in his Aunt Lepidæs house under two Pædagogues, a dauncer and a Barber.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>But when Claudius was come once to the Empire, hee not onely recovered his patrimonie<note type="numerical" n="1">Fathers goods.</note>, but also was enriched by the inheritance of Crispus Passienus his mothers husband, that fell unto him. And verily through the grace and power of his mother now called home againe and restored to her estate, hee flourished and grew so great, that commonly it was bruted abroad, That Messallina the wife of Claudius sent some of purpose to take the opportunity of his noones sleep, and so to smuddre and strangle him, as the onely Concurrent of Britannicus<note type="numerical" n="2">Her Sonne.</note>, and one that eclipsed the light of his glorie. Now in the tale it went, besides: that the said parties tooke a fright at a Dragon issuing out of his pillow, whereupon they fled backe and forsooke the enterprise. Which fable arose upon this, that there was in deede found the slough<note type="numerical" n="3">Or skinne.</note> of a serpent in his bed about the bolsters. And yet, this slough he enclosed within a bracelet of gold (as his mother willed him) and wore it a good while after, upon his right arme: and at length, wearie of any memoriall and monument of his mothers flung it away: but in his extreamity and despaire of his estate sought for the same againe in vaine.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="7">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In his tender yeeres, and whiles hee was yet a boy of no full growth, hee acted at the Circeian Games the warlike Troy fight most resolutely, with great favour and applause of the people. In the eleventh<note type="numerical" n="4">Undecimo: some reade rather tertio et decimo, i. the thirteenth.</note> yeere of his age adopted he was by Claudius and put to schoole unto Annæus Seneca, <pb n="104"/> even then a Senatour, for to be trained up in good literature. The report goes, that Seneca, the next night following, dreamed as hee lay in bed, that hee was teaching C.<note type="numerical" n="1">Caligula.</note> Cæsar: and shortly after Nero proved his dreame true, bewraying the fell stomacke and shrewd nature of the said Prince, by the first experiments that he could give thereof. For when his brother Britannicus saluted him after he was once adopted, (as his wonted manner was before) by the name of Ænobarbus, hee went about to lay this imputation upon him before his Father, that he was some Changeling and no sonne of his as he was reputed. His Aunt Lepida likewise being in trouble, hee deposed against, in the open face of the Court, thereby to gratifie his mother her heavie friend, and who followed the suite hotly against her.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Being honourably brought into the Forum<note type="numerical" n="2">Or Hall of Justice.</note>, the day of his first plea and Commencement, hee promised publiquely for the people a Congiarie, and Donative for the Souldiours. Having proclaimed also a solemne Justing<note type="numerical" n="3">Or running at tilt.</note>, himselfe rode before the Pretorian Souldiours bearing a shield in his owne hand. After this, hee solemnly gave thanks to his Father in the Senate. Before whom being then Consull, hee made a Latine Oration in the behalfe of the Bononians, and for the Rhodians and Inhabitants of Ilium, another in Greeke. His first Jurisdiction hee began as Provost of the Citie<note type="alphabetical" n="a"><p>The manner was, during these solemnities in the Albane mount, (where the chiefe magistrates were present) to leave for Provost of the Citie, some principall young Gentleman of the Nobilitie, before whom sitting judicially, causes of no great importance should be brought.</p></note>, during the celebration of the Latine holidaies: what time the most famous Advocates and Patrones in those daies strove a vie, who could bring before him most accusations<note type="numerical" n="4">Or declarations.</note> and longest<note type="numerical" n="5">Drawne in large bookes.</note>; not (as the manner was) such as were ordinarie and briefe: the expresse commaundement of Claudius forbidding the same, notwithstanding. Not long after, hee tooke to wife Octavia: and for the good health of Claudius, exhibited the Cirque Games and baiting of wild beasts.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="8">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Being seventeene yeeres olde, so soone as it was knowne abroad that Claudius was dead, hee came forth to those (of the Pretorian Cohort) that kept watch and ward, betweene <pb n="105"/> the sixth and the seventh houre of the day<note type="numerical" n="1">Betweene noone and one of the clock.</note>: for by reason that the whole day beside was ominous and dismall, there was no time thereof thought more auspicate and convenient than it, to enter upon the Empire: and so before the Pallace staires being proclaimed and saluted Emperour, he was in a Licter brought to the Camp<note type="numerical" n="2">Pretorian.</note>: and hastily from thence, after a short speech made unto the Souldiours, conveied into the Curia. From whence he departed home in the evening: and of those exceeding and infinite honours which were heaped upon him, hee refused onely the Title in his stile of Pater Patriæ<note type="numerical" n="3">Father of his Countrey.</note>, in regard of his young yeeres.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="11">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Many and sundry kindes of shewes he set forth: to wit, the Juvenall sports<note type="alphabetical" n="a"><p>These youthfull sports Iuvenalia, or Iuvenales ludi, were first instituted by this Nero, privately in houses or gardens, and orchards. Wherein, of all degrees, ages and sexes they daunced and revelled.</p></note>, the Circeian Games, and the Stage-playes: also a Sword fight. In the Juvenall pastimes, he admitted old men even those of Consuls degree: aged women also and matrones to disport themselves. At the Circenses, he appointed places for the Gentlemen of Rome a part by themselves: where hee put also to runne a race for the prise chariots drawne with foure Camels.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>In the Stage plaies, (which beeing instituted for the eternizing and perpetuitie of his Empire hee would have to be called Maximi), very many of both degrees and sexes plaied their parts upon the Stage. A Romaine Gentleman of very <pb n="107"/> good note and especiall marke, mounted upon an Elephant ranne downe a rope<note type="numerical" n="1">Per Catadromum, for there were Elephanti Funambuli, vide Galb. cap. 6, et Xiphilinum.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

<div type="chapter" n="12">
          <div type="section" n="1">
            <p><note place="margin">A.U.C. 810.</note>These Games hee beheld from the top of the Proscenium<note place="foot" n="4">The fore-stage.</note>. At the Swordfight which hee exhibited in the Amphitheatre built of Timber in one yeeres space within the ward of Mars field hee suffred not one man to be killed, no not so much as a guilty malefactour. Moreover, hee brought into the Lists for to fight at sharpe even 400<note place="foot" n="5">Quadringenos, rather quadragenos, i. 40.</note> Senatours and 600<note place="foot" n="6">Sexacentosque, rather Sexagenos, i. 60, according to Justus Lipsius.</note> Gentlemen of Rome. Some of good wealth and reputation, out of the same degrees, he caused to come forth into the Shew-place, for to kill wild beasts, and performe sundry services therto belonging. He represented also a Naval fight upon salt water from the Sea, with a devise to have sea beasts<note place="foot" n="7">Or great fishes.</note> swimming therein. Semblably, certaine Pyrrhick daunces in armour<note place="foot" n="8">Warlike.</note>, sorted out of the number of young Springals: and after their devoir done, he gave freely unto every one of them patents and graunts to be enfranchized Citizens of Rome.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section" n="2">
            <p>Betweene<note place="foot" n="9">Or, among.</note> the arguments of these Pyrrhick daunces, devised it was, that a Bull should leape Pasiphæ<note place="foot" type="letter" n="a">The fabulous reports of Ladie Pasiphæ wife to King Minos, how she was enamoured of a Bull, as also of Icarus the sonne of Dædalus, who would needs attempt to flie in the ayre, be well enough knowen to them that are but meanely seene in Poetrie.</note> hidden within a frame of wood resembling an Heiffer<note place="foot" n="10">To the likenesse of that which was devised by Dædalus.</note>, which was acted so lively, that many of the 
            <pb n="108"/>
            beholders beleeved verily it was so in deede. As for Icarus, at the first attempt to flie, hee fell presently downe hard by his owne<note place="foot" n="1">Of Nero.</note> Bed-chamber<note place="foot" n="2">Or pavilion.</note><note place="foot" type="letter" n="b">Iuxca cubiculum eius decidit. By Cubiculum, he meaneth heere, a royall seat raised on high within that quarter of the Theater called Orchestra, under a rich Tent or Canopie, where Emperors were wont to sit when they beheld such solemnities. These Pavillions were called in Greeke οὐρανισκοὶ κωνώπεα in some sort resembling bed-chambers.</note> so that he bespreint espreint him with bloud. For very seldome had he used to sit as President at these Games: but his manner was, to behold them as he lay upon his bed<note place="foot" n="3">Or a pallet.</note>. First through little loope holes: but afterwards setting the whole gallerie open from whence he looked.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section" n="3">
            <p><note place="margin">A.U.C. 813.</note>Hee was the first moreover that instituted at Rome, according to the Greeke fashion, Quinquennal games of three kinds, to wit, of Musick and Poetrie, of Gymnick maisteries and of Horsemanship<note place="foot" n="4">Or Horse running.</note>: which Games he called Neronia. After he had dedicated the Baines, and a place therein for Gymnick exercises,<note n="c">So named because they that wrestled, ran, or otherwise exercised, were naked, like as the place itselfe of such exercises thereupon tooke the name Gymnasium.</note> he allowed the oyle that went thereto both for the Senate and also for the Gentlemen. He ordained Maisters and Wardens of all this Solemnity, especiall persons of Consular degree, chosen by lot to sit as over-seers in the place of Pretours<note place="foot" n="5">Where they were wont to sit as Presidents at other games and playes.</note>, and then came downe himselfe into the Orchestra<note place="foot" n="6">In Orchestram, Senatumque aliter, per Orchestram in scenam, by the Orchestra to the very stage.</note> and the Senatours quarter. And verily the victorious coronet for the Latine tongue, both in prose and verse, about which the best and most worshipfull persons had contended, when it was graunted unto him with their owne consents he received: and the harp presented unto him by the Judges he adored, and commaunded that it should bee caried to the Statue of Augustus<note place="foot" n="7">To Jupiter Capitolinus.</note>.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section" n="4">
            <p>At the Gymnick Games which he exhibited in the Septa, during the solemne preparation of the great Sacrifice Buthysia, hee cut off the first beard that he had, which he bestowed within a golden box, adorned it with most pretious pearles and then consecrated it in the Capitol. <note place="margin">A.U.C. 819.</note>To the shew of wrestlers and other Champions he called also the vestall virgins, because at Olympia the priestesses likewise of Ceres, are allowed to see the Games there.</p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <div type="section" n="1">
            <p>I may by good reason, among other Shewes by him ex-<pb n="109"/>hibited, reckon also the entrance into Rome City, of Tiridates: whom being King of Armenia hee had sollicited by large promises. Now, when hee meant to shew him unto the people upon a set day appointed by an Edict, and was driven to put it off, (the weather was so cloudy) he brought him forth before them to be seene upon the best and most opportune day that hee could finde; having bestowed about the temples situate in the Forum<note place="foot" n="1">Or Market place.</note>, cohorts of Souldiours armed, and sitting himselfe upon his yvorie curule chaire of Estate before the Rostra in triumphall habite, among the militarie Ensignes, banners, guidons and streamers.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section" n="2">
            <p>And as the King came up towards him by the ascent of the steepe pulpit, he admitted him first to his knees; and then raising up with his right hand kissed him: afterwards as he was making his praier unto him, having taken off his Tiara<note place="foot" n="2">Resembling a cap of maintenance, or as some thinke, a Turkish tuffe or Turbant.</note>, he did the diademe on<note place="foot" n="3">Which he had laid off again as it shold seeme, like as when he was vanquished by Corbito, he laid downe before the Image of Nero.</note>. Whiles one who had been Pretour, pronounced unto the multitude the Suppliants words, as they were by an Interpretour delivered unto him. Being brought after this into the Theater and making supplication againe, he placed him on his right side next to himselfe. For which he was with one accord saluted Emperour: and so bringing with him the Lawrell branch into the Capitoll, he shut both dores of double faced Janus temple, as if no reliques of warre remained behind<note place="foot" n="4">Tanquam nullo residuo bello.</note>.</p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <div type="section" n="1">
            <p><note place="margin">A.U.C. 808, 810, 811, 813.</note>Foure Consulships he bare: the first for two moneths: the second and last for three: the third for foure. The middle twaine he continued without any intermission: the rest he varied with a yeeres space betweene.</p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <div type="section" n="1">
            <p>In his ordinarie Jurisdiction, he lightly gave no answer to the Proctours before the day following, and that was by writing. In extraordinary Commissions and trials this <pb n="110"/> course he held, namely to decide every cause by it selfe one after another upon certaine daies of the Session; and to surcease quite the hudling up and debatements of matters one in the neck of another: so often as he went aside to consult, he did deliberate and aske advise of nothing either in common or openly: but reading secretly to himselfe the opinions written by every counsellour, what liked his owne selfe, that pronounced hee, as if many more thought well of the same.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section" n="2">
            <p>For a long time hee admitted not the sonnes of Libertines into the Curia: and to those that were admitted by the Emperours his predecessours hee denied all honorable Offices. If there sued for Magistracies more then could speed, or were places void; to comfort their harts againe for delaying and making them to stay longer, he gave unto them the conduct of Legions. He graunted for the most part all Consulships for sixe moneths terme. And if one of the two Consuls hapned to die about the Kalends of Januarie<note place="foot" n="1">Somewhat before.</note>, hee substituted none in his steede: as misliking altogether the old precedent of Cannius Rebilus, who was Consul but one day<note place="foot" n="2">Or rather, one peece of a day: See Julius Cæsar cap. 76.</note>. Triumphall ornaments he gave even unto those that had borne Questours dignity only: yea and to some of the Gentlemens degree, and verily not alwaies for any militarie service<note place="foot" n="3">Or upon occasion of war.</note>. His Orations<note place="foot" n="4">Which else where be called Epistles.</note> sent into the Senate concerning certaine matters, hee caused for the most part to be read and rehearsed by the Consuls, passing by the Questours Office<note place="foot" n="5">Unto whom properly it appertained.</note>.</p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <div type="section" n="1">
            <p>He devised a new forme of the City buildings: and namely, that before the Ædifices standing by themselves<note place="foot" n="6">Ante Insulas.</note>, and other houses, likewise there should be Porches<note place="foot" n="7">Foregates, or Gatehouses.</note>. From the Solars whereof, all Skarefires might be put by and repelled<note place="foot" n="8">From the front of such Ædifices.</note>; and those he built<note place="foot" n="9">Or promised rather to build.</note> at his owne charges. Hee had an intention once to set out and enlarge the walls of <pb n="111"/> Rome, even as farre as to Ostia; and from thence by a Fosse to let the Sea into old Rome<note place="foot" n="1">To bring an arme of it thither.</note>.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section" n="2">
            <p>Many matters under him were both severely punished and also restrained, yea and likewise newly ordained. Expences in his daies had a gage and stint set upon them<note place="foot" n="2">In costly and excessive fare at the table.</note>. The publick suppers<note place="foot" type="letter" n="a">Full and formall suppers, whereto men were invited, and at which the guestes sate orderly marshalled according to their worth place, and were called cænæ rectæ, and after this manner in other Princes daies were their favorites feasted. In steed hereof came in Sportula, i. allowances given unto them, eyther in money, or cates, in recompence of their ordinarie salutations and attendance.</note> were brought downe to small Collations. Forbidden it was that any thing sodden<note place="foot" n="3">Ne quid cocti.</note>, but only pulse, and worts<note place="foot" n="4">As Potherbs.</note> should be sold in Taverns and Cookes houses; where as before time, there was no maner of viands but it was set out to sale. The Christians, a kinde of men given to a new, wicked and mischievous Superstition, were put to death with grievous torments. The sports of Chariotiers, wherein by an old and licentious custome they had been allowed to range up and downe, to beguile folke, to pilfer and steale in merriment, were prohibited. The factions of the Pantomimi<note place="foot" n="5">Cunning Actours, playing all parts, and resembling all gestures.</note><note place="foot" type="letter" n="b">As there were sundrie factions or crewes favourizing this or that colour of the Chariotters, so were there likewise of Actours and players, whereupon many roiots, outrages, Fraies and murthers were committed.</note> together with the Actours themselves were banished and sent away.</p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <div type="section" n="1">
            <p>Against forgers of writings, then first came up this invention that no books or instruments should be signed unlesse they were boared and had a thred three times drawne through the holes. Provided it was, That in Wills the two first parts thereof<note place="foot" n="6">Or uppermost.</note><note place="foot" n="7">Or cered tables.</note> should be shewed as blanks, unto those that came to seale the same: having the Testatours name onely written therein. Item, that no Clerk or Notarie, who was to draw and write another mans will, should put downe any Legacie for himselfe. Item, that they who had sutes depending in Court, should pay the certaine due fee set downe by Law, for pleading of their causes: but for the Benches<note place="foot" n="8">Pues or seats, some expound this of the Judges Bench, as if their sentences should not be bought and sold.</note><note place="foot" type="letter" n="a">It should seeme, that for the pleading and triall of causes, such Tribunal seats, pues, benches and barrs, were erected at first, for the present occasion, and taken downe againe by certaine persons, who gathered therfore a rent of those that went to law.</note> nothing, considering the Chamber of the Citie allowed the same gratis and to be free. Item, that in the pleading<note place="foot" n="9">Or Pleas.</note> and deciding of controversies all causes debated afore time before the Maisters of the Exchequer or Citie Chamber should bee removed unto the Common Hall, to <pb n="112"/> be tried before the Commissioners and Delegates called Recuperatores. Finally, that all appeales from the Judges should be made unto the Senate.</p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <div type="section" n="1">
            <p>Having no will, no motion, nor hope at any time, to propagate and enlarge the Empire, he thought once to have withdrawne the forces even out of Britaine: neither gave he over that intent of his, but onely for very shame; least he might be thought to deprave the glory of his Father (Claudius). Onely the realme of Pontus with the leave of lemona<note place="foot" type="letter" n="a">Divers Kings of Pontus were named Polemones as of Ægypt Ptolemæi, whereupon the realme Pontus, is by Vopiscus called Polemonius, like as the Alpes Cottiæ of Cottius.</note>, as also the Kingdome of the Alpes, by the death of King Cottius hee reduced into the forme of a Province.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="19">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Two voyages and no more he undertooke, the one to Alexandria, the other into Achaia. But his journey to Alexandria hee gave over the very day of his setting forth: by occasion that he was disquieted at once, both with a religious scruple and also with some perill. For when hee had gone in procession about all the temples, and sitten downe within the Chappel of Vesta, as he was rising up, first the hem<note type="numerical" n="1">Jag, welt or fringes.</note> or edge of his Gowne stucke to the seate, and after this, arose so darke a mist before his eyes, that uneth he could see and looke about him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>In Achaia hee attempted to digge through Isthmus<note type="alphabetical" n="a"><p>Many had attempted this beside him but all their cost and labour came to nought: οὕτως χαλεπὸν ἀνθρώπῳ τὰ θεῖα βιάσασθαι.</p>.</note>, and in a frequent assembly made a speech unto the Pretorian Souldiours, exhorting them to begin the worke: and having given the signall by sound of trumpet, himselfe first brake up the ground with a little spade<note type="numerical" n="2">Rastello, i. ligone, the same that Dikella in Greeke with a cloven bit.</note>; and when hee had cast up the earth, caried it forth upon his owne shoulders in a scuttle<note type="numerical" n="3">This by some Writers, was of gold.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="20">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Among other arts and sciences, beeing in his childhood trained up in the skill also of musick: no sooner attained he to the Empire, but he sent for Terpnus the harper, renowmed in those dayes for his cunning above all other. Sitting by him as he played and sung, day by day after supper until it was far in the night, himselfe likewise by little and little began to practise and exercise the same: yea and not to let passe anie meanes that expert professours in that kind were wont to do... so long, untill his proceedings stil drawing him on, (a smal and rusty<note type="numerical" n="1">Or hoarse.</note> voice though he had) he desired to come forth and shew himselfe upon the open stage, having among his familiar companions this Greeke proverbe<note type="alphabetical" n="a">τῆς λανθανούσης μουσικῆς οὐδεῖς λόγος.</note> evermore in his mouth, That hidden musicke was nought worth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>The first time that he mounted the stage was at Naples, where he gave not over singing, (albeit the Theatre was shaken and ready to fall by a suddaine earthquake) before he had finished the song begun. In the same place he chaunted often and many dayes together.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>...Now, beeing much delighted with the Alexandrines praises in prict song<note type="numerical" n="1">Tuned and composed to the rules and measures of Musick, in the praise of him, by the merchants of Alexandria.</note>, who newly in a second voiage had with their fleet conflowed to Naples<note type="alphabetical" n="b">In respect of a former fleet, that was wont to come before, and bring newes of the second laden with marchandise and under saile. Therefore those ships were called naves Tabellaria. Seneca.</note>, he sent for more of them out of Alexandria. And never the later he chose from all parts youths of Gentlemens degree, and not so few as 5000 of the lustiest and strongest young men out of the commons, who beeing sorted into factions should learne certaine kinde of shouts and applauses, which they tearmed Bombos,<note type="alphabetical" n="c">Bombos, resembling either the buzzing and humming noise of Bees, or the sound of trumpets.</note> Imbrices<note n="d">
            <p>Imbrices, much after the manner of that rattling, which a sodaine shewre makes upon the tiles of an house, or the sound that crest tiles or gutter tiles may make.</p>
        </note> and Testas<note type="alphabetical" n="e">
            <p>Testas, to expresse the crashing of potsheards or earthen pots, clattering one against another.</p>
        </note>: also that deft and trim boyes, such as had the thickest bush of haire upon their heads<note type="alphabetical" n="f"><p>Insignes pinguissima coma. In which sense we read of pingues togæ and Lacerna. Yet some understand thereby λιπαροπλοκάμους, i. whose lokes and faix were so slicke and glib with sweet oyles, that they shone againe.</p></note>, and were set out in most excellent apparell... should give their attendance upon him as he sung. The cheiftaines and leaders of these had for their stipend 400000 sesterces<note type="numerical" n="5">A Knights living.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="21">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Esteeming so highly as he did of singing, he solemnized at Rome also againe the foresaid games called Neroneum before the day and time by order appointed<note type="numerical" n="6">Every fifth yeares.</note>. And when all the people called upon him for his celestial voice<note type="alphabetical" n="a">For, so would he have it to be called. And Thraseas Pætus was judicially convented, and deeply charged, because he had never offred sacrifice for that heavenly voice of his. Tacit.</note>, he made answere: That he verily would do them that pleasure (being so willing and desirous as they were to heare him): but it should be in his Hortyards. Howbeit, when the corps de guarde of the (Pretorian) Souldiers which at that time kept watch and ward seconded the praiers of the common people, willingly he promised to fulfill their minds out of hand in the very place; and without any farther delay caused his owne name to be written in the roll of other professed minstrels and singers to the harpe. Thus having put his lot into the pitcher with the rest, hee entred the stage when his turne came: and withall the Capitaines of the Guard supporting his harpe: after them the tribunes militarie, and close unto them his most inwarde friendes and Minions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Now when hee had taken up his standing, and ended his Proæme, he gave publike notice and pronounced by the voice of Cluvius Rufus, (no meaner man than of Consuls degree) that he would sing and act the storie of Niobe<note type="numerical" n="1">Wife of Amphion King of Thebes, who priding herself in her faire issewe 6 sonnes and as manie daughters durst compare with Latona...</note>: and so continued hee well neere unto the tenth houre of the day<note type="numerical" n="2">Foure of the clocke after noone.</note>: which done he differred the Musicke Coronet due for the present victorie... unto the next yeare following; and all because he might have occasion oftener to chaunt.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="115"/> Hee sung moreover, disguised, Tragædies of the worthies and gods: of noble Ladies likewise in olde time and of goddesses, having their visards<note type="numerical" n="5">Or Masques.</note> framed and made to the likenesse of his own face and of some woman whom hee loved. Among the rest he chanted the tale of Canace travailing in child-birth<note type="alphabetical" n="b"><p>Who was with child by her owne brother Macareus, whereupon her father Æolus caused the childe new borne to be cast before hungrie dogs and sent a sword to his daughter to kill her selfe with.</p></note>: of Orestes who killed his own Mother<note type="alphabetical" n="c">In revenge of his father Agamemnons death, by her murdered...</note>: of Edipus that plucked out his own eyes<note type="alphabetical" n="d">Who unwitting killed his owne father Laius, and as ignorantly wedded his owne mother Iocasta.</note>, and of Hercules enraged<note type="alphabetical" n="e">By putting on a garment next his skinne, envenomed with the poison of Nessus the Centaure...</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="22">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Exceedingly given hee was of a boy to delight in horse-manship, and with the love of charioting mightily inflamed : and very much would he be talking (forbidden though he were) of the Circeian games. And one time as hee was making mone, and bewailing among his skoole-fellowes, the hard fortune of a chariot driver, one of the greene-coate faction, drawen and dragged by his steedes<note type="numerical" n="1">Or sore wounded and bruised with the wheeles running over him. See Plin. Nat. Hist. lib. 28 cap. 17.</note>, being chidden therefore by his schoole-master, he had a lye ready, and said that he spake of Hector<note type="numerical" n="2">Who was likewise, Raptatus Bigis as Virgil writeth.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="116"/> Soone after himselfe also would needs make one and be seene oftentimes to play the Chariotier. And when he had tryed what hee could doe, and performed, as it were, his first Actes in (private) hortyardes among verie slaves and the base commons, he proceeded to shew himselfe in the greatest Cirque in all mens eyes...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Those Cities and states where solemne gamings of musicke are usually held, had brought up a custome to sende all the Coronets of harpe-players unto him. This he accepted so kindly, that he not onely admitted at the very first to his presence the Embassadors who brought the same, but also placed them among his familiar guestes at the table. And being requested by some of them to sing at supper time, and highly praised with <pb n="117"/> excessive applause, he came out with this speech, That Græcians were the onely skilfull Hearers, and the men alone worthie of his studies.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="23">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>After this, he went to all the games of prise, one after another: for even those that usually are celebrated at most remote and distant times he commanded to be reduced all into one yeare, and some of them also to be iterated<note type="numerical" n="3">Solemnized twice in the same yeare.</note>. At Olympia likewise hee caused, (contrarie to the manner and custome of that place) a game of musick to be held.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>All the while hee was singing, lawefull it was not for anye person to depart out of the Theatre, were the cause never so necessarie. Whereupon reported it is, that some great bellied women falling into travaile were delivered upon the very skaffolds : yea and many men besides, wearie of tedious hearing and praysing him, when the towne gates were shut, eyther by stealth leapt downe from the walles, or counterfeiting themselves dead were caried forth as corses to bee buried. But how timorously, with what thought and anguish of minde, with what æmulation of his concurrents and feare of the Umpiers, hee strove for the Mastery, it is almost incredible.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="118"/> His manner was to deale with his adversaries... to ly in the wind for to catch advantage: to defame them under hand... yea and to corrupt with bribes<note type="numerical" n="1">Thereby to make them relent and not to do their best.</note> and giftes such as excelled in skill and cunning.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="24">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>During the time that hee strove for to winne any prise, so strictely obeyed hee the lawes of the game, that hee never durst once spit and reach up fleame: and the very swet of his forehead hee wiped away with his arme onely<note type="numerical" n="2">Or sleeve and not with anie handkercheife.</note>. Moreover in the acting of a Tragædie, when he had quickly taken up his staffe<note type="alphabetical" n="a">It may be thought, that he then acted Edipus or Creon or some other King, and therefore carried in his hand a regall staffe or Sceptre.</note> againe, which he happened to let fall, being much dismaied and in great feare... by no meanes tooke he heart againe, until an under actor or prompter standing by sware an oth that it was not espied... Now, whensoever he wan the victorie, he used to pronounce himselfe victour. For which cause, he contended also in every place for the Criers coronet<note type="numerical" n="4">Due to him that had the lowdest voice.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="b">For, at Olimpia, were Games also of Criers, striving who could cry lowdest, for the prize.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="119"/> Furthermore, he ran with chariots for the best game in many places, and at the Olympicke solemnities with one that had a teeme of tenne steedes... But being once shaken and hoisted out of his Chariot and set therein againe, howbeit not able to hold out, he desisted and gave over, before he had runne the race through. Yet was he crowned neverthelesse.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="25">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Beeing returned out of Greece hee entred Naples, mounted upon a Chariot drawne with white horses... Semblably rode he into Antium, and from thence into Albanum and so forward into Rome. But he entred Rome in the very same Chariot, wherein sometime Augustus had rode in triumph, clad in a purple cloke<note type="numerical" n="1">Or Mantell.</note>, and the same garnished with starres embrodered in golde: wearing upon his head the Olympicke Coronet<note type="numerical" n="2">Made of the wilde Olive branches.</note>, and bearing in his right hand the Pythisk<note type="numerical" n="3">Of Lawrell.</note>...  not without a traine also of Applauders, following his Chariot, after the manner of those that ride ovant in petie Triumph<note type="alphabetical" n="a">Five thousand were there of these Gallants, as Xiphilinus writeth, ready to applaud him when he chaunted.</note> setting up a note, and crying with a lowde voice, That they were Augustians, and the souldiers of his triumph.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="120"/> As for the sacred Coronets and guirlands aforesayde, he bestowed them in his owne bed-chamber round about his beds: likewise his owne statues pourtraied in the habit of an harper<note type="numerical" n="1">Or Minstrell.</note>, and with that marke stamped he his money.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="26">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His unruly wildnesse, unbridled lust, wastfull riotousnesse, avarice and cruelty, he practised verely at first, by leasure closely, as the trickes of youthfull folly: yet so, as even then no man might doubt, that they were the inbred vices of nature, and not the errors of young age. No sooner was it twi-light and the evening shut in but presently he would catch up a capsa<note type="alphabetical" n="a">He meaneth eyther a peruke and cap of counterfait haire... thereby disguising himselfe...</note> on his head, and so disguised, goe into tavernes and victualling houses... For he used to fall upon those that came late from supper and knocke them soundly... to breake into petie shops also, and rifle them: for he had set up in his house at home a faire<note type="alphabetical" n="b">Quintana was a Gate or Street rather in the Roman Campe... in resemblance whereof, he termed a certaine place in his house Quintana, in which he made sale of such wares...</note>, there to receive the price of the bootie which hee had gotten...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="121"/> But many a time at such brawles and skufflings aforesaied, he endangered his eyes, yea and his life too; being once beaten well neere to death by a certaine young gentleman of Senatours degree<note type="alphabetical" n="c">It appeareth by Tacitus, that this was Julius Montanus, who, albeit he had not sitten in counsell as Senator, yet was Laticlavius, and wore the Senators Robe.</note>, whose wife he had misused with uncleane handling.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="27">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>But as his vices grewe by little and little to get head, he laide aside these wilde trickes by way of sport and in secret : and without all care of concealing and dissimuling the matter, broke out openly to greater outrages.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>His meales hee drewe out at length<note type="alphabetical" n="a">The manner was in old time to imploy the day in businesses, and therein to take no liberall meales, putting off the full refection... Convivia de die, argued Intemperance...</note>: eating and drinking from noone to midnight... His suppers hee tooke divers times abroade also in publike place, to wit, in the Naumachia<note type="numerical" n="5">A broad place, wherein a Naval fight had sometime been exhibited...</note> shut up and enclosed... where hee was served and attended upon by all the common Queanes of the Citie, and stinking strumpets of the stewes<note type="alphabetical" n="b">Ambubaiarum. These tooke their name... Quod circa Baias versarentur. ... Copas imitantium... indifferently for strumpets and curtesans.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="122"/> His manner was also to give warning unto his familiar friends, and bid him selfe to supper: and one of them it cost in sweet meats<note type="alphabetical" n="c">Mellita, others Myrtitrichila. By which are ment certaine sweat junkets, as daintie wafers, etc.</note> 4 millians<note type="numerical" n="1">Quadragies HS.</note> of sesterces<note type="alphabetical" n="d">This may be thought incredible, that banqueting conceits at one sitting should cost so much...</note>: and another a good deale more in rose water and odoriferous oyles...</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="28">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Over and besides the unnaturall abusing of boyes free-borne, and the keeping of mens wives as his concubines, he forced also and defloured Rubria, a vestale Virgin. Acte a freed woman he went very neere to have wedded as his lawefull wife<note type="numerical" n="2">Which had beene a great disparagement.</note>... A boy there was named Sporus<note type="alphabetical" n="a">Him he called, as other Authors write, Sabbina and Poppæa, after the name of his wife deceased.</note>, whose Genitories he cut out, and assayed therby to transforme him into the nature of a woman. Him he caused to be brought unto him as a bride, with a dowry, in a fine (yellow) veile, after the solemne maner of mariage... whom he maintained as his wife.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>...For, that he had a lust to ly with his owne mother, and was frighted from it by some depraving backe-friendes of hers; for feare, least the proude and insolent dame might by this kind of favour grow too mightie, no man ever made doubt...</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="29">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>As for his owne body, certes, he forfeited the honour thereof, prostituting it to bee abused so farreforth, as having defiled in-manner all the parts of it, at the last, he devised a kind (as it were) of sport and game: that being covered all over in a wilde beastes skin, hee should be let loose forth of a cage<note type="numerical" n="1">Or grate. I wish that both Suetonius and Dio had in this place and such like been altogether silent.</note> and then give the assault upon the privities of men and women both as they stood tyed fast to a stake: and when he had shewed his rage to the full, be killed, forsooth by Doriphorus<note type="alphabetical" n="a">In other writers he is named Pythagoras, so that it should seeme he caried two names.</note> his freed-man, unto <pb n="123"/> whom him selfe also was wedded like as Sporus unto him: insomuch as hee counterfeited the noise and cries of maidens, when they bee forced and suffer devirgination<note type="numerical" n="2">Confessed of themselves and their owne accord.</note>. I have heard of divers that he was fully perswaded, No man nor woman was honest, or in any part of their bodies pure and cleane...</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="30">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The fruite of richesse and use of money, he tooke to be nothing else but lavish expense: thinking them to be very base niggards and mechanicall pinch-pennies, that kept any account or reckoning what they spent and layde out...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>...Hee allowed unto Tiridates<note type="alphabetical" n="a">A great Magician, whom he intertained thus royally, because he would have learned magicke of him. See Plinie.</note> (a thing almost incredible) 800000 Sesterces, day by day, for his expenses, and at his departure bestowed upon him not so little as one hundred milians.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="124"/> No garments did hee on his backe twice: at hazard when he played, he ventured no lesse than 400000 sesterces at a cast, upon every point or pricke of the chaunce<note type="numerical" n="1">Quadringenis Sestertiis. Take Sestertium here in the newter gender...</note><note type="alphabetical" n="b">Whereas Augustus when he played at this game, ventured no more, than for everie Talus, which were foure in all, a single denier.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="c">For it should seeme that the game of Tali heere mentioned, was Pleistobolinda, i. who could throw most with four Tali...</note>. Hee fished with a golden net<note type="numerical" n="2">Aurato rete. Orosius saith more expresly, retibus aureis.</note> (drawen and knit) with cords twisted of purple and crimsen silke in graine....His mules were shod with silver. His mulitiers arraied in fine (red) Canusme cloth: and attended he was with a multitude of Mazaces and Curreurs gaily set out with their bracelets and riche Phalers<note type="alphabetical" n="d">It is evident hereby, as also out of that verse of Juvenal... that these Phaleræ were not Trappings and furniture belonging to horses, but some other ornaments...</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="31">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In no one thing was hee more wastefull and prodigall then in building. Hee made an house, that reached from the Palatium to the Esquiliæ: which at first he called his Transitorie: but when it had been consumed with fire and was reedefied hee named his golden ædifice. As touching the large compasse and receit, the rich furniture and setting out thereof, it may suffice to relate thus much. The porch was of such an heigth as therein might stand upright the geant-like image representing his owne person, an hundred and twentie foote high. So large was this house, as that it conteined three galleries of a mile a peece in length<note type="numerical" n="6">Porticus triplices milliarias. If a man expound it thus: Galleries with three rows of pillers... it wold be more consonant to the truth I suppose.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="125"/> In all other parts thereof, all was laide over with golde, garnished with precious stones and shels of pearle<note type="numerical" n="1">Mother of pearle.</note>. As for the parlours, framed they were with enbowed roufs... But of al these parlours and banqueting roomes, the principall and fairest was made rounde, to turne about continually both day and night, in manner of the World<note type="numerical" n="2">Or heaven.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>...Furthermore, hee began a poole<note type="numerical" n="4">Piscinam.</note> reaching from Misenum to the Meere<note type="numerical" n="5">(Or lake.)</note> Avernus...</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="32">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>To these outragious expenses, beside the trust and confidence he had in the revenewes of the Empire, put forward hee was upon a certaine unexpected hope also that he <pb n="126"/> conceived, of finding a world of wealth... that the rich treasure and old store of silver and gold both, which Queene Dido flying out of Tyros caried away with her, lay buried in Affricke within most huge and vaste caves...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>But when this hope failed him... he bent his mind to promoting of false imputations, to pilling also and polling....Afterwards, that their wils should be forfaite and confiscate, who were unthankeful to the Prince<note type="numerical" n="1">Remembred him not in their wils and made him not an heyre.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>...And whereas hee had prohibited the use of the Amethist<note type="numerical" n="2">Or violet in graine.</note> and purple colours, he suborned one of purpose under hand to sell upon a market day<note type="numerical" n="3">Or faire.</note> some few ounces therof...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p><pb n="127"/> To conclude, he robbed the Temples of many giftes and oblations: the Images likewise therein made of golde or silver he melted into a masse: and among the rest, even those of the Tutelar gods<note type="numerical" n="3">Apollo, Neptune, Jupiter, Juno, Minerva.</note> (of Rome) : which soone after Galba restored and erected againe in their places.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="33">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>As touching his Parricides and murders hee began them first with Claudius: of whose death although he were not principall author, yet he was privie and accessarie thereto. Neither dissimuled he so much, as who afterwards was wont by a Greek by-word, to praise mushromes, (in which kinde of meat Claudius had taken his bane), as the foode of the gods<note type="numerical" n="5">θεῶν βρῶμα, alluding to the deification after his death.</note>. For, in scoffing wise he would say of him that hee had left now moraria<note type="alphabetical" n="a">In this verbe Morari, there is couched a double sense... it signifieth, to stay or to make long abode... But take the same word, as Nero spake it, derived of μῶρος in Greeke, which signifyeth, A foole... Read the little pamphlet of Seneca entituled ἀποκολοκήντωσις...</note> anie longer among mortall men, using the first sillable of the sayd word long....Finally, he neglected the place of his funerall fire<note type="alphabetical" n="b">The Greekes call this Κανστραν οι τύβον. And the Romans in honour of their Princes, were wont to compasse the same all about with a wall of flint, or other durable stone, as marble.</note>: suffering it to be empaled<note type="numerical" n="7">As the manner was for certaine daies before the ashes and reliques were gathered up.</note>, but with sleight stuffe and low railes of timber.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>As for Britannicus... he attempted to make him away by poison. This poison, Nero had received at the hands of one Locusta... <pb n="128"/> Now when shee alleaged for her excuse that she gave him the lesse dose<note type="numerical" n="1">In quantitie.</note>, thereby to colour and cloke the odious fact... 'Why! then belike,' quoth he, 'I am affraide of the lawe Julia<note type="numerical" n="2">De Veneficiis. For her former practise of poisoning, by which she stoode condemned.</note>. And so hee forced her before his face in his owne bed-chamber to compound and seeth a poison that should be most quicke and of present operation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>...No sooner had he tasted it but hee fell downe dead.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="34">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His owne mother, for looking narrowly into him, and examining his words and deedes somewhat streightly... <pb n="129"/> pretending that he was about to resigne up the Empire and depart to Rhodes<note type="numerical" n="1">As if she were the cause therof.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>...But beeing terrified with her threats and violent shrewdnesse, hee determined to kill and dispatch her at once. Having attempted it with poison thrice... he provided a bed-chamber for her, with so ticklish an arched roufe over her head, as beeing easily unjoincted, the frame thereof might fall in peeces in the night... And so, making a semblance of a Love-day and reconciliation, hee sent for her by most sweet and kinde Letters, training her unto Baiæ, there to celebrate with him the solemnity of the Quinquatrian<note type="numerical" n="3">A feast in the honour of Minerva, beginning five daies before the Ides of March, i. the 11 of March.</note>. And having given order before hand to certaine Maisters of Gallies for to split the Foist<note type="numerical" n="4">Or Pinnace.</note> wherein she was embarqued... he put unto her the other abovesaid made with joints and vices... <pb n="130"/> accompanied her (to the water side<note type="numerical" n="1">Or to the staires.</note>) and at the parting also kissed her paps.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>...But when he understood that all went crosse, and that she was escaped to land by swimming... caused the said Agerinus to be apprehended and bound with chaines: and withall, his mother aforesaid, to be murdred...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>...yet could he not either for the present or ever after, endure the worme and sting of conscience for this foule fact, but confesse many a time, that haunted and harried he was with the apparition of his mothers ghost: tormented also with the scourges and burning torches of the Furies. ...Verily as hee travailed through Greece, at the sacred Eleusine ceremonies<note type="alphabetical" n="a">It may be it was in the same forme, that Justinus Martyr citeth out of Orpheus: θύρας δ᾽ ἐπίθεσθε βεβήλος... Which Virgil in some sort hath expressed thus: Procul este profani.</note>... he durst not be present.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>To this parricidy of his mother, he adjoyned also the murder of his aunt<note type="numerical" n="4">Domitia by his fathers side.</note>. <pb n="131"/> For, even before she was through dead, he laide sure hold of her goods, and suppressed her last wil that nothing might escape his clutches.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="35">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Besides Octavia, he maried afterwards two wives: to wit, Poppæa Sabina the daughter of one who had beene Questor, and the wedded wife before of a romane Knight : then, Statilia Messallina, neice<note type="numerical" n="8">In the right line of descent.</note> in the third degree removed of Taurus, twice Consul, who had once triumphed. For to have and enjoy her, he murdred her husband Atticus Vestinus then Consul, even during the time of that honorable Magistracie. Soone wearie he was of Octaviæ's companie and forsooke her bed. And when some friends reproved him for it he made answere, that the jewels els and ornaments only of a wife ought to content her.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Soon after, when he had assayed many times (but in vaine) to strangle her, he put her away, pretending she was barraine.  But when the people misliked this divorse, and forbare not to raile upon him for it, he proceeded, even to confine and banish her quite. In the end he murdred her, under a colourable imputation of divers adulteries, charged upon her so impudently and falsely, that when al generally who were by torture examined upon the point, stood stoutly to the very last in deniall, he suborned and brought in Anicetus<note type="numerical" n="10">Who had brought him up in his childhood.</note> his own Pædagogue against her, who should slander himselfe with her and confesse that by a wile he had abused her bodie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The twelfth day after the said divorcement of Octavia, he espoused and maried the aforesaid dame Poppæa, whom he loved intirely; and yet even her also he killed with a kicke<note type="numerical" n="1">Or spurne.</note> of his heele, for that, being big with child and sickly withall, she had reviled him and given him shrewd words, for comming home so late one night, after his running with chariots. By her he had a daughter named Claudia Augusta, whom he buried when she was a very infant.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>There was no kinde of affinitie and consanguinity were it never so neere, but it felt the waight of his deadly hand. Antonia, the daughter of Claudius, refusing after the death of Poppæa to bee his wife, he slew, under a pretense as if she went about to conspire against him and to alter the state. Semblably, he killed all the rest, that were either allied unto him or of his kinred. ...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>His Preceptor and Schoole-master Seneca he compelled to dye: albeit he had sworne unto him very devoutely... That he had no cause to suspect him: for he would rather lose his owne life then doe him anie hurt. Unto Burrhus, Captaine (of the guarde) he promised a medicine to heale his swollen throat<note type="numerical" n="1">A squinancie.</note>, and sent him the rank poison Toxicum for it.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="36">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>With no lesse cruelty raged hee abroad even against strangers and meere forainers. A blazing hairy starre, commonly thought to portend death and destruction to the highest poures, began to arise, and had appeared many nights together. Beeing troubled therewith, and enformed by Babilus the Astrologer, that Kings were wont to expiate such prodigious signes with some notable massacre... he thereupon projected the death of all the Noblest personages in the Citie. And verily, so much the rather, and, as it were, upon just cause, by reason of two conspiracies by him published and divulged abroad: of which, the former and the greater, bearing the name of Piso<note type="numerical" n="3">And his friends, Pisoniana.</note>, was plotted and detected at Rome: the latter going under the name of Vinicius<note type="numerical" n="4">And his adherents, Viniciana.</note> at Beneventum.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="37">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>After this without all choise and respect, without all measure in his hand, he spared none: he put to death whomsoever it pleased him, and for what cause it skilled not. ... To Cassius Longinus the lawier (a man bereft of both his eyes) objected it was, that in the antient pedigree of his own house and linage, he had set up againe the images of C. Cassius, one of them that murdred Cæsar. To Pætas Thraseas, for having a sterne and severe countenance like a Pædagogue. ...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Being lifted and puffed up, with these as it were, so great successes<note type="numerical" n="2">Or prosperity.</note>, he said that no prince ever knew what he might do: and oftentimes he cast out many words betokening very significantly, that he would not spare the Senators remaining behind, but one day utterly rase that order and degree out of the common-wealth...</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="38">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>But yet for al that, he spared not the people nor forbare the very wals and buildings of his country the Citie. When one in common talke upon a time chaunced to say, Ἐμοῦ θανόντος γαῖα μιχθήτω πυρία... 'Nay rather,' quoth he, 'Ἐμοῦ ζῶντος'. And even so he did indeede: for being offended, as it were with the ylfavoured fashion of the olde houses, as also with the narrow, crooked and winding streets, he set the citie of Rome on fire so apparantly, that many Citizens of Consuls degree, taking his chamberlaines in the maner with matches, touchwood and hurds in their messuages... would not once lay hand on them but let them alone...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>For 6 dayes and 7 nights together raged he in this wise making havocke of all, and driving the common-people to take up their Innes and shrowd themselves the while about the toumbs and moniments of the dead. ... This fire, beheld he daily out of Mæcenas high toure: and taking joye (as he sayd himselfe) at the beautiful flame that it made, chaunted the winning and destruction of Troie, in that Musitians habit wherein he was wont to sing upon the stage.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="39">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>To amend the matter well, unto these harmes and reprochefull dishonors (of the State) so great as they were arising from the Prince, there happened also some other calamities by chance and fortune: to wit, a pestilence continuing one autumne, whereby thirtie thousand burials were reckoned in the record<note type="numerical" n="1">As we say in the Church booke.</note> of Libitina... But a wonder it was to see, and a thing especially to be noted, that amid all these infortunities hee tooke nothing lesse to the heart, than the shrewd checks and reviling taunts of Men: and was to none more milde, than to such as had provoked him, either with hard speeches, or opprobrious verses.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Many infamous libels and defamatorie words, both in Greek and Latine, were publikely written, or otherwise cast and spred abroad against him...</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="40">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Well, the world having indured such an Emperour as this, little lesse than 14 yeares, at length fell away and forsooke him cleane. And first the French began, following as the ringleader of their insurrection Julius Vindex, who that very time governed the Province<note type="numerical" n="2">Of Gaule.</note>, as Propretour.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Foretold it had been long agoe unto Nero by the Astrologers, That one day he should be left forlorne. ...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>But sending one time to the Oracle of Apollo at Delphi, and hearing this answere from thence, That hee must beware of the yeare 73... and divining no whit of Galbæs yeeres, with so assured confidence hee conceived in his heart not onely long life but also a perpetuall and singular felicity...</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="41">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>At the last, throughly mooved and netled with the contumelious edicts of Vindex comming so thicke one in the necke of another, he exhorted the Senate, in a letter written unto them, to revenge him and the commonwealth... But nothing vexed him so much as this, That hee was by him blamed for an unskilfull musician, and because in steede of Nero, he called him Ænobarbus. And verely as touching this name appropriate to his house and family... he professed to resume the same, and to lay away the other that came by adoption. ...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>But when messengers came still one after another, in great feare he returned to Rome.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="42">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>After that he understood besides, how Galba likewise and the provinces of Spaine were revolted, he fell downe at once : his heart was then daunted and cleane done: and so he lay a good while speechlesse in a traunce, and ready, as one would say, to goe out of the world. And so soone as he came againe to himselfe, he rent his clothes, beat and knockt his head, saying plainely, That he was utterly undone...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Neither yet for all this strucke he saile one whit in laying away or leaving out one jot of his ordinary riot and supine slouthfulnesse.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="43">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Immediatly upon the beginning of this feareful tumult, it is credibly thought that he intended manie designes and those very cruell and horrible: yet such as agreed well enough with his naturall humour: namely, to sende under hand successours and murderers of all those that were Commanders of armies and regents of Provinces... Item, to massacre all banished persons where soever, and the Frenchmen every one that were to be found in Rome... Item to poyson all the Senate generally at some appointed feast. Last of all to fire Rome and let wild beasts loose among the people, that thereby there might be more adoe and greater difficulty to save the Citie.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="47">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In this meane while, when newes came that all the other armies also rebelled, the letters delivered unto him, as hee sate at dinner hee tare in peeces, overthrewe the table, and two cuppes (of Chrystall) out of which he tooke the greatest pleasure to drinke... he dashed against the paved floure. Then, after he had received a poison of Locusta and put it up in a golden boxe, he went directly into the hortyards of the Servitii: where, having sent before his most trusty freed-servants unto Ostia for to rig and prepare a fleet to sea, he sounded the Tribunes and Centurions of the guard, whether they would beare him company and flie with him, or no. ...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Thus, putting off all farther cogitation of this matter unto the next day, and awakened about midnight; when he understood that the guard of his Souldiours was retired and gone, hee leapt forth of his bed, and sent all about to his friends. ... Then straightwaies he sought for Spicillus the Sword-fencer<note type="numerical" n="1">Mirmillonem.</note>, or any other common hackster he cared not who, by whose hand he might receive his deaths wound.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="48">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>But having reclaimed once againe that violent moode, hee desired some more secret retyring place, wherein he might lurke a while and recall his wits together. And when Phaon his freed man made offer unto him of a Farme house of his, that he had by the Citie side, about foure miles off... bare footed as hee was and in his shirt, hee cast over it a cloake all sullied and which had lost the colour. ...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>There, when the said Phaon perswaded him to bestow himselfe the meane while, within a pit, from whence sand had beene cast forth, 'Nay,' quoth he, 'I will never goe quick under ground'... ... received hee was into the next backe roome: where he laid him downe on a pallet made of a simple scant mattrice, and an olde over-worne cloake cast over it for a coverlet.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="49">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>When as each one called then instantly on every side upon him, to deliver him selfe with all speede from the reproachfull contumelies and abuses... he commaunded a grave to be made before his face, and gave a measure therefore according to the just proportion of his body... weeping at every word he spake, and inserting ever and anone this pittifull speech, Qualis artifex Pereo! ...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Sometime also he checked and blamed his owne timorousnesse in these wordes, 'I live shamefully': and in reproach, Οὐ πρέπει Νέρωνι, οὐ πρέπει· νήφειν δεῖ ἐν τοῖς τοιούτοις· ἄγε ἔγειρε σεαυτόν... Nowe by this time approached the Horsemen neere at hand, who had a warrant and precept to bring him alive. Which when hee perceived... he set a dagger to his throat, whiles Epaphroditus his Secretarie lent him his hand to dispatch him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>When he was yet but halfe dead, a Centurion brake in upon him... unto whom he answered nothing but this, 'Too late. And is this your loyaltie and allegeance?' In which very word he yeelded up his breath, with his eyes staring out and set in his head...</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="50">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His funerals were performed with the charges of 200000 Sesterces: his corps was caried forth (to buriall) enwrapped within white cloathes of Tinsel, woven with gold wire betweene... His reliques, Ecloge and Alexandra his two Nources, together with Acte his Concubine bestowed within the monument belonging to the house of the Domitii his Auncestours...</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="51">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Hee was for stature almost of complet heighth<note type="numerical" n="5">Within a little of sixe foote.</note>. His body full of specks and freckles, and foule of skinne besides. The haire of his head somewhat yellow: his countenance and visage rather faire, than lovely and well favoured. His eyes gray and somewhat with the dimmest. His neck full and fat. His belly and paunch bearing out: with a paire of passing slender spindle shanks: but withall, he was very healthfull. ... For the most part, he ware a dainty and effeminate pied garment called Synthesis: and with a fine Lawne neck Kercheif bound about his neck he went abroad in the Streetes, ungirt, untrussed, and unshod.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="57">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>He died in the two and thirtieth yeere of his age; that very day of the yeere, on which in times past he had murdred his wife Octavia: and by his death brought so great joy unto the people generally, that the Commons wore Caps<note type="numerical" n="5">Or Bonets, to testifie freedome recovered.</note>, and ranne sporting up and downe throughout the Citie. Yet there wanted not some, who a long time after decked his Tombe with gay flowers that the Spring and Sommer doe affourd...</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>To conclude, when twenty yeeres after his decease (whiles I my selfe was but a young man) one arose among them (no man knew from whence, nor of what condition) who gave it out, That hee was Nero... he was mightily upheld and maintained, yea and hardly delivered up againe.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>