<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>THE HISTORIE OF OCTAVIUS CÆSAR AUGUSTUS</title>
        <author>C. Suetonius Tranquillus</author>
        <editor>Philemon Holland (Translator)</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Encoded for TEI XML</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Transcribed from PDF source files of Philemon Holland's 1898 edition.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <pb n="81" />
      <head>THE HISTORIE OF OCTAVIUS CÆSAR AUGUSTUS</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>THAT the principall name and linage of the Octavii, dwelt in times past at Velitræ, there be many evidences to shewe: for, both a street in the most frequented place of the said towne long since carried the name Octavius, and also there was to be seene an Altar there consecrated by one Octavius<note place="bottom" n="1">Or to Octavius: Octavio Consecrata.</note>, who being Generall of the field in a warre against the borderers, when he happened to be sacrificing to Mars, upon newes brought that the enemie gave a suddaine charge, caught the Inwards of the beast sacrificed halfe raw as they were, out of the fire<note place="bottom" n="2">Where they were a boyling or rosting.</note>; cut and offered them accordingly: and so entred into battaile and returned with victorie. There is beside, a publike Act extant upon record, wherein decreed and provided it was, that everie yeare after, the inwards in like manner should bee presented unto Mars, and the rest of the sacrifice remaining, carried backe unto the Octavii.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>These Octavii<note place="bottom" n="3">Ea gens inter Romanos allecta.</note>, being by K. Tarquinius Priscus naturalized Romaines soone after translated and admitted by Servius Tullus, into the Senate among the Patritians, and Nobles, in processe of time ranged themselves with the commons, and with much adoe at length, by the meanes of Julius of <pb n="82" /> sacred Memorie returned to the Patritian degree again: the first of these that by the peoples election bare any Magistracie, was C. Rufus:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
          <p>who having beene Questor begat Cn. and C. From them descended two families of the Octavii, and those for their estate of life farre different. For Cn. and all the rest from him one after another, attained to places of highest honour: but Caius and his posteritie everie one even unto the father of Augustus, (such was either their fortune or their will,) staied in the order and degree of gentlemen, and rose no higher. The great Grandfather of Augustus, in the second Punike war<note place="bottom" n="1">Against Anniball and the Carthaginians.</note>, served in qualitie of a Militar Tribune<note place="bottom" n="2">Colonel of 1000 footmen.</note>, in Sicilie, under Æmilius Papus Lord generall. His father contenting himselfe with bearing office like another Burgesse in his owne Bourrough, being left welthie by his father, grew to a good estate, and lived to be an olde man, in much peace and tranquilitie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
          <p>But of these matters let others make report. Augustus himselfe writeth noe more but thus. That the house from whence he came, was of Romaine Gentlemen, welthie and ancient withall, wherein the first that ever came to be Senatour was his father. M. Antonius hitteth him in the teeth with his great Grandfather: saying he was but a Libertine borne, and by occupation a roper<note place="bottom" n="3">A seller of ropes: restionem, not Restionem with a capital R, as if it were a proper name.</note>, and come out of a Village of the Thurines: also that his Grandfather was no better then a verie banquer. Neither have I founde any more, as touching the Auncestours of Augustus by the Fathers side.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>Octavius his father, from the verie beginning of his age, was of great welth and reputation; so that I cannot but mervaile, that hee also hath beene reported by some a banquer or monie changer: yea and one of the dealers of monie<note place="bottom" n="4">Argentarium an exchanger of monie for gaine.</note><note type="annotation" n="a">Inter divisores, operasque campestres. This was thought to bee but a base occupation, namely, to give among the Tribes, such sums of money as the Candidati, or those that stood in election for offices promised and pronounced for the buying of voices. The name also grew to be odious, howsoever Plautus in Aulul. calleth them Magistros Curiæ. Likewise all such servitours as otherwise gave attendance in Campo Martio, and thereby gat a living, whom he termeth here operas campestres, were but of meane reckoning.</note> and servitours employed in Campus Martius, by those that stand for offices: for having beene from his verie cradle brought uppe in wealth highly and plentifully, he both <pb n="83" /> attained unto honorable dignities with facilitie, and administred the same with credite and reputation. Presently uppon his Pretourshippe, the province of Macedonie fell unto his lot. And in his journey thither, the fugitives, to wit the reliques of Spartacus and Catilines forces, who then helde the Thurine teritorie hee defaited; having commission extraordinarily given unto him in the senate so to doe:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
          <p>this province hee governed with noe lesse justice then fortitude. For having discomfited in a great battaile the Bessi and the Thracians, he dealt so well with the Allies and confederats of that Kingdome: that there be certaine letters of M. Tullius Cicero extant, wherein he exhorteth and admonisheth his brother Quintus, (who at the same time, little to his credite and good name, administred the proconsulship of Asia) for to imitate his neigbour Octavius, in doing well by the Allies, and winning their love thereby.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>As he departed out of Macedonie before that he could professe himselfe to be a suiter for the Consulship, he died a suddaine death: leaving these children behind him alive, namely two daughters Octavia the elder, which hee had by Ancharia: Octavia the younger, and Augustus likewise, by Atia. This Atia was the daughter of M. Atius Balbus, and Julia the sister of C. Cæsar. Balbus by his fathers side was an Aricine, a man that shewed Senatours Images and armes in his house: by his mother linked to Magnus Pompeius in the neerest degree of consanguinitie. And having borne the office of Pretorship he among the xx. Commissioners devided by vertue of the Law Julia, the lands in the territory of Capua among the Commons.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
          <p>But M. Antonius, despising the parentage and petegree of Augustus by the mother side also, twitteth him and layeth in his dish, that his great Grandsire was an African borne: saying on while, that he kept a shop of sweete oyles, Ointments and perfumes; another while, that he was a baker in Aricia: Cassius verily of Parma, in a certaine Epistle taxeth Augustus as being the Nephew not of a Baker onely, but also of a banker, in <pb n="84" /> these termes. 'Thou hast meale for thy mother. And then comes a banker of Nerulone, who out of a most painefull backehouse in Aricia knedeth and mooldeth it with his hands sullied by telling and exchanging monie<note place="bottom" n="1">Al this is spoken allegorically of his base parentage.</note>.'</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>Augustus was borne, when M. Tullius Cicero and Antonie were Consuls, the ninth day before the Calends of October<note place="bottom" n="2">23 of September.</note>, a little before the Sun rising, in the palatine quarter of the Citie<note type="annotation" n="a">Regione Palatii. In old time Rome was divided into foure principall regions or quarters: Suburrana, Equilina, Collina, and Palatina.</note>, at a place called Capita Bubula<note place="bottom" n="3">Oxe or Bull-heads.</note>: where now it hath a sacred Chappel, built and erected a little after he departed out of this world: for, as it is found in the records of the Senate, when C. Lectorius a young gentleman of the Patritian order, pleaded to have some easier punishment for the adulterie, and alledged, over and besides his yong yeares and parentage this also in his plea before the Senatours, that he was the possessor and as it were, the warden and Sextaine of that ground or soyle, which Augustus of happy memorie touched first<note type="annotation" n="b">The manner in old time was, that the newe borne babe should be set up on the bare ground to cry and call upon the Goddesse Ops, who so gently had received it. And the Goddesse forsooth, that helped to lift it up againe, was called Levana, i. a Levando. Augustin. Macrob.</note>, and requested that it might be given and granted unto the said Augustus as to his domestical and peculiar god: decreed it was that the same part of the house should be consecrated to that holy use.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>There is yet to be seene the place of his nourcery, within a suburbian house belonging to his Auncesters, neere unto Velitræ: a very little Cabin, about the bignes of a Larder or Pantry: the neighbours are possessed with a certaine conceit, as if he had been there also borne. To enter into this rowme unlesse it be of necessitie and with devout chastitie, men make it scrupulous and are affraide: upon an old conceived opinion, as if unto as many as came thether rashly and inconsiderately, a certaine horror and fearefulnes were presented. And verily, this was soone after confirmed by this occasion: for when the new Land lord and possessor of that farme house, either by chance and at unwares, or els to <pb n="85" /> try some experiment, went into it, there to take up his lodging, it happened that in the night within verie fewe houres after, being driven out from thence by some sodaine violence, (he knoweth not how,) he was found in manner halfe dead, together with bed and all, before the dore.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>Being yet an infant, surnamed he was Thurinus, in memorial of the beginning of his Auncestours: or else because in the countrie about Thurii, when hee was newly borne, his father Octavius fought a battaile against the Fugitives. That he was surnamed Thurinus, my selfe am able to report by a good and sufficient evidence, as having gotten an olde little counterfeit in brasse representing him being a child: which had in yron letters and those almost worne out, this name engraven. This said counterfeit, being given by me unto the Prince<note place="bottom" n="1">Hadrian the Emperor.</note>, is now devoutely kept and worshipped among other his bed chamber Images. Moreover called he is oftentimes in taunting wise by M. Antonius in his Epistles, Thurinus: and himselfe writeth unto him backe againe as touching that point, nothing but this: That he marvaileth why that former name of his should be objected unto him as a reproach.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
          <p>Afterwardes, he assumed the surname of C. Cæsar: and after it of Augustus: the one by the last will of his great Uncle, by the mother side, the other by the vertue of Munatius Plancus his sentence: for when some gave their opinion, that he ought to be stiled Romulus, as if he also had beene A Founder of the Cittie, Plancus prevailed, that he should be called rather Augustus: not onely for that it was a new Surname, but also greater and more honourable, because Religious and holy places, wherein also any thing is consecrated by bird flight, and feeding of them be called Augusta, ab auctu, i, of growing, or else ab avium gestu gustuve: i. Of birds gesture and feeding. Like as Ennius also teacheth writing in this manner:
        <quote>Augusto Augurio postquam inclyta condita Roma est.</quote>
        After that Noble Rome was built by sacred flight of Birds.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p><pb n="86" /> He was 4 yeares old when his father died: and in the xij. yeare of his age he praised in a publike assemblie, his Grand-mother Julia deceased. Foure yeeres after having put on his virill robe<note type="annotation" n="a">The Virile robe was the ordinary Romane gowne, all white without purple, which they wore when they came to be past 16 yeares of age.</note>, he had militarie gifts<note type="annotation" n="b">To wit, bracelets, chaines and collars, Speare staves without iron heads, trappings, chaplets and guirlands, etc.</note> bestowed upon him at the African tryumph of Cæsar, albeit by reason of his yong yeares he had not once served in the warres. Soone after, when his Unkle (Cæsar) was gone into Spaine against Cn. Pompeius children, he followed with in a while, (being as yet not well recovered out of a greevous sickenesse,) even through waies infested by enemies, with verie few in his traine to accompany him, and having suffred shipwracke besides: whereby he mightily won his Uncles love, who quickely approved his towardly behaviour and disposition, over and above his diligence in travaile.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
          <p>When Cæsar, after he had recovered Spaine and brought it to his subjection, intended a voiage against the Daci<note place="bottom" n="1">Otherwise called Getæ.</note>, and from thence against the Parthians, he being sent afore to Apollonia, became a Student there and followed his booke. And so soone as he had certaine intelligence that Ceasar was slaine, and himselfe made his heire: standing in doubt and suspense a long time, whether he should implore the helpe of the Legions or no: at length he gave over that course verily, as too hastie and untimely, but when he was returned againe to Rome, he entred upon his inheritance, not withstanding his mother made some doubt thereof and his father in law Martius Philippus<note place="bottom" n="2">His mothers husband.</note> a man of Consular degree much disswaded him therefrom.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
          <p>And from that time having levied and assembled his forces, he governed the common welth first jointly with M. Antonius and M. Lepidus<note type="annotation" n="c">This was the Triumvirate, so much spoken of: during which, M. Antonius, M. Lepidus, and Augustus ruled joyntly together. Marcus Brutus.</note> for the space almost of 12 yeres, and at the last for xliiij. yeares by himselfe alone.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>Having thus laid open the very sum as it were, of his life, I will goe through the parts thereof in particular: not by the times but by the severall kinds therof, to the end the same may be shewed and knowne more distinctly. Five <pb n="87" /> civill warres he made, to wit, at Mutine, Philippi, Perusium, in Sicilie, and at Actium. Of which the first and last were against M. Antonius: the second against Brutus and Cassius, the third against L. Antonius brother to the Triumvir, the 4 against Sex. Pompeius, Cn. Pompeius his sonne. Of all these warres he tooke the occasion and quarrell from hence, namely, reputing and judging in his mind nothing more meet and convenient than the revenge of his unkles death and the maintenance of his acts and proceedinges.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
          <p>No sooner was he returned from Apollonia, but he purposed to set upon Brutus and Cassius at unwares: and (because upon foresight of daunger they were fled secretly out of the way) to take the course of law, and in their absence to endite them of murder. As for the Plaies and games for Ceasars victory because they durst not exhibit them, whose lot and office it was so to do, himselfe set them forth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
          <p>And to the end that he might go through all other matters also more resolutely; he professed himselfe to labour for the Tribuneship<note place="bottom" n="1">Of the commons.</note> in the rowme of one who fortuned to die: albeit he was one of the Nobility, though not of the Senate. But seeing that M. Antonius the Consul withstood his attempts, where as he hoped he would have beene his principall friend in that suit: and vouchsafed not unto him so much as the assistance of his owne publike authority, or helpe procured from others in any thing, without he agreed and covenanted to yeeld unto him some exceeding consideration: he betooke himselfe unto the protection of those Nobles and chiefe Senatours unto whom he perceived that Antonius was odious: in this regard especially, that he<note place="bottom" n="2">i. Antonius.</note> endevored all that he could by force of armes to expell Decimus Brutus besieged at Mutina, out of that province which by Ceasar was granted and by the Senate confirmed unto him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
          <p>And thereupon by the advice and perswasion of some he set certaine persons privily in hand to murder Antonius; which perilous practise of his being detected and fearing still the like danger to himselfe, he waged the old <pb n="88" /> soldiers with as bountifull a larges as possible he could, for the defence as well of his owne person as of the state. And being appointed to lead this armie thus levied, in qualitie of propretour, and together with Hirtius and Pansa, who had entred upon the Consulship, to aide D. Brutus, he made an end of this warre committed unto him within three moneths, in two fought fieldes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
          <p>In the former of which, Antonie writeth that he fled, and without coat armour or horse appeared at length after two dayes and shewed himselfe. But in the battaile next following, well knowne it is, that he performed the part not onely of a Captaine but also of a soldier: and in the very heat and midst of the medly, by occasion that the Standerd bearer of his owne Legion was grievously hurt, he supported the Ægle with his owne shoulders<note place="bottom" n="1">As massie and heavie as it was.</note> and so carried it a good while.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="11">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>During this warre, when Hirtius had lost his life in the conflict, and Pansa soone after of his wound, it was bruited rifely abroad, that both of them were by his meanes slaine: to the ende that having defaited Antonius, and the Commonwealth beeing bereift of both Consuls, he alone might seize uppon the victorious armies. And verily the death of Pansa was so deepely suspected that Glyco the Physitian was committed to ward and durance, as if he had put poyson into his wound. Aquillius Niger addeth moreover and saith, that the one of the Consuls, to wit, Hirtius, was in the verie confused medly of the battaile killed by Augustus himselfe.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="12">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>But so soone as he understood that Antonie after his flight was intertained by M. Lepidus: that other Captaines also and armies consented to take part with the side<note place="bottom" n="2">Propartibus: of Pompeius and the common wealth. If you read pro patribus, i. with the Nobilitie.</note>: he forsooke without all delaies the cause of the Nobles and principall Senatours: and for the better pretence of this change and alteration of his minde, craftily and unjustly <pb n="89" /> alleadged the words and deedes of certaine of them as if some had given it out of him: That he was a boy; others<note type="annotation" n="b">Hee meaneth Cicero, as appeareth by an Epistle of D. Brutus unto Cicero in these words, Narravit mihi, etc., ipsum Cæsarem (Augustum) nihil sane de te questum nisi dictum quod diceret, te dixisse laudandum adolescentem, ornandum, tollendum: se non commissurum ut tolli possit. In which words, as also in this place of Tranquillus, there is an æquivocation or doubtfull sense in this Verbe Tollendum: which in one signification, is in manner æquivalent with laudandum and ornandum; and betokeneth, to bee advanced, extolled, or lifted up and so is to be taken in good part: but in another, it is all one with tollendum de medio, or occidendum, id est, to be dispatched out of life: or killed. In which sense Cicero ment it, and Augustus tooke it, namely in ill part. Much like to this, you shall reade in Nero, sustulit hic matrem, sustulit ille patrem. The grace lieth in the ambiguitie of the Latine word tollendum, which cannot in English be so well delivered.</note>, that he was to be adorned, and honoured<note place="bottom" n="1">Et tollendum.</note>: that neither himselfe nor the olde beaten soldiers might be rewarded according to their desarts. And the better to approove his repentance of the former side and faction that he tooke: he fined the Nursines, in a great summe of monie, and more than they were able to pay for that upon the Monuments or Tombe of those Citizens that were slaine in the battaile at Mutina (which at their common charges was reared) they wrote this Title, That they died for the Libertie and Free-dome of their Cittie.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="13">
        <note type="annotation" n="a">The Egnatii, as Appian witnesseth.</note>
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Being entred into Societie with Antonie and Lepidus, hee finished the Philippian warre also, (although he was but weake and sickely,) and that with two battailes: in the former being discamped and driven out of the field, hardly hee escaped by flight and recovered the Regiment or wing of Antonius. Neither used he moderately the successe of his victorie, but when hee had sent the head of Brutus to Rome for to bee bestowed under the Statue of Cæsar, he dealt cruelly with the Noblest and most honourable prisoners, and not without reproachfull words:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>so farre forth verily, that to one of them, making humble suite and prayer for his Sepulture, he answered, (by report) in this wise: That it would be anone, at the dispose of the foules of the Aire: and when others, to wit, the Father, and sonne together intreated for their lives; he commanded them either to cast lots or trie by combate whether of them should have life granted; and so beheld them both as they dyed, whilest the father who offred himselfe to die was slaine, and the sonne voluntarily take his death. Whereuppon the rest, and amongst them M. Favonius that worthie follower of Cato, when they were brought forth with their yrons and chaynes to execution, after they had in honorable termes saluted Antonius by the name of Emperour<note place="bottom" n="2">Soveraine commander.</note>, openly reviled and let flie at him most foule and rayling words.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Having parted <pb n="90" /> betweene them their charges and offices after this victorie, when Antonius undertook to settle the East in good order, and himselfe to bring the olde Soldiers backe into Italie, and to place them there, in the lands and teritories belonging to the free Townes and Burowghes, he kept himselfe in favour neither with the said old soldiers, nor the former possessors of those lands: whilest the one sort complained, that they were disseized: and the other, that they were not well entreated according to their hope, for so good deserts.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="14">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>At which verie time, he forced L. Antonius (who confidently presuming upon the Consulship which he then bare, and his brothers power withall, went about to make an insurrection and alteration in the state) to confesse and flie unto Perusia, and there for verie hunger compelled him to yeeld: but yet not without great jeopardie of his owne person, both before and after the warre: for when at a certaine solemne sight of stage plaies, he had commanded an ordinarie and common soldier who was set within the 14 ranks<note type="annotation" n="a">Which by the Lawe Julia, Theatralis, and Roscia, were allowed for the knights or Gentlemen of Rome, whose estate was valued not under 400000 Sesterces. The lawes abovesaid, were promulged by Augustus Cæsar, and L. Roscius Otho a Tribune of the Commons. And these 14 Seates named Equestria were the next unto the stage after the Orcestra arising by degrees and staires, as it were higher and higher, and so farther of. Above which in the upper and more remote scaffolds sat the common people, and thereupon they were called Popularia. Howbeit, for all the lawe Roscia, many Commoners of good wealth and credit, used to sit indifferently in the said 14 formost seats, untill the other Lawe Julia was enacted, which distinguished the orders more precisely. Carol. Sigon. De Antiq. Jur. Civ. Rom. lib. 2, cap. 19.</note>, to be raised by an officer, and thereupon a rumor was carried and spred by his malicious ill willers and back-biters, as if presently after torture he had put the same soldier to death. There lacked verie little, but that in the concourse and indignation of the militarre multitude, he had come to a mischiefe and beene murdered. This onely saved his life: that the man for a while missed, sodainely was to be seene againe alive and safe without any harme done unto him. About the walls of Perusia, as hee sacrificed, he had like to have been intercepted by a strong companie of sword fencers that sallied out of the Towne.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="15">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>After he had forced Perusia, he proceeded to the execution of verie many, and ever as any went about either to crave pardon or to excuse themselves, with this on word he stopped their mouthes, 'Die yee must.' Some write, that iij. hundred of both degrees (to wit Senatours and Knights) <pb n="91" /> chosen out of them who had yeelded, were killed as sacrifices<note place="bottom" n="1">Brained with an axe: and not beheaded.</note> upon the Ides of March<note place="bottom" n="2">On which day Julius Cæsar was murdred.</note>, at the Alter built in the honor of Julius (Cæsar) of famous memorie. There have been others who wrote, that of verie purpose he tooke armes and made this warre to the end that his close adversaries and those who rather for feare, then of good will held in, upon occasion given and opportunitie by L. Antonius there leader, might be detected: that having once vanquished them and confiscated their goods, the rewards promised unto the olde soldiers he might the better performe.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="16">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The warre in Sicile he began betimes and with the first, but drewe it out a long time; as being often intermitted: one while, for the repairing and rigging of his fleete which by two ship-wrackes in tempest, (and that in summer time<note place="bottom" n="3">When commonly it is calme in those Seas.</note>) he had lost: another while by occasion of peace made at the earnest cry of the people, for the provision of their victuales cut off and kept from them: and the famine thereby dayly growing: untill such time as having built newe ships, manumised and set free xx. thowsand slaves, and those put to the ore for to learne to row gallies, he made the Haven Julius at Baiæ by letting the sea into the Lakes, Lucrinus and Avernus. In which when he had trained and exercised his sea forces whole winters, he overcame Pompeius betweene Milæ and Naulochus<note place="bottom" n="4">An harbour neere Messanah.</note>: at the verie houre and instant time of which Navall battaile, he was suddenly surprized with such a sound sleepe, that his friends were faine to waken him and raise him out of bed for to give the signall.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Wherupon occasion and matter was ministred (as I thinke) to Antonius<note place="bottom" n="5">Marcus, the Triumvir.</note>, for to cast this in his teeth, that he could not so much as with his eyes open see directly before him the battaile set in ray, but lay like a sencelesse blocke on his backe, looking onely into the skie aloft<note place="bottom" n="6">For Gods helpe.</note>: nor once arose and came in sight of his soldiours, before that M. Agrippa had <pb n="92" /> put his enemies 12 ships to flight. Others blame and charge him both for a speech and deede also of his: as if he should crie out and say, That seeing his owne regiment of ships were cast away by tempests, he would even against the will of Neptune obtaine victorie. And verily the next day of the Circensian Games, he tooke out of the solemne pompe there shewed<note type="annotation" n="a">When in stately Pompe, the sacred chariot Thensa, with the images of the Gods in it, was devoutly drawen according to the solemne manner.</note>, the Image of the said God:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>neither in any other warre lightly was hee in more and greater dangers. For having transported one armie into Sicilie, when he sailed backe againe for to waft over the rest of his forces from the continent and firme land<note place="bottom" n="1">Of Italie.</note>, he was at unwares overtaken and surprised by Demochares and Apollophanes the Lievetenants and Admirals of Pompeius, but at the length with verie much ado, he escaped with one onely barke. In like manner as he travailed by land unto Rhegium neere Locrie<note type="annotation" n="b">A coast-towne of Italy affronting Sicile, from whence it is a very short cut over sea: so called by the Greekes, as if even there a breach was made by the sea, dividing Italie from Sicilie which before time was a part of the continent or mainland and no mervaile of that Name: since that Maritime Region, wherein Locri stood, was in times past called Magna Græcia.</note>, kenning a farre of Pompeis gallies sayling along the coasts, and weening them to be his owne, he went downe to the shore, and had like to have been caught and taken by them. And even then as he made shift to flie and escape through by-waies and blind-lanes: a bond-servant of Æmilius Paulus a companion of his, taking it to the heart that his Maisters father Paulus, was in times past by him proscribed and outlawed, and imbracing, as it were, the good occasion and opportunitie of revenge now offered, gave the attempt to kill him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>After the flight of Pompeius<note place="bottom" n="2">Sext.</note>, when M. Lepidus one of his Collegues, whome hee had called forth of Afrike to his aide, bearing himselfe proude uppon the confidence of xx. Legions, challenged a soverainetie over the rest, and that, with terrour and menaces: hee stript him of all his armie, and uppon his humble submission and supplication, pardoned his life, but confined him for ever to Circeii.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="17">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The Societie of M. Antonius<note place="bottom" n="5">M. Antonius and Octavius Augustus.</note> wavering alwaies in doubtfull tearmes and uncertaine, and notwithstanding many and sundrie reconciliations, not well knit and confirmed, he brake of quite in the ende: and the better to proove and make good that he had degenerated from the civill <pb n="93" /> behaviour and modestie of a (Romaine) Citizen, he caused the last will and testament of the said Antonie, which he had left at Rome<note type="annotation" n="d">In the custodie of the Vestall Nunnes, or Votaries, as Julus Cæsar had done before him: of such integritie and so good conscience they were thought to be, as things of greatest weight were committed unto them in trust.</note>, and therein nominated even the Children of Cleopatra<note type="annotation" n="c">In that hee put downe in his will the children which he had by Cleopatra a stranger and barbarian borne, which also were begotten in bastardie, as well as if they had beene naturall Romanes and legitimate, hee faulted in common civilitie, but much more, when hee proceeded to call the sonnes that he had by her, Reges Regum, i. the King of Kings. As absurd also and immodest hee shewed himselfe, when having by her at one birth two twinnes, the male infant he surnamed Sol, i. the Sunne, and the Femall, Lunà, i. the Moone.</note> among his heires to be opened and red in a publike assemblie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Howbeit when hee was judged by the State an enemie, hee sent backe unto him those of his neerest acquaintance and inward friendes and among other C. Sosius, and T. Domitius<note place="bottom" n="1">Cn. Domitius.</note><note type="annotation" n="e">This forename, Titus cannot truly be given to any of the Domitii, if that bee true which is written of them afterward in Domitius Nero, cap. 1. But in the behalfe of M. Antonius, considering he was their Patrone and Protector. For other forain States and Cities usually were shrouded under the favour of Gentlemen at Rome. In which regard, he laid not to their charge that they had not sided with himselfe, but rather taken part with their Patron Antonii: considering that nere bond wherewith such Protectors and Clients or Dependents were linked together: which Dionysius supposeth to bee almost as ancient as Rome it selfe, and almost æquall to that of Allies, yea and kinsfolke in bloud.</note>, being Consuls at that time still. The Bononians also, for that of olde they were dependantes of the Antonii and in there retinue and protection, hee by a publicke Act acquit and pardoned for not entring into a confederace with all Italie, on his side. Not long after, he vanquished him in a Navall battaile before Actium, what time by reason that the fight continued untill it was late in the evening hee was forced to lodge all night conqueror as he was, on ship board.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>When he had retired himselfe from Actium into the Iland Samos for his winter harbour, being disquieted with the newes of his soldiers mutinie demanding rewardes and discharge from service; those I meane, whom after the victorie atcheived hee had from out of the whole number sent before to Brindis, he went againe into Italie: but in crossing the Seas thither, twice was he tossed and troubled with Tempests: first betweene the promontories or Capes of Poloponensus and Ætolia: againe, about the Mountaines or Cliffes Ceraunii. In both which places, part of his pinnaces were cast away and drowned: and with all, the verie takling of that shippe wherein he embarked was rent and torne asunder: Neither staied he at Brindis above 27 daies, that is to say untill hee had setled his soldiers and contented them in their desires and requests: but fetching a compasse about Asia, and Siria, sailed into Ægypt. Where after hee had laied seige unto Alexandria, whether Antonie and Cleopatra were together fled: he soone became Mais. of that Cittie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>And as for Antonie, who now (all to late) <pb n="94" /> made meanes for conditions of peace hee enforced to make himselfe away, and saw him dead<note place="bottom" n="1">Viditque mortuum. In some copies we read thus: Viditque mortuam Cleopatram, i. And he saw Cleopatra dead: for he heard onely of Antonies death and saw the sworde wherewith hee wounded himselfe.</note>. And to Cleopatra whom most gladly he would have saved alive for to beautifie his tryumph hee set the Psylli<note type="annotation" n="a">These Psylli are people in Affricke supposed to have bodies of a singular vertue to kill serpents, as also a speciall skill in sucking foorth venome out of the wound made by their sting. Yet Cornelius Celsus, lib. 5, cap. 27, is of opinion, that they have no principall gift or cunning in this feate above other men, but more boldnesse rather, confirmed by use and practise. For the venome of a serpent, saith hee, hurteth not by being tasted, but as it is infused by a wound, which he proveth by those poysons that the French use especially in hunting. And therefore a verie Snake or Adder it selfe, may bee eaten safely, how ever the sting is deadly and if whiles it lyeth astonied or benummed (the cast wherof these Monte-bankes or juglers have by meanes of certaine medicines) one put his finger into the mouth thereof, and be not bitten or stung withall, there is no spettle or slimie humours there to doe harme. So that whosoever else, by example of these Psylli shall sucke any wound inflicted by a Serpent, he shall doe it safely, and cure besides, the party that is stung. Provided alwaies, that hee have no sore or ulcer, in gummes, palate, or any part of his limmes.</note> to sucke out the venime and poyson within her bodie: for that supposed it was she died with the sting of the Serpent Aspis<note type="annotation" n="b">Some thinke this kinde of Aspis which shee used, was Pytas, others Hypnale; for that the sting brought drowsinesse upon her: and Lucane called it Aspida Somniferam. But common it is unto all the sortes to kill by sleepe and stupefaction without paine, some sooner, some later: but all within the space of 6 houres: so that Hypnale may seeme to be a generall attribute to them all.</note>. This honour he did unto them both, namely to burie them in one sepulcher: and the Tombe by them begun, he commanded to be finished.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>Young Antonie the elder of those twaine whom he had by Fulvia, he caused to be violently haled from the Statue of Julius Cæsar of famous memorie, unto which, after many prayers but all in vaine, he was fled as to sanctuarie, and so killed him. Likewise Cæsario whom Cleopatra gave out openly that she had conceived by his father Cæsar<note place="bottom" n="2">His great Unkle indeede but father by adoption.</note>, he fetched backe againe from the place whether he was fled, and put him to death. The rest of the Children of Antonie and the Queene togither, he both saved (no lesse than if they had beene linked in neere Alliance unto himselfe,) and also according to the state of everie one of them, he maintained and cherished respectively.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="18">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>About the same time, when he beheld the Tombe together with the corps of Alexander the great, taken newly foorth of the vaute or secret Chappell where it was bestowed, he set upon it a coronet of gold: and strewing flowers thereupon worshipped it: and being asked the question, whither hee would looke upon the Ptolomes also<note type="annotation" n="a">As if hee counted those Ptolemees dead, who left no memorable actes behinde them and Alexander, a King still, or worthie alone to be called King, whose memoriall was yet so fresh and lively.</note>? he answered that he was desirous indeed to see a King but not the dead<note place="bottom" n="3">Or Ptolemais, i. the bodies or Tombes of the Ptolemæes. If you read Ptolemæum, it is meant of Lagus.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>When he had reduced Ægypt in the forme of a province, to the end that he might make it more fruitfull and fit to yeeld corne and victuals for the Cittie of Rome, he skowred and cleansed by helpe of soldiers, all those ditches where into Nilus over- <pb n="95" /> floweth, which by long time had been choaked with mud. And that the memorie of his Actiake victorie might be more renowmed among posteritie, he built the Cittie Nicopolis over against Actium, and ordained certaine games and plaies there, everie 5 yeeres: and having enlarged the old Temple of Apollo, and the place werein he had encamped, he beautified with Navall spoiles and then consecrated it to Neptune and Mars.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="19">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>After this, sundry tumults and the verie beginnings of commotions and insurrections, many conspiracies also detected before they grew to any head, he suppressed: and those, some at one time, and some at an other: namely first one of Lepidus the younger: then, another of Varro Muræna, and Fannius Capio: soone after that, of M. Genatius<note place="bottom" n="2">Or Egnatius.</note>: and so forward of Plautius Rufus and L. Paulus, his neeces husband: and besides all these, that of L. Audasius accused of forgerie, and counterfeit seales; a man neither for yeares able nor bodie sound: likewise of Asimius Epicadus descended from the Parthynes Nations a Mungrella<note type="annotation" n="a">For that one of his parentes was a Parthine, that is to say, a stranger of Illyricum, and the other a Romane.</note><note place="bottom" n="3">Begotten betweene a bond slave and a Libertine.</note>: and last of all, of Telephus, a base Nomenclator<note place="bottom" n="4">Or Prompter of names, emploied in telling of their names who came to salute and bid good morrow, and placing also of guests at the Table, and in no better service.</note>, servant to a woman: for free was not Augustus from the conspiracie and daunger, no not of the most abject sort of people.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>As for Audasius and Epicadus, they had entended to carrie away Julia his daughter and Agryppa, his Nephew (out of those Ilands wherin they abode confined) unto the armies: and Telephus purposed upon a deepe conceite that the soveraintie of dominion was by the Destinies and will of God due unto him, even to lay upon him and the Senate violent hands. And more then that, one time there was taken neere unto his bed-chamber by night, a camp-slave belonging to the Illyrian armie, who had deceived the porters and gotten thither with a wood knife at his side, but whether he were out of his wits, or feigned himselfe mad, it was uncertaine: <pb n="96" /> for nothing could bee wrung out of him by examination upon the racke and torture.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="20">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Foraine warres he made in his owne person ij. in all and no more: that is to say, the Dalmatian<note type="annotation" n="a">Warres take the name of those that bee vanquished. As, Gallicum bellum, Germanicum, Dalmaticum, etc., in which Gaule, Germanie, and Dalmatia be subdued.</note>, when he was yet a verie youth: and the Cantabrian, after he had defaited Antonie. In the Dalmatian warre, he was wounded also: for in one battaile he gat a blow upon his right knee with a stone: and in an other, not his leg onely, but also both his armes were hurt with the fall from a bridge<note place="bottom" n="1">Or turret of woode.</note><note type="annotation" n="b">Some take this bridge to be a kinde of fabrick or skaffold reared for the assault of the towne Metulium, and not an ordinarie bridge built over some river.</note>. The rest of his warres he managed by his Lieftennants: yet so as that in some of them namely the Pannonian and the Germaine, hee would either come betweene times, or else remaine not farre of: making his progresse from the Cittie of Rome, as farre as to Ravenna, or Millaine or to Aquileia.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="21">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>He subdued partly by his owne conduct in proper person, and in part by his Lieftenants having commission immediatly from him and directed by his auspicies, Cantabria, Aquitaine, Pannonia, and Dalmatia together with all Illyricum, Rhætia likewise, the Vindelicis, the Salassians and the Nations inhabiting the Alpes. He repressed also the incursions of the Dakes, having slaine three of their Generals with a great number of them besides. And the Germaines he remooved and set further of; even beyond the river Albis. Howbeit, of these the Suevians and the Sicambrians, because they yeelded themselves, he brought over into Gaule, and placed them in the lands next unto Rhene. Other Nations being mal-content, he reduced unto his obedience.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Neither made hee warre upon any people without just and necessarie causes: and so farre was he from desire of enlarging his Empire, or advancing his martiall glorie, that he compelled certaine princes and potentates of the Barbarians, to take an oath in the Temple of Mars the Revenger<note type="annotation" n="a">This temple, as appeareth afterwards, hee had vowed in the Philippian warre, which hee undertooke in revenge of his Father Julius Cæsars death, and therefore dedicated it unto Mars, Revenger.</note> for to continue in their allegiance, and in the protection and peace which they sued for: yea and from some of them he assaied to exact a new kind of Hostages, even women<note place="bottom" n="1">Unusuall in those days.</note>, for that he perceived, that they neglected the pledges of the males. And yet he gave them libertie, as often as they would, to receive their hostages againe. Neither proceeded he at any time against those, who either usually or trecherously above the rest tooke armes and rebelled, to any punishment more greivous then this, even to sell them as captives: with this condition, that they shold not serve in any neighbour Country, nor be manumised and made free within the space of 30<note place="bottom" n="2">Or 20, rather.</note> yeares.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>By which fame of vertue and moderation that went of him, he induced and drew the very Indians and Scythians, Nations knowen by report and heere say onely, to make suite of their owne accord by Embassadours, for amitie of him and the people of Rome. The Parthians also, when as he laied claime unto Armenia, yeelded soone unto him: and those militarie Ensignes which they had taken from M. Crassus and M. Antonius, they delivered unto him againe at his demaund: and moreover, offred hostages unto him. And finally when there were many Competitours together at one time claiming a title to the Kingdome, they would not allow of any, but one by him elected.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="22">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The temple of Janus Quirinus<note type="annotation" n="a">The Temple of Janus Quirinus, or Quirini, because it was first founded by Romulus, Numa Pompilius his successor ordained to be set open in time of warre, and shutte when there was peace. Whereupon Janus was termed under a two-folde name, Patucius and Clausius. Once it was shutt in the said Numa his reigne; and a second time, after the first Punick warre ended, when M. Atilius, and T. Manlius, or Mallius, were Consuls. At all times before and after it stood open, untill Augustus Cæsars daies; during whose Empire it was thrice shut. First, upon the defeature of Antonius and Cleopatra before Actium. Secondly, after his victorie in Spaine over the Cantabri. Last of all, when all nations (in manner) of the earth by occasion of his victories, grew to an universall peace. About which time our Saviour Jesus Christ, Immanuel, that True Peace-maker betweene God and us, was borne. Thus Orosius reporteth, and readeth, ter, not tertio. Howbeit Livie seemeth to acknowledge, but once, namely, upon the Actiack victorie.</note>, which from the foundation of the City before his daies had once and twice beene shut, he in a farre shorter space of time (having peace both by sea and land) shut a third time<note place="bottom" n="3">Tertio, or ter. i. thrice.</note>. Twice he rod on horsebacke ovant<note type="annotation" n="b">Ovation was a kinde of petie triumph: wherin the Captaines victors rode not in a Chariot, nor wore a Coronet of Laurell, but of the Myrtle. It tooke the name ab ovibus, i. Sheepe Sacrificed, or rather all the voyce, Ovoe, which the Soldiours in their acclamations resounded.</note> into the City: once presently upon the Philippian warre; and againe, after the Sicilian. He kept three Triumphes riding in his chariot: to wit, the Dalmatian, the Actiak, and the Alexandrian, and these continued all for three dayes together.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="23">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Of shamefull foiles and grievous overthrowes, he received but two in all: and those in no place else but in Germanie; namely when Lollius and Varus<note place="bottom" n="4">Quintilius Varus.</note> were defaited. That of Lollius, was a matter of dishonour more than losse and domage; but the other of Varus, drew with it in manner utter destruction; as wherein three Legions with their Generall, the Lieutenants and Auxiliaries<note type="annotation" n="a">The Romane Armie consisted of Legions, who were all Romanes, and of Auxilia, i. aids, and those were of Allies and confederate nations.</note>, all were slaine. Upon the newes of this Infortunity, he proclaimed a set watch both day and night through the City of Rome; for feare of some tumult and uprore: and the commissions of Presidents and Deputies over Provinces, he renewed and enlarged their time of government: to the end, that the Allies of the people of Rome might bee kept in alleageance by governours, such as were both skilfull and also acquainted with them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Hee vowed also the great (Romaine) Games and Playes to the honour of Jupiter Opt. Max. if the Commonwealth turned to better State<note place="bottom" n="1">Si Resp. in meliorem statum vertisset.</note>. This happened, during the time of the Cimbrian and Marsian warre<note place="bottom" n="2">Which also was called Bellum sociale, wherein the Associate nations in Italy rebelled: of which Rebellion the Authors were the Marsi.</note>. For, therewith (by report) hee was so troubled and astonied, that for certaine moneths together hee let the haire of beard and head grow still and wore it long, yea and other whiles would runne his head against the dores<note place="bottom" n="3">Upon an opinion of the Painims, that if they did injurie to their owne bodies they should sooner pacifie the Gods.</note>, crying out, 'Quintilius Varus, Deliver up thy Legions againe.' And the very day<note type="annotation" n="b">This day, was Ante diem quartum non Sextil, i. the second daye of August. Which was also that verie daye of the moneth, wherein the Romans in times past suffered the desasterous overthrow at Cannæ.</note> of this infortunate calamity he kept every yeere mournfull, with sorow and lamentation.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="24">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In warfare and feates of armes<note type="annotation" n="a">By which the people of Rome wonne their immortall fame, and conquered the whole world: as Cicero saith: Pro Muræna.</note>, he both altered and also instituted many points: yea and some he reduced to the auncient manner. Militarie discipline he exercised most severely. He permitted not so much as any of his Lieutenants, but with much adoe and discontentment, to visite otherwhiles their wives; and never but in the winter moneths<note type="annotation" n="b">December, Januarie, and Februarie.</note>. A Romaine Knight, for cutting off the thombs<note type="annotation" n="c">Thereby disabling them for being serviceable souldiers.</note> of two young men his sonnes, to avoid the militarie oath and warre service, he set in open port sale, himselfe (I say) and all his goods. Whom notwithstanding, because he saw the Publicanes<note type="annotation" n="d">These Publicanes, so called for that they fermed their Cities revenewes, as Customes, Tolles, Imposts, etc., were likewise Knightes or Gentlemen of Rome, and by being so earnest to buy out one of their owne sort, were thought to favour him, and minded presently to dismisse him at liberty: which was contrary to his intent.</note> about to buy, and bid very well for him, he appointed and delivered to his owne Freed man, that being confined and sent away unto his living and lands in the Country, he might permit him to live as Free.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>The tenth Legion, for being stubborne and unwilling to obey, he dismissed all and whole with ignominie: other legions likewise, requiring malapertly their discharge, he cassed without allowance of rewards due for their service. Whole bands or cohorts, if any of them gave ground and reculed, he tithed, that is to say, executed every tenth man of them: and the rest, he allowed barly in steed of wheat to feede upon. Those centurions who forsooke their Stations, he punished with death, even as well as the common soldiors of their bands: and for other kinds of Delinquencie he put them to shame sundry waies, as commanding them to stand all the day long before the Prætorium<note place="bottom" n="1">The Generals Pavilions.</note> sometimes in their single coates<note place="bottom" n="2">Or wastcoates, without their Saga.</note> and ungirt; other-whiles with ten foote perches<note place="bottom" n="3">Or meeting poles, in token of Regradation or putting downe to a lower place.</note> in their hands; or else carying turfes of earth.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="25">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>After the civile warres, he called none of his soldiours either in any publike speech, or by way of edict or proclamation, by the name of Fellow-soldiours, but plaine Souldiours<note type="annotation" n="a">For his Uncle and Predecessor Julius Cæsar, had taken up that familiar terme of Commilitones, by occasion of so many troubles that followed him, and therefore was driven to speake his Souldiers fayre.</note>. Nay hee would not suffer them otherwise to be termed so much as by his sonnes, or his wives sonnes: thinking it was a more affected manner of Appellation than stoode either with martial Law, or the quietnes of those times, or the majestie of himselfe and his house.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Libertines<note type="annotation" n="b">Libertines were those who having beene bond were made free or manumised: and these were not capable of Militia Romana, but in time of great extremitie and desperate cases.</note> he emploied in soulderie unlesse it were at Rome about skarfires by night, (notwithstanding there was feared some tumult and uprore by occasion of great dearth and scarcity) but twice onely: once in garizon for defence of those Colonies which bounded fast upon Illyricum; a second time for keeping the banks of the river of Rhene. And those, being as yet bond, imposed upon men and women of the wealthier sort for to set out, but without delay manumised, he kept with him to serve under one of the formost banners<note place="bottom" n="1">Sub primore vexillo or sub proprio vexillo, i. under his owne banner.</note> in the vantguard; neither intermingled with such as were Free borne, nor in the same manner armed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>As for militarie gifts hee gave unto his souldiours trappers collars and whatsoever stoode upon gold or silver<note place="bottom" n="2">Quicquid auro argentoque; constaret: or rather, quanquam auro argentoque; constarent, i. Albeit they were made of gold and silver.</note>, much sooner than Vallar or Mural coronets<note type="annotation" n="c">It seemeth by this, that these vallare and murall coronets were made of some other matter than Silver and Gold. Yet Aul. Gell., lib. 5, cap. 6, writeth that both these, as also the Navale, were of gold. Now, the Vallare or Castrensis coronet, (for they were both one) resembled vallum, i. the Rampier a palaisade about a Camp, made ex vallis, i. stakes or pales sharpened at the head, wherewith the banke or mure was the better fortified, and hee received it as an honorable reward, who first mounted the said palaisade, and entered the Camp of his enemies. The Murall, was fascioned like to the battlements of a wall, given likewise unto that souldier, who approached the enemies wall first, skaled, and climbed over it into the Citie. As for these Phaleræ, albeit they be commonly taken for the ornaments or trappings of horses, yet it appeareth that they be the ornaments of the men themselves: and as well they as Torques were, Tralatitia militum dona, i. ordinarie and common gifts bestowed upon good souldiers. See Juvenal, Satyr. ult.: Ut læti phaleris omnes, et torquibus omnes.</note> which were more honourable. These he bestowed most sparily; and when he did, it was without suit made therefore: and many times upon the common and base souldiers<note type="annotation" n="d">Such as he called before Manipulares and Gregarios: although in other authors, Caligati stand for all manner of souldiers.</note>. He gave unto M. Agrippa after a navale victory in Cilicia a blew streamer. Those Captaines onely who had triumphed, albeit they were both companions with him in his expeditions, and also partakers of his victories, he thought not meete to be rewarded with any gifts at all: because they also had power to bestow the same upon whom they would.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Moreover he deemed nothing lesse beseeming a perfit and accomplished Captaine, than hast-making and rashnesse. And therefore, these mots and sentences were rife in his mouth. Σποῦδε βραδέως<note type="annotation" n="e">In Latin Festina lentè: much to this sense in our English tongue: No more hast then good speed: for, The soft fire makes sweet malt. This proverbe the same Augustus expressed also in his coines, wherein hee stamped together with lightning or a thunderbolt, the God Terminus, representing by the one, Celeritie; and by the other, Stayednesse. Like as Titus Vespasianus the Emperour joyned an Anchor and a Dolphin together in his coine, to the same purpose.</note>, Ἀσφαλὴς γὰρ ἐς ἀμείνων, ἢ θρασύς στρατηλάτης<note type="annotation" n="f">A verse of Euripides, in the Tragedie Phœnissa, i. A warie Captaine is better than a venterous.</note>: As also, Sat celeriter fieri, quicquid fiat satis bene<note type="annotation" n="g">It was the Apophthegme of Cato, Soone enough is that done, which is well done.</note>. His saying was, That neither battaile nor warre was once to be under taken, unlesse there might be evidently seene more hope of gaine than feare of domage: for such as sought after the smallest commodities, not with as little daunger, he likened unto those, that angle or fish with a golden hooke: for the losse whereof, if it happened to be knapt or broken off, no draught of fish whatsoever, was able to make amends.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="26">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>He managed magistracies and honorable places of government before due time<note place="bottom" n="3">By the lawes Annuaria, or Annales.</note>; some of them also of a new kinde<note place="bottom" n="4">As the Triumvirate.</note>; and others in perpetuity<note place="bottom" n="5">As the Tribunes authoritie and Censureship.</note>. The Consulship hee usurped and entred upon in the twentieth yeere of his age<note type="annotation" n="a">By the law Annaria, that L. Julius, or Villius rather promulged, required it was, that a Consull should not be under the age of 43. Yet for their worthinesse and demerits, some attaine to that dignitie, under 30.</note>, presenting forcibly and in hostile manner his legions before the City, sending some of purpose to demaund it, even in the name of the Armie for him. What time verily, when the Senate made some doubt and stay of the matter, Cornelius a Centurion and the chiefe man of that message, casting of<note place="bottom" n="1">Or casting it behind him, rejecto sagulo.</note> his souldiours Jacket and shewing his swords haft, stucke not to say thus openly in the Senate house, 'This here shall doe the deede, if yee will not'<note type="annotation" n="b">Like unto this was the speech of that Centurion, who being sent by Julius Cæsar Dictator, for to have the time of his government and conduct of an Armie in the province proroged, standing before the doore of the Senate house, and taking knowledge that it would not be granted, shooke his sword hilt with his hand and said, Hic prorogabit, i. This then shall proroge it.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>His second Consulship hee bare nine yeares after: the third, but one yeare betweene: the rest ensuing hee continued one after an other unto the eleventh. Afterwardes having refused many Consulships when they were offered unto him, his twelfth Consulship a greater while after, even 17 yeares, himselfe made suite for: so did hee againe, two yeares after it, for his thirtenth: to the ende that being himselfe in place of the Soveraine and highest Majestrate, hee might bring honorably into the Common Hall, C. and L. his (adopted) sonnes<note place="bottom" n="2">The naturall sonnes of his daughter Julia and C. Agrippa.</note>; each of them to commence and performe their first pleadings at their due time in virile gownes<note place="bottom" n="3">The elder in his twelfth, the younger in his thirteenth Consulate.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The five middle Consulships betweene, to wit from the sixth to the eleventh he helde the whole yeeres thorough: the other, for the space of sixe, or nine, foure, or three moneths: but the second, very fewe howers: for uppon the very Calends of Januarie<note place="bottom" n="4">The first of Januarie or Newyeeres day.</note>, when hee had sitten a while upon his curule chaire of estate before the temple of Jupiter Capitolinus; hee resigned up the Office, and substituted another in his place. Neither entred hee upon all his Consulships at Rome: but the fourth in Asia; the fifth, in the Iland Samos; the eigth and ninth at Tarracon.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="27">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The Triumvirate for setling of the Common-wealth<note place="bottom" n="5">That was the colour and pretence of it.</note>, hee administred for the space of tenne yeeres: wherein verily, hee stoode against his colleagues proceedings for a good while, that there might be no proscription: but when it was once on foote, hee executed it more sharply than they both. For, whereas they were exorable and would bee oftentimes intreated by favour and prayer, to respect the persons of many, hee alone was very earnest, that none might bee spared: among the rest, hee proscribed C. Toranius also, his owne Tutour and guardian, yea and the companion in the Office of Ædileship with his father Octavius.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Junius Saturninus writeth moreover, that after the proscription was ended, when M. Lepidus had in the Senate-house excused all that was past and given good hope of clemencie for the time to come, because there had beene execution enough done alreadie: he on the contrarie side professed openly, That hee had determined no other end of the saide proscription, but that hee might have liberty still to proceede in all things as he would. Howbeit, in testimonie of repentance for this rigour and obstinacie of his, hee honoured afterward with the dignitie of Knighthood T. Junius Philopæmen<note place="bottom" n="1">Or Vinius, for so was his Patrone named.</note>, for that hee was reputed to have in times past hid his owne Patron, that was proscribed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>In the same Triumvirate, hee incurred many waies the ill will and heart-burning of the people: for he commaunded that Pinarius a Gentleman of Rome, (what time as he himselfe made a publike speech in an assembly whereunto hee had admitted a multitude of Paganes, that is to say, such as were no souldiours, and espied him there to take notes of something that he delivered before the souldiours, supposing him to be over busie and a spie,) should be stabbed to death even in his sight: yea, and hee terrified Tedius Afer, Consull elect, (because hee had maliciously in some spitefull termes depraved something that he had done) with so great menaces, that in a melancholy hee cast himselfe headlong and brake his owne necke.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Likewise, as Q. Gallius the Pretour held under his robe a paire of duple writing tables, when hee came of course to doe his duty and salute him, he suspecting, that he had a (short) sword hidden underneath, and not daring straightwaies to search him farther, for feare something else than a sworde should bee found about him, within a little while after caused him to be haled out of the Tribunall seate of Judgement, by the handes of certaine Centurions of Souldiours, and put to torture like a bondslave; yea and seeing he would confesse nothing, commanded him to be killed; having first with his owne hands plucked his eies out of his head. Howbeit Augustus writeth, that the said Gallius by pretending to parle secretly with him, laid waite for his life; whereupon hee committed him to prison, and afterwards dismissed and enlarged him onely to dwell in Rome: and that in the end hee perished either by shipwracke, or else by the hands of theeves who forlayed him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>Hee received and held the Tribunate in perpetuity. Therein, once or twice, he chose and assumed unto him a colleague, for severall Lustra<note place="bottom" n="1">1. The space of 5 yeeres.</note>. Hee tooke upon him likewise the government of manners and Lawes as a perpetuall Censour: in full right whereof, although hee had not the honourable title of Censureship, yet hee helde a survey and nombring of the people thrice: the first and third with a companion in office; the middle by himselfe alone.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="28">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Twice hee was in minde, to have resigned up his absolute government: first, immediatly uppon the suppressing of Anthonie, mindfull of that which oftentimes hee had objected against him<note place="bottom" n="2">The saide Antonie.</note>, namely, as if it had beene long of him<note place="bottom" n="3">i. Augustus.</note>, that it was not resigned, and the Common-wealth brought to a free state againe: and secondly, by reason that hee was weary of a long and lingering sicklinesse; what time he sent also for all the Magistrates and the Senate<note place="bottom" n="4">Ac Senatum: or, e senatu, i. out of the Senate.</note>, home to his house; and delivered up an Account-booke or Register of the whole Empire<note place="bottom" n="5">Or of his acts and proceedings in the government.</note>. But considering better with himselfe, that were he once a private person, he could not live without daunger; and withall, that it would greatly hazard the Common-wealth, to be put into the hands and dispose of many, he continued in the holding thereof still. And whether the event ensuing, or his will heerein were better, it is hard to say.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Which will of his, as hee pretended oftentimes when he sate in place, so hee testified also by a certaine edict in these wordes: 'O that I might establish the Common wealth safe and sound in her owne proper seate<note place="bottom" n="1">Base or Piedstall.</note>, and thereof reape that fruite which I desire: even that I may be reported the Author of an excellent estate, and carie with mee when I die this hope, that the groundworke and the foundations of the Common-wealth which I shall lay, may continue and abide stedfast in their place.' And verily what hee wished, himselfe effected and brought to passe<note place="bottom" n="2">As if he had beene a God himselfe, according to the saying, Sapiens ipse fingit fortunam sibi.</note>, having endevoured and done his best every way, that no man might repent of this newe estate.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>For the Citie beeing not adourned according to the majestie of such an Empire and Subject to the casualties of Deluges and fires, hee beautified and set out so, as justly he made his boast, that where he found it built of bricke, hee left it all of marble. And for the safety thereof, hee performed as much for future posterity as could be fore-seene and provided for by mans wit and reason.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="29">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Publike works he built very many whereof the chiefe and principal was his Forum<note type="annotation" n="a">Three such Halles there were in Rome, wherein Judiciall courts were held, and causes pleaded. 1. Romanum, which was so much frequented with Lawyers and their Clients, that Cato Censorius delivered his opinion, that it should bee paved with Calthrops, to keepe out that rabble which hanted it. 2. Cæsareum, that Cesar Dictator built, and adjoyned thereto the Temple of Venus Genitrix. 3. Augusti, whereto was annexed by him one Temple of Mars Revenger. For, another he erected in the Capitoll, after he had regained from the Parthians, the Roman Standerds and militarie ensignes, which they wonne from Crassus.</note> or stately Hall of Justice, together with the temple of Mars the Revenger: the temple of Apollo in Palatium; the Temple likewise of Jupiter the Thunderer, in the Capitol. The reason why he built the said Forum, was the multitude of men and their suites: which because ij. would not suffice, seemed to have need of a third also. And therfore with great speed erected it was for that publike use, even before the temple of Mars was finished. And expresly provided it was by law, that in it publike causes should be determined apart, and choosing of Judges (or Juries) by it selfe.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>The temple of Mars hee had vowed unto him, in the Philippian warre which hee tooke in hand for the revenge of his fathers death. He ordained therefore by an Act, that heere the Senate should be consulted with, as touching warres and triumphs: that from hence those Pretours or Governours who were to goe into their provinces should be honorably attended and brought onward on their way: and that hither they should bring the ensignes and ornaments of triumph, who returned with victorie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The temple of Apollo he reared in that part of the Palatine house, which being smitten with lightning was by that God required, as the Soothsayers out of their learning had pronounced: hereto was adjoyned a gallerie, with a librarie of Latine and Greeke bookes. In which temple, he was wont in his old age both to sit oftentimes in counsaile with the Senate, and also to over-see and review the Decuries of the Judges. He consecrated the temple unto Jupiter the Thunderer, upon occasion that he escaped a daunger, what time as in his Cantabrian expedition, as he travailed by night, a flash of lightning glaunced upon his licter, and strucke his servant stone dead, that went with a light before.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Some works also he made under other folkes names, to wit his nephew, his wife and sister; as the Gallerie and stately Pallace of Lucius and Caius<note place="bottom" n="1">His daughters children by Agrippa.</note>: likewise the Gallerie or Porches of Livia and Octavia: the Theatre also of Marcellus. Moreover divers other principall persons hee oftentimes exhorted to adorne and beautifie the City, every man according to his ability either by erecting new monuments, or else by repairing and furnishing the old.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>By which meanes many an Ædifice was by many a man built: as namely the temple of Hercules and the Muses by Marcus Philippus: the temple of Diana by L. Cornificius: the Court of Liberty<note place="bottom" n="2">Atrium libertatis. Atrium, quasi aithrion. A place where learned men were wont to meete and conferre, as our Merchants doe in the Royall Exchange, built not unlike unto it with arched walks on every side standing upon pillers: and as this cloisture was called Peristylium, so, the open yard within, Atrium, or Subdival.</note> by Asinius Pollio: a temple of Saturne by Munatius Plancus: a Theatre by Cornelius Balbus; and an Amphitheatre<note type="annotation" n="b">An Amphitheater, and a Theater, differs as the full Moone from the halfe, or a compleat roundle from a semicircle.</note> by Statillus Taurus: but many and those very goodly monuments by M. Agrippa.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="30">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The whole space of the City he devided into wards<note type="annotation" n="a">Pliny writeth, that Rome was devided into foureteene Regions, or wards, and into more than a thousand streets.</note> and streetes. He ordained, that as Magistrates or Aldermen yeerely by lot should keepe and governe the former: so their should be Maisters or Constables elected out of the Commons of every streete, to looke unto the other. Against skarefires he devised night-watches and watchmen. To keepe downe Inundations and Deluges, he enlarged and cleansed the channell of the River Tiberis, which in times past was full of rammell and the ruines of houses, and so by that meanes narrow and choaked. And that the Avenues on every side to the City might be more passable, he tooke in hand himselfe to repaire the high way or Cawsie Flaminia, so farre as to Ariminnum and the rest he committed to sundry men who had triumphed, for to pave; and the charges thereof to be defraied out of the money raised of spoiles and sackage.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>The sacred Churches and Chappels decayed and ruinate by continuance of time, or consumed by fire he reedified: and those together with the rest hee adorned with most rich oblations; as who brought into the Cell, or Tabernacle of Jupiter Capitolinus at one Donation, 16000 pound weight of gold, besides pretious stones valued at 50 millions of Sesterces.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="31">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>But after that hee entred now at length upon the High priesthood when Lepidus was once dead, which he never could finde in his heart to take from him whiles he lived: what bookes soever of prophesies and destinies went commonly abroad in Greeke and Latine, either without authors, or such as were not authenticall and of credite, he caused to be called in from all places, to the number of 2000 and above: and when he had burnt them, he reteined those only of Sibyls prophesies. And even of those also he made some special choice: and bestowed them close in two litle Desks or coffers under the base and piedstoole of Apollo Palatinus.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>The yeeres revolution reduced as it was into order by Julius of sacred memory, but afterwards through negligence troubled and confused, he brought againe to the former calculation. In the dispose whereof, he called the moneth Sextilis (rather than September wherin he was borne,) by his owne name, because in it there befell unto him both his first Consulship and also notable victories.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Of all the Religious and priests, but especially of the vestall virgins he augmented the number, the dignity and the commodities also. And whereas in the rowme of any vestall Nun deceased, there must another of necessity be chosen and taken, he perceiving many to make suite that they might not put their daughters to the lottery; protested and bound it with an oath, that if any one of his owne Nieces or daughters daughters were of competent age he would present her to the place.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Divers auncient ceremonies also which by little and little were disused and abolished, he restored againe, as namely the Augurie of Salus<note type="annotation" n="a">Augurs were certaine Priests employed about the observation of Birds, and from them out of their learning gave directions. In number at first they were but three belonging unto the three ancient tribes of Rome. In processe of time there was a Colledge or convent of them to the number of 24, namely, in the daies of Sulla Dictator: so that I doubt not but among these were some appointed for this ministerie eyther about the Goddesse Salus, i. Health or safety, unto whom there was likewise a Temple built, or else in the name and behalfe of the people, Captare Augurium salutis, which as Dio maketh report, was in this manner: That they should call unto God for safetie, if he would permit: as if it were not lawfull to crave it at the Gods hands, unlesse they first granted it. And one day every yeare was chosen for this buisinesse, in which no Armie did set forth to warre: no man warre against them, nor toke weapon in hand to fight: a thing that could not be, during the late troubles and civill warres. No merveile therefore, if this function being forelet, was now taken up againe by Augustus, when by occasion of peace, he did shut the Temple of Janus. And as this function was called Augurium, so I see no reason but the very Augurship or Sacerdotall dignity it selfe in this place might be named Augurium, in the same forme, that presently after, the Flamenship or Priesthood belonging to Jupiter, is named Flaminium: and this I take to be the meaning of our Author.</note>, the Flaminship of Jupiter, the sacred Lupercal, the Sæcular playes<note type="annotation" n="b">Which were solemnized once in an hundred, or as some say, an hundred and ten yeares.</note> and the Compitalitii. At the Lupercall Solemnities, he commanded that no beardless boyes should runne. Likewise, at the Secular playes, he forbad young folke of both sexes, to frequent any shew exhibited by night; unlesse it were in the company of some auncient person of their kindred. The Tutelare Images of crosse-wayes called Lares Compitales he was the first that ordained to adorne twice in the yeere with flowers of the spring and sommer seasons.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>The principal honour next unto the immortall gods, he performed to the memoriall of those worthy Captaines, who had raised the Romaine empire from a small thing to so high and glorious a state. And therefore both the works and monuments of every of them he repaired and made againe, reserving their titles and inscriptions still; and all their Statues also in triumphant forme and shape he dedicated in both the Porches or galleries of his Hall of Justice. And in a publick edict he professed thus much, that he devised it to this end, That both himselfe whiles he lived, and the Princes or Emperours his successors for the ages to come, might be called upon and urged by their subjects and Citizens to conforme themselves as it were to their patron and example. The Statue likewise of Pompeius, translated out of the Court wherein C. Cæsar was murdered, he placed over against the princely Pallace of his Theater under an Arch of marble in manner of a Through-fare<note place="bottom" n="1">Supposuit: some reade, superposuit, i. upon such an arched Janus or Through-fare.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="32">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Many most daungerous enormities and offensive abuses, which either had continued by custome and licentious liberty during the civill warres, or else crept in and began in the time of peace to the utter ruine of the Commonwealth, he reformed. For a number of bold roisters and professed robbers jetted openly with short swords and skaines by their sides, under colour of their owne defence: passengers and waifaring men, as they travailed through the Country, were caught up (by them) as well Free borne as slaves without respect; and kept hard to worke in the Prisons of landed men<note place="bottom" n="2">In manner of Bridewels or houses of correction.</note>: many factious crewes also, under the title of a New Colledge had their meetings and joyned in fellowship to the perpetrating of mischiefe whatsoever. Whereupon, he disposed strong guards, and set watches in convenient places: he repressed those Robbers and Hacksters, he visited and surveyed the foresaid prisons: and all Colledges or Guilds save onely those of auncient foundation and by law erected, he dissolved and put downe.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>The bills of old debts due to the Chamber of the City, he burnt, as being the chiefe matter and occasion of malitious accusations. The publike places and houses in the City, whereof the tenure and hold was doubtfull, he adjudged unto those who were in present possession. The debts and actions commenced against such as had been troubled and sued a long time in the Law, by whose mournfull habite and distressed estate their adversaries sought for nothing but pleasure and the fulfilling of their wils, he anulled and denounced this condition withall, that if any one would needes bring them into new trouble againe, he should be liable to the like daunger of punishment or penalty as the molested party was. And to the end that no lewd Act might escape with impunity; nor businesse<note place="bottom" n="1">Or cause.</note> in Court be shuffled over by delaies, he added unto the Terme<note place="bottom" n="2">Law daies, or pleading time.</note> time 30 daies<note type="annotation" n="a">By which addition, there were in the yeare 230 Law-daies or pleadeable.</note> over and above: which daies the Honorarie Games and playes tooke up (before).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>To three Decuries of Judges he added a fourth out of a lower and meaner degree, which went under the name of Ducenarii<note place="bottom" n="4">For that they were valewed at 200 Sestertia: where as the other were worth 400.</note>, and were to judge of smaller summes. As for those Judges hee enrolled and elected them into the Decuries after they were once 30 yeeres<note place="bottom" n="5">Or 20 rather, for the ordinarie age was 25 yeares, at which they were eligible.</note> of age: that is to say, five yeeres sooner then they were wont. But seeing that most of them refused and were loth to execute this burdensome office of judging, he hardly granted that each Decurie should have their yeeres vacation<note place="bottom" n="6">Quarto quoque anno: everie 4 yeare.</note> by turnes; and that the law matters which were wont to be pleaded and tried, in the moneths of November and December<note place="bottom" n="7">Uppon certaine dayes of those moneths, during which, there were Sports and Revels and the licentious feast Saturnalia.</note> should be let passe and omitted quite.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="33">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Himselfe sat daily in Judgement, yea and other whiles untill it was darke night, lying if he had not his health, in a licter which was of purpose set before the tribunall seate, or else in his owne house: and he ministred justice not onely with exceeding severity, but also with as great lenity. For when upon a time there was one accused for a manifest parricidy<note type="annotation" n="a">More maiorum ordained it was, that a Paricide, should first be beaten with rods, and then, sowed within a lether male or budge togither with a dog, a cocke, a viper, and an ape, and so throwen into the sea or some running water.</note>, because he should not be sowed up in a leather male or budget (a punishment that none suffred but such as had confessed the Fact) he examined (by report) upon interrogatives in this maner, Certes thou never murderedst thy father, diddest thou?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Againe, when as a matter was handled before him as touching a forged will, and all the witnesses that set their hands and seales thereto, were attaint by the Law Cornelia<note type="annotation" n="b">Whereof Cornelius Sylla was the Author intituled: de falsis, or Testamentaria.</note>, he delivered unto the Commissioners who had the hearing and deciding together, of the cause, not onely the two (ordinarie) tables of condemnation and acquitall, but a third also; whereby they might have their pardon, who were certainly knowne to have beene seduced and brought to be witnesses as is before said, either by fraudulent practise or error and oversight.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>As for the appeales in Court, he yeerely assigned those which were for the City-Suiters unto Pretours of the City; but if they were for provinciall persons unto certaine men of the Consuls degree, such as he had ordained, in every province one, for to be in commission and to determine provinciall affaires.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="34">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The lawes made before time he revised and corrected: some also hee ordained and established a-new: as namely Sumptuaria<note type="annotation" n="a">Many lawes went under the title Sumptuaria, to represse the immoderate expense in apparell, and belly-cheere especially: as namely, Fannia, Didia Oppia, Cornelia, Julia, as well Cæsaris as Augusti. But in the time of Tiberius Cæsar, notwithstanding he did what he could to keepe them in force, yet they were all abrogated.</note>, as touching expenses at the bord: of Adulteries<note type="annotation" n="b">Lex Julia, Cæsaris et Augusti, de Adulteriis et Pudicitia. For albeit the law Scatinia, provided against the later, to wit Pæderestie, yet the penaltie thereof by vertue of the said law was but Pecuniaria, i. a mony matter. Whereas by Julia it was Capitalis, i, worthie of death. And, that Augustus established and inforced this law against Incontinencie, it may appeare by this, that Sextus Aurelius reprooved him: because being himselfe given to lasciviousnesse, yet he was a most severe and sharpe chasticer of that vice as also by that answere of a young man, whom he for committing adultery with his daughter Julia smote with his owne hands. Who thereupon cried out, Νόμον ἔθηκας, ὦ Καίσαρ, i. Thou hast made a lawe O Cæsar. Now as touching the foresaid law Scatinia, it was so called (as Valerius Maximus writeth) by occasion of one Scatinius a Tribune of the commons, who against kinde had abused a sonne of Marcellus, and was therefore condemned accordingly.</note> and unnaturall filthinesse committed with the male kind<note place="bottom" n="1">Or Scantilia.</note><note place="bottom" n="2">Or Scantinius.</note>: of indirect suite<note type="annotation" n="c">De ambitu. Of which there were divers, namely, Acilia Calpurnia, Aufidia, Bæbia Æmilia, Cornelia Fulvia, Maria, Pompeia, Pætilia, Tullia and Julia, Cæsaris and Augusti.</note> for offices: of the mutall mariages of Senatours and Gentlemen with Commoners<note type="annotation" n="d">Lex papia poppæa, de maritandis ordinibus, wherof, there were many branches and chapters, not only respecting this conjunction of the Gentrie and commons: but also concerning penalties to be laid upon those that neglected mariage, and rewards due to such as lived in wedlocke and begat children, etc.</note>. This act last named, when he had amended and reformed somewhat more precisely and with greater severitie then the rest, he could not carie cleerely and go through with, for the tumult of those that refused so to do, but that part of the penalties at length was quite taken away or els mitigated; an immunity also and toleration (of widow-head)<note place="bottom" n="3">After the decease of a former wife or husband.</note> graunted for 3 yeeres, and the rewards besides augmented.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>And notwithstanding all that, when the order of Gentlemen stood out stifly and stoutly, calling in open sight, and publikely for the repealing of the said Statute, he sent for Germanicus his children, and taking some of them himselfe, and bestowing the others in their fathers armes, shewed and presented them unto their view: signifying as well by the gesture of his hand, as by countenance, That they should not be loath nor think much, to imitate the example of that young Gentleman. Moreover perceiving that the force and vigor of that Law was dallied with, and avoided by the immaturity<note place="bottom" n="4">Unripe age, i. under 12 yeres.</note> of young espoused wives, as also by often changing of mariages: he brought into a narrower compasse the time of wedding and having such spouses, and also limited divorcements<note place="bottom" n="5">By meanes of divorses.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="35">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The number of Senatours growing still to a shameful and confused company (for there were not of them so few as a 1000, and some most unworthy: as who after Cæsars death were taken into the house for favour or bribes; whom the common people termed abortive<note place="bottom" n="1">Abortivos: Some reade orcivos or orcinos, velut Orco seu terra natos, i. obscure and base.</note>, as it were untimely births or born before their time): he reduced to the auncient stent<note place="bottom" n="2">300.</note> and honorable reputation: and that in two elections: the former, at their owne choise, wil, and pleasure, whereby one man chooseth his fellow; the second, according to his owne and Agrippaes mind: at which time he is thought to have sitten as president, armed with a shirt of maile or privie coate under his gowne, and a short sword or skeine by his side; having a gard also standing about his chaire of estate, to wit, ten of the stoutest and tallest men that were of Senatours degree, and all his friends:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Cordus Cremutius writeth, that there was not so much as admitted then into the Senate-house any Senatour but singly one alone by himselfe, and not before his clothes were well serched and felt, for having any weapon under them. Some of them he brought to this modestie, as to excuse themselves: and yet for such as thus made excuse he reserved still the liberty to weare a Senatours habite<note type="annotation" n="a">The badges that distinguished Senatours from others, were their Robes purfled or embrodered with broad studs of purple like naile heads, called thereupon Laticlavi, and shoes with peakes resembling the horned tips or pointed ends of the moone, named therefore Calcei lunati, in token of their auncient Nobilitie, as some interpret it.</note>: the honor also to sit and behold the Games and plaies in the Orchestra<note place="bottom" n="4">Among other Senators.</note>; together with priviledge to keepe their place at the solemne publique feasts<note type="annotation" n="b">These solemne feastes at which Senators were allowed to be present, were Epulum Jovis otherwise called Cæna Dialis within the capitoll: likewise Cæna Triumphalis Pontificialis, and Auguralis, i. the sumptuous suppers to the honour of Jupiter, at triumphes, given by the Pontifies and Augurs.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Now, to the end that being thus chosen and allowed (as is above said) they might with more religious reverence and lesse trouble execute the functions belonging to Senatours<note place="bottom" n="3">For taking upon them that dignity.</note>: he ordained, That before any one sat him downe in his chaire, he should make devout supplication and sacrifice with frankincense and wine, at the altar of that God<note place="bottom" n="5">And that they should not need to come and salute him, but save that labour.</note>, in whose temple they assembled for the time: and that ordinarily the Senate should not be holden oftner then twice in a moneth, to wit upon the Calends<note type="annotation" n="c">The first day of everie moneth.</note>, and Ides<note type="annotation" n="d">The 15 of March, May, July, and October, the 13 of the rest.</note> of the same: and that in the moneths September and October<note place="bottom" n="1">Haply, by reason of vintage that was not to be neglected.</note>, none els should be bound to give attendance, save those that were drawne by lot: by whose number, Decrees might passe. Furthermore, he devised to institute for himselfe, and that by casting lots, a privie Counsell for 6 moneths: with whom he might treat before hand of businesses and affaires to be moved unto a frequent Senate-house fully assembled.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>As touching matter of greater importance put to question, he demanded the opinion of the Senatours, not after the usuall manner and in order, but as it pleased himselfe: to the end that everie man should bend his mind so intentively thereto, as if he were to deliver his owne advise, rather then give assent unto another.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="36">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Other things there were besides, wherof he was the author and beginner: and among the rest: That the Acts<note place="bottom" n="2">Acta Senatus and not Senatus consulta: he meaneth Diurna acta, i. the proceedings that passed there every day of sitting.</note> of the Senate should not be published nor appeare upon record. Item that no magistrates after that they had left or given up their honorable places, should eftsoones presently, be sent as governours into any provinces. That for proconsuls or presidents, their should be a certaine rate in monie set downe and allowed, for their sumpter-mules, for their tentes and hales: which were wont really beforetime to be set out and allowed for them, at the publike cost of the Citie. Item, that the charge of the Citties Treasure should be translated from the Questours or treasurers of the Citie, unto those that had been pretours, or to the pretours for the time being: lastly, that certaine Decemvirs<note place="bottom" n="3">Ten men either chosen out of the Centumvirs by lot, or created of purpose.</note> should summon and assemble the Centumvirall court<note type="annotation" n="a">A judiciall court there was at Rome called Centumviralis Hasta, for that it consisted of certaine Commissioners or judges named Centumviri, i. The Hundred men. Before whom were debated civill matters and causes betweene citizen and citizen, of no great importance. Chosen these were out of everie Tribe three and those were in all 35, which number doth arise to 105, but in round reckoning they went for an hundred.</note>, and call the Centumvirs to the speare, which they onely were wont to do, that had borne the office of Questourshippe.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="37">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>And to the end that more men might beare their part in administration of the common weale, he devised new offices: to wit, The overseeing of the publike workes, the surveying of the waies, streetes, and causies, of the water courses or conduits, of the channel of Tybris, and distributing corne among the people. Also the provostship of the Cittie: one Triumvirate<note place="bottom" n="1">An office which 3 men joinctly bare.</note>, for chusing Senatours; and another for reviewing and visiting the troupes or cornets of horsemen, so often as need required. The Censours, whose creation was forlet and discontinued, after a ong time betweene, he created againe. The number of pretours he augmented. He required also and demanded, that so often as the Consulship was conferred upon him, he might have for one, ij. colleagues or companions in office: but he cold not obtaine it; whilest all men with one voice cried out, That his majestie was abridged enough alreadie, in that he bare not that honourable office by himselfe, but with another.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="38">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Neither was he more sparing in honorably rewarding martial prowes, as who gave order, that to 30 Captaines and above, there should be granted by publike decree full tryumphs: and to a good many more tryumphall ornaments<note type="annotation" n="a">What these ornaments and badges were, T. Livius reporteth in the 30 booke of his Romane Historie: to wit, a crowne of Gold, and a faire golden Boll: a curule, Ivorie chaire, with a staffe likewise or scepter of Ivory: a long Robe embrodered of sundrie colours, and a rich coate of Needle worke representing the Date tree.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Senatours Children, to the end they might be sooner acquainted with the affaires of State, he permitted to put on even at the first their viril gown: to weare likewise the Senatours robe poudred with broad headed purple studs; and to have their places in the Senate house. Also at their first entrance into warfare, he allowed them to be, not onely militarre Tribunes in the legions<note place="bottom" n="2">Colonels of 1000 fotemen.</note>, but also captaines over the horsemen in the wings<note place="bottom" n="3">Or men of Armes.</note>. And, that none of them might be unexpert of the Camp-affaires: he ordained for the most part over everie wing or Cornet, ij. such Senatours (sonnes) to be provosts.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The troupes and companies of Romaine Gentlemen, he often reviewed; and after a long space of time betweene, brought into use againe the manner of their muster<note place="bottom" n="1">Transvectionis.</note><note type="annotation" n="b">This solemne shew or Riding of Roman Gentlemen, was upon the Ides: the 15 day of Quintilis, alias July yearely. Instituted first by Fabius Rutilianus in the honour of Castor and Pollux, who appeared unto the Romans, at the battell neere the Lake Regillus, what time they atchived a noble victorie. They rode from the Temple of Honour, as some write, or as others, of Mars without the walles, through the Forum, and by the Temple of Castor, up into the Capitall, dight with chaplets of Olive braunches, as Plinie writeth, lib. 15 Natur. Hist.</note> or riding solemnly on horse backe, to shew themselves. Neither wold he suffer any on of them during this solemnity, to be unhorsed and arrested by his adversary, that pretended any matter in law against him: a thing that was usually don. And to as many as were known to be aged or to have any defect or imperfection of body, he gave leave to send their horses before, and to come on foote to aunswere when so ever they were cited. And soone after he did those this favour, to deliver uppe their (publike) horses, who being above 45 yeares of age, were unwilling to keepe them still.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="39">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Having obtained also by the Senate<note place="bottom" n="2">A senatu or senatoribus, i. out of the Senatours degree.</note> x. Coadjutours, hee compelled everie Gentleman (that served with the Citties horse) to render an accoumpt of his life. And of such as were blameable and could not approve their living, some he punished, others he noted with shame and ignominie: the most part of them with admonition, but after sundrie sorts. The easiest and lightest kind of admonition, was the tendering unto them in open place and all mens sight, a paire of writing tables<note place="bottom" n="3">Wherein were written al their faults.</note>, to read unto themselves presently, in the place where they stood. Some also he put to rebuke and disgrace for taking up of mony upon smal interest for the use, and putting it forth againe for greater gaine and usurie.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="40">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>At the Election of Tribunes<note place="bottom" n="4">Demarchia. Dion.</note><note type="annotation" n="a">By this it appeareth, that ordinarily he might not bee a Tribune of the commons, who was not a Senator: for albeit this be a Plebian Magistrate, yet might a commoner be a Senator.</note> (of the Commons) if their wanted Senatours to stand for that office, he created them out of the degree of Romaine Gentlemen: so as, after they had born that magistracy, they might remaine ranged in whether degree<note place="bottom" n="5">Of gentlemen or of the Senatours.</note> they would themselves. Now, when as many of the Romain Gentlemen, having wasted and decaied their patrimonie, and estate in the civil wars, durst not out of the 14 formost seats behold the publike plaies and games, for feare of the penalty by the law (Roscia and Julia) caled Theatralis, he pronounced openly and made it knowne, that such gentlemen were not liable thereto if either themselves or their fathers<note place="bottom" n="1">Parentibus: comprehending all auncestours.</note> before them, were ever at any time valued to the worth of Romaine Gentlemen<note place="bottom" n="2">400 Sestertia or 400000 Sestertii, i. 3215 l. sterling.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>He made a review of the people of Rome, street by street: and to prevent that the common people shold not be often called away from their affaires by occasion of the dole and distribution of corne<note type="annotation" n="b">Whereupon, Suidas thinketh, Annonas to take their name, quasi ἀνὰ τὰς Νώνας διδόμενας, i. because corne was wont to be dealt among the people, upon the Nones of everie moneth, namely, the seventh day of March, May, July and October, and the fifth of the rest: whereas indeed Annona is derived ab anno, i. the yeare, quasi annalis alimonia, i. the yeares provision of food.</note>, he purposed to give out thrice a yeare, tiquets or talies for to serve 4 moneths<note place="bottom" n="3">Nonis cuiusque Mensis.</note>: but when the people were desirous of the old custom he granted them again to receive the same upon the Nones of every moneth. The ancient right and libertie also, in Elections and Parliamentes he brought in again: and having restrained the indirect suing for dignities by manyfold penalties, upon the day of such elections he distributed out of his own purse among the Fabians and Scaptians, who were of the same Tribes<note type="annotation" n="c">It seemeth that Augustus held of two Tribes: to wit, Scaptia, unto which the Octavii belonged, and wherein he was borne: and Fabia, by his adoption into the familie of the Julii.</note>, wherein himselfe was incorporate, a thousand Sesterces a peece, because they should not look for ought at any of their hands who stood for offices.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Moreover supposing it a matter of great consequence to keepe the people incorrupt and cleare from all base mixture of forain and servile blood, he both granted the freedom of the City of Rome most sparily, and also set a certain gage and limitation of manumising and enfranchising slaves. When Tiberius made request unto him by letters, in the behalfe of a Grecian, his client to be free of Rome: he wrot backe unto him, That he would not grant it unlesse he came personally himselfe, and could perswade him, what just causes he had of his suite: and what time as Livia intreated the like for a certaine French-man, tributarie to the Romains: he flatly denied the freedome of the Citty, but offred in lieu thereof immunitie and remission of Tribute; avowing, that he would more easily abide that somewhat went from the publike treasure and chamber of the Cittie, than have the honour of the Romaine Citie to be made vulgar, and common.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Nor content, that he had by diverse straight edicts and provisoes kept many slaves from all manner of freedome, but more a great deal from ful freedom in the best condition; as having precisely and with much curiositie put in caveats both for the number and also for the condition and respect otherwise of those that were to be made free: he added thus much moreover: That no slave, who had ever beene bound and imprisoned, or examined by torture should obtaine the freedome of the Cittie, in any kind of enfranchisement what soever.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>The olde manner of going and wearing apparell also, he endevoured to bring into use againe. And having seene upon a time assembled to heare a publike speech, a number of Citizens cladde all in blacke clokes<note place="bottom" n="1">By blacke he meaneth clokes or gownes of a selfe russet colour, for their gownes should be white and faire, not sullied.</note> or sullied gownes, taking great indignation thereat crying out with all: Beholde, quoth he,
          <quote>Romanos rerum dominos gentemque togatam.</quote>
          The Romaines, Lords of all the world, and longe rob'd Nation<note place="bottom" n="2">By the trope Ironia, meaning those that were in clokes or foule gownes.</note>.
          He gave the Ædiles in charge not to suffer any person from thence forward, to abide or stay, either in the Common place or the Cirque, but in a gowned<note type="annotation" n="d">For, howsoever the Romane habit was the Gowne, yet permitted were they, upon necessitie, namely to save the said gowne in foule wether, or to defend themselves from cold, to cast over it a cloake in any frequented place of the Citie, as were the Forum, i. the common pleading courtyard or Market place, and the Circus, i. the Shew place.</note>, laying a side all clokes or mantills thereupon.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="41">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His liberality unto all degrees of Citizens he shewed often times as occasions and opportunities were offred: for both by bringing into the Cittie in the Allexandrine Tryumph the treasures of the Ægyptian Kings he caused so great plentie of monie, that usurie fell, but the price of Landes and Lordships arose to a verie high reckoning: and also afterwards, so often as out of the goods of condemned persons there was any surplusage of monie remaining above their fines; he granted for a certaine time the free lone and use thereof to as many as were able to put in securitie for the principall, by an obligation in duple the summe. The substance and wealth of Senatours hee augmented, and whereas the valew thereof before amounted to the summes of 800000 Sesterces<note place="bottom" n="4">Duple the worth of Gentlemen.</note>: he taxed or sessed them at 1200000: and looke who had not so much, he supplied and made it up to the full.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>He gave Congiaries<note place="bottom" n="1">Largesses.</note> often times to the people, but lightly they were of diverse summes, one while 400, another while 300, and some times 200 and fiftie Sesterces: and he left not so much as boyes under age, whereas they had not wont to receive such congiaries, unlesse they were above eleven yeares olde. Hee measured out also to the people by the Poll, Corne in times of scarcitie oftentimes at a verie lowe price, and otherwhiles freely, without payinge therefore and as for the Tickets, of monie, he dupled the summe in them conteined.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="42">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>And that you may know, hee was a prince more respective of thrift and holesomenes, than desirous of popularitie, praise, and honour: when the people complained of the want and dearth of wine, he checked and snibbed them with this most severe speech, That his sonne in lawe Agrippa had taken order good enough that men should not be athirst, by conveighing so many waters into the Cittie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Unto the same people demanding the congiarie; which indeede was by him promised, he aunswered; That his credite was good, and he able to performe his word: but when they earnestly called for one which hee had never promised, hee hit them in the teeth by an edict or proclamation with their dishonestie, and impudencie: assuring them, that give it he would not although he had intended it. And with no lesse gravitie and resolution, when uppon his proposing and publishing of a congiarie, he found that many in the meane time were manumised and inserted into the number of Citizens, he rejected such, and said, they should not receive any, unto whom he had made no promise: and to all the rest hee gave lesse than he promised: that the summe which he had appointed, might hould out and be sufficient.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>When upon a time, there was great barrainnesse and scarcitie of corne, being put to an hard exigent and to seeke a difficult remedie, in so much as he was driven to expell out of the Cittie, all the sort of young slaves pampered and trimmed up for sale, as also whole scholes and companies of Novice-fencers and sword players: all strangers and forainers, except Physitians and scholemaisters: yea and some of the ordinarie houshold servants: so soone as the market began to mend, and victuals grew plentifull, he writeth, That it tooke him in the head to abolish those publike doles of Corne for ever: because upon the trust and confidence of them, tillage was cleane laid downe. Howbeit he continued not in that mind long, as being assured, that the same doles might be set up againe one time or other by the ambitious humour (of Princes his successors). And therefore after this he ordred the matter so indifferently, as that he had no lesse regard of the Citties fermours of tillage, and other undertakers and purveiours of the publike corne, than of the people and commons of the Cittie.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="43">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In number, varietie, and magnificence of solemne shewes exhibited unto the people he went beyond all men. Hee reporteth of himselfe that he set foorth plaies and games in his owne name foure and twentie times<note place="bottom" n="1">Quater et vicies.</note>: and for other magistrates who either were absent or not sufficient to beare the charges, three and twentie times. Divers times, he exhibited plaies by everie streete, and those uppon many stages, and acted by plaiers skilfull in all languages not in the Common forum onely, nor in the ordinarie Amphitheater, but also in the cirque. In the enclosure called Septa, he never represented any sportes but the baiting and coursing of wild beasts and the shewes of champions-sight; having built woodden scaffolds and seates for the nonce in Mars field. In like manner, he made the shew of a Navall battaile about the River Tiberis, having digged of purpose a spacious hollow pit within the ground, even there whereas now is to be seene the grove of the Cæsars. On which dayes he bestowed warders in diverse places of the citie, for feare it might be endangered by sturdie theeves and robbers, taking their vantage, that so few remained at home in their houses.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>In the Cirque he brought forth to doe their devoir, Charioters, Runners, and killers of savage beasts: otherwhiles out of the noblest young gentlemen of all the Cittie. As for the warlike Riding or Turnament called Troie, he exhibited it oftenest of all other, making choyse of boyes to performe it, as well bigger as smaller: supposing it a matter of antiquitie: a decent and honorable maner besides, that the towardly disposition and proofe of noble bloud should thus be seene and knowne. In this solemnitie and sport, he rewarded C. Nonius Asprenas weakened<note place="bottom" n="1">Or lamed.</note> by a fall from his horse, with a wreath or chaine of gold, and permitted both himselfe and also his posteritie to beare the surname of Torquatus. But afterwards he gave over the representation of such pastimes, by occasion that Asinius Pollio the Oratour, made a agrievous and invidious complaint in the Senate house, of the fall that Æserninus his nephew tooke, who likewise had thereby broken his legge.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>To the performance of the sword fight, he employed some times even the Gentlemen and knights of Rome: but it was before he was inhibited by vertue of an Act of the Senate. For after it verily, he exhibited no more, save onely a youth called L. Itius, borne of worshipfull parentage, onely for a shew: that being a dwarfe not two foote high, and weighing 17 l.<note place="bottom" n="2">His lightnes was more to be noted than his short stature: for wheras the full height is 6 foote and the weight somewhat above 100 l. this levity of 2 foot is under that proportion the one halfe.</note> yet he had an exceeding great voice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>One day of the sword fight that he set forth, he brought in for to behould the solemnitie, even through the midst of the Shew place, the Parthians hostages who then were newly sent (to Rome) and placed them in the second ranke or row of seates above himselfe<note place="bottom" n="3">Superque se: or behind at his backe higher, and therfore further of: or else in a second seat from him of the one side, but in the same ranke for honor sake.</note>. His manner was moreover, before the usuall daies of such spectacles and solemne sights, and at other times, if any strang and new thing were brought over unto him, and worthie to be knowne, to bring it abroad for to be seene upon extraordinary daies, and in any place whatsoever. As for example, a Rhinoceros within the empaled or railed enclosure called Septa: a Tigre upon the stage: and a Serpent 50 cubits long, within the Hall Comitium.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>It fortuned that during the great Circeian games which he had vowed before, he fell sicke: whereby he lay in his litter and so devoutly attended upon the sacred chariots called Thensæ. Againe, it happened at the beginning of those plaies, which he set out when he dedicated the temple of Marcellus, that his curule chaire became unjoincted, and thereby he fel upon his back: also at the games of his nephewes when the people their assembled were mightily troubled and astonied, for feare that the Theater would fall: seeing that by no means he cold hold them in, nor cause them to take heart againe, he removed out of his owne place, and sat him downe in that part thereof which was most suspected.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="44">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The most confuse and licentious manner of beholding such spectacles, hee reformed and brought into order; mooved thereto, by the wrong done to a Senatour, whom at Puteoli in a frequent assemble sittinge at their right solemne Games, noe man had received to him and vouchsafed a rowne. Hereupon when a decree of the Senate was passed, That so often as in any place there was ought exhibited publikely to be seene, the first ranke or course of Seates should be kept cleere and wholly for Senatours: he forbad the Embassadour of free nations and confederats to sit at Rome within the Orchestra: because he had found, that even some of their libertines kind were sent in embassage.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>The soldiers hee severed from the other people. To maried men that were commoners, he assigned several rewes by themselves. To Noble mens children under age his own quarter<note place="bottom" n="1">Cuneum suum or a rancke of their owne.</note>: and to their teachers and governers the next thereto. He made an Act also, that not one of the base Commons wearing blacke and sullied gownes should sit so neere as the midst of the Theatre<note type="annotation" n="a">For the ordinarie Roman Gownes were white and faire kept.</note>. As for women he would not allow them to behold so much, as the sword Fencers, (who customarily in the time past were to be seene of all indifferently) but from some higher loft above the rest<note place="bottom" n="1">And by consequence farther of.</note>, sitting there by themselves<note place="bottom" n="2">Spectare concessit solis.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>To the Vestall Nunnes he graunted a place a part from the rest within the Theatre, and the same just over against the Pretours Tribunall. Howbeit from the Solemnitie of Champions-shew, he banished all the female sex: so farre forth, as that during the Pontificiall Games<note place="bottom" n="3">Which him selfe exhibited being Pontifex Maximus, i. the High priest.</note>, he put of a couple of them who were called for to enter in to combat, untill the morrow morning b<note type="annotation" n="b">Of these spectacles and games, some were Matutini, some Meridiani, and other Pomeridiani: according as they were exhibited, in the morning, at noone, and after-noone.</note>. And made proclamation, that his will and pleasure was, That no woman should come into the Theatre before the fift hower of the day<note place="bottom" n="4">Eleven of the clok, by which houre all that sight was past.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="45">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Himselfe behelde the Circeian Games, for the most part from the upper lofts and lodging of his friendes and freedmen, sometime out of the Pulvinar<note place="bottom" n="5">And not, e pulvinari, i. The bedloft wher the sacred Images of the Gods were devoutly bestowed, which had beene brought in their Thenses and carried thether, at these solemn games.</note>, sitting there with his wife onely and children. From these shewes and sights he would be absent many houres together, and otherwhiles whole dayes: but first having craved leave of the people, and recommended those unto them, who should sitte as presidentes of those Games in his turne. But so often as he was at them, he did nothing els but intend the same<note place="bottom" n="6">As if he had no delight in those games.</note>: either to avoide the rumor and speech of men, whereby his father Cæsar (as he said himselfe) was commonly taxed, namely for that in beholding those solemnities he used betweene whiles to give his mind to read letters and petitions, yea and to write backe againe: or els uppon an earnest desire and delight he had, in seeing such pastimes, his pleasure and contentment wherein, he never dissimuled, but oftentimes frankely professed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>And therefore he proposed and gave of his owne at the games of prise and plaies even of other men, Coronets and rewards, both many in number, and also of great worth: neither was he present at any of these Greek games<note type="annotation" n="a">These were called likewise sacred Games, as Stage-playes, Gymnicke Exercises, and Masteries in Musicke, in Neroes time.</note> and solemnities, but he honored everie one of the Actors and provers of Maisteries therein according to their deserts. But moste affectionately of all other he loved to see the Champions at fist fight<note place="bottom" n="1">Pugiles, aunswerable in Greece to the Romaine Gladiatores.</note>: and the Latines especially; not those onely who by lawfull calling were professed<note place="bottom" n="2">And so had learned the skil and feate of fighting.</note>, and by order allowed (and even those he was wont to match with Greeks) but such also as out of the common sort of townes-men, fell together by the eares pell mell in the narrow streets, and though they had no skill at all of fight, yet could lay on load, and offend their concurrents one way or other.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>In summe, all those in generall, who had any hand in those publike games or set them forward any way, he deigned good rewards and had a speciall respect of them. The priviledges of Champions he both maintained entier, and also amplified. As for sword fencers he would not suffer them to enter into the lists, unlesse they might be discharged of that profession, in case they became victours. The power to chastice<note place="bottom" n="3">By beating with rods.</note> Actours and plaiers at all times and in everie place (granted unto the Magistrates<note place="bottom" n="4">Pretours and Ædiles. Pompeii, Balbi, Metelli.</note> by auncient law) he tooke from them, save onely during the plaies and uppon the stage.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Howbeit he examined streightly neverthelesse at all times either the matches or combats of Champions called Xystici<note type="annotation" n="b">They tooke that name of a spatious Gallerie or walking place called Xystos, wherein they were woont to exercise in winter time.</note>, or the fights of sword fencers. For the licentiousnesse of stage plaiers he so repressed, that when he had for certaine found out, that Stephanio, an actor of Romaine playes had a mans wife waiting upon him shorne and rounded in manner of a boy, he confined and sent him away as banished: but well beaten first with rods through all the three Theatres<note place="bottom" n="5">For so many there were in Augustus dayes, besides the Amphitheatre of Statilius Taurus.</note>. And Hylas the Pantomime<note place="bottom" n="6">A cunning Actour counterfaiting all parts.</note> at the complaint made of him by the Pretour, he skourged openly in the Court yard before his house: and excluded no man from the sight thereof: yea and he banished Pylades out of the Cittie of Rome and Italie, because he had pointed with his finger at a Spectatour who hissed him out of the stage, and so made him to be knowne.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="46">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Having in this manner ordred the Cittie and administred the civile affaires therin, he made Italie populous and much frequented with Colonies<note type="annotation" n="a">Colonies, were Towne-ships in Italy and other Provinces planted with Romane Inhabitants. In which Decuriones, as one would say Aldermen, had the same authoritie as Senators in Rome.</note> to the number of 28, brought thither and planted by him; yea he furnished the same with publike workes and revenues in many places. He equalled it also after a sort, and in some part with the verie Cittie of Rome in priviledges and estimation: by devising a new kind of Suffrages<note place="bottom" n="1">Voices.</note> which the decurions or elders of Colonies gave every one in their owne Towneshippe<note place="bottom" n="2">Cuiuscunque oppidi.</note>, as touching Majestrates to bee created in Rome, and sent under their hands and seales to the City against the day of the solemne Elections. And to the end, there should not want in any place either honest and worshipfull inhabitants, or issue of the multitude; looke who made suite to serve as men of armes on horse-backe upon the publique commendation of any towneship whatsoever, those hee enrolled and advanced unto the degree of Gentlemen. But to as many of the Commoners as could by goode evidence prove unto him as hee visited the Countries and Regions of Italy, that they had sonnes and daughters he distributed a thousand sesterces a piece, for every child they had.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="47">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>As for those Provinces, which were more mighty than other, and the government whereof by yeerely Magistrates was neither easie nor safe, he undertooke himselfe to rule<note type="annotation" n="a">Hereupon, some Provinces were called Cæsaris, or Præsidiariæ : namely, which were ruled by the Emperours sole appointment, and had strong Garrisons placed in them others, Populi, and they were named Prætoriæ, Consulares, or Proconsulares, governed by Pretors, Consuls, or their Vicegerents.</note>: the rest hee committed to Proconsuls by lot<note place="bottom" n="3">And those were eleven.</note>: and yet otherwhiles he made exchange of such Provinces: and of both sorts, hee oftentimes visited many in person. Certaine Cities, confederate and in league with Rome, howbeit by over-much libertie running headlong to mischiefe and destruction, hee deprived of their liberties. Others againe, either deepely in debt he eased, or subverted by earthquake he reedified, or able to alledge their merits and good turnes done to the people of Rome hee endowed with the franchises of Latium; or else with freedome of Rome. There is not, I suppose, a Province, (except Affrick onely and Sardinia) but hee went unto it. Into these Provinces after he had chaced Sextus Pompeius thither, he prepared to saile out of Sicilie and to crosse the Seas: but continuall stormes and extreame tempests checked him: neither had hee good occasion or sufficient cause afterwards to passe over unto them.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="48">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>All those kingdomes which he wan by conquest and force of armes, unlesse some fewe, hee either restored unto those Princes from whom hee had taken them, or else made them over to other. KK. mere Aliens, Princes, his Associates hee conjoyned also together among themselves by mutuall bonds of alliance, as being a most ready procurer and maintainer of affinity and amity of every one; neither had he other regard of them all in generall than of the very naturall members and parts of his owne Empire. Moreover, he was wont to set Guardians and Governours over the saide Princes, when they were either young and under age, or lunatick and not well in their wits; untill such time as they were growne to ripe yeeres, or began to come againe to themselves. The children of very many of them, he both brought up and also trained and instructed together with his owne.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="49">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Out of his militarie forces, he distributed both Legions and Auxiliaries by Provinces. He placed one fleete at Misenum, and another at Ravenna, for the defences of the upper<note place="bottom" n="1">Superi, called otherwise the Adriatich Sea: Venice-gulfe.</note> and nether<note place="bottom" n="2">Inferi, otherwise Tusci, or Tyrrheni, i. the Tuskane Sea.</note> Seas. A certaine number of Souldiours he selected for a guard, partly of the City, and in part of his owne person, having discharged the regiment of the Calagurritanes<note place="bottom" n="3">People of Spaine.</note>, which hee had retained about him, untill he vanquished Antonius; and likewise of the Germaines which hee had waged among the Squires of his body, unto the disasterous overthrow of Varus: And yet he suffred not at any time, to remain within the City more then 3 cohorts, and those without their pavilions. The residue, his manner was to send away to wintering places and sommer harbours about the neighbour-townes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Moreover, all the souldiours that were in any place whatsoever, hee tied to a certaine prescript forme and proportion of wages and rewards, setting downe according to the degree and place of every one, both their times of warfare, and also the commodities<note place="bottom" n="1">Fees, pensions, land and living.</note> they should receive after the terme of their service expired and their lawfull discharge: least that by occasion of old age, or for want, they should after they were freed from warfare, be solicited to sedition and rebellion. And to the end, that for ever, and without any difficulty, there might be defrayed sufficient to maintaine and reward them accordingly, he appointed a peculiar Treasurie for soldiors with new revenewes devised for their maintainance<note place="bottom" n="2">Ducentesimis et quinquagesimis rerum venalium. Bonis etiam damnatorum, i. with the two hundreth peny, and the fiftieth peny of wares sold: with the goods also of condemned persons.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>And that with more speede and out of hand word might be brought, and notice taken what was doing in every province, hee disposed along the rode high-waies, within small distance one from another; first, certaine young men as posts; and afterwards swift wagons to give intelligence. This he thought more commodious, and better to the purpose, that they who from a place brought him letters might be asked questions also, if the matters required ought.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="50">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In charters, patents, writs, bils and letters he used for his seale, at the first, the image of Sphinx<note type="annotation" n="a">There is a kinde of Munkey or Marmoset in Æthiopia, going under the name of Sphinx, in Plinie. The Poets also faine, that a certaine monsterous beast so called, sometime did haunt the Citie of Thebes and the Territorie about it which from a rocke proposed ridales unto the passengers. This monster by their report, caried the resemblance of three creatures, to wit, a Foule, a Lion, and a mayden, according to these verses of Ausonius. Terruit Aoniam volucris, Leo, virgo, triformis Sphinx: volucris penna, pedibus fera, fronte puella. A three-shap'd Sphinx, Bird-Lion-Maid, Aonian land did fright, In wing a foule, in feete a beast, In face a virgin [bright]. Plinie writeth in the last booke of his Naturall Historie, That Augustus used at the beginning to signe with this Sphinx engraven upon his Signet. 'And verily,' quoth he, 'in the casket of his mothers Jewels two of these he found, so like, that one could not be discerned from the other. And as hee was woont to weare the one wheresoever he went, so in his absence during the civill warres with Anthonie, his friends that menaged his affaires at Rome, sealed with the other, those missives and edicts which passed in his name. And from hence it came, that those who received any such letters or edictes conteyning matter of difficultie, were wont merily to say, that the said Sphinx came ever with some hard riddle or other, which could not be assoiled. Whereupon Augustus to avoid the obloquie that arose by his Sphinx gave over sealing therewith, and signed alwaies after with the image of King Alexander the Great,' etc.</note>: Soone after, that of Alexander the great: and last of all, his owne; engraven by the hand of Dioscurides<note place="bottom" n="3">A cunning Lapidarie and graver in pretious stones.</note>: wherewith the Princes and Emperours his successours continued to signe their writings. To all his missives his manner was, to put precisely the very minutes of houres, not of day onely but of night also, wherein it might be knowne, they were dated.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="51">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Of his clemencie and civill curtesie<note type="annotation" n="a">This humanitie and affable courtesie termed by Sueton. Civilitas, was reproved in Alexander the Emperour by his mother and wife both, as not beseeming the Majestie of a Prince: for they told him many times, that thereby he caused his Imperiall power and dignitie to be the more contemptible: Yea, but it is by that meanes, quoth he, both surer, and like also to last the longer. Lamprid. in Alexandro.</note>, there be many, and those right great proofes and experiments. Not to reckon up, how many and who they were of the adverse faction, that he vouchsafed pardon and life; yea, and suffred to hold still a principall place in the City: he was content and thought it sufficient, to punish Junius Novatus and Cassius Patavinus, two commoners; the one with a fine of money and the other with a slight banishment: notwithstanding that Junius Novatus in the name of young Agrippa had divulged a most biting and stinging letter, touching him, and Cassius Patavinus at an open table and full feast, gave out in broad termes, That he wanted neither harty wishes nor good will to stab him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Moreover in a certaine judiciall triall, when among other crimes this article was principally objected against Æmilius Ælianus of Corduba, That hee was wont to have a bad conceite<note place="bottom" n="1">Male opinari. The same in this Author, that Male dicere.</note> and to speake but basely of Cæsar, himselfe turned unto the accuser, and as if he had beene sore offended, 'I would,' quoth he, 'thou wert able to prove this unto me: in faith Ælianus should well know, that I also have a tongue: for I will not stick to say more by him.' And farther than this he neither for the present nor afterwards inquired into the matter.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Likewise, when Tiberius grieved and complained unto him of the same indignity in a letter, and that uncessantly and after a violent manner, thus he wrote back againe: 'Doe not my good Tiberius in this point follow and feed the humor of your age<note place="bottom" n="2">Young: imputing his coller and cruelty to the heate of youth and hote bloud: measuring Tiberius by himselfe.</note>: neither set it too neere your heart, That there is any man who speaketh evill of me; for it is enough for us, if no man be able to doe us harme.'</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="52">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Albeit, he wist well enough, that Temples were usually graunted by decree even unto Proconsuls, yet in no Province accepted hee of that honour, but joyntlie in the name and behalfe of himselfe and of Rome. For in Rome verily, he forbare this honour most resolutely: yea, and those silver Statues which in times past had beene set up for him, he melted every one. Of which<note place="bottom" n="1">With the money, for which they were sold.</note>, he caused golden Tables<note place="bottom" n="2">Cortinas, otherwise called Tripodas, standing upon 3 feete: from which Oracles were delivered.</note> to be made, and those he dedicated to Apollo Patavinus. When the people offered and instantly forced upon him the Dictatourship, he fell upon his knees, cast his gowne from off his shoulder, bared his brest, and with detestation of the thing, besought them not to urge him farther.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="53">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The name and title of Lord<note place="bottom" n="3">Domini, or Sr.</note><note type="annotation" n="a">This name Dominus among the Romans, like as Sir with us, was diversly used. In the sense of imperious and Lordly commaund, as wee sometime take [Lord] it was odious: as having a relation to Servus a slave or villaine. To mollifie therfore the harshnesse of the word, they used to terme housholders or masters of families, patresfamilias, in steed of Dominos, as also houshold servants familiares, and not servos. Otherwise they used it by way of flatterie or faire speech, as appeareth in the chap. 21 of Claudius following. Hence it is, that lovers call their sweet hearts, Dominas, i. Mistresses. Also if a man speaketh unto one, whom he eyther knoweth not, or hath forgotten, he saith, Domine, i. Heere you, Sir, according to that Epigram in Martiall. Cum te non nossem, Dominum Regemque vocabam. Al while that I you kenned not, I cald you L. and King. Last of all, by way of scorne and derision. And so, the same Martial testifyeth in this Distichon. Cum voco te dominum, noli tibi, Cinna, placere, Sæpe etiam servum sic resaluto meum. When I O Cinna call you sir, joy not, I you advise, For even my servant I salute oft times no otherwise. In which manner we speake unto our servant, or any other in contempt, by this terme sirrha: to say nothing of sir knave. No mervaile therefore, if Augustus could not abide this word Dominus so doubtfully taken, and seldome in good sense.</note> he alwaies abhorred as a contumelious and reproachfull terme. When upon a time, as he beheld the plaies, these words were pronounced out of a Comedie<note place="bottom" n="4">Or Enterlude, Mimo.</note>, O good and gracious Lord: whereupon the whole assembly with great joy and applause accorded thereto, as if they had beene spoken of him: immediatly both with gesture of hand and shew of countenance, he repressed such undecent flatteries: and the next day reproved them most sharply by an edict: neither would hee ever after suffer himselfe to be called Dominus, no not of his owne children and nephewes either in earnest or boord. And that which more is, such faire and glavering wordes hee forbad them to use among themselves.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Lightly, you should not have him depart forth of the City or any Towne, nor enter into any place, but in the evening, or by night for disquieting any person in doing him honour by way of dutifull attendance<note type="annotation" n="c">He looked not for their attendance at home in his owne house, neyther would he be thought to have conferred with any one privately, as touching the publike affaires.</note>. In his Consulship hee went commonly in the streetes on foote: out of his Consulship oftentimes in a close chaire or licter b<note type="annotation" n="b">If you read [adoperta], i. close and shut, it may have reference to this, That he tooke not state upon him, nor sought the peoples applause: which accordeth to his other behaviour reported before. If [ad aperta], i. open, it sheweth likewise his courteous cariage and affabilitie: as who was readie to accept of petitions and requests: a thing right commendable in a Prince, as it is written of King Artaxerxes surnamed Mnemon, how riding in a Carroch with his Queene, he commaunded her to draw open the curtaines thereof, that he might the better attend upon his subjects. And this agreeth as well with that which followeth of Augustus. And hereto I rather encline.</note><note place="bottom" n="6">Ad operta: if adaperta the sence is contrarie.</note>. In generall Salutations and duties done unto him he admitted the very Commons, entertaining the suites and desires of all commers with so great humanity as that he rebuked one of them merily, because in reaching unto him a supplication, he did it so timorously, as if hee had raught a small peece of coine<note place="bottom" n="7">Stipem. Quintilianus reddidit assem. lib. 6. cap. de risu.</note> to an Oliphant.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>On a Senate-day, he never saluted his Nobles but in the Curia: and those verily as they sat, every one by name without any prompter<note place="bottom" n="8">Or Nomenclator.</note>: and at his departure out of the house, he used to bid them farewell one by one as they were set, in the same manner. With many men he performed mutuall offices yeelding one kindnes for another interchangeably. Neither gave he over frequenting their solemnities and feasts<note place="bottom" n="1">As Birthdayes, and Mariage Minds.</note> untill he was farre stept in yeeres: and by this occasion, that once upon a day of Espousals<note place="bottom" n="2">Assurance making of a mariage.</note> he was in the presse and throng of people sore crouded. Gallus Terrinius a Senator, and none of his familiar acquaintance, howbeit fallen blinde and purposing resolutely to pine himselfe to death d<note type="annotation" n="d">It is generally a received opinion, that within seven naturall daies such voluntarie abstinence from food is not mortall, as Plinie writeth in his eleventh booke, who reporteth also, that many have continued fasting more than eleven daies. Which I easily beeleeve. For, in mine owne knowledge I may be bold to report, that a Bitch lived so long, and yet died not, nor miscaried the whelps within her. Some meloncholicke persons therefore, may within the Latitude of Health endure so long, yea and those likewise who are fraught top-full with a ballanse of crud and cold humours, which may engender a quartaine ague as well as melancholie doth. For, I doubt not, but in such chronicke diseases occasioned and maintained by grosse matters, one may abide above eleven daies without all manner of food. Yet Aulus Gellius saith, that beyond seven daies wilfull abstinence, a man is not able to live.</note>, he visited in proper person, and by his consolatory and comfortable words perswaded him to live still.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="54">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>As he delivered a speech in the Senate, one said unto him, 'I conceived you not': and another, 'I would gain-say you if any place were left for me to speake'<note place="bottom" n="3">As if Augustus by his absolute power had taken up all.</note>. Divers times when upon occasion of excessive altercation and brabbling among the Senatours in debating matters, he was about to whip out of the Senate a pace in a great chafe, some of them would choke him with these words, 'Senatours ought to have liberty to speake their mindes concerning the Common-weale.' Antistius Labeo at a certaine Election of Senatours, when one man chooseth another<note place="bottom" n="4">Cum vir virum, not Triumvirum.</note>, made choise of M. Lepidus, who sometime was (Augustus) mortall enemie, and then in Exile. Now when he demaunded of the said Antistius, If there were not others more worthy to be chosen ? hee returned this aunswere, That every man had his owne liking and judgement by himselfe. Yet for all this, did no mans free speech or froward selfe-will, turne him to displeasure or danger.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="55">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Moreover, the diffamatory libels of him cast abroad and dispersed in the Curia, he neither was affrighted at, nor tooke great care to refute; making not so much as search after the Authors. Onely this he opined, That from thenceforth there should be inquisition made, and examination had of those that either in their owne name or under other mens, did put forth libels<note type="annotation" n="a">For, as Ulpian testifyeth, 1. 18, de Testamento, a law there was, that whosoever to the infamie of any person published a Libell eyther in his owne or another mans name, yea without name at all: if he be convict thereof, shall be Intestabilis, i. disabled both for making a will himselfe, and also for to be a witnesse unto another mans.</note>, rimes, or verses to the infamie of any person.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="56">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Furthermore, to meete with the spitefull taunts and skurrile scoffes of some, wherewith he was provoked, he made an Edict against such. And yet, to the end that the Senate should passe no Act, for the Inhibition of their licentious liberty in their last wils and testaments<note place="bottom" n="1">Wherein, the manner was to use broad jests, of any person. Casaubonus.</note>, he interposed his negative voice. Whensoever he was present himselfe at the Generall Wardmotes for Election of Magistrates, he went with his owne Candidates<note type="annotation" n="a">By these Candidates, he meaneth eyther such as himselfe recommended unto the people for any office, as Cæsar his predecessor did before him, and those were called Cæsaris Candidati, or else his especiall friends whom he laboured for.</note><note place="bottom" n="2">Or graces.</note> round about to the Tribes, and humbly craved their voices according to the usuall custome. Himselfe also gave a voice in his owne Tribe<note place="bottom" n="3">In Tribu, or in Tribubus, i. among other Tribes.</note> as one of the ordinary people. When hee appeared as witnesse in judiciall courts, hee suffred himselfe right willingly to be examined upon interrogatives, and also to be impleaded against and confuted.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>His common Hall of Justice<note place="bottom" n="4">Called Forum Augusti.</note> he made lesse, and of narrower compasse<note place="bottom" n="5">Than the other.</note>; as not daring to encroch upon the next houses and dispossesse the owners. He never recommended his sonnes unto the people, but with this clause added thereto, If they shall deserve. When, beeing yet under age, and in their purpled childs habit<note place="bottom" n="6">Prætextatis adhuc.</note>, al the people generally that sat in the Theater rose up unto them, and the standers below clapped their hands, hee tooke it very ill and complained grievously thereof. His minions and inward friends he would have to bee great and mighty men in the City; yet so, as they should have no more liberty than other Citizens, but be subject to lawes and judgements as well as the rest.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>When Asprenas Nonius, a man of neere alliance and acquaintance with him was accused by Cassius Severus, for practising poison, and pleaded for himselfe at the Barr, hee asked counsell of the Senate, what they thought in duty he was to do? 'For I stand in doubt, quoth he, 'least being here present as an advocate, I should acquit the prisoner defendant<note place="bottom" n="1">Or offender.</note> and so hinder the course of law; againe, if I be absent and faile him, least I might be thought to forsake and prejudice my friend': wherupon, by all their consents, he sat there in the Pues<note place="bottom" n="2">Within the Barr, among the Advocates, as a well willer.</note> certain houres, but spake never a word nor affourded so much as a commendatorie speech in the defendants behalfe, as the maner of friends was to do in the triall of such cases.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>He pleaded the causes even of his very clients, and by name, of a certain shield-bearer<note place="bottom" n="3">Or Targuatier, Scutario: some take this for a proper name of some souldiour of his.</note>, whom in times past he had called forth to serve him in the wars: he spake I say in his defence, when he was sued in an action of the case. Of all those that were thus in trouble, he delivered one and no more from making his appearance in Court: and him verily no otherwise, but by earnest praiers and entreating the Accuser before the Judges: and him he perswaded at length to let fal his action. And Castritius it was, a man, by whose meanes he came to the knowledge of Murenaes conspiracie.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="57">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>How much, and for what demerits of his, he was beloved, an easie matter it is to make an æstimate. The acts and decrees of the Senate concerning his honors I passe over, as which may be thought wrested from them either upon mere necessity or bashfull modesty. The Gentlemen of Rome of their owne accord and by an uniforme consent celebrated his birth-feast alwaies for 2 daies together. All States and Degrees of the City, yeerely upon a solemne vow that they made, threw small pieces of brasse-coine into Curtius lake<note place="bottom" n="4">Into the railed or empaled place named Septa, where sometime was that Lake.</note> for the preservation of his life and health. Semblably, at the Calends of Januarie every yeere they offred a new yeeres-gift in the Capitol unto him, although he were absent. Out of which masse and grosse sum he disbursed as much money, as wherewith he bought the most pretious Images of the Gods, and dedicated them in divers streets : as namely Apollo Sandaliarius<note place="bottom" n="5">In the Shoomakers street,</note>, and Jupiter Tragædus<note place="bottom" n="6">In the Tragædians street.</note>, and others besides<note place="bottom" n="1">Aliaque. In restitutionem, etc.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>For the reedification of his house in Palatine<note place="bottom" n="2">Mount Palatine.</note> consumed by fire, the old soldiours, the Decuries (of the Judges) the Tribes, and many severall persons by themselves of all sorts, willingly and according to each ones ability brought in their monies together. Howbeit, he did no more but slightly touch the heapes of such money as they lay, and tooke not away out of any one above one single denier<note place="bottom" n="3">7d. ob.</note>. As he returned out of any province, they accompanied him honorably, not onely with good words and lucky osses<note place="bottom" n="4">Faustis omnibus, or, nominibus, i. names.</note>, but also with songs set in musicall measures. This also was duly observed, that how often so ever he entred Rome, no punishment that day was inflicted upon any person.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="58">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The surname<note place="bottom" n="5">Or addition.</note> in his stile of Pater Patriæ, they all presented unto him with exceeding great and unexpected accord. The Commons, first, by an Embassage which they sent unto Antium: then, because he accepted not therof, at Rome as he entred the Theater to behold the plaies, they tendered it a second time themselves in great frequencie, dight with Lawrell branches and Coronets. Soone after, the Senate did the like, not by way of decree nor acclamation, but by Valerius Messalla, who had commission from them all, to relate their minds in this maner.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>'That,' quoth he, 'which may be to the good and happinesse of thee and thy house O Cæsar Augustus (for in this wise we think, that we pray for perpetuall felicity<note place="bottom" n="6">Felicitatem Reip. et læta huic: pro, felicitatem et læta Reip. huic.</note> and prosperity to this Commonwealth). The Senate according with the people of Rome, do jointly salute thee by the name of Pater Patriæ<note place="bottom" n="7">Father of the Countrey.</note>. Unto whom, Augustus with teares standing in his eyes, made answere in these words, (for I have set the very same downe, like as I did those of Messalas<note place="bottom" n="8">Sicut Messella.</note>) 'Now that I have (mine honorable Lords) attained to the heighth of all my vowes and wishes, what remaineth else for me to crave of the immortall Gods, but that I may carie with mee this universall consent of yours unto my lives end?'</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="59">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Unto Antonius Musa his Physitian, by whose meanes he was recovered out of a dangerous disease, they erected a Statue, by a generall contribution of brasse, just by the image of Æsculapius. Some housholders<note place="bottom" n="1">Patres familias, good honest Citizens of Rome that were sui juris.</note> there were who in their last wils and testaments provided, That their heires should leade beasts for sacrifice into the Capitoll and pay their vowes, with this title caried before them containing the reason of so doing, Because they had left Augustus living after them<note place="bottom" n="2">i. their Fathers, the testatours.</note>. Certaine Cities of Italy began their yeere that very day, on which he first came to them. Most of the Provinces, over and above Temples and Altars, ordained almost in every good Towne, solemne Games and Playes every fifth yeere in his honor<note place="bottom" n="3">As if he had beene a Demi-God.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="60">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Kings his friends and Confederates both severally every one in his own kingdome built Cities calling them Cæsareæ, and jointly altogether intended, at their common charges fully to finish the temple of Jupiter Olympicus at Athens which long time before was begun, and to dedicate it unto his Genius. And oftentimes, the said Princes leaving their realmes, going in Romaine gownes, without Diadems and regall Ornaments, in habit and manner of devoted Clients, performed their dutifull attendance unto him day by day : not at Rome only, but also when he visited and travailed over the provinces.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      
      </body>
      </text>
      </TEI>