<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>THE HISTORIE OF TIBERIUS CLAUDIUS DRUSUS CÆSAR</title>
        <author>C. Suetonius Tranquillus</author>
        <editor>Philemon Holland (Translator)</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Encoded for TEI XML</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Transcribed from PDF source files of Philemon Holland's 1898 edition.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
     <pb n="54" />
      <head>THE HISTORIE OF TIBERIUS CLAUDIUS DRUSUS CÆSAR</head>
      <div type="chapter" n="1">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>AS touching Drusus father to this Claudius Cæsar, which Drusus was in times past forenamed Decimus and afterwards Nero; dame Livia wedded unto Augustus even when she was great with child, brought him into the world within three moneths after the said mariage, and folke suspected that begotten he was in adulterie by his (supposed) father in law himselfe<note place="bottom" n="1">Augustus: and not by Tiberius Nero, his mothers husband.</note>. Certes presently after his birth, this verse went rife in every mans mouth, τοῖς εὐτυχοῦσι καὶ τρίμηνα παιδία, 
          <quote>On persons great this fortune doth attend, <lb/> That children they may have at three moneths end.</quote></p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>This Drusus in the honorable place of questure and pretureship, being L. Generall of the Rhætian, and so foorth of the Germane warre, was the first Romane Captaine that sayled in the North Ocean: and on the farther side of Rhene caste those trenches of a straung and infinite worke which yet at this day be called Drusinæ<note place="bottom" n="2">Or Drusianæ, Tacit.</note>. Many a time he put the enemy to sword, and when he had driven him as farre as to the inmost deserts, gave not over chasing and pursuing, <pb n="55" /> untill there appeared unto him the likenesse of a Barbarian woman<note place="bottom" n="1">Representing Germanie.</note>, more portly than a mortall wight, which in the Latine tongue forbad him to follow the traine of victorie anie farther.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>For which acts atchieved, he enjoyed the honour of a pety Triumph<note place="bottom" n="2">Called Ovation.</note>, and had the Triumphall ornaments graunted unto him. After his pretureship, he entred immediatly upon the Consulate: and having enterprised a second expedition thither, fell sicke and dyed in his summer campe, which therupon tooke the name of Castra Scelerata<note place="bottom" n="3">The wicked and mischievous camp.</note><note type="annotation" n="a">LIKE as in Rome, the gate called Porta scelerata, and the Streete Vicus sceleratus upon some semblable infortunate accidents.</note>. His corps by the principall Citizens and Burgesses of the free-burrowes and colonies, by the decuries also and orders of the Scribes<note place="bottom" n="4">Or Chancelors.</note> (who met them in the way and received it at their hands) was conveied to Rome and buried in Mars-fielde. Howbeit the armie reared in honour of him an honorarie tombe<note place="bottom" n="5">Which the Greeks call Cenotaphium, i. an empty tomb.</note> (or stately herse) about the which every yeare afterwards upon a certain set day, the souldiers should runne at tilt, keepe jousting and turnament: the Citties likewise and States of Gaule, sacrifice and make publike supplications to the gods. Moreover the Senate among many other honors, decreed for him a Triumphant arch of marble, with Tropees thereto in the street Appia<note place="bottom" n="6">Or port-way.</note>: as also the surname of Germanicus to him and his posterity for ever.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Furthermore he is thought to have caried a mind no lesse glorious than civil and popular. For over and above the conquests gained of his enemies, he wan also from them Royall spoyles<note place="bottom" n="7">Which he tooke from their cheife generals.</note>: and oftentimes to the uttermost hazard of his life coursed and chaced the General of the Germans all over the field: neither dissembled he, but gave it out, that one day he would restore unto the Common-wealth their ancient state and libertie againe. Whereupon, I suppose, some presume to write, that Augustus had him in jelousie and suspicion: called him home out of his Province: and because he lingred and delayed his returne, made him away by poyson.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>Which verily put downe I have, because I would not seeme to pretermit such a matter, rather, <pb n="56" /> than for that I thinke it either true or probable: considering that Augustus both loved him whiles hee was alive so entirely, as that he alwayes ordained him fellow-heire with his sonnes, (like as he openly professed upon a time in the Senate house) and also commended him after his death so highly, that in a solemne oration before the bodie of the people he prayed unto the gods, To vouchsafe his owne Cæsars to be like unto him and to grant himselfe one day such an end as they had given him. And not contented with this that he had engraven upon his tombe an Epitaph in verse which he himselfe composed, he wrot also the historie of his life in prose.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="6">
          <p>By Antonia the yonger, he became father verily of many children, but three onely hee left behind him at his death, namely, Germanicus, Livilla, and Claudius.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="2">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>This Claudius was borne at Lyons, in the yeare when Julius Antonius and Fabius Africanus were Consuls, upon the Calends of August, that very day on which the altar was first dedicated there unto Augustus: and named he was Tiberius Claudius Drusus: and a while after, when his elder brother was adopted into the family Julia, hee assumed into his stile the surname of Germanicus. Being left an infant by his father, all the time in manner of his child-hood and youth<note place="bottom" n="1">Or growing age.</note>, piteously handled he was with sundrie diseases, and those tough and such as stucke long by him: in so much as being dulled and enfeebled thereby both in mind and bodie, he was not thought in the very progresse of riper age, sufficient and capable of any publike office or private charge:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>yea and many a day after that hee came to full yeares and had sued out his liverie, hee was at the dispose of another, even under a pedagogue and governour; whom in a certaine booke himself complaineth of, terming him a barbarous fellow, and no better sometime than a mulitier<note place="bottom" n="2">Olim superiumentarium, rather a maister of mulitiers.</note>, set over him of purpose to chastice and punish him most cruelly for everie light cause and occasion whatsoever. By <pb n="57" /> reason of this his sicknesse, both at the sword-play which he and his brother joyntly exhibited in memoriall of their Father, he sat as president (not after the accustomed manner) lapt in a cloake; and also upon his commensement day, when he was to put on his virile gowne, about midnight without anie honorable attendance and solemne traine, brought he was in a licter into the Capitoll<note type="annotation" n="a">Wheras, by usuall custome such were brought into the Forum or common hall.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="3">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Howbeit, from his very child-hood, he employed no meane studie in the liberall sciences. And oftentimes gave good proofe even in publike place of his proceedings in them all: yet could he never for all that reach to any degree of dignity, or yeeld better hope of himselfe for the time to come.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>His mother Antonia, was wont to call him Portentum hominis, i. The Monster and fantasticall shewe of a man, as if hee had not beene finished but onely begunne by nature: and if shee reprooved anie one for his foolishnesse she would saie, Hee was more sottish then her Sonne Claudius. His Grandmother Augusta<note place="bottom" n="1">Otherwise called Livia and Julia the mother of Drusus.</note> thought alwaies most basely of him, as who used neither to speake unto him but very seldome, nor to admonish him, unlesse it were in some sharpe and short writing, or els by messengers going between. His sister Livilla, when she heard that he should be one day Emperour, openly and with a lowd voice detested and wished farre from the people of Rome so hard and miserable a fortune.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="4">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>And no mervaile: for to the end that it might be more certainly knowen what opinion his great Uncle Augustus<note place="bottom" n="2">His Grandmothers brother by the mothers side.</note> had of him both wayes<note place="bottom" n="3">As well good as bad.</note>, I have set downe certaine Articles and principall pointes gathered out of his owne Epistles. 'I have,' quoth he, 'my good Livia talked and conferred with Tiberius as you charged me, about this, namely, What is to be done to your Nephew Tiberius, at the solemnity of the Martiall Game<note place="bottom" n="4">In honour of Mars Revenger.</note>. Now, wee are both agreed that it <pb n="58" /> must be determined and set down once for all what course we should take and follow with him: for, if he be ἄρτιος<note place="bottom" n="1">Sufficient.</note>, and as I may so say ὁλόκληρος<note place="bottom" n="2">Sound throughout and perfect.</note>, what doubt need wee to make, but that he is to bee trained and brought by the same oportunities of time and degrees<note place="bottom" n="3">Or steps.</note> by which his brother was.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>But if we perceive him ἠλαττῶσθαι καὶ βεβλάφθαι καὶ εἰς τὴν τοῦ σώματος καὶ εἰς τὴν τῆς ψυχῆς ἀρτιότητα<note place="bottom" n="4">To be impaired or disabled and maimed, as wel for the sufficiencie of body as integrity of mind.</note>: we must not minister matter to men, τὰ τοιαῦτα σκώπτειν καὶ μυκτηρίζειν εἰωθόσι<note place="bottom" n="5">Who are wont to make good game and scoffe at such things.</note>, for to deride both him and us. For we shall ever find trouble and vexation inough, in case of every occasion of time presented unto us, we should deliberate, μὴ προϋποκείμενου ἡμῖν<note place="bottom" n="6">If it be not resolved upon and set downe aforehand by us.</note>, whether wee thinke him able to menage honorable Offices in the State or no.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Howbeit for the present (concerning such things whereof youle aske mine advise) I mislike it not, that he have the charge of the Priests dyning chamber, during these Martiall solemnities aforesayd, so that he wil suffer himselfe to be admonished and schooled by Silanus sonne, a man allyed unto him, that he do nothing, which may be noted<note place="bottom" n="7">Conspici or despui, i. spit at.</note>, or derided. That he should behold the games Circenses from out of the Pulvinar<note place="bottom" n="8">A Bedloft at the Games Circenses, whereon the images of the gods are layed.</note>, in no wise can I allow. For being exposed so, to the sight of men in the very forefront of the Theatre, he wil be eyed and observed: neither like we in any hand, that he should goe up the Albane mount, or abide at Rome during the Latine Holy-dayes<note place="bottom" n="9">In the absence of the Consuls attending the sacrifice upon the Albane Hill.</note>. For if he be able to accompany and follow his brother to that mountaine, why is he not as wel made Provost of the Cittie the while ?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Thus, my Livia, you have our opinions delivered, as who are fully resolved, that once for al somewhat must be put downe as touching the whole matter, least we be evermore wavering between hope and feare. You may also if it please you impart unto our (niece) Antonia thus much of this our letter.' Againe, in another Epistle:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>'As for young <pb n="59" /> Tiberius<note place="bottom" n="1">Claudius.</note>, I for my part whiles you are absent, wil dayly invite him to supper, that he may not suppe alone with his Sulpitius and Athenoderus. And I could wish with al my hart that he would more soundly and lesse μετεώρως<note place="bottom" n="2">Superficially.</note> make choice of some special one, whose gesture habite and gang, hee might, silly soule as he is, imitate. ᾿Ατυχει λίαν ἐν τοῖσι σπουδαίοις πάνυ. He comes farre short (when he is matched) with men of deepe understanding. But looke, when his mind is not wandering out of the way, the generosity of his heart appeareth sufficiently.' Likewise in a third letter:</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="6">
          <p>'Your nephew Tiberius my sweet Livia, if I doe not wonder, that when he declamed that he could please and content me, I pray God I be dead. For how he that in his dayly talke speaketh so ἀσαφῶς<note place="bottom" n="3">Darkly and confusedly.</note> should be able when he declameth, to deliver his mind and what he hath to say σαφῶς<note place="bottom" n="4">Cleerely and plainely to bee understood.</note> I cannot see.'</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="7">
          <p>Neither is there anie doubt to be made, but that after all this, Augustus ordained and left him indued with no honorable office, save only the Sacerdotall dignitie of Augurs: nay he nominated him not so much as his Heire, but in a third degree and descent, even among those that were well neere Strangers: and that in a sixth part onely of his substance: and by way of legacie bequeathed unto him not above 800000 sesterces<note place="bottom" n="5">Every one worth 15s. 7d. ob, or one hundred sesterces.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="5">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Tiberius his unkle conferred upon him when he sued for honorable dignities the Ornaments of Consuls. But when he instantly demaunded still, not imaginary but true magistracies indeede, he wrote backe unto him in his writing tables thus much onely, That he had sent unto him fortie peeces of golde to spend at the feast Saturnalia, and to bestow in puppets and trifling gaudes, at the same time. Then, and not before, casting aside all hope of preferment and reall dignities, hee betooke himselfe to rest and quietnesse of life, lying close, one while within hortyardes of pleasure and <pb n="60" /> in a manner house without the Cittie: and lurking otherwhiles in a withdrawing place out of the way in Campania. And by his daily acquaintance and companie keeping with most base and abject persons besides the olde infamous note of sluggardie and foolishnesse hee incurred an ill name for drunkennesse and dice-play: notwithstanding, that all the while he thus led his life, he never wanted the publike attendance and reverent regard of men seeking unto him.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="6">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The order of Gentlemen elected him twice for their patrone, in an embassage that was to be sent and delivered in their owne behalfe: once when the Consuls required to have the cariage of Augustus his corps upon their own shoulders to Rome: a 2 time when they were to congratulate with the same Consuls for the suppressing of Sejanus. Moreover, they were wont in shewes, and in the Theatre, when he came in place, to arise up and lay off their mantels<note place="bottom" n="1">As wee use to veile bonet or do of our hats.</note> in respective honour of him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>The Senate also ordained, that to the ordinarie number of the Priests or Guild-brethren called Augustales, who were by lot chosen, he should be admitted extraordinarily: and soone after, that his house, which by misfortune of a skare-fire he had lost, should at the Cities charges be reedified; as also the priviledge to deliver his minde and opinion in the Senate, among those who had beene Consuls; which decree of theirs was reversed and annulled: whiles Tiberius<note place="bottom" n="2">The Emperour.</note> alleadged by way of excuse his imbecillity, and promised to repaire the foresaid losse out of his owne private purse and liberality. Yet when hee laye upon his death-bed, he both named him among his heires in a third raunge, and in a third part of his estate, and also bequeathed him a legacie of two millions of Sesterces: yea recommended him besides by name unto the armies, to the Senate likewise and people of Rome in the ranke of other his especiall friends and kinsfolke.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="7">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>At length under Caius<note place="bottom" n="3">Caligula.</note> his brothers sonne, who at his <pb n="61" /> first comming to the Empire sought by all manner of enticing allurements, to gaine the good opinion of a bountifull and gracious prince, he began first to beare office of state, and continued Consul together with him for the space of two moneths: and it fortuned at his first entrance into the Forum with his knitches of rods, that an Eagle soaring thereby, setled upon his right shoulder. He was pricked also and allotted unto a second Consulship, against the 4th yeare following. Divers times he sat as president of the solemne shewes in Caius his turne: what time the people cryed Feliciter<note place="bottom" n="1">All haile or happinesse.</note>, partly to the Emperours<note place="bottom" n="2">Caligula.</note> Uncle, and in part to Germanicus his brother.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="8">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Yet lived hee neverthelesse subject to the contumelious reproches of the World: for if at anie time, hee came somewhat with the latest and after the houre appointed to a supper, hardly and with much adoe, was there any roome made for to receive him, and not before hee had gone round about the tables where guests were set, for to finde a place: likewise, whensoever he tooke a nap, and fel a sleepe after meate (which was an ordinarie thing with him) the buffons and jesters<note place="bottom" n="3">A Copreis: See Tiberius Nero Cæsar, cap. 61, vel a Tropais, such as would play Bo-peepe and hide themselves when they had done some unhappinesse.</note> about him, made good sport, pelling him with olive and date stones: otherwhiles also they would by way of merriment awaken him with the clappe of a ferula or lash of some whip. They were wont likewise to glove his hands (as he lay snorting a sleep) with his shoes<note place="bottom" n="4">For whiles they sat or leaned upon pallets at their meat they put off their shoes.</note>, that as he suddenly awaked hee might rub his face and eyes therewith.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="9">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Neither verily could he avoide divers dangerous troubles: first in his very Consulship: for, beeing behind hand and over slacke in taking order with the workmen for the making and erecting of Nero and Drusus Statues, who were <pb n="62" /> Cæsars<note place="bottom" n="1">Caius Caligula.</note> brethren, hee had like to have beene remooved and put out of that honorable office: afterwards, as eyther anie stranger, or one of his own house informed ought against him, he was continually and sundry manner of waies molested. But when as the Conspiracie of Lepidus and Getulicus came to light, being sent among other Embassadours to congratulate Caius in the name of the City, hee was in jeopardy of his very life: whiles Caius chafed and fumed with great indignation, that his Unkle chiefly of all others was sent unto him, as it were to governe a child: in so much, as some have not stuck to report on writing, that hee was turned also headlong into the river in his cloathes and all as he came apparailed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>From which time forward, never spake hee to any matter proposed in the Senate, but last of all those, that had beene Consuls, as being in reproachfull wise and to his disgrace asked his opinion after them all. There was received likewise against him the examination of a forged will, wherein himselfe also had beene a witnesse and put-to his seale. Last of all, hee was forced to disburse eight millions of Sesterces for a fine or Income at his entrance into a new Priesthood: by occasion whereof, his estate being so much decaied, driven he was to those streights, that for his disability to keepe credit and satisfie the debt due unto the Chamber of the City by an Edict of the Citie Treasurers according to the law Prædiatoria hee hung up to be sold in vacuum<note place="bottom" n="2">His lands and goods were forfeited and so were published in table as voide and vacant.</note><note type="annotation" n="a">By vertue of this Act, himselfe, his landes and goods were proscribed and exposed to open sale, in a Table hung up by an Edict from the masters of the Exchequer or Citie-Chamber. And if within the time appointed, he came not in, to satisfie the debt, nor any chapman or suretie to undertake it, he and his whole state fell by escheate as forfait and confiscate into the Princes hands.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="10">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Having passed the greatest part of his time in running thorough these and such like troubles, at length in the fiftieth yeere of age, hee attained to the Empire, and that by a strange and wonderfull hap. Being among others excluded by the Conspiratours that layed waite for Caius life, what time they voided all the Companie about his person, under a colour as if he desired to be a part himselfe alone in some by-place, this Claudius had stept aside and retired into a lodging or parlour called Hermeum: and not long after, <pb n="63" /> being affrighted at the rumour of that murder, slily crept forth and conveied himselfe up into a Solar<note place="bottom" n="1">A garret.</note> next adjoyning, and there hid himselfe betweene the hangings that hung before the dore.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Whiles hee lurked close there, a common Souldiour chauncing to runne too and fro that way, espied his feete, and by earnest enquirie and asking who he was, hapned to take knowledge of him: who having drawne him forth of the place (when as for feare hee fell downe humbly at his feete and tooke hold of his knees) saluted him by the name of Emperour. From thence he brought him immediatly to his other fellow Souldiours, who as yet stoode wavering and wist not what to doe but fare and fume. By them was he bestowed in a Licter: and for that his owne servants were fled scattering heere and there they also by turnes one after another supported the said Licter upon their shoulders: and so was he brought into the (Prætorian) Camp, all sad and amazed for feare: pitied also by the multitude that met him on the way, as if some innocent had been haled to execution.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Being received within the trench and rampire, lodged he was alnight among the souldiours-watch with lesse hope of his a good deale than confidence. For the Consuls together with the Senate and the cohorts of the citie-souldiers, seized the Forum and the Capitol, with a purpose to claime and recover the common libertie: and when himselfe was sent for, by a tribune of the commons into the Curia to sit in consultation and give his advise about those matters that were thought good to be propounded, he made answere, That deteined he was perforce and by constraint.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>But the next morrow, when as the Senate grewe more colde and slacke in following and executing their foresaid projects, (by reason of their tedious trouble and discord who dissented in opinion) whiles the multitude also standing round about, demaunded by this time one Ruler and him by name, he called the Souldiours in armours<note place="bottom" n="3">Armatos, or armatus, i. himselfe armed.</note> to an assembly, and suffred them to take their oath of alleageance, and sweare to maintaine his imperiall dignity: therewith promised unto them 1500 Sesterces<note place="bottom" n="4">Quina dena Sestertia. See Josephus.</note> a peece: the first of all the Cæsars that obliged unto him <pb n="64" /> the Souldiours fealty by a fee and reward.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="11">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Having once established his Empire, hee thought nothing more deere and behovefull than to abolish the remembrance of those two daies, wherein there was some doubtfull question about the change and alteration of the State. Of all deedes and words therefore, which had passed during that time he made an Act there should be a generall pardon and perpetuall oblivion: which also hee made good and performed accordingly. Onely, some few Colonels and Centurions, out of that crew which conspired against Caius, he put to the sword: as well for example sake, as for that he had certaine intelligence, they required to have him also murdered.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Then presently turning and bending his minde to the duties of pietie and kindnesse, hee tooke up no forme of oath, either with more devout religion or oftener, than by the name of Augustus. He gave order, that for his Grandmother Livia, there should by Decree be graunted Divine honours; as also in the stately pompe of the Cirque Solemnities, a Chariot drawne with Elephants, like unto that of Augustus: semblably, for the soules of his owne parents departed, publick Dirges and Funerall feasts: and more than so, particularly in the honour of his father Cirque-Plaies and games every yeere upon his birth-day: and in memoriall of his mother, a coach to be led and drawne along through the Cirque: and the surname of Augusta, which by his Grandmother was refused.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>In remembrance of his brother<note place="bottom" n="1">Germanicus.</note> (to celebrate whose memoriall hee omitted no occasion) hee exhibited a Greeke Comædie at the solemne Games held in Naples: where, by sentence of the Umpiers and Judges he received a coronet therefore. Hee suffered not so much as M. Antonius to passe unhonoured, nor without a thankfull mention and remembrance: protesting one time, and that by an Edict, That so much the more earnest he was, to have men celebrate the Birth day of his father Drusus, because upon the same day, his Grandfather An-<pb n="65" />tonius also was borne. The Marble Arch, decreed verily in times past by the Senate to be erected for Tiberius<note place="bottom" n="1">His Unkle.</note> neere unto the Theater of Pompeius, but for let, hee finished. And albeit hee abrogated and repealed all the Acts of Caius, yet the day of his death, although it were the beginning of his Empire, he forbad to be registred among feasts in the Kalendar.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="12">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>But in honouring himselfe he was sparie, and caried a civile modestie. The fore-name of Emperour he forbare: excessive honours hee refused: the Espousals<note place="bottom" n="2">Or solemnity of nuptiall contract.</note> of his owne daughter, the birth-day also of his Nephew her sonne, he passed over in silence, onely celebrating it with some private ceremonie and religious complements within house. He restored no banished person, but by the authority and warrant of the Senate. That hee might bring with him into the Curia, the Capitaine of the Guard and Tribunes<note place="bottom" n="3">Colonels.</note> of the Souldiours: Item, that those Actes might bee ratified and stand in force, which his Procuratours had set downe in judging of causes, hee obtained by intreatie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>He made suite unto the Consuls for a licence, to hold Faires and Markets, for his owne private Manors and Lands. In Commissions and Examinations of causes held by the Magistrates, he would oftentimes be personally present and sit as one of the Commissioners. To the same Magistrates, when they exhibited any Plaies or Games, himselfe also with the rest of the multitude would arise up, and both with hand and voice<note place="bottom" n="4">By applause and acclamation.</note> doe them honour. When the Tribunes of the Commons repaired unto him before the Front of his Tribunall, he excused himselfe unto them, for that by reason of straight roome hee could not give audience unto them otherwise than standing upon their feete.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Therefore, within a small time hee purchased so much love and favour, as that when newes came (to Rome) that forlaied and slaine hee was in his journey to Ostia, the people in a great tumult and uprore, fell to banning and cursing both the Souldiours as Traitours, <pb n="66" /> and the Senate also as Paricides: neither ceased they thus to force against them, untill first one messenger, and then another, yea and soone after many more were produced by the Magistrates to the publick Rostra, who assured them that he was alive and approached homeward.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="13">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Yet continued hee not for all this secured every way from the danger of secret practises and wait-laying: but assailed hee was as well by private persons, as whole factions and conspiracies, yea and sore troubled in the end with civill warres. For there was a man, one of the Commons, taken about midnight neere unto his bed-chamber with a dagger. Found there were likewise twaine of the Gentlemens degree, in the open streete with a staffe having a blade in it<note place="bottom" n="1">Some cal this a Jacobs staffe.</note>, and a Hunters wood-knife waiting for him: the one to assault his person when he was gone forth of the Theater: the other as hee sacrificed at the temple of Mars.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Now there had conspired to make an insurrection and to alter the State, Gallus Asinius and Statilius Corvinus, the Nephewes of Pollio and Messalla the Oratours, taking unto them for their Complices many of his owne freed-men and servants. As for civile warre, kindled it was and begun by Furius Camillus Scribonianus, Lieutenant generall of Dalmatia: but within five daies quenched cleane and suppressed; by reason that the Legions, which had chaunged their oath of alleageance, in remorce of conscience and touch of religion repented, after that upon signification given<note place="bottom" n="2">Ominous and unlucky signes.</note> of a journey to their new Generall, neither the Ægles could bee dight and trimmed, nor the militarie ensignes plucked up and removed.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="14">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>To his first Consulship he bare foure more of which, the two former jointlie and immediatly one after another: the rest ensuing, with some time betweene, to wit, each one in the fourth yeere: and as for the third, hee had no precedent for it in any other Prince, as being substituted in the voide <pb n="67" /> place of a Consull deceased. A precise Justicer he was, ministring Justice, both when hee was Consull, and also being out of that Office, most painfully; even upon the solemne daies instituted for him and his: yea, and otherwhiles upon the auncient festivall daies and such as were religious. He followed not alwaies the prescript rule of lawes, moderating either the rigour or the lenity of penalties, by equity and reason, according as he stood affected to a cause: for, both unto those he restored their actions and gave leave to commense them a new, who in the Court before private Judges<note place="bottom" n="1">Of private matters, as Prætours and Centumvirs.</note> had once lost their suites, by claiming more than was due: and also, such as were convict of some greater deceite and cousenage, he condemned to be cast unto wilde beasts: exceeding therein the ordinarie punishment by law appointed.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="15">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Moreover, in the examination, triall, and deciding of controversies, he was wonderous variable: one while circumspect, wary, and of great insight: otherwhiles as rash and inconsiderate: now and then also foolish, vaine, and like to one without all reason. When hee reviewed upon a time the Decuries of Judges, and put whom hee thought good from their Jurisdiction: one of them, who had answered to his name, and concealed the immunity and priviledge that he had by the benefit of children, he discharged quite, as a man desirous to be a Judge<note place="bottom" n="2">And therfore, ambitious.</note>. Another of them being molested and called into question by his adversaries before him, as touching a matter betweene him and them, and pleading withall for himselfe, That it was a case to be tried not extraordinarily (by Cæsar) but by the common course of Law, and in an ordinary Court of deputed Judges: he compelled immediatly to handle and decide his owne cause before him: as who in his proper businesse should give proofe how indifferent a Judge he would be heereafter in the matter of another.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>There was a woman that would not acknowledge her owne sonne. Now, when by evidences and arguments alleadged pro et contra on both sides, the <pb n="68" /> question rested in equall ballance doubtfull, he awarded, that she should be wedded to the young man: and so forced her to confesse the truth and to take him for her child. Most ready he was to give judgement on their side, who made appearance in Court when their adversaries were absent: without any respect and consideration, whether a man slacked and staied by his owne default, or upon some necessitie. One cried out upon a forger of writings, and required, That both his hands might be cut off. Hee made no more a-doe, but forthwith called instantly, to have the hangman sent for, with his chopping knife and butchers block, to do the deed. There hapned one to be called judicially to the barre, For that being a forainer he bare himselfe as a Romaine Citizen: and when the advocates of both sides grew to some little variance about this circumstance, namely, Whether the party Defendant ought to make his answere and plead his owne cause in a gowne<note place="bottom" n="1">As a Citizen of Rome.</note> or a cloake<note place="bottom" n="2">As a forainer.</note>, he then, as if hee would make exceeding shew of pure and uncorrupt equitie, commaunded him to shift and change his habite often in the place, according as he was either accused or defended.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Moreover, sitting in judgement to decide a certaine controversie, when he had heard what could be said, hee pronounced sentence out of a written table, as it is verily thought, to this effect, That hee judged on their side, who had alleadged the truth. For which prankes hee became base and contemptible, in so much as every where, and openly he was despised. One, to excuse a witnesse<note place="bottom" n="3">Or deponent.</note>, whom Cæsar<note place="bottom" n="4">Claudius.</note> had called for out of a Province, alleadged in his behalfe, and said, Hee could not possibly come in time and be present, dissimuling the cause thereof a great while: at length, after manie long demaunds, what the reason might be, 'Why,' quoth hee, 'the man is dead at Puteoli.'</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Another when hee gave him thankes, for suffering a person accused to have the benefite of a triall and to bee defended, added more-over these wordes, 'And yet this is an usuall and ordinarie thing.' Furthermore, I my selfe have heard olde folke say, that these Lawyers and Barristers were <pb n="69" /> wont to abuse his patience so much, that as hee was going downe from the Tribunall<note place="bottom" n="1">Or judgement seat.</note>, they would not onely call upon him to come backe againe, but also take hold of his gowne lappet and skirt, yea and otherwhile catch him fast by the foote, and so hold him still with them. And that no man need to mervaile heereat, there was one of these Greeke Lawyers, who pleading before him hapned in earnest altercation to let fall these words, Καὶ συ γέρων εἰ καὶ μωρός, Thou art both old, and a foole besides. And verily it is for certaine knowne, that a Gentleman of Rome, accused before him for his obscene filthinesse and unnaturall abuse of women, (although untruly) as having an enditement framed against him by his enemies that were mighty: when he saw common strumpets cited and their depositions heard against him, flung his writing steele and the bookes which he had in his hand, with great ubraiding of him also for his foolishnesse and cruelty, even at his very face, so as he rippled and hurt therewith his cheeke not a little.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="16">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>He bare also the Censureship: an office that a long time had beene discontinued, after Paulus and Plancus the Censours: but even this very place he held with an uneven hand and as variable a minde, as the event and successe ensuing. In the review taken of Romaine Gentlemen, hee dismissed without shame and disgrace, a young man charged with many infamous villanies, howbeit one whom his owne father testified upon his knowledge and triall to bee right honest: saying withall, That he had a Censor of his owne.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>To another youth, who was in a very bad name for spoiling of maidens, and adulteries committed with wives, he did no more but give warning, either more sparily to spend him selfe in those young and tender yeeres of his, or else more warily at least-wise, to goe to worke: adding thus much beside, 'For why know I,' quoth hee, 'what wench thou keepest?' And when upon the intreaty of his familiar friends he had taken of the infamous note which was set upon the name of one, 'Well,' quoth he, 'let the blot yet <pb n="70" /> remaine still to be seene<note place="bottom" n="1">Litura tamen extet. Some read extat, i. yet the blot remaineth: meaning the filthines of the fact.</note>.' An honourable man and a principall personage of the Province Greece, howbeit ignorant in the Latine tongue, he not onely rased out of the ranke and roll of Judges, but also deprived of his freedom in Rome, and made him a meere alien. Neither suffred he any man to render an account of his life, otherwise than with his owne mouth, as well as every one was able, and without a patrone to speake for him. Hee noted many with disgrace, and some of them without their knowledge, as mistrusting no such thing: yea, and for a matter that had no precedent, namely, because without his privity and a pasport obtained they went forth of Italy: one also among the rest, for that in the Province he accompanied a King in his traine: alledging for example, that in his Auncestours daies Rabirius Postumus for following of K. Ptolomæus into Alexandria to save and recover the monie which he had lent him, was accused before the Judges, of Treason to the State<note place="bottom" n="2">For these matters would beare action.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Having assaied to put many more to rebuke with great imputation of the Inquisitours negligence, but with greater shame of his owne: looke whomsoever he charged with single life, with childlesse estate or poverty, those lightly he found guiltlesse, as who were able to prove themselves husbands, fathers, and wealthy. Certes, one there was, who being accused to have laied violent hands upon himselfe, and wounded his owne body with a sword, stript himselfe naked, and shewed the same whole and sound, without any harme in the world.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Many other Acts he did of speciall note whiles he was Censour as namely these: He commaunded a silver Chariot sumptuously wrought and set out to sale in the streete Sigillaria, for to be bought and broken all to peeces openly. Item, in one day he published 20 Edicts or Proclamations: and ij. among the rest: in the one whereof hee gave the people warning, That when their Vineyards bare Grapes plentifully, they should pitch<note place="bottom" n="3">Or enhuile.</note> their vessels very well within: in the other, he did them to understand, That there was nothing so good against the stinging of a Viper, as the juice of the Ughtree.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="17">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p><pb n="71" /> One expedition and no more hee undertooke, and that was very small. When the Senate had by Decree allowed him Triumphall ornaments, hee supposing that a bare title of honour was inferiour to the majestie of a Prince and Emperour, willing also to enterprise some exploit, whereby he might win the due glorie of a complet triumph, made choise before all other Provinces of Britaine; attempted by none since Julius (Cæsar) of famous memorie, and at that time in a tumultuous uprore, for that certaine revolts and rebels fled from thence, were not rendred.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>As he sailed from Ostia thitherward, twice had he like to have beene cast away and drowned, by reason of the strong blustring Southerne winde Circius, neere unto Ligaria, hard by the Ilands Stoechades<note type="annotation" n="a">These Ilands are situate in the mouth of the River Rhodanus¹: and they be so called of the order in which they lie.</note>. Having therefore travailed by land, from Massiles as farre as to the Cape Gessoriacum<note place="bottom" n="1">Where Calais standeth, or Bulloin, as som thinke.</note>, he crossed the seas from thence into Britaine: and in very few daies<note place="bottom" n="2">16 according to Dio.</note>, without battaile or bloudshed, part of the Iland yeelded to his devotion. So, in the sixth moneth after his first setting forth hee returned to Rome, and triumphed with most sumpteous pompe therefore prepared.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>To the sight of which Solemnitie, hee suffred not onely the Presidents and Governours of Provinces to have recourse into the Citie, but also certaine banished persons. And among the enemies Spoiles, hee set up a navall Coronet, and fastened it to the Finial of his house Palatine, hard by another civick guirland, in token and memoriall of the Ocean by him sailed over and subdued. After his triumphant Chariot rode Messallina his wife in a Coach: then followed those gallants also, who in the same warre had attained to triumphall ornaments: the rest went on foote and in their rich robes garded with purple: onely Crassus Frugi mounted upon a brave Courser trimly trapped<note place="bottom" n="3">Mounted likewise.</note>, and arraied himselfe in a triumphant mantle of estate, for that now twice hee had atchieved that honour.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="18">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p><pb n="72" /> Hee was at all times most carefull and provident for the Citie<note place="bottom" n="1">When so ever you read in Suetonius (City) absolutely, understand therby Rome: Kat exocheen: as one would say, The City of all Cities: an ordinarie phrase in other Romain writers: according as Virgil hath fitly expressed in this verse, Eclog. 1.: Urbem quam dicunt, Romam, etc.</note>, especially that the market might bee well served with victuals: what time, the Æmilian Ædifices (or Tenements) were on fire and continued still burning, hee remained two nights together in the place called Diribitorium: and when the multitude of Souldiours and household servants failed, hee called together by meanes of the Magistrates, the Commons of the Citie out of all the streetes and Parishes to come in and helpe, setting before him his chests full of money: exhorting them to doe their best for the quenching of the fire: and readie for to pay presently every one a good reward according to the paines hee tooke.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Now, when corne and victuals were growne very scarce, (such was the continuall unseasonable weather that brought barrainnesse) he was uppon a time in the middes of the market place<note place="bottom" n="2">Or Forum.</note> deteined by the multitude and so assayled and pelled what with reviling taunts and what with peeces of broken bread, that hardly and with much adoe he was able to escape, and no otherwise than by a posterne gate, unto the Pallace. Wherupon he devised all the means he possibly could to bring into the Citie provision of corne and victuals, even in the winter season. For, he not onely proposed certaine set gaines to all cornemasters, that would venture for graine, undertaking himselfe to beare all the losse that should happen unto anie of them by tempest: but ordained also great fees and availes for those that would builde ships for such traffique and merchandise, according to the condition and quality of each one:</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="19">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Namely for everie Romane Citizen exemption from the lawe Papia Poppæa: for enfranchised Latines, the freedome of Romane Citizens: and for women, the priviledge and benefit of those that had 4 children, which constitutions stand in force and be observed at this day.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="20">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p><pb n="73" /> Many works he finished, and those rather for greatnesse, huge, then for use, needfull. But the chiefe and principall were these: The conduit of water begun by Caius. Item a scluse<note place="bottom" n="1">Or Gott.</note> to let out and draine the lake Fucinus; and the haven at Ostia<note place="bottom" n="2">Or Pere.</note>: although he knew well enough, that the one<note place="bottom" n="3">The drawing of the lake Ficinus.</note> (of the twaine) Augustus had denied unto the Marsians who continually entreated him about it: and the other<note place="bottom" n="4">Alterum, i. the Pere at Ostia. But because there is no mention made in Julius Cæsars life of this Pere or haven, some read for Alterum in this place Cæterum: and then the word Alterum before, is meant of the second worke of these three, denied unto the Marsians, etc. Caterum, i. but intended oftentimes in the designement of Julius, etc.</note> intended oftentimes in the designment of Julius Cæsar of sacred memorie, was for the difficultie thereof layde aside. The two colde and plenteous fountaines of the water Claudia, of which the one beareth the name of Cæruleus, the other of Curtius or Albudinus<note place="bottom" n="5">Or heads.</note>, as also the new river of Anio<note place="bottom" n="6">Novi Anionis: some read novi opere, i. within new stonework.</note> he conveied and brought to Rome all the way, within stone-work: and then derived and devided the same into many and those right beautifull pooles<note place="bottom" n="7">Or Cisternes.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>He went in hand with the mere Ficinus in hope of gaine as well as of glorie: when some there were, who would have bound themselves in covenant and promise, to draine the sayd marrish at their owne private charges, in case the grounds being once made drie might be graunted unto them in free-hold. Now, for the length of three miles, partly by digging through the hill, and partly by hewing out the rocke before him, hee finished the channell at last with much adoe and after eleven yeares labour: albeit thirty thousand men were at worke continually about it and never rested between.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The Pere at Ostia beforesayd he made, by drawing an arme of the sea about, on the left and right hand both: and with all, at the mouth and entrance thereof, where now the ground lay deepe, raising an huge dam or pile against it. For the surer foundation of which pile, he drowned before hand that ship, wherein the great Obelisk had beene trans-<pb n="74" />ported out of Ægypt: and when hee had supported it with buttresses of many stones, hee planted aloft upon the same an exceeding high watch-towre to the patterne of that Pharus at Alexandria, to the end that by the fires burning there, in the night season, vessels at sea might direct their course.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

     <div type="chapter" n="21">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Esteeming so highly as he did of singing, he solemnized at Rome also againe the foresaid games called Neroneum before the day and time by order appointed<note type="numerical" n="6">Every fifth yeares.</note>. And when all the people called upon him for his celestial voice<note type="alphabetical" n="a">For, so would he have it to be called. And Thraseas Pætus was judicially convented, and deeply charged, because he had never offred sacrifice for that heavenly voice of his. Tacit.</note>, he made answere: That he verily would do them that pleasure (being so willing and desirous as they were to heare him): but it should be in his Hortyards. Howbeit, when the corps de guarde of the (Pretorian) Souldiers which at that time kept watch and ward seconded the praiers of the common people, willingly he promised to fulfill their minds out of hand in the very place; and without any farther delay caused his owne name to be written in the roll of other professed minstrels and singers to the harpe. Thus having put his lot into the pitcher with the rest, hee entred the stage when his turne came: and withall the Capitaines of the Guard supporting his harpe: after them the tribunes militarie, and close unto them his most inwarde friendes and Minions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Now when hee had taken up his standing, and ended his Proæme, he gave publike notice and pronounced by the voice of Cluvius Rufus, (no meaner man than of Consuls degree) that he would sing and act the storie of Niobe<note type="numerical" n="1">Wife of Amphion King of Thebes, who priding herself in her faire issewe 6 sonnes and as manie daughters durst compare with Latona, and prefer herselfe before her, who had but 2, Apollo and Diana. Whereupon they two, to wreke their mothers injurie, shot all the said children to death. Wherewith the mother halfe franticke for sorrow, was turned into a stone.</note>: and so continued hee well neere unto the tenth houre of the day<note type="numerical" n="2">Foure of the clocke after noone.</note>: which done he differred the Musicke Coronet due for the present victorie, and the residue of the games, unto the next yeare following; and all because he might have occasion oftener to chaunt.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="115"/> Hee sung moreover, disguised, Tragædies of the worthies and gods: of noble Ladies likewise in olde time and of goddesses, having their visards<note type="numerical" n="5">Or Masques.</note> framed and made to the likenesse of his own face and of some woman whom hee loved. Among the rest he chanted the tale of Canace travailing in child-birth<note type="alphabetical" n="b"><p>Who was with child by her owne brother Macareus, whereupon her father Æolus caused the childe new borne to be cast before hungrie dogs and sent a sword to his daughter to kill her selfe with.</p></note>: of Orestes who killed his own Mother<note type="alphabetical" n="c">In revenge of his father Agamemnons death, by her murdered, whereupon he fell into a furious kinde of deepe melancholie.</note>: of Edipus that plucked out his own eyes<note type="alphabetical" n="d">Who unwitting killed his owne father Laius, and as ignorantly wedded his owne mother Iocasta.</note>, and of Hercules enraged<note type="alphabetical" n="e">By putting on a garment next his skinne, envenomed with the poison of Nessus the Centaure, and so sent unto him as a token, from his wife Deianira.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="22">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Exceedingly given hee was of a boy to delight in horse-manship, and with the love of charioting mightily inflamed : and very much would he be talking (forbidden though he were) of the Circeian games. And one time as hee was making mone, and bewailing among his skoole-fellowes, the hard fortune of a chariot driver, one of the greene-coate faction, drawen and dragged by his steedes<note type="numerical" n="1">Or sore wounded and bruised with the wheeles running over him. See Plin. Nat. Hist. lib. 28 cap. 17.</note>, being chidden therefore by his schoole-master, he had a lye ready, and said that he spake of Hector<note type="numerical" n="2">Who was likewise, Raptatus Bigis as Virgil writeth.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="116"/> Soone after himselfe also would needs make one and be seene oftentimes to play the Chariotier. And when he had tryed what hee could doe, and performed, as it were, his first Actes in (private) hortyardes among verie slaves and the base commons, he proceeded to shew himselfe in the greatest Cirque in all mens eyes, appointing a certaine freed man of his to put out a white linnen cloth<note type="numerical" n="3">Mappam. To give the warning peece or token to start.</note> for a signall, from the place where Magistrates are wont to doe it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Those Cities and states where solemne gamings of musicke are usually held, had brought up a custome to sende all the Coronets of harpe-players unto him. This he accepted so kindly, that he not onely admitted at the very first to his presence the Embassadors who brought the same, but also placed them among his familiar guestes at the table. And being requested by some of them to sing at supper time, and highly praised with <pb n="117"/> excessive applause, he came out with this speech, That Græcians were the onely skilfull Hearers, and the men alone worthie of his studies. Neither would he deferre his journey thither but embarqued incontinently.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="23">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>After this, he went to all the games of prise, one after another: for even those that usually are celebrated at most remote and distant times he commanded to be reduced all into one yeare, and some of them also to be iterated<note type="numerical" n="3">Solemnized twice in the same yeare.</note>. At Olympia likewise hee caused, (contrarie to the manner and custome of that place) a game of musick to be held. And that he might not whiles he was thus busied, be called away or withdrawen by any meanes: when his freed-man Helius advertised him that the Citie affaires required his presence, he wrote backe unto him in these words, Howsoever your counsell to me, and your willing desire is, that I should returne with all speede: yet ought you to advise me rather and wish, that I may returne worthie of my selfe, that is to say, of Nero.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>All the while hee was singing, lawefull it was not for anye person to depart out of the Theatre, were the cause never so necessarie. Whereupon reported it is, that some great bellied women falling into travaile were delivered upon the very skaffolds : yea and many men besides, wearie of tedious hearing and praysing him, when the towne gates were shut, eyther by stealth leapt downe from the walles, or counterfeiting themselves dead were caried forth as corses to bee buried. But how timorously, with what thought and anguish of minde, with what æmulation of his concurrents and feare of the Umpiers, hee strove for the Mastery, it is almost incredible.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="118"/> His manner was to deale with his adversaries, as if they had beene but his equals and of the same condition: to ly in the wind for to catch advantage: to defame them under hand: otherwhiles to raile at them and give them hard words when he met them: yea and to corrupt with bribes<note type="numerical" n="1">Thereby to make them relent and not to do their best.</note> and giftes such as excelled in skill and cunning.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="24">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>During the time that hee strove for to winne any prise, so strictely obeyed hee the lawes of the game, that hee never durst once spit and reach up fleame: and the very swet of his forehead hee wiped away with his arme onely<note type="numerical" n="2">Or sleeve and not with anie handkercheife.</note>. Moreover in the acting of a Tragædie, when he had quickly taken up his staffe<note type="alphabetical" n="a">It may be thought, that he then acted Edipus or Creon or some other King, and therefore carried in his hand a regall staffe or Sceptre. Yet some interprete this of a Lawrel rod or braunch, such as Actors held in their hands while they sung.</note> againe, which he happened to let fall, being much dismaied and in great feare, least for that delinquent he should be put from the stage: by no meanes tooke he heart againe, until an under actor or prompter standing by sware an oth that it was not espied, for the shouts and acclamations of the people that were about him. Now, whensoever he wan the victorie, he used to pronounce himselfe victour. For which cause, he contended also in every place for the Criers coronet<note type="numerical" n="4">Due to him that had the lowdest voice.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="b">For, at Olimpia, were Games also of Criers, striving who could cry lowdest, for the prize. These were called Hieronica, as one would say, sacred victories, to witt at the solemne games in Greece, Nemea, Pythia, Istmia, and Olimpia.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="119"/> Furthermore, he ran with chariots for the best game in many places, and at the Olympicke solemnities with one that had a teeme of tenne steedes, notwithstanding he had in a certaine Poeme of his, reproved King Mithridates for the same. But being once shaken and hoisted out of his Chariot and set therein againe, howbeit not able to hold out, he desisted and gave over, before he had runne the race through. Yet was he crowned neverthelesse.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="25">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Beeing returned out of Greece hee entred Naples, mounted upon a Chariot drawne with white horses, through a breach in the wals made of purpose, (as the manner of all victors in those sacred games is). Semblably rode he into Antium, and from thence into Albanum and so forward into Rome. But he entred Rome in the very same Chariot, wherein sometime Augustus had rode in triumph, clad in a purple cloke<note type="numerical" n="1">Or Mantell.</note>, and the same garnished with starres embrodered in golde: wearing upon his head the Olympicke Coronet<note type="numerical" n="2">Made of the wilde Olive branches.</note>, and bearing in his right hand the Pythisk<note type="numerical" n="3">Of Lawrell.</note>...  not without a traine also of Applauders, following his Chariot, after the manner of those that ride ovant in petie Triumph<note type="alphabetical" n="a">Five thousand were there of these Gallants, as Xiphilinus writeth, ready to applaud him when he chaunted.</note> setting up a note, and crying with a lowde voice, That they were Augustians, and the souldiers of his triumph.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="120"/> As for the sacred Coronets and guirlands aforesayde, he bestowed them in his owne bed-chamber round about his beds: likewise his owne statues pourtraied in the habit of an harper<note type="numerical" n="1">Or Minstrell.</note>, and with that marke stamped he his money. And after all this, so far was he from letting slacke and remitting one jote his ardent studie of Musick, that for the preservation of his voice, he would never make speech unto his souldiers but by messages, or else having another to pronounce the same for him, when he was present himselfe: neither did he ought in earnest or mirth, without his Phonascus by, a governour of his voice, to put him in minde for to spare his wind and hold his handkercheife to his mouth. Unto many men he either offered his friendship or denounced enmitie, according as every one praised him more or lesse.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="26">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His unruly wildnesse, unbridled lust, wastfull riotousnesse, avarice and cruelty, he practised verely at first, by leasure closely, as the trickes of youthfull folly: yet so, as even then no man might doubt, that they were the inbred vices of nature, and not the errors of young age. No sooner was it twi-light and the evening shut in but presently he would catch up a capsa<note type="alphabetical" n="a">He meaneth eyther a peruke and cap of counterfait haire, Κόμας περιθέτους, Dioni thereby disguising himselfe: the same that in Caligula he termeth Capillamentum, or else some hood covering his head all save the eyes. Julius Capitolinus calleth it Cucullionem, wherewith the Emperour Verus played such parts by night, in imitation of Caligula and Nero.</note> on his head, and so disguised, goe into tavernes and victualling houses, and range sporting about the streetes, howbeit not without shrewd turnes and mischiefe. For he used to fall upon those that came late from supper and knocke them soundly; yea and if they struggled with him and made resistance, to wound them and drowne them in the sinkes and bogs: to breake into petie shops also, and rifle them: for he had set up in his house at home a faire<note type="alphabetical" n="b">Quintana was a Gate or Street rather in the Roman Campe, wherein was usually kept, Forum rerum utensilium, in resemblance whereof, he termed a certaine place in his house Quintana, in which he made sale of such wares and commodities, as he had gotten together by rifling and robbing.</note>, there to receive the price of the bootie which hee had gotten, and so was sold to who would give most and bid best for it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="121"/> But many a time at such brawles and skufflings aforesaied, he endangered his eyes, yea and his life too; being once beaten well neere to death by a certaine young gentleman of Senatours degree<note type="alphabetical" n="c">It appeareth by Tacitus, that this was Julius Montanus, who, albeit he had not sitten in counsell as Senator, yet was Laticlavius, and wore the Senators Robe. Such Gentlemen were called Iuvenes secundi ordinis, in distinction of those of the Imperiall bloud, or otherwise neere allied unto the Emperour.</note>, whose wife he had misused with uncleane handling. Whereupon, never after durst he goe abroad into the streets at that time of the night, without his Tribunes following him a farre off and secretly. In the day time also, being closely caried in a chaire into the Theater, he would be present in person, and out of the upper part of the proscene<note type="numerical" n="1">Where he might directly sit and looke downe upon the stage.</note> looking downe give a signall to the seditious factions of players, and animated them. Now when they were come once to plaine battell, and fought with stones and peeces of broken seats, himselfe flung many among the people, and with one brake the head of a Prætor.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="27">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>But as his vices grewe by little and little to get head, he laide aside these wilde trickes by way of sport and in secret : and without all care of concealing and dissimuling the matter, broke out openly to greater outrages.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>His meales hee drewe out at length<note type="alphabetical" n="a">The manner was in old time to imploy the day in businesses, and therein to take no liberall meales, putting off the full refection, and cherishing of the bodie untill night. Convivia de die, argued Intemperance, much more then feasting from noone to midnight.</note>: eating and drinking from noone to midnight, foveting and cherishing himselfe oftentimes in hote baines, and in sommer season in bathes cooled with snowe. His suppers hee tooke divers times abroade also in publike place, to wit, in the Naumachia<note type="numerical" n="5">A broad place, wherein a Naval fight had sometime been exhibited. Read Tacit. annal lib. 15.</note> shut up and enclosed, or else in the Mars field, where hee was served and attended upon by all the common Queanes of the Citie, and stinking strumpets of the stewes<note type="alphabetical" n="b">Ambubaiarum. These tooke their name (as most expositors have conjectured), Quod circa Baias versarentur. Yet some learned men of later time fetch the same from this Syriacke word Anbubaicæ, as if such were Syrian women, who being otherwise naughtie packes and callots, gat their living also by playing upon certaine instruments of musike, which they brought with them out of their native countrey. Copas imitantium. Although Copæ, properly be such women as keepe victualling houses, readie not onely to entertaine, but also to invite and call in guestes, yet because these commonly are verie bold and unshamefaced, this terme goeth indifferently for strumpets and curtesans. For seldome shall a man see an impudent woman that is not withall incontinent, so inseparably is modestie joyned with Chastitie.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="122"/> His manner was also to give warning unto his familiar friends, and bid him selfe to supper: and one of them it cost in sweet meats<note type="alphabetical" n="c">The corrupt text in this place hath given occasion of much obscuritie, and ministred matter enough for Criticks to worke upon, while some read Mellita, others Myrtitrichila. By which are ment certaine sweat junkets, as daintie wafers, etc.</note> 4 millians<note type="numerical" n="1">Quadragies HS.</note> of sesterces<note type="alphabetical" n="d">This may be thought incredible, that banqueting conceits at one sitting should cost so much, and the aspersion of rose-water or other odoriferous liquors arise to more. Where is to be noted the observation of some, who for ab Syrtio rosaria read aspersio rosaria, that is to say, the artificiall besprinkling and aromatizing (as I may so say) of banqueting rowmes, out of spouts and pipes, conveying odoriferous waters and oyles, going under the name of Rosaria. Which spouts, if they were made of silver or gold, (as we read they were at the feast of Otho, when he gave Nero entertainment) might soone amount to that somme. To say nothing of the costly compound distilled waters, or extracts and oyles, themselves, drawen out of most pretious simples and spices.</note>: and another a good deale more in rose water and odoriferous oyles.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="28">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Over and besides the unnaturall abusing of boyes free-borne, and the keeping of mens wives as his concubines, he forced also and defloured Rubria, a vestale Virgin. Acte a freed woman he went very neere to have wedded as his lawefull wife<note type="numerical" n="2">Which had beene a great disparagement.</note>, suborning certaine men who had beene Consuls, to sweare and forsweare that shee was borne of King Attalus his royal bloud. A boy there was named Sporus<note type="alphabetical" n="a">Him he called, as other Authors write, Sabbina and Poppæa, after the name of his wife deceased.</note>, whose Genitories he cut out, and assayed therby to transforme him into the nature of a woman. Him he caused to be brought unto him as a bride, with a dowry, in a fine (yellow) veile, after the solemne maner of mariage, not without a great traine and much pompe: whom he maintained as his wife. Touching which Sporus, a pretie and merrie conceited speech of a certaine person is still currant, That it had been speeded well with the world, if Domitius his father had wedded such a wife.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>This Sporus, trimmed and set out with the abiliments of the Empresses, he caried about with him in his owne litter, both through the streets and markets of all Corporations in Greece, and also at Rome, in the Sigillaria<note type="numerical" n="3">A street in Rome where such wares were to be sold.</note>, kissing him other-whiles as they rode together. For, that he had a lust to ly with his owne mother, and was frighted from it by some depraving backe-friendes of hers; for feare, least the proude and insolent dame might by this kind of favour grow too mightie, no man ever made doubt: especially after that he had entertained among his concubines a certaine strumpet, most like in all points unto Agrippina.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="29">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>As for his owne body, certes, he forfeited the honour thereof, prostituting it to bee abused so farreforth, as having defiled in-manner all the parts of it, at the last, he devised a kind (as it were) of sport and game: that being covered all over in a wilde beastes skin, hee should be let loose forth of a cage<note type="numerical" n="1">Or grate. I wish that both Suetonius and Dio had in this place and such like been altogether silent.</note> and then give the assault upon the privities of men and women both as they stood tyed fast to a stake: and when he had shewed his rage to the full, be killed, forsooth by Doriphorus<note type="alphabetical" n="a">In other writers he is named Pythagoras, so that it should seeme he caried two names.</note> his freed-man, unto <pb n="123"/> whom him selfe also was wedded like as Sporus unto him: insomuch as hee counterfeited the noise and cries of maidens, when they bee forced and suffer devirgination<note type="numerical" n="2">Confessed of themselves and their owne accord.</note>. I have heard of divers that he was fully perswaded, No man nor woman was honest, or in any part of their bodies pure and cleane: but cloaked their uncleannesse onely, and craftily hid it. And therefore to such as freely confessed unto him their obscene filthinesse, he forgave all other faults and iniquities whatsoever.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="30">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>The fruite of richesse and use of money, he tooke to be nothing else but lavish expense: thinking them to be very base niggards and mechanicall pinch-pennies, that kept any account or reckoning what they spent and layde out: but those onely right noble and brave gallants, who unthriftily wasted and confounded all. Neither praised hee or admired he his uncle C. Caligula for any thing so much as this, that in so short a time hee had spent downe to the bare pomeall that huge masse of wealth, which Tiberius left behind him. Knowing therefore no meane nor end of prodigalitie, he dealt and spent upon his favorites most excessive summes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Hee allowed unto Tiridates<note type="alphabetical" n="a">A great Magician, whom he intertained thus royally, because he would have learned magicke of him. See Plinie.</note> (a thing almost incredible) 800000 Sesterces, day by day, for his expenses, and at his departure bestowed upon him not so little as one hundred milians. Unto Menecrates the harper and Spicillus the fencer he gave the livelode and houses of men that had triumphed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p><pb n="124"/> No garments did hee on his backe twice: at hazard when he played, he ventured no lesse than 400000 sesterces at a cast, upon every point or pricke of the chaunce<note type="numerical" n="1">Quadringenis Sestertiis. Take Sestertium here in the newter gender, of which 400000 make of our money about 3125 pound, which in four cast he might hap to loose.</note><note type="alphabetical" n="b">Whereas Augustus when he played at this game, ventured no more, than for everie Talus, which were foure in all, a single denier. For it should seeme that the game of Tali heere mentioned, was Pleistobolinda, i. who could throw most with four Tali, whether the same were cockall bones in deed, or made of gold, silver or Ivorie, with foure sides, everie one representing a chaunce, an Ace or unitie and sise, a trey and quatre, opposite, one unto the other. For they wanted deux and cinque, which the Tessera Cubus, or Die carying six faces, hath.</note> Hee fished with a golden net<note type="numerical" n="2">Aurato rete. Orosius saith more expresly, retibus aureis.</note> (drawen and knit) with cords twisted of purple and crimsen silke in graine. He never ordinarily journed with fewer than a thousand caroches drawen with mules. His mules were shod with silver. His mulitiers arraied in fine (red) Canusme cloth: and attended he was with a multitude of Mazaces and Curreurs gaily set out with their bracelets and riche Phalers<note type="alphabetical" n="d">It is evident hereby, as also out of that verse of Juvenal, Ut læti phaleris omnes et torquibus omnes, that these Phaleræ were not Trappings and furniture belonging to horses, but some other ornaments, wherewith footmen and horsemen both were trimly decked.</note>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="31">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In no one thing was hee more wastefull and prodigall then in building. Hee made an house, that reached from the Palatium to the Esquiliæ: which at first he called his Transitorie: but when it had been consumed with fire and was reedefied hee named his golden ædifice. As touching the large compasse and receit, the rich furniture and setting out thereof, it may suffice to relate thus much. The porch was of such an heigth as therein might stand upright the geant-like image representing his owne person, an hundred and twentie foote high. So large was this house, as that it conteined three galleries of a mile a peece in length<note type="numerical" n="6">Porticus triplices milliarias. If a man expound it thus: Galleries with three rows of pillers, a mile long, it wold be more consonant to the truth I suppose.</note>. Semblably, a standing poole like unto a sea, and the same enclosed round about with buildings in forme of Cities. It received moreover, rurall tractes, medowes, vinyards, pastures, and woods, replenished with a multitude of tame and wilde beastes of all kindes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p><pb n="125"/> In all other parts thereof, all was laide over with golde, garnished with precious stones and shels of pearle<note type="numerical" n="1">Mother of pearle.</note>. As for the parlours, framed they were with enbowed roufs, seeled with frets of Ivorie, devided into panils, which might turne about and let fall downe floures, and out of pipes shed forth sweet oiles from aloft. But of al these parlours and banqueting roomes, the principall and fairest was made rounde, to turne about continually both day and night, in manner of the World<note type="numerical" n="2">Or heaven.</note>. The baines within this house were continually supplied with salt water from the Sea, and rowghish water from the springs of Albula. This edifice thus finished, when hee came to dedicate and consecrate, hee liked it so well, that he commended it thus far forth, as to say, He now at length began to live like a man.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Furthermore, hee began a poole<note type="numerical" n="4">Piscinam.</note> reaching from Misenum to the Meere<note type="numerical" n="5">(Or lake.)</note> Avernus, cloystered and roofed all over, into which he might turne all the hote waters that were in the bathes of Baiæ. Likewise hee went about a Fosse or ditch, from the said Avernus unto Ostia, thereby to travell by water in shippes, and yet never be on the sea: in length 160 miles: and so broade, as five galleys with three bankes of Ores a peece, might passe in front one by another. For the performance of these workes, hee gave order, That all prisoners round about from every place should be convayed into Italie; and that no person convict of any wicked act, should in other manner bee condemned, but to these workes.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="32">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>To these outragious expenses, beside the trust and confidence he had in the revenewes of the Empire, put forward hee was upon a certaine unexpected hope also that he <pb n="126"/> conceived, of finding a world of wealth. And that by the intelligence given unto him of a Romane Knight, who assured him, that the rich treasure and old store of silver and gold both, which Queene Dido flying out of Tyros caried away with her, lay buried in Affricke within most huge and vaste caves: and might bee gotten out with a little labour.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>But when this hope failed him, and came to nothing, being altogether destitute and behind hand, so as he was hardly able to yeeld full pay unto the Souldiers, and exhibit the benefits due unto the olde servitours, he bent his mind to promoting of false imputations, to pilling also and polling. Before hee first established this order, That out of the goods of freed-men deceased, insteede of the one halfe, hee should exact five parts of sixe, if without good cause they bare the name of any family into which himselfe was engraffed<note type="numerical" n="1">Namely the Claudian or Julian.</note>. Afterwards, that their wils should be forfaite and confiscate, who were unthankeful to the Prince<note type="numerical" n="1">Remembred him not in their wils and made him not an heyre.</note>. Also, that the Lawyers who drew and wrot such wils, should not scape fine and punishment. Furthermore, that all words and deedes, whereby there was any waight to bee gotten by the law, should bee brought within the compasse of high Treason. Hee called in also the rewards and donatives, which he had given unto any Cities.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>And whereas hee had prohibited the use of the Amethist<note type="numerical" n="2">Or violet in graine.</note> and purple colours, he suborned one of purpose under hand to sell upon a market day<note type="numerical" n="3">Or faire.</note> some few ounces therof, and so shut up the shoppes of all the Marchants and occupiers therabouts. More then so, having espied once as he was singing a dame of the citie in the stage<note type="numerical" n="4">Among the beholders.</note> arrayed in purple, he pointed at her (as it is verily thought), and shewed her to his Procurators: who presently haled her downe, and stript her, not of her garment onely, but also of her goods and lands.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p><pb n="127"/> To conclude, he robbed the Temples of many giftes and oblations: the Images likewise therein made of golde or silver he melted into a masse: and among the rest, even those of the Tutelar gods<note type="numerical" n="3">Apollo, Neptune, Jupiter, Juno, Minerva.</note> (of Rome) : which soone after Galba restored and erected againe in their places.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="33">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>As touching his Parricides and murders hee began them first with Claudius: of whose death although he were not principall author, yet he was privie and accessarie thereto. Neither dissimuled he so much, as who afterwards was wont by a Greek by-word, to praise mushromes, (in which kinde of meat Claudius had taken his bane), as the foode of the gods<note type="numerical" n="5">θεῶν βρῶμα, alluding to the deification after his death.</note>. For, in scoffing wise he would say of him that hee had left now moraria<note type="alphabetical" n="a">In this verbe Morari, there is couched a double sense, which gives the grace unto this pleasant scoffe. For, being a meere Latin word, and having the first sillable by nature short, it signifieth, to stay or to make long abode: and taking it thus, Nero might be thought to imply thus much, that Claudius was now departed out of the companie of mortall men, and raunged among the heavenly wights. But take the same word, as Nero spake it, derived of μῶρος in Greeke, which signifyeth, A foole, and hath the first syllable long, it importeth, that Claudius played the foole no longer here in the world among men. Read the little pamphlet of Seneca entituled ἀποκολοκήντωσις, if ye would see Claudius depainted in his colours, and in a fooles coat: which he, as it may appeare, composed of purpose to gratifie Nero in that humour of his.</note> anie longer among mortall men, using the first sillable of the sayd word long. Many a time also he threw out many by-words and invectives against him, blaming his folly and cruelty: for hee would say, that he left off among men morari, staying upon the first sillable. Finally, he neglected the place of his funerall fire<note type="alphabetical" n="b">The Greekes call this Κανστραν οι τύβον. And the Romans in honour of their Princes, were wont to compasse the same all about with a wall of flint, or other durable stone, as marble.</note>: suffering it to be empaled<note type="numerical" n="7">As the manner was for certaine daies before the ashes and reliques were gathered up.</note>, but with sleight stuffe and low railes of timber.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>As for Britannicus, not so much for envie that he had a sweeter and better voice than himselfe, as for feare least sometime or other hee should bee preferred before him in the good grace and favour of the people, in the respect of his fathers memorie, he attempted to make him away by poison. This poison, Nero had received at the hands of one Locusta, a finder out of divers receipts, and a witnesse deposing against him. <pb n="128"/> Now when shee alleaged for her excuse that she gave him the lesse dose<note type="numerical" n="1">In quantitie.</note>, thereby to colour and cloke the odious fact... 'Why! then belike,' quoth he, 'I am affraide of the lawe Julia<note type="numerical" n="2">De Veneficiis. For her former practise of poisoning, by which she stoode condemned.</note>.' And so hee forced her before his face in his owne bed-chamber to compound and seeth a poison that should be most quicke and of present operation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Which done, he tryed it upon a kidde: and when the beast lingred 5 howres before it died, he caused the said potion to be boiled againe, and many times put his owne thereto. Then he offred it to a pigge; and seeeing it die presently upon the taking thereof, he commaunded it should be brought into the dining chamber, and given unto Britannicus as he sate at supper. No sooner had he tasted it but hee fell downe dead. Nero made no more adoe, but lying then as hee did, told the guestes, It was the falling sicknesse, wherewith he useth to bee caught. But the morrow after, he buried him in all hast, with meane and base obsequies, and in an outragious storme of raine. Unto this Locusta, for her paines, he gave a pardon and franke seidge<note type="numerical" n="4">Lands by patent without rent.</note> in the countrey: yea, and put unto her for to be taught, certaine schollars.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="34">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His owne mother, for looking narrowly into him, and examining his words and deedes somewhat streightly: for seeming also to correct and reforme the same, hee stomaked so much, that oftentimes he strained and wrung her with odious and bitter words: yea, and brought her to that passe, that shee was faine to depart his house, and retire into a private <pb n="129"/> place of her owne. Thus, for an amendment, he added one disgrace more unto another, withdrawing from her all honour, withdrawing the guarde of Souldiers, and the watch of Germans from her attendance. Furthermore, he forbad her his own company, and thrust her out of the Palatium. Passing from these indignities, he left no meanes unassayed to vexe and disquiet her: suborning some, who whiles she lay in Rome should daily trouble her with sutes and actions: and when she was retired for her rest into the country, other, who coasting as they went both by land and sea, should abuse her with reviling tauntes, and skoffing reproches. Pretending that he was about to resigne up the Empire and depart to Rhodes<note type="numerical" n="1">As if she were the cause therof.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>But beeing terrified with her threats and violent shrewdnesse, hee determined to kill and dispatch her at once. Having attempted it with poison thrice, and perceiving that she was defenced with preservatives, he provided a bed-chamber for her, with so ticklish an arched roufe over her head, as beeing easily unjoincted, the frame thereof might fall in peeces in the night, and light upon her as she lay a sleepe. When this designe was bewrayed and defeated by the complices that were privie thereto, he devised a pinnace that should be easily undone and floted, that either by the shipwracke, or by the fall of the cabbine aloft she might quickly perish. And so, making a semblance of a Love-day and reconciliation, hee sent for her by most sweet and kinde Letters, training her unto Baiæ, there to celebrate with him the solemnity of the Quinquatrian<note type="numerical" n="3">A feast in the honour of Minerva, beginning five daies before the Ides of March, i. the 11 of March.</note>. And having given order before hand to certaine Maisters of Gallies for to split the Foist<note type="numerical" n="4">Or Pinnace.</note> wherein she was embarqued (as if by chaunce they had runne against her), he put unto her the other abovesaid made with joints and vices, and protracted the <pb n="130"/> time of his feast until it was late in the night. Then at her returne unto Bauli, in liew of her owne which was broken, he offred her the said peecemeale barke, accompanied her (to the water side<note type="numerical" n="1">Or to the staires.</note>) and at the parting also kissed her paps.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The rest of that night he watched, with great trembling and feare, waiting for the event of his enterprise. But when he understood that all went crosse, and that she was escaped to land by swimming, being at his wits end and to seeke what he should doe, upon the sodaine comming of Lucius Agerinus her freed-man, by whom she sent him word with great joy, that she was both alive and safe, he slily conveied a skeane into the hand of the said Agerinus: and immediately catching him with the maner (as if he had beene suborned and hired by her to assassinate him) caused the said Agerinus to be apprehended and bound with chaines: and withall, his mother aforesaid, to be murdred, that he might give it out, she had made her selfe away, for that her treachery was detected.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>Hereunto are added matters of a more hideous and feareful nature, by the report of men upon their credit: namely, that he came to see his mother when she was dead: that he felt and handled all the parts of her naked bodie: that he found fault with some, and commended others: and taking a thirst upon it, dranke his liquor. Yet could he not either for the present or ever after, endure the worme and sting of conscience for this foule fact, but confesse many a time, that haunted and harried he was with the apparition of his mothers ghost: tormented also with the scourges and burning torches of the Furies. Which was the cause that with a sacrifice made by the direction of Magicians, he obeied and called up her spright, and humbly besought her to release him of his paines. Verily as hee travailed through Greece, at the sacred Eleusine ceremonies<note type="alphabetical" n="a">It may be it was in the same forme, that Justinus Martyr citeth out of Orpheus: θύρας δ᾽ ἐπίθεσθε βεβήλος. Fortes opponite profanis. Which Virgil in some sort hath expressed thus: Procul este profani. And Claudian after him: Gressus removete profani.</note>... he durst not be present, when the cryer made a publike proclamation, That all wicked and ungodly persons should depart from thence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>To this parricidy of his mother, he adjoyned also the murder of his aunt<note type="numerical" n="4">Domitia by his fathers side.</note>. <pb n="131"/> For, finding her sore sicke in her bed, and feeling her pulse, when she as old folkes are wont to doe, soothingly flattered him, and saied, Let me once see the day that I may receive the mosse growing upon your chin<note type="numerical" n="1">i. your first beard downe.</note>, and then I care not if I die: he turning unto those that stood by, with a mocke, saied he would cause it to be taken off streight waies: and so commaunded the Physicians to give her a purgative more than ordinary. For, even before she was through dead, he laide sure hold of her goods, and suppressed her last wil that nothing might escape his clutches.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="35">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Besides Octavia, he maried afterwards two wives: to wit, Poppæa Sabina the daughter of one who had beene Questor, and the wedded wife before of a romane Knight : then, Statilia Messallina, neice<note type="numerical" n="8">In the right line of descent.</note> in the third degree removed of Taurus, twice Consul, who had once triumphed. For to have and enjoy her, he murdred her husband Atticus Vestinus then Consul, even during the time of that honorable Magistracie. Soone wearie he was of Octaviæ's companie and forsooke her bed. And when some friends reproved him for it he made answere, that the jewels els and ornaments only of a wife ought to content her.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Soon after, when he had assayed many times (but in vaine) to strangle her, he put her away, pretending she was barraine.  But when the people misliked this divorse, and forbare not to raile upon him for it, he proceeded, even to confine and banish her quite. In the end he murdred her, under a colourable imputation of divers adulteries, charged upon her so impudently and falsely, that when al generally who were by torture examined upon the point, stood stoutly to the very last in deniall, he suborned and brought in Anicetus<note type="numerical" n="10">Who had brought him up in his childhood.</note> his own Pædagogue against her, who should slander himselfe with her and confesse that by a wile he had abused her bodie.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>The twelfth day after the said divorcement of Octavia, he espoused and maried the aforesaid dame Poppæa, whom he loved intirely; and yet even her also he killed with a kicke<note type="numerical" n="1">Or spurne.</note> of his heele, for that, being big with child and sickly withall, she had reviled him and given him shrewd words, for comming home so late one night, after his running with chariots. By her he had a daughter named Claudia Augusta, whom he buried when she was a very infant.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="4">
          <p>There was no kinde of affinitie and consanguinity were it never so neere, but it felt the waight of his deadly hand. Antonia, the daughter of Claudius, refusing after the death of Poppæa to bee his wife, he slew, under a pretense as if she went about to conspire against him and to alter the state. Semblably, he killed all the rest, that were either allied unto him or of his kinred. Among whom was A. Plautius a young gentleman... against whom he offered force by way of unaturall pollution, before he put him to death... </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="5">
          <p>His Preceptor and Schoole-master Seneca he compelled to dye: albeit he had sworne unto him very devoutely, oftentimes making sute to depart the Courte, and yeelding up all his wealth into his handes, That he had no cause to suspect him: for he would rather lose his owne life then doe him anie hurt. Unto Burrhus, Captaine (of the guarde) he promised a medicine to heale his swollen throat<note type="numerical" n="1">A squinancie.</note>, and sent him the rank poison Toxicum for it. Free men of his own, that were rich and olde, whose favor, helpe and advise had been the chiefe meanes of his advancement to the Empire, he tooke away by poyson, partly mixt in their meates, and partly in their drinke.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="36">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>At the headlesse report and flying newes of some treason that should bee practised against him, he was so affrighted, that hee went about to lay downe his Imperiall dignity. By occasion, that one (as I related before) was taken with a weapon upon him, about his person as hee sacrificed, in all hast he sent out the Bedels and called the Senate together: before whom, with teares and loude out-cries hee bewailed his owne piteous case, as who no where could make account of any safety: and thereupon for a long time forbare to come abroad. His affectionate love also to Messallina, most fervent though it were he renounced and cast cleane from her, not so much for any indignity of the dishonourable wrongs she offred unto him, as upon very feare of daunger, as fully perswaded that shee practised to bring the Empire into Silius the Adulterers hands. At which time in a great fright he fled in shamefull manner to the camp, asking and enquiring all the way nothing else, but whether the Empire remained still safe to his behoofe.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="37">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>There arose no suspition, there came forth no Author so light and vaine, but gave him a bone to gnaw upon, and put no small toyes in his head: wherby he was forced to beware and seeke revenge. One of those, that had a matter depending in Court before him, taking him a side, when hee came by way of salutation to doe his duty, avowed unto him, that he dreamed, How hee was killed by one. Then within a while after, the same party, (as if he had now taken knowledge who that one was that should murder him) pointed unto his owne adversarie, even as hee tendered a supplication unto Claudius, and said, 'This is he.' Whereupon immediatly apprehended he was, and haled to execution.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>After the semblable manner by report, came Appius Silanus to his death. For, when Messallina and Narcissus had conspired to worke his overthrow and finall destruction, they complotted thus, that Narcissus betimes in a morning before day light rushed like a man amazed and astonied into the bedchamber of his Patrone (Claudius) relating unto him his dreame, namely that Appius had laid violent hands upon him: and Messallina for her part, composing and framing her selfe as if shee wondered greatly thereat, reported, How shee likewise had seene already the same vision for certaine nights together. And not long after this, word came, (as it was before agreed betweene them) that Appius was comming to rush in among them: who in deed had beene bidden the day before to be present at the same instant. Whereupon, as if the said dreame had now proved true and beene plainly represented in effect, order was given for Appius, to be endited, arraigned, and to suffer death. Neither doubted Claudius the morrow after to report the whole storie and the order thereof unto the Senate: and withall to give thanks unto his freedman<note place="bottom" n="1">Narcissus.</note>, for being so vigilant and watchfull in his very sleepe for his sake.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="38">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Being privie to himselfe of passionate anger<note type="annotation" n="a">Iræ atque Iracundiæ. The manner is of this Author throughout his story to set those points downe first in a word, whereon he meaneth to stand, and then in order to particularize presently upon them. By which method of his, it appeareth in this place, that hee meaneth by Ira, the momentarie passion of anger, which we call heat and choler, soone up and as soone downe, quickly kindled and as quickly quencht: by Iracundiæ, the habite of inveterat wrath continuing still untill revenge be had: which we call malice and rancour. Howsoever our modern Lexicographers have in their Dictionaries put downe the contrary.</note> and bearing malice, he excused them both in an Edict, distinctly promising that the one of them verily should be but short and harmlesse, the other not unjust nor causelesse.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Having sharply rebuked the men of Ostia, because they had not sent boats and barges to meet him as he came upon the river Tiberis: and that in such odious termes as these, That he was now become base and abject in their eies: all on a suddaine, he pardoned them upon the submission and readinesse to make satisfaction. Some there were, whom in the very open street he thrust from him with his own hand, comming unto him somewhat out of season. Semblably he confined and banished the Court a Scribe who had been Questour: a Senatour likewise that had born the Pretureship, both of them without their cause heard and altogether guiltlesse, for that the one pleading in Court as an Advocate against him when he was a private person, had caried himselfe not so modestly as he should: and the Senatour in his Ædileship had amerced and fined certaine tenants of his dwelling upon his lands, for selling boiled meats contrary to the law expresly forbidding so to do: and withall whipped his Bailife comming betweene (to intercede for them).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>For which cause also, he tooke from the Ædiles their authority to punish the disorder of those that kept Tavernes and victualing houses. But as touching his owne foolishnes, he concealed it not, but gave it out and protested in certaine short orations, That he counterfaited himselfe a foole for the nonce during Caius daies; because otherwise he should not have escaped, nor attained to that (imperiall) place which hee aimed at and was now entred upon. Howbeit, he could not make the world beleeve so much, untill there was a book put forth within a short time after, entituled μωρῶν ἀνάστασις, i. The resurrection (or Exaltation) of fooles. The argument and matter whereof was, That no man faigneth folly.<note n="b">
            <p>These words without all rime or reason were rife in his mouth, which unadvisedly he had taken up, and by use could not leave them. </p>
        </note></p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="39">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Among other thinges, men wondered at him for his oblivion and unadvisednesse, or (that I may expresse the same in Greeke) his μετεωρίαν καὶ ἀβλεψίαν, i. his grosse over-sight or forgetfulnes, and inconsiderate blindnes. When Messallina was (by his owne commaundement) killed, within a while, after he was set in his dining parlour hee asked why his Lady<note place="bottom" n="1">Or Mistres of the house, Domina Grace, δέσποινα.</note> came not. Many of those whom he had condemned to death, the very morrow immediatly after, he commaunded to have warning both to sit in counsell with him, and also to beare him company at Dice-play: yea, and by a messenger chid and checked them as drowsie and slothfull for staying so long and making no better hast.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>Being minded to take Agrippina to wife against all law of God and man, he ceased not in all his speech to call her, his daughter<note place="bottom" n="2">And in deede he was her Unkle.</note> and nourceling: to give out also, That she was borne and brought up in his bosome. Having a purpose to admit Nero into the very name of his owne house and family, as if he had not incurred blame enough already for adopting (him) his wives son, having a naturall sonne of his owne who was now of ripe yeeres, he eft-soones divulged, That never any one had beene by adoption inserted or incorporate into the family of the Claudii.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="40">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>He shewed oftentimes so great negligence and carelesnes what he said or did, that he was thought not to know nor consider, either who made any speech, or among whom, or at what time, and in what place? When there was some question and debate about Butchers and Vintnars, he cried out in the Senate house, 'I beseech you, my Maisters, who is able to live without a little piece or morsell of flesh?' and withall described the abundance of the olde Tavernes, from whence himselfe also in times past was wont to bee served with wine.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>As touching a certaine Questour, who was a Candidate of his and by him recommended: among other reasons why he favoured him, he alleadged this, Because his Father had quickly and in due time given him lying sick, cold water to drinke. Having in the Senate brought in a woman to depose, 'This,' quoth he, 'was my mothers freed woman, and she that kept her ornaments, and used to deck and dresse her: but she alwaies tooke me for her Patrone. This have I,' quoth he, 'delivered of purpose because there be some yet in mine house, who think me not to be her Patron.'</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Moreover, sitting upon the Tribunall, when he was in a great chafe, and the men of Ostia requested at his hands (I wot not what) in the name of their towne, he cried out aloud, That he knew nothing wherefore he should oblige them unto him: 'And if any man else,' quoth he, 'I also am free and at mine owne liberty.' As for these words of his which now I will relate, they were rife in his mouth daily, yea every houre and minute therof: 'What doest thou take me for Theogonius and λογιώτατος?'<note n="a">
            <p>Some thinke, that he devised not new letters in the Alphabet, but new formes rather of the former: as namely to write for the Æolick digamma F the inverted character, and for dipthong, ai. </p>
        </note> beside many such foolish termes, not beseeming private persons, much lesse a Prince, otherwise not uneloquent nor unlearned: nay, rather one eagerly given to his booke, and a great Student in the liberall Sciences.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="41">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>In his youth, he attempted to write an Historie, exhorted thereto by Titus Livius; and having the help besides of Sulpitius Flavus. And when he put the same first to the triall and judgement of men in a frequent auditorie, hardlie and with much a-do he read it through, being often in the while coldly heard, by an occasion that himselfe gave. For, when, (as hee began his reading) there was set up a laughter, by reason that many of the seates brake with the weight of a certeine corpulent and fat swad, he was not able to hold, no not after the tumult appeased, but eftsoones ever and anon call to minde that accident and fall afresh to unmeasurable laughing.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>During his Empire likewise, hee both wrote much and also rehearsed the same continually by his reader. The beginning of his foresayd historie he tooke from the time presently ensuing the murder of Cæsar Dictator: but hee passed over to the latter dayes: and began againe at the civill pacification: perceiving that it was not left in his power and libertie to write of the occurrents in those former times, as who was often checked both by his mother and also by his grandame. Of the former argument he left behinde him two volumes, of the later, fortie-one.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Hee compiled of his owne life eight bookes: a report not so wisely and discreetly put downe, as otherwise elegantly penned: Item, an Apologie or defense of Cicero against the bookes of Asinius Gallus: a peece of worke full enough of learning. He devised moreover three new characters or letters in the (Latine) Alphabet, and put them to the number of the olde as most necessarie. And having published whiles he was yet a private person, concerning the reason of those letters, one booke: soone after beeing Emperor he easily effected that they should be brought into use also indifferently with the rest. And verely such manner of writing with those characters is now extant to be seene in many bookes of records in Journels, and titles or inscriptions of works.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="42">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>With no lesse diligence studied hee the Greeke disciplines, professing as any occasion was offered, his affectionate love to that tongue, and the excellency thereof. When a certaine Barbarian discoursed in Greeke and Latine, 'See you be skilfull,' quoth he, 'in both our languages'; and in recommending Achaia unto the LL. of the Senate, he sayde it was a province that he affected well and delighted in, for the commerce and society of studies common to him and them: and many a time he answered their embassadors in the Senate, with a long and continued oration (in Greeke). But upon the Tribunall he used very much verses also out of Homer. Certes whensoever he had taken revenge of enemie or traytor, he lightly gave unto the Tribune over the Sentinels and guard of his person, calling unto him after the usual manner for a watchword, none other but this:
          Ανδρ᾽ ἐπαμίνασθε ὅτε τις πρότερος χαλεπήνῃ.
          Resist, revenge with maine and might,
          When one provokes thee first to fight.
          To conclude, in the end he wrote Greeke histories also, to wit twentie books entituled Tyrrhenicoon<note place="bottom" n="1">Of Tuskane affaires.</note>, and 8 entituled Carchedoniacoon<note place="bottom" n="2">Of Carthaginian matters.</note>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>In regard of which histories, unto the auntient schoole at Alexandria he adjoyned another bearing his owne name: and ordained it was, that every yeare in the on of them his books Tyrrhenicoon; and in the other his Carchedoniacoon upon certaine daies appointed therefore should (as it were in a frequent Auditorie) be read whole through by severall single readers in their turnes.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="43">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Toward the end of his life, hee shewed certaine signes and those evident enough, that he repented both his mariage with Agrippina, and the adoption also of Nero. For by occasion that his freed-men made mention and gave their commendation of a judiciall proceeding of his, wherein he had condemned the day before, a Woman in the case of adulterie, hee avouched that the destinies likewise had so ordained, that all his mariages should bee unchaste howbeit not unpunished: and soone after, meeting his sonne Britannicus and embracing him harder and more closely than his manner was, 'Growe apace,' quoth hee, 'and take account of me for all that I have done.' Using withall these Greeke words, ὁ ἔρως δ' ἐπείγεται, i. love enforced me. And when he had fully purposed to give him being as then very young and of tender yeeres his Virile Robe, seeing that his stature and growth would beare and permit it,<note n="a">
            <p>For, by report of Dion and Xiphilinus his stature farre exceeded the proportion of his years. </p>
        </note> he uttered these words moreover, 'To the end that the people of Rome may yet at last have a true and naturall Cæsar.'</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="44">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>And not long after this he wrote his wil and signed it with the seales of al the head-magistrates: whereupon before that he could proceed anie further, prevented hee was and cut short by Agrippina. Whom they also who were privie to her and of her councell<note place="bottom" n="1">Conscii: some read Conscientia quoque, even his owne conscience.</note>, yet neverthelesse enformers, accused besides all this of many crimes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <p>And verely it is agreed upon generally by all, that killed he was by poyson: but where it should be, and who gave it, there is some difference.<note n="a">
            <p>And yet by circumstances it may be collected, that he caught his bane and died in the Palatium at Rome. </p>
        </note> Some write, that as he sat at a feast in the (Capitoll) Castle with the priests, it was presented unto him by Halotus the Eunuch his taster: others report that it was at a meale in his owne house by Agrippina herselfe, who had offered unto him a mushrome empoisoned; knowing that he was most greedy of such meats. Of those accidents also which ensued hereupon, the report is variable.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section" n="3">
          <p>Some say, that streight upon the receipt of the poyson he became speechlesse, and continuing all night in dolorous torments, dyed a little before day. Others affirme, that at first he fell a sleepe: and afterwards, as the meate flowed and floted aloft vomited all up, and so was followed againe with a ranke poyson<note place="bottom" n="2">Toxico.</note>. But whether the same were put into a messe of thicke gruell, (considering hee was of necessitie to be refreshed with food beeing emptied in his stomacke) or conveied up by a clister, as if being overcharged with fulnesse and surfeit, he might be eased also by this kind of egestion and purgation, it is uncertaine.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="45">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>His death was kept secret until all things were set in order about his successour. And therefore, both vowes were made for him as if hee had lyen sicke stil, and also comicall Actours were brought in place colourably to solace and delight him, as having a longing desire after such sports. He deceased A.U.C. 807. three dayes before the Ides of October<note place="bottom" n="1">The 13th of October.</note>, when Asinius Marcellus and Acilius Aviola were Consuls: in the 64th yeere of his age, and 14th of his Empire. His funerals were performed with a solemne pompe and procession of the Magistrates: and canonized he was a Saint in heaven: which honor forlet and abolished by Nero hee recovered afterwards by the meanes of Vespasian.</p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div type="chapter" n="46">
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Especial tokens there were presaging and prognosticating his death: to wit the rising of an hairy<note place="bottom" n="1">Or blazing.</note> starre which they call a Comet: also the monument<note place="bottom" n="2">Or tombe.</note> of his father Drusus was blasted with lightning: and for that in the same yeere most of the Magistrates of all sorts were dead.<note n="a">
            <p>These were, as it plainly appeareth, Questors, Ædiles, Tribunes, Prætors, Censors and Consuls.  Of all these, some one or other died, excepting Censors, as Tacitus writeth, 12 Annal. </p>
        </note> But himselfe seemeth not either to have beene ignorant that his end drew neere, or to have dissimuled so much: which may bee gathered by some good arguments and demonstrations. For both in the ordination of Consuls hee appointed none of them to continue longer then the moneth wherein he dyed: and also in the Senate, the very last time that ever he sat there, after a long and earnest exhortation of his children to concord, he humbly recommended the age of them both to the LL. of that honourable house and in his last Judiciall Session upon the Tribunal once or twice he pronounced openly, That come he was now to the end of his mortalitie: notwithstanding they that heard him, greived to heare such an Osse, and praied the gods to avert the same.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>