<div type="annotations" subtype="Tiberius_Nero_Caesar">
    <div type="notes" n="1">
        <note n="a">
            <p>IT seemeth that in his owne Native countrey, where the Inhabitantes before time were descended from the Greeks, he had to name Atta Clausus and being once incorporate among the Romans, changed it, into Appius Claudius. Now, Atta savoreth of the Greeke word ἄττειν, which is in going, not to set the sole of the foote firmely upon the ground, but rather lightly to tread as it were, on tiptoe. Heereupon, as Festus noteth, they that have that imperfection in their feete, whereby they can go no better, be called Attæ: which was the occasion, that one of the said house tooke that name first, and so his posteritie after him. Like as among the Romanes, of another accident, arose the name Agryppa first for that one was borne into the world with his feete forward. And these additions, whether they were forenames or surnames in the beginning, it skilleth not: for surnames in continuance of time came to be forenames, and contrariwise.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>If you have recourse unto the Originall, Nero is as much as Νεύρων, Νευρώδης,  . Nervatus or Nervosus: that is to say, well compact of nerves and sinewes: and such are strong.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="2">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Seneca reporteth in his booke De Brevitate Vitæ, cap. 12, That this Claudius perswaded the Romanes first, to go to sea, and embarke : whereupon he was styled Caudex, which in our Latin is as much to say, as the framing, and joyning together of many plants or ribs of timber, which is the very Periphrases of a Barke.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>One of his predecessours who had a Jurisdiction there, gave it that name, as having built likewise a Forum or Hall of Justice there, whereupon the Inhabitants of it and the territour thereabout, owing service to that court, as Clients and dependants to that Family, afforded this Claudius a meete place for him of Innovation and usurping unlawfull dominion.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Observing signes from Birds, by their feeding, flying or otherwise, that might give him warrant to go forward with the favour of the Gods, in his Enterprise.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Adoptions by order of Law, should follow the course of Nature, whereby the sonne, cannot be elder than the Father.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>The cause why he sought thus extraordinarily to bee adopted a commoner, was that he might be chosen Tribune of the Commons.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>The usuall manner in Rome was, that those persons who were arrested for criminall causes, during all the time of their trouble and triall, should chaunge their apparell, and in steed of gownes which were faire and white, put on others sullied and foule, thereby to moove mercie and compassion of the people. Whereupon such Rei were called Sordidati.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>These Tribunes of the commons as may appeare in T. Livius were sacrosancti, i. Unviolable, and such as no violent hands might bee laid upon.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="3">
        <note n="a">
            <p>So called, of Salina, the salt pits or salt houses. For being Censor he set an impost upon salt, and thereby augmented the revenewes of the State, little to the benefit or contentment of the people.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="4">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For the manner was, that Governours of provinces, who (as they were) so would be counted also, more courteous than others, should unrequested allow some of their lectors unto all Roman Senators that repayred unto them, for to doe them honour: Cic. Ep. ad Cornificium.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="5">
        <note n="a">
            <p>In token of his nativitie there, which as they gave out, was borne to the good urbis et orbis, i. Of Rome and the whole world besides, for so, by way of flatterie they magnified their Princes.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="6">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Some read, Luctuosam, i. sorrowfull, in regard of many hurts and dangers.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>When a chariot is drawne by a teeme of foure steeds all in one ranke or affront, as we may see them pourtraited upon divers coines, it must needs bee that the two middle are joyned or yoaked as it were to the spire pole running betweene them and these be called sύγιοι. The other two then are without, the one on the left, and the other on the right side, called παρήοροι in Greeke, and in this place by our Authour Funales, because they are guided and ruled by a cord, or some reines or cheine in lieu thereof. And say, that these quadrigæ or foure steeds drawe two by two in files, one payre before the other: those which be next unto the chariot be aptly called Jugales, and those before them beyond the spire, Funales, of which, Tiberius rode upon one and Marcellus upon the other.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="10">
        <note n="a">
            <p>According to the vulgar speach, Nimia familiaritas parit contemptum.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="14">
        <note n="a">
            <p>These dice were called Tali, because at first they used with such cockall bones named Tali to play: but afterwards they were made of Ivory, gold, etc. Among many sorts of sorceries and divinations, one there was by these bones or dies, and the wisards that professed their cunning in it, were termed 'Αστραγαλομαντεῖς.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>For the greater light to this place, and better proofe of Thrasillus skill, Dion reporteth, that when Tiberius intended verily to throw him downe headlong, he perceived him by his countenance to be much troubled and disquieted in minde, whereupon he demaunded the cause thereof, and then Thrasyllus answered, that by speculation of the Stars he foresaw some present daunger to himselfe, and so Tiberius durst not proceede to execute this intent of his.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="17">
        <note>
            <p>Septa, was a place in Mars Field railed about at first like a sheepe Pen: whereupon it was called Ovilia. But afterwards mounded with Marble stone, beautified also with stately galleries and walks, within which cloysture and precinct, the people oftentimes assembled about Election of Magistrates and other publicke affayres: yea and with wares which were there set out to be sold. As Alex. ab Alexandro witnesseth.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="19">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Some read Bructero, of which name there is a nation, as well as of the Rhutaine in Gaule. Others, Rutero, as if he meant one of those horsemen or riders in Germanie, which at this day be called Rutters.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="20">
        <note n="a">
            <p>A long robe embrodred and garded with purple, a cassocke branched with Date tree worke, a rich mantell of sundry colours. A chaplet of Laurell, a staffe and chaire, both of Ivorie. Liv. lib. 30.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="21">
        <note n="a">
            <p>By this ænigmaticall speech, Augustus compareth the state of the people of Rome, unto the miserable case of one, whom some savage and cruell beast hath gotten betweene his teeth, not devouring and dispatching him at once, but there holdeth and cheweth him a long while in exceeding paine: alluding to the secret malice, and dreaming nature withall of Tiberius.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>It should seeme that in adopting him, he used these very words, Hoc Reipub. causa facio, i. This doe I for the common-wealthes sake. Alluding to this verse of Ennius in the commendation of Qu. Fabius Max.</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Unus homo nobis cunctando restituit rem.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>One man alone by sage delay<br/>
            Restor'd our state fall'n to decay.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>In the tenth booke of his Iliads, where Diomedes in making choise of Ulysses, to exploit a peece of service with him, giveth him this praise.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="23">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The Tribunes of the commons had power to call a Senate, but not whensoever they would, without a speciall Decree graunted by the Nobles.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="25">
        <note>
            <p>The cohort or band of Souldiers which were of the Princes Guard, were called Prætoriani, taking that name of Prætorium which signifieth the Lord Generals Pavilion in the campe, his Royall Pallace in Rome and else where. As also the Lord Deputies house of Estate in any Province. Now those Souldiers that gave attendance and served in this place about the Prince or Governour, were intertained in better condition than the rest, because their wages was greater, and the time of their service shorter. For Augustus had set downe their terme twelve yeares, whereas the rest, before they could be discharged, were to serve sixteene.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>It may be thought, that Germaniciani as well by the Grammaticall Analogie of the letter, as also by some circumstance of this verie place, import a reference unto Germanicus the son of Drusus disceased. Like as Vitelliani, Flaviani, etc. But the learned observe, that as an Armie lying encamped or in Garrison, in Germanie, is properly in Latin called Germanicus, so the Soldiours of the said Armie be fitly named Germaniciani.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="26">
        <note>
            <p>These solemnities were exhibited about the midst of November, whereas the other, named Romani, were held in the beginning of September. To be noted, that the name of Imperator in the Roman Historie is taken three waies: First, for him, who by commission or warrant from the State, hath the conducting of an Armie: and in this sense, it hath relation to Souldiers, and is all one with Lord Generall of the field, or a commaunder, etc., and the same that Prætor was in olde time. Secondly, for a Victor or Conquerer, namely when such a Generall or chiefetaine hath by martial prowesse atchieved many valiant exploits, and put to sword such a number of enemies, as the law setteth downe. For then the souldiers were wont to salute him by the name of Imperator, i. Conquerour. Lastly for a Soveraigne Prince, King and Monarch. In the first acception, it is a meere Relative, in the second a surname, in the third and last, the forename of all the Romane Emperours, to wit, from Julius Cæsar forward. Who although they wore not the Crowne and Diademe, were neverthelesse absolute Princes, Soveraignes, Kings and Monarches. The want of this distinction may breed some trouble in the readers of the Romane Historie.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>Made of Oke branches, or in default thereof, of some other tree bearing mast: which garland by the first institution, was given to that souldier, who in battell had rescued a Citizen of Rome and saved his life. And afterwards, it, together with the Laurell, beautified the gates of the Cæsars Palaces, although some of them were bloodie Tyrants, and made no spare of their citizens and subjects lives.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="30">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The manner was, if Prince or Senatour were caried in his Litter, usually supported by eight bond-servants, and thereupon called Octophoron, to have a companie of Citizens in their gownes going before, and accompanying him by his side, as also certaine servitours to carie his curule chaire of ivory behinde.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="31">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This free embassage, called Libera legatio, was granted many times to such, as being desirous eyther to travell and see forraine countries, or to fly, for avoiding of daungerous troubles at home: therby to be better intertained abroad, and with the more honest colour, to conceale the occasion of their departure, and absence as if they were sent from the state, about the affayres onely of Common-weale.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="32">
        <note n="a">
            <p>It was not ordinarie with the Emperours to accompanie the corpes unto the funerall Fire: but onely to vouchsafe their presence at the Funerall Oration in the Forum or common place. This therefore may be attributed unto Tiberius his civill humanitie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>It appeareth by Dion, that they had omitted to subscribe the clause which went in this forme, Vota facimus pro te, Imperator, i. We make our vowes (and pray) for thee O Emperour.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="33">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Causes were heard judicially, and Justice ministred, eyther from a superiour place as the Tribunall, or beneath upon the even and plaine ground, de plano, as the Lawyers speake, so that there were a Chaire or seat for the judge to sit upon. And the said place of Justice wheresoever, eyther pro tribunali, or de plano posita sella, is properly called Ius: as Carolus Sigonus hath observed, lib. 1, cap. 5, de Judiciis. Whereupon commeth the usuall phrase, In ius vocare. It seemeth therefore, that Tiberius would come into the Comitium or Hall of Justice, and take his place, sometime within the Tribunall (for it was a spacious rowme) or else sit in his Curule chaire of Ivory beneath, as a moderator, which is expressed heere by the terme de plano.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="34">
        <note>
            <p>As Marchpanes, Tarts, Gingerbreed, Custards, Sugred Bisket, and generally all manner of pastrie-conceits, wrought with honie or sugar. The workeman is called Dulciarius, and the things, Bellaria Mellita, or Pemmata. Toyes not onely needlesse, but hurtfull also to the bodie, according to that in Aulus Gellius, lib. 13, cap. 11, Noct. Attic. ex varone. Bellaria ea maxime sunt millita quæ mellita non sunt : Πέμμασι γὰρ πέψει, societas infida, i. Such junkets sort not well with Concoction<note place="foot" n="1">Or digestion.</note>.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="35">
        <note>
            <p>Diverse Statutes there were sharpely punishing the adulterie of Matrones or maried wives. An Act likewise passed in the Senate, that no Person of Knights degree or above, should play upon the stage, performe sword-fight, or combat with wild beastes for hire. Providing all to preserve the honour of wedlocke entire, and to maintaine the reputation of Knighthood and Nobilitie. Those shamelesse dames therefore, of whom Suetonius writeth in this place, eyther because they would be thought unworthie to be reckoned within the censure of Law, or as Tacitus writeth, deemed to have abidden punishment enough in making profession of so base a trade and life: these lewde persons likewise, and unreclaimable unthrifts suffering themselves thus to appeare noted with infamie, and that upon record, made accompt, both the one and the other not to be obnoxious or liable unto the statutes and acts aforesaid.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The manner was at Rome, for Tenaunts to remoove and flit out of one house into another, upon the first day of July, like as with us, at the feastes of Saint Michaell and the Anunciation of the Virgin Marie: which are the ordinarie rent daies.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="36">
        <note>
            <p>Josephus, lib. 18, Antiquit. Judaic. writeth that Tiberius sent 4000 of them into Sardinia, an Iland in Summer time especially, verie intemperate and unwholsome, as may appeare by that pretie Epigram of Martialis, wherein he opposeth the healthie Citie Tibur, to the pestilent Isle Sardinia.</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Nullo fata loco possis excludere, cum mors</l>
                <l>Venerit, in medio Tibure Sardinia est.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>No place exempt from fatall death, for when our time is come,<br/>
            Mid Tibur, will Sardinia be found of all and some.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="38">
        <note>
            <p>This Callipides, who gave occasion of this By-word, was a famous Stage-player, or one of these Mimi, counterfaiting other mens gestures, as Beraaldus supposeth. See Plutarch in Apophtheg. Laconic.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="42">
        <note>
            <p>Biberius, a bibendo, i. of drinking. Calius, a Calda, or Calida, i. hote. Mero of Merum, i. strong wine. An elegant Agnominiation: whereby is shewed, that he loved to drinke wine hote, which is right delicate, and goeth downe more merily.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The Italicke Amphor conteyneth 48 Sextarii, everie Sextarius 20 ounces Mensurales, which is a wine pinte and halfe of our measure with the better. By which reckoning he dranke at one meale a rundlet of ten wine gallons well neere.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>A Bird that feedeth upon grapes and figges especially, whereupon it tooke the name. In Autumne or the latter end of Summer it is so called: at other times Melanocoryphos, or Atricapilla, of the blacke cop, or hair-like fethers that it carieth upon the head. Of this Bird for the daintie flesh of it Martiall made this Epigram,</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Inter aves, turdus, si quis me judice certet,</l>
                <l>Inter quadrupedes, gloria prima Lepus.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>Of fethered foules, if I may judge, the blackbirde is the best,<br/>
            Among four-footed beasts the Hare surpasseth all the rest.</p>
            <p>To invent and devise new pleasures.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="43">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Alluding partly to the Isle Capræa, and in part eyther to Capra in Latin, a goat, or to Καπρός in Greek, a wild bore, and that member, Quo viri sumus.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="49">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Seneca reporteth thus, lib. 2, de Benefic. cap. 27, Quater millies sestertium suum vidit, i. He saw of his owne, 400 millions of Sesterces.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Provided it was by an auncient law, and the same revived by Jul. Cæsar Dictator, that no person should in silver or gold possesse above 60 sestertia, that is, three score thousand sestertii. This also may have a relation to that order set downe by him a little before, That monied men and usurers should lay out two third parts of their stocke in lands and houses, etc.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="51">
        <note n="a">
            <p>As we say, to make him Justice of Quorum, etc: for the decuries of Judges were they Quorum nomina, were written in the Commission Roll.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="53">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The Greeke verse is red thus, Εἰ μὴ τυραννεῖς, θύγατερ, ἀδικεῖσθαι δοκεῖς, οι Εἰ μὴ τυραννεῖς, τέκνον, etc.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Scale Gemonica. A place at Rome upon the Aventine hill, into which the dead bodies of malefactors were dragged and throwen with shame..</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="56">
        <note n="a">
            <p>They speake the Greeke language generally throughout all Greece, yet not after one manner. For in divers parts were different kindes of Greeke called Dialects, to wit, Attick, Ionick, Æolick, etc. Like as with us in Great Britaine a common English tongue goeth wel neere throughout the whole Iland, albeit there is a diversity perceived between the Scottish or Northren English, and the Southerne, betweene the Cornish and the Kentish, etc.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="58">
        <note n="a">
            <p>In so doing the bodie must needes be bared and some shame discovered which being an Impietie before the sacred Images of the Gods, was made Treason also before the Emperours Statue, unto whom divine honours were exhibited.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="59">
        <note>
            <p>The last Hexastichon or 6 verses, seemeth to make one entier Epigram by it selfe. Every Distichon before, carieth a severall sense. And as for the first two, they seeme to have a reference to the time, whiles he abode in Rhodes, before he was Sui Iuris.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="61">
        <note n="a">
            <p>At which times, both among the Greekes and Romans also, the manner was to forbeare Execution, yea and to ease prisoners of their yrons.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>As if under his person he had offered abuse unto the Emperour Tiberius.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>He would say, The courage and generositys of the Romans died with them, seing that none arose to recover their libertie oppressed and trode under foote by this Tyrant Tiberius.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Rather, two hundred and twentie. For Tacitus, lib. 6, Annal. reporteth, that all the suspected complices of Sejanus were killed, Lacuit immensa strages, omnis sexus, omnis ætas, etc.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>The like hypocriticall Religion was practised during the bloudie proscription in the Triumvirate. A young Gentleman nobly borne, because he might not be killed lawfully, prætextatus, i. under age, and wearing still his embrodered garment prætexta, hee commaunded to put on his virile gowne, and so he was murthered. Appian. Dio.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="67">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For wonderfully addicted he was to the studie of Astrologie, and such curious Arts.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="68">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The full stature of men in Italy, was six foot wanting two ynches, if men grew higher than sixe they were accompted exceeding tall, if to seven, (and to that height men may grow, as Varro, Gellius and Solinus doe write) they went for Giants. So that in Musters yong men were chosen soldiours, five foote high and ten ynches, which was called Iusta Statura.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Some read subiti, and not subtiles, to signifie that such pimples continued not, but arose and fell at times, much like to those that the Physitians call Hidroa, Sudamina, or papulas sudorum, according to Plinie, proceeding of heat or sweat, if the humours be sharpe.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Such be termed in Greeke βυσαυχένες. And if we may beleeve the Physiognomie delivered by Aristotle: they be by nature deceitfull and wilie, given to circumvent, entrap and supplant others.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Cornelius Celsus, among other good rules and precepts of Health, writeth thus, Sanus homo qui et bene valet et sucæ spontis est, nullis obligare se legibus debet, ac ne medico neque alipta egere, etc. But give he what directions he will, and let us say what wee can to this point, that men and women may be Physicians to themselves, such is there misgovernment in diet and otherwise, that Physitians shall never want imployment. And as touching thirty years of age, Tacitus addeth moreover and saith, That he<note place="foot" n="1">Tiberius.</note> was wont to mock those and hold them to be fooles, who after the said yeares had neede of other mens instructions, to know what was good or hurtfull for their bodies. Whereupon might arise our English proverbe, A foole or a physician.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="70">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Such as were sung to the Harpe. In which kinde Pindarus excelled among the Greekes, and Horace among the Romans.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>One of Augustus [adopted] sonnes. Yet some read Julius Cæsar.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="71">
        <note n="a">
            <p>A word usuall with us in these daies, for who knoweth not that Monopoly is, when one man engrosseth some commoditie into his owne handes, that none may sell the same but himselfe, or from him?</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>It signifieth in this place a peece of workmanship set upon a cup or other vessell of Gold or Silver to garnish the same, so fitted, as it may be put to, or taken away at our pleasure. The auncient Poets in Latin called such devises Insertas.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>Contrarie to Augustus Cæsar, whose manner was ever and anone in his speeches and writings to interlace Greeke words and sentences.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="72">
        <note n="a">
            <p>A place neere the river Tiberis, so called of a Navell fight exhibited sometime there, by Julius Cæsar Dictator, within a spatious pit receiving water for that purpose.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>In the port high waies from Rome, the manner of the Romans, was at everie miles ende to pitch downe a great stone, and according thereto were the miles reckoned, like as with us in some places there stand crosses of wood or stone to that end.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>i. A creeping Dragon. Which implieth, that there be others winged, or at least wise supposed to flie, in the common opinion of men. For the attribute, Serpens, signifieth Creeping. Now, because all of them use most so to do, the general name of Dragons, goeth under Serpents. And as for the word Dragon, it is given to the whole kinde for their quicke sight, comming of Draco, in Latine, and δράκων in Greeke, ἀπὸ τοῦ δρακεῖν, ἱ. of seeing.</p>
        </note>
        <note>
            <p>Recidiva peior radice, say the Physitians. The relapse unto a former disease is more dangerous, than it was before.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="73">
        <note>
            <p>It tooke the name of L. Lucullus, the Lord thereof.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="75">
        <note n="a">
            <p>A towne in Campania where he tooke so great delight, and a place infamous for the licentious life of the inhabitants, whereupon grew the name of those lascivious and filthie Comedies, Atellana. A place I say suiting well to his beastly behaviour. As if he had beene unworthie to be conveyed to Rome, the Citie which so long before he had abandoned.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>As poore begger bodies were wont to be served in hast, by the common bearers, and not fully burnt with leasure.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Where malefactors ordinarily were burnt.</p>
        </note>
    </div>
</div>