<div type="annotations" subtype="Caius_Caesar_Caligula">
    <div type="notes" n="1">
        <note n="a">
            <p>CALLED by some, Annales or Annariæ: of others, Comitiales. By which provided it was, In what yeares of a mans age, he was capable of Questure, Preture, Consulate, or any other like Office of State: as also, it was limited, within what time betweene, one might eftsoones beare the same Office againe. Item, what the terme of everie Magistracie should be, etc. And albeit the auncient Romanes had no such lawes, but (as Cornelius Scipio at his petition of Ædileship made answere, when exception was taken against him for his young age) whomsoever the Quirites would charge to be a Magistrate, hee had yeares enough on his backe, yet afterwards, sundrie Statutes were enacted in that behalfe: although by vertue of speciall privileges, the same were not duly observed. By the Chronologie it appeareth, that he was but ninteene yeares old when he became Questor, like as Tiberius before him.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Which Tiberius envying his greatnesse, wrought, therby to expose him unto greater dangers.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="3">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Well might this unseasonable exercise puff up and fill his skin with crudities and foggie humors, but hurtfull unto his health it was, and brought upon him diseases, and namely, that called Cardiacus, of which, some say, he died. Let them looke to it therfore, who, because they would be fat, not only fall to bodily exercise out of time, even upon ful stomacks, but also every morning eate in their beds and sleepe upon it, yea and ordinarily take a nap at noone, so soone as their meat is out of their mouthes.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>By this Attribute, Civill, in our Author, ye must understand, Courtesie, Affabilitie, and a part not exceeding that of private Citizens, without taking any state.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="5">
        <note n="a">
            <p>As if the Gods, whose Images were shrined within, were not to be honoured any longer as Gods, suffering so good a man as Germanicus was, to die. For, as in token of honour, the people used to adorne the Statues and Images of famous persons with flowers and greene leaves, so, whom they did vilipend and despise, they were wont to cast stones at their Images and Statues.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The Tutelarie Gods of the house which ordinarily stood within a closet, called thereupon Lararium.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>For, to what end should they reare children any more? since Germanicus, growen to so good proofe, sped no better, but was taken away by untimely death.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>In this place, the circumstance sheweth, that the King of Parthians is meant, how ever the Persian King and such mightie Monarches, having under their Dominion other pettie Kings as Tributaries or Homagers, be so called: like as Agamemnon also in Homere.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Which at Rome betokened a generall mourning, occasioned upon some extraordinary calamitie, or feare of publicke daunger, even as with us, the shutting in of Shop-windowes, etc.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="6">
        <note n="a">
            <p>About the mids of this moneth, began the feast Saturnalia, celebrated with good cheere, with revels, dances, gaming and all kinde of libertie.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="9">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For, common souldiers wore a certaine studded shoe, named Caliga.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="10">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which was later than the ordinarie time, by reason of Tiberius his lingering. For usually these complements were performed at 47 yeares of age.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="11">
        <note n="a">
            <p>In this habite and manner of attire, counterfeiting a woman, thereby to decline suspicion when he entered into other mens houses for to dishonour them and abuse their wives, whom our author termeth heere Adulteria, pro adulteris, as else where, conjugia, pro conjugibus.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The fabulous Historie of Phæthon is well known, namely, how by misgovernment of the steeds which drew the Chariot of the Sunne his Father, he set the whole world on fire. By Phæthon therfore is meant, a combustion (as it were) and generall confusion of the Provinces, like as by the watersnake, the verie bane and poyson of the Roman State.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="13">
        <note n="a">
            <p>To doe him the greater honour, they intertaine him upon the way (as the maner was) with Sacrifices, Torches, Tapers, and wax lights.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="14">
        <note n="a">
            <p>An opinion there was deepely setled in mens heads, that the death of one man might be excused and redeemed, with the death of another.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="16">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The two hundred penie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>His halfe image downeward from the head to the wast, portrayed with a Shield or Scutchion and the same was commonly set out with the largest. Hereupon, M. Tullius Cicero, when he saw such a demie personage representing his brother Quintus in the province that he governed (and a very litle man he was of stature) 'My brother,' quoth he, 'in his halfe part, is greater than in the whole.'</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>A festivall holiday solemnized by heardmen, in the honour of Pales their Goddesse and Patronesse. Upon which day, the foundation of Rome Citie was laid. This feast they kept, the 12 day before the Kalends of May, to wit, the 20 of Aprill.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="18">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Mænius, a riotous unthrift, when he had wasted his Patrimonie and sold his Capitall house in Rome, excepted in the sale, and reserved to himselfe and his heires, one Columne or Pillar, from which he projected and put forth into the street a jettie, and upon it built a gallerie: out of which he might behold the sword-fencers in the market place, whereunto he had a fayre prospect from the said Pillar. Whereupon all such galleries or buildings jetting out in the street, be called Mæniana.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="22">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The end of one verse, and beginning of another, cited out of Homer in the second of his Ilias. The Poet ascribeth them unto sage Ulysses, in this sense:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>One [Soveraigne] Lord,</l>
                <l>One King let there be.</l>
            </quote>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>By exchaunging the ensignes and Ornaments of the Roman Soveraigne or Emperor, with the Regall Diadem, purple Robe and Scepter.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Phœnicopterus is a water foule haunting lakes and fennes, and the river Nilus, as Hesiodus writeth. The fethers be of colour read, or purple. Whereof it taketh the name: and the tongue is a most daintie and pleasant morsell. So said Apitius, nepotum omnium altissimus gurges. Of this Bird Martiall made an Epigram:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Dat mihi penna rubens nomen: sed lingua gulosis</l>
                <l>Nostra sæpit. Quid si garrula lingua fores.</l>
            </quote>
            <quote>
                <l>My name I take of wings so red, but unto gluttons tast,</l>
                <l>My tongue right pleasing is: oh, what, if it could prate as fast.</l>
            </quote>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Some take them for Bistards: Birds decked, no doubt, with most beautifull fethers: as may appeare by Tertullian against Marcion, in these words: Una Tetraonis pennula, (taceo de pavo) sordidum artificem pronuntiabit tibi Creatorem?</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>By the description of Clitus, they be our Turkies.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>They are thought to be Hens of Guinny.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="g">
            <p>The Phesant called in old time Itis, (which was the sonne of Tereus and Progne, transformed, as Poets feigne, into this Bird) and afterwards Phasianus or Phasiana [Avis], tooke his name of Phasis a river and Citie in Colchis, according to this Epigram of Martials:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Argiva primum sum transportata Carina:</l>
                <l>Ante mihi notum nil nisi Phasis erat.</l>
            </quote>
            <quote>
                <l>In Argive ship transported first, I was to forraine land:</l>
                <l>Fore time, nought else but Phasis towne, I knew, or Phasis strand.</l>
            </quote>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="23">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Philo reporteth this farre otherwise, and telleth a pitifull Narration: How, by commission from Caius, certaine Colonels and Centurians came to young Tiberius, commaunding him to kill himselfe: because, forsooth, unlawfull it was for any other to murder a Prince of the Imperiall bloud. The youth, who had never seene any man killed, and by reason of his tender yeares was nothing at all experienced in the world, requested first of them, who were come thus to him, for to strike off his head, which he held out unto them: but seeing his request would not be heard, he desired them yet, to instruct him, in what part of his bodie he should stab himselfe for the speediest death. And so by instructions from them he was his owne executioner.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="25">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Romulus ravished the Sabine virgins: and Augustus by force tooke from Tiberius his wife Livia.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="26">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Selena, in Greeke, signifieth the Moone. And well knowen it is, that as M. Antonius the Triumvir called himselfe Bacchus and Osiris, so Cleopatra his wife tooke pleasure to be named Luna, i. the Moone, and Isis. Whereupon they gave to their sonne Alexander begotten betweene them, the name of the sunne, and to their daughter Cleopatra the name of the Moone, or Selena, which is all one.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The Consuls were reputed still (in outward shew) Soveraigne Magistrates, although indeed, the Cæsars caried all before them, and were absolute Monarches.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Some read, Tesseras decima citius, i. Before the tenth houre, or foure of the clocke after noone, for so long continued the Stage-plaies ordinarily. At which time, the Emperours were wont to bestow their Tickets or Talies among the people, by vertue whereof they received such and such gifts.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>There be learned Criticks that expound this place farre otherwise, reading Pegmares, in steede of Pegmatis, and understanding thereby such sword-fencers, whose good hap it had beene to escape with life, the fall from those Frames or Pageants called Pegmata or Pegma, which with certaine vices or Skrewes were set up, and let downe, upon which as on scaffolds, malefactors were brought forth, eyther to exhibit a shew unto the people, fighting one with another at sharpe, to the outrance, or to make them sport, by falling downe into a pit underneath, where eyther wild beasts were readie to devoure, or fire to consume them. A devise wrought by dissolving the joynts of the said Pegmes under them. And in this sense they interprete the rest that followeth, concerning patres familias, i. good honest Citizens householders.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="27">
        <note n="a">
            <p>He had espied in the multitude of those prisoners and malefactors, two with bald heads, distant farre a sunder, and happily, as much as from the one end of the place unto the other: all those betweene, without respect of their cause, he commaunded to be put to death indifferently.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>An ordinarie thing it was at Rome, to sweare by the Genius, as also by the Fortune, the health, etc., of their Emperours. And what a devout oth this was, per Genium, i. the Dæmon, the spirit, or superintendent Angell of the Prince, which I take to be as much, as by his owne good selfe, appeareth by Tertullian, Apologet. cap. 28. Citius apud vos per omnes deos, quam per Genium principis peieratur.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Seneca, lib. 2 de Ira, cap. 33, reporteth the like example of Castor a right worshipful Gentleman of Rome, whose sonne, the same Caligula, upon verie envie that the young man was a proper and beautifull person, put to death in his fathers sight, and then invited the old man to supper, provoked him to carouse and be merie, which the good father was faine to endure and make semblance of contentment, for feare, least the Tyrant would have done as much by another sonne, whom he had living.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Catenis verberatum. Among other chasticements of the bodie, there is reckoned Vinculorum verberatio, as Callistratus witnesseth, lib. 7 de Pænis. The ignorance whereof, hath made some to read, in Catenis verberatum, i. bound in chaines and then beaten, others, habenis for catenis: as if he had beene well lindged with lether thongs or halters ends, as slaves were wont to be served by the Lorarii.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="28">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Albeit, the proper use of these Graphia was to cut or engrave letters onely, in tables of barke or soft wood: yet, because it was unlawfull to weare weapons in the Senate house, some, of a mischievous minde, made those writing stiles or Steeles so, as they might kill therewith, enacted therefore it was, that no man should carie about him such writing instruments of yron or steele, but of bone onely. And yet even these, as others also of reeds and quils, were made so keene and sharpe, that they were able to give a mortall wound.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="29">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For the manner of the Roman Emperours was, upon displeasure, to send men and women away into some desert Ísles, and there to confine them.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Ellebor, that groweth in the Isles Antycire, is of most effectuall operation. The roote is that, whereof is made our sneesing powder. It purgeth extreemely by vomit. Thereupon ariseth the Proverb, Naviget Anticyram, i. Let him sayle to Anticyra, applied to one that is melancholicke in the highest degree, and little better than mad. See Plinie, Natural Hist., lib. 35, cap. 5.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="30">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Some conjecture verie well, that this Tetrinius was not surnamed Latro, being the addition appropriate to the noble Family of Rome, of the Portii, but a notorious theefe or robber, such as in Latin is called Latro. And of that sort commonly were they that performed before the people this bloudie fight with unrebated swords, without foiles.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>And no mervaile, if he termed all the Citizens there assembled Tetrinios, i. Theeves, considering he wished before, that he could cut of al their heads at one blow.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="33">
        <note n="a">
            <p>He suspected, that she had given him some love-drinks.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="34">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Præter æquum. How this can stand with his pride or malice, which our author hath propounded to exemplifie, I cannot see. In some copies we read, præter eum, i. beside him, that is to say, otherwise than he would have them, or approve. And one Critick or Judicious Lawier, Franc. Hottoman, as also Coracius, read, præter Eccum, as if hee should say, All Lawyers shall give none other answere but this. Behold him, meaning the Emperor Caius, therby referring the decision of all matters to his will and pleasure. Lastly, Torrentius concludeth the Period thus, Ne quid respondere possint, i. That they should give no answere at all. And for præter æquum, etc., he putteth præterea, i. Moreover, for a beginning of the next chapter.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="35">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Colosseros seemeth to be a word compounded of Colossos and Eros. The one importeth his talnesse, resembling the stately and Giantlike personages called Colossi, and the other, his lovely visage, Eros, even Love, Cupid it selfe.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Threces or Thraces, thought to be the same that Retiarii, were lightly appointed for armour, and put to desperate fight, as having all parts of their bodies exposed to daunger, whereupon they were called also Tunicati, and were matched in opposition with the Mirmillones, as this verse of Ausonius implieth:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Quis mirmilloni componitur?<note place="foot" n="1">Or, committitur.</note> æquimanus Thrax.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>Whereas the other named Hoplomachi, had for their defence, head peeces and targuets. Senec. lib. 1, Epist. 7.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>The priest, called Rex Nemorensis, of a place where Diana Arcina was worshipped, within a temple beautified with a grove about it, by a barbarous custome of the Scithians, so long onely held his place, untill after one yeares revolution, some one stronger than himselfe, stepped unto him and overcame him in single fight, and so deposed him, like as, by the first institution, himselfe, foyling another in combat attained thereto.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="37">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Seneca writeth, Consolat. ad Helv., That it was ordinarie with him to consume at one supper ten millions of sesterces, and who studied himselfe, and laid his head to others, how he might at one supper make an even hand with the revenewes and tributes of all the provinces belonging to the state of Rome.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Some read for [de Cedris] Deceres, after the forme of Moneres, meaning by Deceres a mightie gallie furnished with ten rankes of Oares, for such the Greeks call Δέκηρεις.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="41">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Dum multa commissa fierent. Which may be expounded otherwise thus, When as many things were forfaited and confiscate.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="45">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Taking the name from Exploratores, a militarie terme, signifying the Avant-couriers and fore-riders, to discover the enemy, and to cleere the coasts.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="51">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Yet Dion reporteth of him, that otherwhiles, when it thundred aloft, he would seeme to doe the like beneath with a thunder barrell, or such a kinde of devise: when it lightened, to make flashes with fireworks: and if a thunderbolt fell, to discharge likewise some stone out of an engine.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="52">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which ornaments belonged to Jupiter and Æsculapius.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Resembling thereby Neptune, for it symbolizeth his power over waters in Sea, River, Lakes.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>The Ensigne of Mercury, betokening his Eloquence.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="56">
        <note n="a">
            <p>So called, because they were exhibited in the Palatium.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="57">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Capitolium, although κατ ἐξοχήν, it was the stately mount or Castle of Rome, yet it became a generall name of all Citadels and strong Castles built for the defence of any Citie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Meaning the murder of Caius Julius Cæsar Dictator.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Bearing the name of a notorious theefe, or Captayne rather of theeves, crucified for his desertes.</p>
        </note>
    </div>
</div>