<div type="annotations" subtype="Tiberius_Claudius_Drusus_Caesar">
    <div type="notes" n="1">
        <note n="a">
            <p>LIKE as in Rome, the gate called Porta scelerata, and the Streete Vicus sceleratus upon some semblable infortunate accidents.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="2">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Wheras, by usuall custome such were brought into the Forum or common hall.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="9">
        <note n="a">
            <p>By vertue of this Act, himselfe, his landes and goods were proscribed and exposed to open sale, in a Table hung up by an Edict from the masters of the Exchequer or Citie-Chamber. And if within the time appointed, he came not in, to satisfie the debt, nor any chapman or suretie to undertake it, he and his whole state fell by escheate as forfait and confiscate into the Princes hands.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="17">
        <note n="a">
            <p>These Ilands are situate in the mouth of the River Rhodanus<note place="foot" n="1">Rhosne.</note>: and they be so called of the order in which they lie.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="21">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The name of this Fencer Palumbus, signifieth also in the Latin tongue a Stock-dove: which gave occasion unto him, to come out with this od jeast.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="23">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Provided it was by the law Papiæ, That no woman under fiftie yeares of age should be maried to a man three-scor yeares old or upward: Item, That no man under three score yeares might wed a woman, fiftie yers old or above. Where, note: That these words [à Tiberio] as if he added the said Branch, seeme to have beene foysted in: considering that as it appeareth by Tacitus, the Emperour Tiberius went about to moderate the foresaid law, and not to make it more strict by annexing such a clause.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="25">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For feare of breaking up the pavements, if they rode in coach, wagon, chariot, or on horseback.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>In divers Greeke and Latin writers, the names of Jewes and Christians were confounded: so as by Jewes they understood Christians.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Orchestra was that place in the fore-front of the Theater or Scaffolds, and neerest unto the Stage, wherein the Senators ordinarily sate, and sometime the Emperour himselfe.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Popularia were seats within the scaffolds and Theater, most remote from the Stage, wherein the common people were allowed to stand or sit.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Betweene the said Orchestra and these Popularia were raunged the Knights or Gentlemen of Rome, and those rankes bare the name of Equestria.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>So called, of the mountaine Eryx in Sicilie, where she was highly worshipped, and where she had a Temple.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="28">
        <note n="a">
            <p>As for Drusilla his wife, a Jew borne, she had beene maried indeed before to king Azyzus, as Josephus writeth: but as touching the other two Queens, whosoever they were, he was acquainted with them otherwise, and not in way of mariage, so farre as I can finde.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>For everie man might not so doe, unlesse he had a Knights estate, which was foure hundred thousand Sextarii, or were free borne: neyther Libertines nor Mechanicall persons living by base trades and occupations were allowed.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="29">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Other writers, as Philostratus and Julianus, say moreover, That without his wife and freed men, he was χωφὸν πρόσωπον and δορυφόρημα τῆς βασιλείας, much like to a player in a dumbe shew, and the bare Image of a Kings Majestie, as Plutarch reporteth of Arridaus.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="31">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This disease, some Physicians name Καρδιαλγίαν, i. the heart-ach, or Cardiacam passionem, seated in the orifice of the stomach, which is called Καρδία. The paine whereof, Plinie affirmeth to be most intollerable, next unto the passion of the strangury.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="32">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Flatum crepitumque ventris. By Flatum, understand that riddance of wind downeward, qui nares ferit, non aures. Which in English commeth neere unto the Latin word, Visio, for that the verbe Visire, is the same that τὸ βοίσειν. As Cicero in his Epistles hath well, but covertly observed, out of the word Divisio, wherein he noteth Quiddam Cacemphaton. Which place some interpreters, for ignorance of the said verbe Visio, have expounded very absurdly.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="33">
        <note n="a">
            <p>So sumptuous were these feastes, that Pontificum Cæna, and Saliares Epulæ, grew into a proverb, to expresse exceeding great bellie cheere, and most delicate fare.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="34">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Seneca, lib. 1 De Clementia writeth, That Claudius caused more Paricides to be sowed within a leather male, etc., in five yeares space, than had beene ever before his daies.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Whether they were hired thereto, or presuming of their owne strength, voluntarily entered upon such a combat, or forced to undergo that dangerous fight, or else exposed unto their greedie jawes for to be worried and devoured by them.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>This devise called heere Automatum, Horace by a Periphrasis, pretily expresseth thus,</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Nervis alienis mobile lignum.</l>
            </quote>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="35">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For with their Graphia, as hath beene noted before, they might do a mischiefe.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="38">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Iræ atque Iracundiæ. Ira signifyeth the hote and momentarie passion of anger, soone enflamed and as soone quenched, and Iracundia seemeth to be taken heere, for the continuance of the said anger, and an inveterate setled wrath. Howsoever our Dictionaries would teach us the contrary. The one may be called Gall or Choler, the other Spleene or Melancholy.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Stultitiam neminem fingere, or rather, Stultitiam stultum neminem fingere, i. That no foole counterfaits folly.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="40">
        <note n="a">
            <p>It was an inconsiderate speech of an Emperor, and foolishly let fall, in the Senate especially, tending much to his discredit and dishonour: as if he sent to the Taverne for his wine, by the pot or bottle, and had not his own cellarage stored therewith.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>These words without all rime or reason were rife in his mouth, which unadvisedly he had taken up, and by use could not leave them.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="41">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Some thinke, that he devised not new letters in the Alphabet, but new formes rather of the former: as namely to write for the Æolick digamma F the inverted character, and for dipthong, ai.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="43">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For, by report of Dion and Xiphilinus his stature farre exceeded the proportion of his years.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="44">
        <note n="a">
            <p>And yet by circumstances it may be collected, that he caught his bane and died in the Palatium at Rome.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="46">
        <note n="a">
            <p>These were, as it plainly appeareth, Questors, Ædiles, Tribunes, Prætors, Censors and Consuls. Of all these, some one or other died, excepting Censors, as Tacitus writeth, 12 Annal.</p>
        </note>
    </div>
</div>