<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <text>
    <body>
      <pb n="1"/>
      <note n="1">Sequentibus Coss. For at Rome they reckoned the yeares according to their Consuls: whose office ordinarily continued one yeare, and began with the yeare, upon the first day of Januarie.</note>
      <note n="2">Or Divorse.</note>
      <note n="3">Of Marius.</note>
      <note n="4">To flie into the Sabines Countrie.</note>
      <note n="5">For Aurelia was his mother.</note>

      <pb n="2"/>
      <note n="1">M. Minutius Thermus.</note>
      <note n="2">Surnamed so of the people in Cilicia named Isauri, whom he subdued.</note>
      <note n="3">So variable and indiscreet.</note>

      <pb n="3"/>
      <note n="1">Whiles hee governed his Province.</note>
      <note n="2">For calling into question so honorable a person.</note>
      <note n="3">Moloni, not Molonis, as Plutarch taketh it, that is, the son of Molon.</note>
      <note n="4">Hibernis mensibus, that is, In the Winter moneths Decemb. Januar. Febr.</note>
      <note n="5">Some reade dignatione in a divers sense.</note>
      <note n="6">Medico, vel amico, that is, a friend.</note>
      <note n="7">Or the rest of his companions and servants.</note>
      <note n="8">To the Cities of Asia, a Province adjoyning.</note>

      <pb n="4"/>
      <note n="1">C. Cotta, M. Crassus, and Cn. Pompeius, who were the chiefe.</note>
      <note n="2">A Tribune of the Commons.</note>
      <note n="3">Lepidus.</note>
      <note n="4">Treasurer.</note>

      <pb n="5"/>
      <note n="1">Of the Goddesse Bona: which were celebrated in Cæsars house, being the Pontifex.</note>
      <note n="2">Called Betica.</note>
      <note n="3">Antistius Vetus.</note>
      <note n="4">In head shire Townes which were called Conventus. Plin. lib. 3. cap. 1. That is, 33. C. Philip. 5.</note>

      <pb n="6"/>
      <note n="1">That had been Consul.</note>
      <note n="2">Or L. rather.</note>

      <pb n="7"/>
      <note n="1">So called of a river, neere into which they dwelt beyond the Po.</note>
      <note n="2">Who was slaine by Spanish Horsemen, of whom hee had the conduct.</note>
      <note n="3">Geminis fratribus, that is, Castor and Pollux, who commonly be called Gemini fratres.</note>
      <note n="4">And yet hee exhibited 320 paire, as Plutarch writeth.</note>

      <pb n="8"/>
      <note n="1">That hee might governe it and place the King againe in his roiall Seate.</note>
      <note n="2">Ptolomeus Auletes the Father of Cleopatra, who many yeares after by Gabinius was restored to his Kingdome.</note>
      <note n="3">As Torrentius saith.</note>
      <note n="4">This is by the figure Prolepsis to be understood of Cæsar when hee was Prætour of the Citie: as who favoured the Faction of Marius both then and before, howsoever it may seem that Suetonius speaketh this of him being Ædile, or presently after his Ædileship: which by Torrentius leave, may well stand with the truth.</note>
      <note n="5">In place of the Pretor.</note>
      <note n="6">Cæsar.</note>

      <pb n="9"/>
      <note n="1">That is, Egipt and the restoring of the king afore said.</note>
      <note n="2">Which were 35.</note>
      <note n="3">But not entred yet into the Office.</note>
      <note n="4">Ultimum supplicium.</note>
      <note n="5">As if he ment by ultimum supplicium, imprisonment or some lesse punishment then death.</note>
      <note n="6">Quintus Cicero.</note>
      <note n="7">M. Cicero.</note>

      <pb n="10"/>
      <note n="1">Of Consul and Senate.</note>
      <note n="2">Plutarch nameth Curio for one of them.</note>
      <note n="3">Of M. T. Cicero the Consul his yeere which now drew to an end.</note>
      <note n="4">That is, to Cn. Pompeius.</note>
      <note n="5">Surnamed Nepos (as Valerius witnesseth) for his riotous life and behaviour.</note>

      <pb n="11"/>
      <note n="1">Indice, some reade Judice, that is, as if Judex were his surname.</note>

      <pb n="12"/>
      <note n="1">Ex prætura, whereby it appeareth he was Prator Urbanus.</note>
      <note n="2">Cato, and his followers.</note>
      <note n="3">Optimates.</note>

      <pb n="13"/>
      <note n="1">Consull.</note>

      <pb n="14"/>
      <note n="1">Turbis alias culpis, that is, Trespasses or offences.</note>
      <note n="2">Obnunciaret, by pronouncing out of the Augurs learning, that the day was nefastus et non comitialis, that is, no Law-day.</note>
      <note n="3">Per edicta, some read, per lictores, that is, by his Serjeants and Officers.</note>
      <note n="4">At the discretion of xx. men deputed Commissioners for that purpose.</note>
      <note n="5">For that they had taken things at too high a rate.</note>

      <pb n="15"/>
      <note n="1">Three a clock in the after-noone.</note>
      <note n="2">Indicem, others read Judicem, that is Vettius Judex.</note>
      <note n="3">Id est Vettius Judex aforesaid: For, dead hee was found in prison by night.</note>
      <note n="4">Whom hee promised in mariage the daughter of Cn. Pompeius.</note>

      <pb n="16"/>
      <note n="1">Piso.</note>
      <note n="2">Cn. Pompeius.</note>
      <note n="3">Whether they should be repealed or stand in force.</note>
      <note n="4">When he was Consul.</note>

      <pb n="17"/>
      <note n="1">For that hee was extraordinarily absent, longer than the Law Sempronia did permit.</note>
      <note n="2">The bird Galerita or Cassita, so called of a crest, upon the head. This Legion it should seeme ware Plumes of feathers in their crests of Helmets, whereupon it tooke that name.</note>

      <pb n="18"/>
      <note n="1">Namely Cato, Plutarch.</note>

      <pb n="19"/>
      <note n="1">Aurelia a Dame of singular chastitie.</note>
      <note n="2">Neptem, alii nepotem, that is, Nephew.</note>
      <note n="3">By Milo.</note>
      <note n="4">That is, a hundred millians of Sesterces, and 20, as Plinie writeth, lib. 36, cap. 15, if Glareanus readeth truly, Millies ducenties.</note>
      <note n="5">Domesticatim.</note>

      <pb n="20"/>
      <note n="1">So, hee was great Unkle unto her, like as he was to Octavius Augustus, the Emperour.</note>
      <note n="2">Or Patrone.</note>

      <pb n="21"/>
      <note n="1">Ei plebiscito.</note>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>