<div type="annotations" subtype="C._Julius_Caesar_Dictator">
    <div type="notes" n="1">
        <note n="a">
            <p>CAIUS CÆSAR, hee died sodainly at Pisæ in Italy, as hee put on his shooes in a morning, when hee was newe risen. Plin. Natur. Hist. lib. 7, c. 53.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Flamen Dialis, i. the great Priest of Jupiter. Three Flamens there were at Rome, by the first Institution: Dialis of Jupiter, Martialis of Mars, Quirinalis of Romulus; and these were the principall: unto whom (in processe of time) 12 more were adjoyned, attending all upon severall Godds and Goddesses. Carol. Sig. de ant. Jure Rom. lib. 1, cap. 19.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Ut repudiaret. In the civill Lawe, wee observe a difference betweene Repudium and Divortium. Repudium, when the man rejecteth and casteth off the woman betrothed only unto him before mariage in this forme, Conditione tua non utor. And in this wise Cæsar and Cossutia parted before. Divortium, when hee putteth her away after shee is his wedded wife, with these solemne words: Res tuas tibi habeto, or Res tuas tibi agito. Howbeit, in this place Repudiare is to be taken in this latter sense, for Cornelia was his wife, and had borne him a daughter. Paul. Modestin Caius.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>I take it, that he meaneth such inheritances, as are not Testamentariæ, but Legitima: 1. Which when one dieth intestate, fall unto the children first, and for default of them, to the Agnati and Gentiles, i. to the next of kinne, and to the name. These are called with us, the Right heires at common Law. Vide Car. Sigon. de Judiciis, lib. cap. 4. De antiq. jur. civ. Rom. lib. 1, cap. 7.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>The principall of them was, Cornelius Phagitas, a Freed man of Sulla, unto whom Cæsar gave two talents, for to escape his hands. See cap. 74, and Plutarchus.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>It belonged unto these Votaries and Nunnes of Vesta, to goe betweene parties offended, and make reconciliation. See more hereof Alex. ab Alexandr. Genial die, lib. 5, cap. 12.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="2">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Young gentlemen or noble bloud, the better to bee trained up in martiall feats, and the knowledge of any Province affaires, were wont to attend the LL. Deputies there, and to be entertained with them in the same pavilion, as familiar companions. Cic. orat. pro Cælio et Plancio.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Libertines were such properly, as of bondmen were manumised and made Free, although Sueto. elsewhere, to wit in Cl. Cæs. nameth the children of such, Libertines; by which it appeareth that hee confoundeth them with Ingenui, i. Freeborne.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Clients have a relation to their Patrones: and as these were Patritii and Nobles, so the other were Commoners. And such a mutuall and reciprocall entercourse of duetie was betweene them, that as the Patrons were ready to instruct in the knowledge of the lawes, to defend and protect their Clients, who had put themselves into their patronage: so these were bound to attende their Patrons when they went abroad into the city and returned home, to relieve them with their purse in the bestowing of their daughters etc. And lawfull it was for neither of them to enforme, to depose, to give their voices, or to side with adversaries, one against another, without the note and guilt of treachery and perfidious prodicion.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Made of oken branches, or of Ilex, or Esculus, bearing mast, in defect of the Oke for saving the life of a citizen. Although Generals of the field were honoured therewith, in other respects.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="3">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Who being Consull with Q. Catulus Luctatius, went about to repeale and anull all the Actes of Sulla late deceased, and so kindled a newe civill warre.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="4">
        <note n="a">
            <p>By the death of Lepidus, whom his Colleague Catulus drave out of Italy into Sardinia, where he dyed, as some write, of a violent Rheume: or as others, with a deepe thought that he tooke, upon intelligence that he had of his wives adultery, in which melancholy he pyned away. Plutarch.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="5">
        <note n="a">
            <p>These Tribunes Militarie, call them Colonels over a thousand footmen, whereupon they tooke that name first, to wit, when the Romaine Legion consisted of 3000 according to the three ancient Tribes, Rhamnium, Lucerum and Tatiensium: or High Marshals, as Budæus would have them to be, considering the execution of their office in the campe, not much unlike to our Kn. Marshals in these daies; some by vertue of an Act or Lawe preferred by Rutilus Rufus, were chosen in the Armie by the L. Generall, and named Rutuli or Rufuli, others by the voices of the people in their publick assemblyes for Elections called Comitia, and for distinction sake, named Comitiati. And such a Tribune Militarie was Cæsar in this place.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Rogatione Plotia. A bill preferred, and the same as a Lawe not yet enacted, was called Rogatio, (as one would say) Interrogatio: for that the people were demaunded and asked their opinions in this forme of words: Velitisné, jubeatisné Quirites, etc.: Is it your will and pleasure, yee citizens of Rome, that such a thing should passe, or no? And of him who proposed the same, it tooke the name.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="8">
        <note n="a">
            <p>By the Latine Colonies, are meant here those beyond the Po, which being before endowed Latinitate, i. with the freedome of Latium, stood not therwith contented, unlesse they might be donati civitate, i. enjoy the Franchises and Freedome of Rome.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="10">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Commitium was one part of the Forum Romanum, wherein stood the Rostra, and the people used to assemble for election of Magistrates, for making of Lawes, and hearing of publike Orations.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="11">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Sulla, in the time of his proscription and outlawing of the adverse faction of C. Marius, ordained two talents for every one that killed any of the proscribed and brought him his head, not sparing master or father: but that the servant might kill his master and the sonne his father; nay hee made it death if they saved any such.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Of Cornelius Sulla.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="12">
        <note n="a">
            <p>T. Labienus. Cicero and Hortensius pleaded for him.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>For, to kill a Tribune of the Commons, who were Sacrosancti and Inviolabili, would beare the Action Perduellionis. And that was laide to Rabirius a Senatour his charge, although indeede hee slewe him not, but one Scava: mary, when he was killed, hee caused his head, in most ludibrious manner to be caried about. Now was the crime Perduellionis, all one with treason against the Common wealth, or a principall person of State: or else Felonie in some high degree.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>The liberty of appealing unto the people, was graunted by Tullus Hostilius the third king of the Romaines, as appeareth by Livius, in the case of Horatius, for killing his owne sister.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="13">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Q. Lutatius Catulus, and P. Servilius Isauricus.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="15">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Cæsar envying such an honour unto Catulus, as to reedifie and dedicate the Capitol consumed with fire, a peece of worke that Sulla the Dictatour tooke in hand but finished not, and the onely thing wherby his felicity was not compleat, would have put him by it and conferred it upon another and therefore put the matter in question before the bodie of the people, there to bee discussed and debated, whether it were their minde and will that Catulus should doe it, or some other.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>A Lawe is said to be promulged, after it is once proposed for to bee considered upon, untill it be fully enacted: during which time, reasons were alledged for the convenience thereof, or otherwise; and free it was for any man who had a voice to impugne or allowe it.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Optimates and Populares, were in the citie of Rome opposite either against other, and are lively described by Cicero in his Oration, pro Sextio, in these wordes. Duo genera in hac civitate semper fuerunt eorum, qui versari in rep. atque in ea se excellentius gerere studuerunt. Quibus ex generibus, alteri Populares, alter, Optimates et haberi et esse voluerunt. Qui ea quæ faciebant, quæque dicebant, multitudini jucunda esse volebant, Populares: qui autem ita se gerebant, ut sua consilia optimo cuique probarentur; Optimates habebantur. Item. Quis ergo est Optimas? quis? De numero si quæris innumerabiles, neque enim aliter stare possemus. Sunt principes consilii publici. Sunt qui eorum sectam sequuntur. Sunt maximorum Ordinum homines quibus patet Curia, Sunt municipes Rusticique; Roma, Sunt negotia gerentes, sunt etiam Libertini Optimates. Wherby it appeareth, that those were counted Optimates, not simply of noble birth, and of great wealth, etc.: but were they Patritii, Equites, or Plebeii, if they stoode for good thinges, or favoured those that so did; nay, whether they were Burgesses of Free Burroughes, yeomen of the country following husbandry, Merchants and Tradesmen, or very Libertines, so they affected good causes, they were reckoned in the number of Optimates. On the other side, as many as aymed onely at this, to please and content the multitude, were they never so well borne or otherwise qualified, they went in the rancke of Populares; so that it seemeth, that Populares were the Forensis factio, that Livie writeth of, and whome Q. Fabius reduced all in to the foure Tribus urbanas; and Optimates, the Tribus rusticæ, wherein was integer populus, fautor et cultor bonorum. Thus much of the strickt signification of this worde Optimates. But for as much as commonly fewe of the Nobilitie and Gentry of Rome were Popular, and as fewe of the Communaltie favourers of the best things usually; by these Optimates, or the better sort, are ment the Patritii and Gentlemen.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Upon the Kalends of January, i. the first day of the yeare, the Consuls entred their officie, on which day attended they were obsequiously by those better sort of the citizens and their friends, waiting upon them, when they went up into the Capitoll for to Sacrifice, and home againe. On this day likewise it appeareth, that Cæsar began his Pretorshipp.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="16">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This purple Robe bordered, called Prætexta, was a Garment not proper to the Pretors onely, but to other Magistrates also. Embrodered it was or garded about with purple. For Plinie writeth, that Lentulus Spinter Ædile Curule, wore in his Robe, purple of a duble die, called thereupon, Dibapha. And thereupon it was called in Greek περιπόρφυρος. And not onely citie-Magistrates, but Priestes and children of gentle birth used the same. Setting aside the border of purple, it was otherwise white.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>By Curia simply without any adjunction, is ment Curia Hostilia, as witnesseth Alex. ab Alexandro. i. A statly place built by K. Tullius Hostilius in the Forum Romanum, neere unto the Rostra: where, as in the Parliament house assembled the Senators ordinarily to consult upon the affaires of State. For, other places there were, under the name of Curia, wherein likewise the Senat met together, as Curia Pompeii, in which Cæsar was murdered, Divi Augusti, etc., but then they had their addition. I am not ignorant, that other Curiæ there were for the Pontifies and Priestes. To say nothing how the people was divided into Curisa, id est, Parishes, and in every of them was a Curia, and a superintendent or Curate called Curio.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="17">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Superiour Magistrates, bee the Consuls, Pretours and Censors, the rest as Ædiles, Questors, were accounted inferiour, etc.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="18">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Crassus is named for one, who entred into a bond for him of 830 talents, what time Cæsar deeply indebted, said, bis millies et quingenties centena millia numum sibi adesse oportere, ut nihil haberet, id est, that 250 millions of sesterces would but set him cleare with the world.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>By the Lawes, none might make suit for a tryumph, but whiles they remained absent without the citie, nor for a Consulship except they were present as private persons within the citie. In these streights, Cæsar made choyce to be Consull, and gave over his right to a triumph, for the victorie obteyned in Spaine over the Calleci and Lusitanes.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="19">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The manner was at Rome, that they who sued for Magistracies should for the obteining of the peoples voices and suffrages make promise of certaine summes of money to be distributed amonge them, and such as were appointed to deale the saide Largesse, they called Divisores. Now, for that the Election of Consuls passed by Comitia centuriata, that is, by the assembly of the people, by their centuries or Hundreds according as Serv. Tullus first ordeyned them, therefore was this money to bee devided amongst them, as they gave their voices.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Provinces signifie three things, the countries conquered or yeilded, and the same governed by Roman Deputies: and this is the proper and primative signification thereof, also the Region wherein any Roman Generall by commission from the state maketh warr: and last of all, what publick function or affaires soever is to be administred. In which sence it is heere taken.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Either for the cutting downe of trees for the best commodities. or els for a gaurd to be kept neare unto them, to suppresse the outrage committed by theeves, haunting the same and robbing and spoyling passengers.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>To amend the waies and beaten pathes, where, either wayfairing men or beastes shoulde passe with more ease. And verily these were base matters and requiring no great forces to bee performed: and so by consequence, the Consuls employed therein could compasse no greate projects and therefore lesse to be feared.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>This societie bred the Civill warre that after ensued, betweene Ceasar and Pompeius unto which the Poet Lucan alluded writing thus.</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Tu causa malorum</l>
                <l>Facta tribus dominis communis Roma.</l>
            </quote>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="20">
        <note n="a">
            <p>As well to avoide tedious canvassings and consultations as to provide for the historie and memoriall of every matter.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>One of the Consuls onely had the twelve Lictors going before him, with the rods and axes to witt, each of them their moneths, by turnes one after the other, Ne si ambo fusces haberent duplicatus terror videretur. As Livie writeth: An ordinance as auncient well neere, as the first institution of Consuls.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Accensus, an officer attendant upon Magistrate, so named ab acciendo, id est, of giving summons to any for appearance, or of calling any to the Magistrate.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Great indulgences, immunities and priviledges were graunted by the Romanes unto those that had jus trium liberorum: but as Appian writeth more particularly to the explication of this place, there assembled 20000 together, craving maintenance and foode every man, for three children and more that they had.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Publicanes were they that either for a certaine rent tooke to ferme the publicke revenewes of the City, whether it were corne, pasturage, customes, impostes, etc., or undertooke by the grosse to make provision for the state, or to build and repaire any citie-workes, etc.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="21">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This was not more maiorum, for then his sentence should have bene demaunded first, that by the Censors was elected Princeps Senatus, id est, President of the Counsell: but extraordinarily, as appeareth by Aul. Gel. Noct. Attic. lib. 4, cap. 10, and lib. 14, сар. 7.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="22">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For as Livie testifieth, lib. 38. The Romanes triumphed oftener over the Gaules, than over all the world beside.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Which Vatinius a Tribune of the Commons proposed in the behalfe of Julius Ceasar, that for five yeares together, hee should (without casting lots, and the Senates decree), governe Cisalpine Gaule, together with Illyricum: contrarie to the Lawe Sempronia, which provided that such Provinciall Governours, or LL. Deputies, should yearely bee chosen by the Senate. Carol. Sigon. lib. 2, cap. 1, de antiquo jure provinciarum.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Cisalpina Gallia, is that, which lay betweene Italy and the Alpes, divided into Cispadana and Transpadana, according to the site thereof, either on this side, or beyond the river Po: it caried the name likewise of Togata, either because it was much inhabited by the Romanes, or for that unto this Province the Romane Robe Toga was graunted, or els in regard that the saide Province was more civill and peaceable, than the other called Transalpina.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Comata Gallia, a part of Gallia Transalpina, lying beyond the Alpes, from Italy toward Spaine: so called for the long haire that they wore: and συνεκδοχικῶς put for the whole Transalpine Province, like as Brachata, one part of the said Province, so called of a certaine kinde of apparell, is taken for the whole and confounded with Comata.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>This terme, which they commonly use, who threaten such as they contemne, may bee drawen to an obsceene and filthy sense, not heere to bee named: and albeit Ceasar hereby was galled to the quick, as privie to himselfe, of the passive abuse of his body with K. Nicomedes, yet in his answere thereto, he turned it to another signification.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>Warlike women, so called (as some write) of their paps which they did cut off and sear, therby to bee more expedite and nimble in fight, and to shoot at greater ease. See Strabo, Justin. Q. Curtius, Herodotus, etc.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="23">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For, if his Questour or Treasurer had beene condemned, it would have beene a shrewde precedent for his conviction also in the same cause.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="24">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Who stoode in Election for the Consulshippe: so called of the whited robe, which they put on, who sued for such Magistracies and places of Honour. For whereas the ordinarie gowne that Romaine citizens daily wore, was white of it selfe, against such a time they made it whiter with chalke: so that a difference there was betweene Toga alba, and candida, whereupon they were called Candidati, as appeareth by Macrobius, and T. Livius, lib. 4 ab urb. condita.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Supplication, was a solemne Honour done unto the Lord Generall of a Province upon some notable victorie. For the manner was, that LL. Governours, after they were by their Souldiers salute by the name of Emperour, i. Soveraigne commanders, should send their Letters dight with Lawrell unto the Senate, wherin they required both to be stiled by the saide name, and also to have solemne processions made by the people in the Temples, and thanksgiving unto the Gods for their good successe, which solemnity, at the first continued but one day, as T. Livius reporteth in the 304 yeare after the foundation of Rome: but processe of time, it grewe to 4 and 12. And at length, Ceasar obtained it for 15, yea and 20 daies together, as Plutarch testifieth in his life, and himselfe in his owne Comentaries, of the Gauls warre.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="26">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Super HS. millies. This character HS. standeth for a Silver coyne in Rome, which is the three halfe pence, farthing, cue, the 4 part of Denarius: and is called Sextertius quasi sesquitertius: as one would say, valuing two brasen Asses and the halfe of a third: so common a peece of money there, that Numus put absolutely alone, standeth for it and no other coine: so that Millies sestertium and millies nummum are both one. Now if the Romaine Denier bee valued at vii d. ob. with us, and 100 Deniers arise to one pound starling: this summe here set downe, that is to say, a Sesterne multiplyed by the Adverbe Millies, amounteth by just account unto 781250 li. starling. And thereto for the overdeale or surplusage ducenties sestertium, which is one 5 part of the former summe, it maketh up 937500 li. sterling. A thing that may be thought incredible, but that we reade that Ceasar himselfe saide, hee was 250 millions in debt when he went into Spaine, and P. Clodius, whom Milo slewe, dwelt in a house, the purchase whereof cost him almost 15 millions. No marvell therefore, if so many houses, which Cæsar must needs buy for the plot of ground aforesaid and in so populous a city, cost not so little as a hundred millions.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="27">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The dole given by a Prince or great man unto the people, was properly called a Congiarie, which word tooke name of the measure Congius among the Romaines, consisting of 6 Sextarii, and is answerable to our gallon: by which Oyle or wine was given. Howbeit καταχρηστικώς, any such publicke munificence, in mony or otherwise is so called: and in this place, by it are ment other gifts bestowed upon private persons.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="28">
        <note n="a">
            <p>In some copies, wee reade, Quando nec plebisicito Pompeius postca abrogasset. To this sence: That Cæsar beeing absent, was not eligible by vertue of an Act made by Pompeius to that effect, considering he had not abrogated the same by any ordinance of the people, but onely of his owne authority corrected it after it stood upon record in the city chamber.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="30">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This hath reference unto his violent dealing with his fellowe Consull Bibulis. See before in the 20 chapter.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="33">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The fourth finger next unto the little one, honoured especially with a golde ring, for that there is an evident arterie from the heart reaching unto it. Gellius. But Plinie alledgeth another reason.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>He would doe any thing rather than his souldiers so well deserving at his hands, should not bee satisfied: such a credit caried the ring upon a Romaines finger.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Which is the State and worth of a Romaine knight or gentleman according to this verce of Horace: Si quadringintis sex, septem millia desint, Plebs eris, etc., and amounteth to 3125 li. starling.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="34">
        <note n="a">
            <p>As if Petreius, Afranius, and Varro had no skill in martiall feats.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>He meaneth Cn. Pompeius, for his militarie knowledge and warlike exploytes surnamed Magnus, i. the Greate: whose principall power was now overthrowne at Ilerda in Spaine.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="37">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Lychnuchos Gestantibus, bearing either young men that caried Linckes, Torches, and cresset lights: or els braunches and candle stickes, resembling them, and holding the said lights. Some reade, Lychnos gestantibus, i. bearing lights: but to the same affect.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="38">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Super bina HS., i. Sestertia: that is to say, 15 li. 12s. 6d.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Quaterna Sestertia, i. 31 li. 5s.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Vicena quaterna millia, 187 li. 10s. By which reckning, hee gave unto horsemen foure times as much as to footemen. Looke in the marginall note to the text, and you shall finde this donative much more: which may seeme incredible: but consider what provinces hee spoyled, and what pillage hee made, in regard whereof hee was called of the Greekes χρηματυποιὸς ἀνήρ.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Denos modios, in round reckoning may goe for ten peckes or hoopes with us.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Totidem libras, i. so many pynts,</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>Trecenos nummos, i. 46s. 10d. ob.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="g">
            <p>Centenos, i. 15s. 7d. ob. with the better. (Which being put together make 100 Denarii or Drachemes, that is, one Mina, and amount in all to 3 li. 2s. 6d.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="h">
            <p>Bina millia nummorum, i. 15 lib. 12s. 6d.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="i">
            <p>Quingenos sestertios, i. 31. 18s. 1d. ob.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="39">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Regionatim urbe tota. Rome, as Plinie witnesseth, was divided into 14 regions, and every one of these had their severall Stage Playes by themselves.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The Games Circenses, I take to be so called of the Greet Cirque or Shewplace, wherein they were performed: and not of swordes, wherewith they were environed, as one would say, Circa enses. Indeede these games resembled the Olympick in Greece by Elis, where the runners with chariots were hemmed in of the one side with the running river, and of the other with swordes pitched pointwise, that they should hold on the race directly, and not swerve aside without danger. Herein were performed running with horses and chariots, justing, tilt, and turnement: baiting and chasing of wild beasts, etc.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Pyrrhica: Of some, thought to bee the same that Enoplia was, a kinde of Moriske daunce, after a warlike manner in harnois, devised in Creta first by Pyrrhus. Plin. lib. 7 Nat. Hist. cap. 56. In which young gentlemen were trained to exercise all parts of the body by sundry gestures as well to avoide all venues and defende themselves, as to annoy and offend the enimie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>This Decimus Laberius was a poet also, that kind which wrote wanton Poems or lascivious Comœdies called Mimi. For, howsoever in all Stage Playes, there is represented a lively imitation in gesture and voice of others, yet in these Mimi, these same are done after a more licentious manner and without all modest reverence, even in unseemely and filthy arguments as Ovid testifieth in these words, imitantes turpia Mimi. It seemeth therefore, that as well the Poemes as the Authours and Actours be called Mimi.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Orchestra, is here taken for the most commodious place in the Theatre, wherein the Senators and Nobles of Rome were allowed to sit and behold the Stage Playes, apart from the people. For so the Poet Juvenal understandeth it in these words, Similemque videbis Orchestram et populum.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>As touching this Orchestra and the Poet Laberius above named, Seneca in his second booke of Controversies, and third controversie, reporteth thus. Julius Cæsar, at the solemnitie of his Playes, brought Laberius forth to act upon the Stage: and when he had made him a gentleman, or Knight of Rome, willed him to take his place among them of that degree, but as he came toward them, they all sat so close and neere one another, that there was no rowme for him. Now by the way, you must understand that Cicero then in place, had gotten himselfe an ill name, for that hee was no fast and faithfull friend, either to Pompeius, or to Ceasar, but a flatterer of them both. Againe, Cæsar at that time had chosen many unto the range of Senatours, partly to supply and make up their number, which during the late civill warres was much diminished, and in part to gratifie those who had well deserved of him and the side. Cicero therefore alluding to the extraordinary number of newe Senatours, sent unto Laberius as hee passed by, this word merily, Recepissem te nisi angustè sederem, i. I would have taken you to mee and give you a place, but that I sit my selfe very streight. Then Laberius returned this pleasant answere backe unto him, Atqui solebas duabus sellis sedere, i. And yet you were wont to sit upon two stooles, skoffing at him for his double dealing with Pompeius and Ceasar.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="g">
            <p>The Troy fight, was in warlike manner on horsbacke, brought by Æneas into Italy. The manner whereof is described by Virgil, Eneid, 5.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="h">
            <p>These Goales called in Latine Meta, above which the horses and chariots ranne, were in fashion broad beneath and sharpe above, in manner of Pyramides, Steeples or cocks of hey, and for their mater, of wood first, or of soft gritstone, but afterwards of marble and laid over with gold.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="i">
            <p>Concerning this Cirque why Cæsar enlarged it and brought water round about it, reade Plinie, 8 lib. cap. 7 and 36 lib. cap. 15 Naturall Hist.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="j">
            <p>To try maisteries in footemanshippe, leaping, flinging the coit or hammer, darting and wrestling: which Game was called Pentathlon, of those five kindes of exercises.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="k">
            <p>In minore Codeta, which was a place on the further side of Tiberis, so called of certaine plots of young springs or shootes there growing which resemble horsetailes. Some reade In morem cochleæ, that is, narrow beneath and broad above, like to the shell of a periwincle or such like fish.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="40">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This day is called Bissextus, and falleth out to bee the fift day before the end of Februarie, to wit, the sixt before the Calends of March, by interposing whereof wee say twise Sext Calend Martii, of which day our leape yeare hath the name Bissextilis.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="41">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which by the first institution were 300, and by occasion of the late troubles much impaired.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Patritios allegit. For those that were Plebei generis, might bee Senatours: or els, as some expound it, he advanced divers to the degree and ranck of the Patritii.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>All but Consuls, Prætors and Censors, were counted inferiour Magistrates.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>For the Censours with the publicke Notaries ordinarily tooke this reviewe, and that in Campus Martius, and Villa publica.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>By reason of so great a number receiving corne from the State, the purveyance hereof stoode the city yearely as Plutarch writeth in a thousand two hundred and fiftie talents.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="42">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For they might discontinue out of Italy eleven yeares. Plutarch.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Such were called Comites, or quasi ex cohorte Prætoria, as it were gentlemen of the privie chamber.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Noverum tabularum. To wit, when the olde bonds being cancelled, and therby former debts remitted, new obligations were made.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Parricidis, i. Parenticidis, such as kill father, mother, brother, sisters and such like, nere in bloud, as also, any other man or woman wilfully, according to the Lawe of K. Nume, Si quis hominem liberum sciens monti duit parricida esto.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="43">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Repetundarum convictos. Such governours as by way of extortion pilled and polled the Provinces which they ruled: who after their time expired, were many times called judicially to their answeres.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Many Lawes there were called Sumptuariæ and Cibariæ, to restraine the excesse at the table, as namely Fannia, Licinia, Æmilya, Julia, etc. Read Aul. Gell. Noct. Att. lib. 2, cap. 24, Macro. Saturnal. lib. 3.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="44">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Of whom Terentianus writeth thus, Vir doctissimus undecunque Varro.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Isthmus is a narrow straite or foreland by Corinth, five miles over, lying betweene the two seas Ionium and Ægeum, or as Plinie writeth, lib. 4, cap. 4, betweene the two Gulfes Corinthiacus and Saronicus. The cutting through whereof, was attempted before by K. Demetrius, and afterwards by C. Caligula and Nero, but without effect.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Which Crassus before him had not done; and therefore was overthrowne.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="45">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Comitiali Morbo, so called, for that the assemblies of the people called Comitia, were dissolved and broke up by occasion thereof, in case any one among them fell downe of that disease, according as Q. Serenus Semonicus hath testified in these verses, cap. 57.</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Est morbi species subiti, cui nomen ab illo est,</l>
                <l>Quod fieri nobis suffragia justa recusant.</l>
                <l>Sæpe etenim membris acri languere caducis,</l>
                <l>Concilium populi labes horrenda diremit.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>As also for that, they who were subject thereto, fell into a fit thereof ordinarily at such assemblyes, if they were crossed in their suites and businesses there. Cornelius Celsus calleth it Morbum maiorem, i. a great sicknesse. It is named likewise ἱερὸν νόσημα, i. the sacred disease, either because it affecteth the heade, which is the most honorable place of the body and the seate of the Soule, or in regard of the greatnesse thereof, which the Græcians expresse by the ἱερὸν. Also Epilepsia, for the sodaine invasion of it. Herculeus Morbus, either for the strength of the malady, whereby a man is forced to fall, or because Hercules was troubled therewith. Plinie nameth it, Senticus, for the hurt that it doth unto the bodie: others Caducus, for that upon it, men fall to the ground. It is called moreover Lunaticus, of the Moone: because it keepeth time with the course of the Moone, or apprehendeth them that are borne in the change thereof, as the same Serenus reporteth in these verses:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Huc quoque commemorant dubicæ per tempora Lunæ,</l>
                <l>Conceptum talem, quem sæpe ruina profudit.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>Lastly Hippocrates nameth it Pædicon, i. puerilem morbum, for that children bee subject thereto: whereupon some tearme it, Mater puerorum.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>This manner of going so loosely girt, might signifie a dissolute and effeminate wanton. Hereupon Cicero made choyce in the civill warre to take part with Pompeius against Ceasar: and when one asked him how it came to passe, that in siding with Pompeius hee was so much overseene, for that hee had the worse, this answere hee made, Præcinctura me decepit, i. deceived I was by that loose girding of his,</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="49">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Cæsar derived his pedegree from Jülus, the sonne of Æneas, whose mother was Venus.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The grace which is in the Latine cannot be expressed well in English, because the word, Subegit, carieth a double sence, the one signifieth the conquering of a nation, and so it is taken in the former place, as it is applyed to Gaule: the other, the wanton abuse of the bodie: in which acception it is to bee understood in reference to Ceasar, abused by K. Nichomedes.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="50">
        <note n="a">
            <p>In the twofold sense likewise of these two words, Tertia and Deducta, lyeth the pleasant grace of this conceipted speech. By the one, may be understoode, that a third part of the price was deducted by the other Cicero ment, That her daughter Tertia was brought by her to his bed.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="51">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This Distichon, or ii verses, which his souldiers after their licentious manner in the Tryumph chaunted may thus be Englished.</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Looke to your wives, yee cytizens, a lecher bald wee bring.</l>
                <l>In Gaule Adultery cost thee gold, heere 'tis but borrowing.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>For, as hee borrowed of other men, so hee lent or paide as much againe, in that his owne wife Pompeia, as is thought, was kept by P. Clodius.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="52">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Such a vessell as this named here Thelamegos, and by Seneca, 7 lib. de Beneficiis, Naviscubiculata, Ptolomæus Philopater, as witnesseth Athenæus, had, which caried in length halfe a furlong ¹, in bredth 30 cubites, and in heigth little lesse then 40. ¹ Semistadium.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Impudicitiæ. I observe, that both in this Authour and also in other approved writers, Impudicitia, is properly and peculiarly taken for that abhominable uncleannesse onely, which is named Sodomie: like as Pudicitia, for the integritie of the bodie, and clearenesse from that detestable filthinesse. And so, Pudicus and Impudicus are to bee understoode.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="54">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which commeth to 23 pound, 8 shillings, 9 pence, and is not much more than halfe the worth. According to Budeus it was 7 pound dim of Silver for one of Gold.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>For it was esteemed a great honour to be called Allies and Associates, or stiled Kings, by the people of Rome.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="56">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Anticatones. Whereas Cicero had written in the prayse of Cato (Uticensis) he wrote two bookes against the said Cato, which he called Anticatones.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="61">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Venus, surnamed Genitrix, i. Mother, Cæsar honoured, as the goddesse from the which he was descended, by Jülus or Ascanius, her nephew.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="62">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The principall ensigne or standerd of the Romane Legion was an Ægle of Silver, reared upon a Speare toppe, the poynt whereof beneath was sharpe, and fastened into the ground: and the same stood within a little shrine, not to bee remooved, but when the Armie was on foote.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="64">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Dion, lib. 42, and Appian, Civil. 2, report this otherwise: namely, that he forsoke the said Coat armour (it clogged him so much), and so the Ægyptians got it.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="68">
        <note n="a">
            <p>E viatico suo. Albeit viaticum properly signifyeth the store and provision set by for a journey, yet heere it is put for the wealth and the substance of a souldier: like as in Horat. lib. 2, Epist. 2.</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Luculli miles collecta viatica multis</l>
                <l>Aerumnis, etc.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>In which sense, ἐφίδιεν likewise in Greeke is taken.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Plinie calleth it Lapsana, lib. 19, cap. 8, Natural. Histor. A kinde of wilde worte or cole.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>To be tithed, i. everie tenth man to suffer death. Appian.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Which ordinarily consisted of 550 footemen, and 66 horse, whereof ten went to a Legion. Some, I wot well had more, some fewer. But for this place it may suffice, that it was the tenth part of a Legion.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="70">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Quirites, i. Romane Citizens. As freed now from their alleageance, which by their military oath they were bound unto.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="71">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which was a great abuse offered, among the Barbarians, who set great store by their beards, and suffered them to grow very long.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="76">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Thensa or Tensa et ferculum, a Chariot of Silver or Yvorie, with a frame in it sustaining the Images of the gods, which was drawen in most solemne and stately manner unto the Pulvinar.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Pulvinar. A bed loft, or place where certaine rich beds were made for the said Images to be laid upon.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Flamin. A certaine priest, bearing the name of that god, for whose service he was instituted. As Dialis of Jupiter, Martialis of Mars, Quirinalis of Romulus, etc. Cic. 2 Phil saith that M. Antonius was Flamen to Julius Cæsar.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Luperci, were certaine young men, who at the licentious feast, Lupercalia, instituted to the honour of Pan Lycæus, otherwise called Inuus, by Romulus and Remus, ran up and downe naked in the Citie of Rome. A new kind of these Luperci ordained Cæsar, of his owne name called Juliani. At this feast Lupercalia, M. Antonius played the part of a Lupercus, at which solemnitie, when Cæsar sat in a Throne of Gold, arayed in a purple robe, the said M. Antonius attempted to doe upon his head the royall Band, called a Diademe. Cicero.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Whereas, before it was called Quintilis, he named it Julius.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>This was Caninius Rebitus: of whose Consulship, there go divers jestes, as namely these, whereof Cicero was the Author. A vigilant Consull we have had of Caninius, who in all his Consulship never slept winke, Also, A consull we have had so severe and Censar-like, as that during his Consulship, no man dined, no man supped, no man so much as once slept. Likewise Pithalus said of him, Heretofore we had Flamines Diales, and now wee have Consuls Diales, playing upon the æquivocation or double sense of the word Dialis, which being derived of Διός, i. Jupiter, signifieth his Flamin: but of Dies, i. a day, betokeneth a day Consul or Flamin.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="77">
        <note n="a">
            <p>According to Lucane, Omnia Cæsar erat. Cæsar was all in all.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Well knowne it is that Sulla was passing well learned both in Greeke and Latine. But in that he resigned up the absolute power of his Dictatorship, which he tooke upon him, for an hundred and twentie yeares, that is to say, for ever; Cæsar said he was no Gramarian, quia nescivit dictare, quod munus est Grammatici: alluding to the ambiguous word dictare, i. to endite, or give precepts as Grammarians doe to their schollers, as also, to commaund absolutely, whereof it may seeme that Dictator tooke the name.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="78">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Who were in number 10.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Or, if I may for Pontius Aquila: spoken by way of a scornefull Ironia.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="79">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Plebeio, and not Plebi, for the commons could not endure that name, as may appeare by Ciceroes words in his second Philippica or invective against M. Antonius: Thou shewedst the Diademe. The people all over the common place gave a groane thereat. Thou wert about to set it upon his head, to the great griefe and sorrow of the people, hee rejected it, with as great joy and applause of theirs.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The name Optimus Maximus, wherewith the auncients styled Jupiter, signifieth most bountifull and most powerfull: wherein it is observed that Bountie goeth before Power: because as M. Tullius writeth, it is better and more acceptable to doe good unto all, then to have power over all.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>In Ægypt: a renowmed Citie, built by King Alexander the Great for the pleasant site much commended, and therefore might bee affected by Cæsar: at which, there is no day almost through the yeare, but the Inhabitants behold the Sunne shining cleare upon them and which Ammianus calleth Verticem omnium civitatum, i. The chiefe of Cities.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Ilium, a Citie where Troy stood the Citizens whereof, as Strabo writeth, Cæsar in memoriall of his progenitors from thence descended, and namely, from Jülus or Ascanius the Sonne of Æneas, had indowed with many franchises and immunities, and therefore it caried some likelihood, that he ment there to make his abode.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>These Quindecim-viri, or fifteene men, were instituted in the daies of Cornelius Sylla with this addition Sacrorum: unto whose charge it appertained to see that Sacrifices and Divine service, that supplications, and processions, expiations, and ceremoniall rites should bee duely performed, as also to peruse the bookes and prophesies of Sibylla. At first they were but two, called Duumviri, afterwards x. under the name of Decemviri sacris faciendis. Alex. ab Alex. lib. 3, Genial. dierum. сар. 16.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="80">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Bonum factum. A forme of preface which in olde time they use, boni omnis causa, before their Edictes and decrees, etc., so commonly, as that these two Capital letters B. F. did betoken the same as ordinarily, as S. C. stand for Senatus consultum. It had the same use, as In nomine Dei with us.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Some take these Brache, whereof Brachata Gallia, a part of Transalpine Gaule, tooke name, for frize rugges striped with sundrie colours, which may resemble Irish mantles; but I suppose them to be a kinde of course breches, much like to the Irish trousses, but that they are more full.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>By rising up unto him, and shouting or applauding as he passed along.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Utinam viveres.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <quote>
                <l>Brutus quia Reges ejecit consul primus factus est:</l>
                <l>Hic, quia consules ejecit, Rex postremò factus est.</l>
            </quote>
        </note>
        <note n="f">
            <p>Certaine bridges there were for the time made, upon which the Tribes passed when they gave their voyces in Campus Martius, at their solemne Leets and assemblies for Election of Magistrates.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="81">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Some take it to bee the same that Regulus, or Trochilus, thought to be the Wren, and is likewise named King of Birdes, in Greeke βασιλεύς, ominous therefore unto Cæsar, seeking to be king.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="82">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This is diversly reported by authors. The occasion of which varietie ariseth upon the affinitie of these names, Cassius and Casca. For as there were two Cassii at this action, so likewise were there two Servilii brethren, both surnamed Casca. By Alter Cassius or Casca, therefore, you may understand one of the two brethren, or the second of them. For some write, that the one Casca gave him in the necke a wound, but not deadly, whereupon Cæsar caught hold of his dagger, crying out, Scelerate Casca quid agis? i. What meanest thou, O wicked Casca? and then Casca called unto his brother for helpe, who came in, and gave him his deathes wound, in the breast under the chanell bone. Plutarch.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Albeit, Graphium doth signifie a writing punch (or steele or wier), otherwise called Stylus, wherewith they wrote in hard matter, as wood, or barke, before the use of our parchment and paper, as also our pen made of a quill or other substance, as brasse, etc., in which sense it is taken in that verse of Ovid, Amor. lib. 1, Eleg. 11:</p>
            <quote>
                <l>Quid digitos opus est graphium lassare tenendo?</l>
            </quote>
            <p>And probable it is that Cæsar sitting in counsell was not without such a writing instrument: yet both Dominicus Marius upon the foresaid verse, and Perottus also the author of Cornucopia, expounding this place of Suetonius, takes Graphium, pro pugiunculo, i. a little poyniard, poinado, or pocket dagger. And hapely therwith Cæsar wounded Cassius or Casca (whether you will) being more readie at hand, hanging at his girdle, than the style or steele aforesaid, which by all likelihood was yet in the case or sheath, called Graphiarium, considering Cæsar was but new set. But I leave the exposition of this place, in medio.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Valerius Max. under the title of Verecundia, commendeth this maydenlike modestie of Cæsar, who notwithstanding that he was maskared with 23 wounds, for manhood sake forgot not to hide his nakednesse, and to die in decent manner: but as Euripides writeth of the virgin Ladie Polixena.</p>
            <quote>
                <l>πολλὴν πρόνοιαν ἔσχεν δυσχήμως πεσεῖν.</l>
            </quote>
            <p>Where, by the way it may be noted, that the Romanes wore not trusses or breches, as we doe, to cover those inferior and secret parts.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>This may have reference to that which is reported before, how in his youth, he loved Servilia, the mother of this Brutus: for his age falleth out to agree fitly with that time in so much as he was commonly thought to be a sonne of his. And yet this attribute Fili, may sort well with the familiaritie that was betweene them.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="e">
            <p>Some read Καί συ εἷς ἐκείνων,  . And art thou one of them?</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="83">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Virgini Vestali Maxime. That Nun or Vestall virgin, who in age and dignity excelled the rest, and was the Mistresse as it were, and governesse of them, they called Maxima: much like unto the Ladie Abbesse or Prioresse in our daies.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="84">
        <note n="a">
            <p>The argument whereof was the deciding of the contention betweene Ajax and Ulysses, about Achilles Armor.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>For, some of these who tooke part with Pompeius, he had pardoned.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Quicquid præterea ad manum aderat. Others read, ad donum aderat: understanding thereby those giftes which they brought as offerings to his Ghost, and be called Inferiæ.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="88">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which is counted one of the Climacterich years, in which it falleth out that 7 is multiplied by 8, which two numbers, as Cicero hath observed, 6 de Rep., be complete. A revolution fatal to Scipio Africanus the yonger, to Virgil also and Plinie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Appian writeth, that it was in a sodaine uprore of the people burnt to the ground.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>To signifie, that upon that day, The father of his countrie was killed.</p>
        </note>
    </div>
</div>