<text><div type="annotations" subtype="Marcus_Salvius_Otho">
    <div type="notes" n="1">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Nor without the Rampyer and precinct of the Campe, where was the ordinarie place of execution: nor by the ministerie of a Centurion, who by order was deputed, to see Justice done: but in the verie face and most frequented quarter of the Campe called Principia, not farre from the Lord Generals Pavilion, and where the Principall Captaines quartered and lodged: wherein also, the maine Standard named the Ægle and other militarie ensignes of the bandes and cohorts were kept: even in his owne sight being Generall, whose manner was not to be present.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="2">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This rude and grosse kinde of sport was thereupon called Sagatio, not unlike to that pastime with us in some place called the canvasing, and else where, the vanning of dogs.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="3">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For, after that by commaundement of Nero, he and Poppæa, were in some sort put asunder, he sollicited her as being his owne wedded wife to keepe him companie, which, in regard of her marriage with Nero, was held Adulterie.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="6">
        <note n="a">
            <p>A Columne erected in the upper end or head of the Forum Romanum: at which, all the principall high waies in Italy began, with directions therein engraven, to everie gate of the Citie, leading unto the said highwaies.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="7">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Some read, for ἀυλοῖς ἀσυλοῖς, to no good sense at all. But the former, accordeth well with Juvenal, Satyr. 11. Who to the same effect saith:
            <quote>
                <l>Bucca</l>
                <l>Noscenda est mensura tuæ,</l>
            </quote>
            and proverbially implyeth thus much, that he was not able to manage the Empire.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="8">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Germaniciani exercitus. Which served in Campe, or as Garison Souldiers in Germanie, whether they were Romanes, Germanes or any other Auxiliaries from Associate Nations, it skilled not.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>The manner was, that who soever enterprised a warre-voyage should enter into the Chappell of Mars, where hung the sacred Scutcheons or Shields called Ancilia, and first stirre them, after that, shake the speare also of Mars, and say with all Mars, Vigila, i. Awake Mars. This had Otho done, but according to the religious ceremonie, not bestowed them quietly againe in their places.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="12">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This bread was made of Beane and Rice flower, of the finest wheat also, a verie Psilothrum as the Physicians terme it, or a Depilatorie, to keepe haire from growing, especially being wet and soaked in some juyce or liquor appropriate therefore, as the bloud of bats, frogs, or the Tunie fish, etc. To this effeminacie of Otho, alludeth the Satyricall Poet Juvenal¹ in this verse:
            <quote>
                <l>Et pressum in faciem digitis extendere panem.</l>
            </quote>
            </p>
        </note>
    </div>
</div>

<div type="annotations" subtype="Aulus_Vitellius">
    <div type="notes" n="1">
        <note n="a">
            <p>THIS Quintus Eulogius was the freed man of the said Quintus Vitellius.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="2">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Some read Sectionibus et Suturis: expounding it thus, as if his sonne had been not a cobler, but a shoomaker indeed, occupied in cutting of new shoes and sowing them together.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>These kinde people, so double diligent about the feminine sexe, be fitly called good womens-men: and doting overmuch upon their wives, Uxorii in Latin, as one would say Bridegroomes still. Such an one Seneca makes report he knew, who could not endure to be without his wives company, one minute of an houre: and if upon necessitie he went abroad into the towne, yet would he take with him a stomacher of hers, and weare it ever next his heart, etc.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>No doubt the same was garnished with Gold, rich stones and pretious pearles. See Plin. lib. 9, cap. 35.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>It may be gathered it was Hemiplegia, which we call the dead Palsey, taking the one side of the bodie, and most commonly ensuing upon an Apoplexie, if it were not the verie Apoplexie it selfe, (which is none other but an universall palsey) considering the quicke dispatch it made.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="7">
        <note n="a">
            <p>He meaneth the crew, or faction of chariotiers holding of the blew or watchet colour: which Vitellius and Galba both affected.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="11">
        <note n="a">
            <p>So called, of an infortunate battaile fought that day neere the river Allia: in which, the Romans were overthrowne by the French : who following the train of their victory, advanced their ensignes to Rome, forced the Citie, and put it to the sacke.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Some read De Dominico, i. out of Dominicus, for so it may seeme, was the booke of Neroes Canticles entituled, alluding to himselfe, who would be called Rerum Dominus, i. Lord of the world.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="13">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Cornelius Celsus findeth no fault with Asclepiades, who condemned vomiting, Offensus eorum consuetudine, qui quotidie eiiciendo vorandi facultatem moliuntur, i. as utterly disliking their manner, who by daily casting up their gorge, seeke to enable themselves for beastly gourdmandise. And to the same purpose he saith: Istud luxuria causa fieri non oportere, i. That this ought not to be put in use, for to maintaine riotous excesse. He admonisheth also, Ne quis qui valere et senescere volet, hoc quotidianum faciat, That no man who desireth to live long and in health would make it a daily practise. But Seneca reproveth such verie aptly in these words: Edunt ut vomant, vomunt ut edant. They eat, to vomit, and they vomit, to eat.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>If Scarus were not the guilt head, a delicate fish no doubt it was in those daies, and better esteemed than the Acipenser, i. the Sturgion. It cheweth cud, and hath plaine teeth to grind withall, not indented like a combe or saw.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="14">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Veraculis or vericulis, or divinaculis: all to one sense, Such as will take upon them to tell fortunes, etc. Women of this profession Apuleius termeth veratrices.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Bonum factum. The usuall preface or preamble premised before Edicts and Proclamations, Boni ominis causa.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="15">
        <note n="a">
            <p>By this ceremonie, he seemed to resigne up his Empyre.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="16">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Making semblance thereby, that he was fled and gone, for, the manner was, at the Porters lodge doore, if no bodie were within, to tie up a mastive dog, for to give warning abroad if any man came. And not farre from the said lodge, such a dog, with a chaine, was usually painted upon the wall, with these words, in great letters: Cave, Cave Canem, i. Beware, Beware the Dog.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="18">
        <note n="a">
            <p>He meaneth that Gallus Gallinaceus, or dunghill cocke, that before had perched upon his head and shoulders, alluding to the French, who are likewise named Galli.</p>
        </note>
    </div>
</div>

<div type="annotations" subtype="Flavius_Vespasianus_Augustus">
    <div type="notes" n="1">
        <note n="a">
            <p>THE fortieth part. Happily the fortieth penie of all bargaines of sales that were unlawfull.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="2">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which had a border or broade gard about it, embroidered with purple studdes like naile-heads, and therefore was called Latas clavus: and thereupon, Senators themselves, Laticlavii.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="4">
        <note n="a">
            <p>In liew of φυλλοβολία : for, in token of love and affection they should have heaped upon him gay flowers, greene leaves and pleasant fruits.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>This, no doubt, had relation to the prophesie of the True Messias, and Saviour, Jesus Christ. The very words imply no lesse, according with these out of Holy Scripture: Ἐκ σοῦ ἐξελεύσεται ὁ ἡγούμενος, etc. Read Joseph. 6 book, chap. 31, of the destruction of Jerusalem.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="5">
        <note n="a">
            <p>There is an hill of that name in Judæa. And because answers had beene given from thence, and nothing there was to be seene, neyther Image of a God, nor Temple, but a bare Altar, and the reverence onely of the place, both Tacitus and Suetonius by the name of Carmelus, call that unknowen God unto them, who reigneth for ever.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>This sight, and the other following, betokened soveraigntie unto Vespasian, who warred then in the East countries, Judæa and Syria.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="7">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This Basilides seemeth rather to have beene some Priest, or principall man of note, and not Libertus, i. his freed man, as some copies have. But who ever he was, to the setting forward of this dissignement of Vespasian, Nomen et omen erat.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="10">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Out of the 35 Tribes of Rome, were chosen certaine Judges or Commissioners, named Centumvirs, to wit, out of every Tribe three, and albeit their number arose to an hundred and five, yet roundly they went for an hundred, and so were called. These I say, being ordained Stelitibus judicandis, determined private and civill matters betweene man and man, de Testamentis, Stillicidiis, and such like of no great moment. They put forth or erected a speare in the place where they sate in Jurisdiction: whereupon their court was named Hasta Centumviralis.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="13">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Alluding to the name Cynicus. For these Philosophers tooke this denomination Cynicks, eyther of their dogged and currish demaund, or of a place where they taught and disputed, called Cynosarges.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="16">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Which in Augustus Cæsars time amounted to twelve hundred thousand Sestertii: triple to the worth of a Roman Knight.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="17">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This Colossus, Zenodorus a famous workeman, made before time for Nero.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="18">
        <note n="a">
            <p>As namely, Pueros Symphoniacos, etc., Choristers or quiristers with most sweet breaths and pleasant voyces, etc.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>For, then had women their Saturnalia, like as the men in December. Those festivall holidaies were called Matronalia, in memoriall of Ladie Hersilia and other noble Dames, who in old time upon that day, interposed themselves as Mediatrices, betweene the Romans and Sabines, readie to strike a most bloodie battell.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="19">
        <note n="a">
            <p>This is reprehended by Cornelius Celsus, lib. 2, cap. 14, in these words, Neque audiendi sunt, qui numero finiunt, quoties aliquis perfricandus est: Illud enim ex viribus hominis colligendum est.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="20">
        <note n="a">
            <p>To be caried between men in a chayre or seat called thereupon Sella gestatoria, or Lectica. Celsus reckoneth sundrie sorts of this Gestation, to wit, Navi, Lectica, Scamno, Vehiculo.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="21">
        <note n="a">
            <p>For, it was an ordinarie matter, in supper time, betweene the services and severall dishes, to cast the Dice or cockall bones, by fits.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>Prætextata verba, by the figure Antiphrasis, are put for such words as beseemed not either the mouth or the eares of Prætextati, i. youths well borne, and of gentle bloud descended: who, in truth, should be modest and maidenlike: and in like manner, prætextati mores, signifie such behaviour.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Noting him for his ridiculous vanitie: which φλαύρος in Greeke doth signifie.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="d">
            <p>Or, if ye read before, [perductæ] it must so stand in the Page of expenses, to this sense, laid out, for, or to Vespasian beloved: as if he had given her a reward for loving him, whereas she should have given unto him.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="22">
        <note n="a">
            <p>Some read, in steed of Improbius irato, improbius nato, that is to say, of no good making, but ill shaped to his height.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="b">
            <p>A peece of a verse in Homer, Iliad 7, spoken there of Ajax, advancing forward to fight with Hector, unto whom, or to whose long pike rather, he likeneth this gangrell.</p>
        </note>
        <note n="c">
            <p>Eyther of Fullers, Walkers, and Diers, who gathered and occupied much thereof about their clothes, or else, for the tubs that commonly stoode in od corners and noukes of the streets, to receive every mans water, that he made as he went.</p>
        </note>
    </div>

    <div type="notes" n="23">
        <note n="a">
            <p>At the foresaid Cutiliæ, which was a naturall bath in the Sabines country, of medicinable waters, howbeit exceeding cold. Plin. lib. 31, cap. 31.</p>
        </note>
    </div>
</div>

</text>