<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Annotations upon Titus Flavius Vespasianus Augustus</title>
        <author>Philemon Holland</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Transcription for Digital Humanities Research</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The History of Twelve Cæsars</title>
          <author>Suetonius</author>
          <editor role="translator">Philemon Holland</editor>
          <biblScope unit="page">285-286</biblScope>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="annotations" n="Titus">
        <head>ANNOTATIONS UPON TITUS FLAVIUS VESPASIANUS AUGUSTUS </head>

        <div n="1" type="chapter">
          <note place="margin">
            <p><label>a</label> A PLACE in Rome so called of a building there, which stood upon seven courses of Columnes or Pillars, arising all round and higher every one than other, in manner of so many circles or girdles. </p>
          </note>
        </div>

        <div n="2" type="chapter">
          <note place="margin">
            <p>
              <label>b</label> He meaneth not a Physiognomer, who hath taken upon him by inspection of eyes, forehead, face, etc., to tell ones nature and disposition: such an one as Zopyrus was, who noted Socrates for to be by naturall inclination a wanton lover of women:  
              but a fortune teller, by looking on the forehead onely. 
              Such as in these daies, by the art of Palmestrie, for-sooth, can assure folke, how long they shall live, and what not. 
              If they do but see lines in the palmes of their hands, or by feaxe in the forehead, will say, how many wives a man shall have, etc. 
              As vaine as those, who by counting the letters of the husband and the wives name, will confidently pronounce, whether of them shall burie the other. 
            </p>
          </note>
        </div>

        <div n="3" type="chapter">
          <note place="margin">
            <p>
              <label>a</label> By titles in this place, and many others of Suetonius, are to be understood inscriptions, testifying for what considerations such Statues were erected. 
              Such also were usually set up at publicke executions, to shew the offences and causes why any suffered. 
              A thing usuall among the Romanes in their government, in what Province so ever, as may appeare by that which stood upon the Crosse of our Saviour Christ. 
            </p>
          </note>
        </div>

        <div n="4" type="chapter">
          <note place="margin">
            <p><label>a</label> That is to say a white band or ribband: such as the Royall Diademe at first was. </p>
          </note>
        </div>

        <div n="6" type="chapter">
          <note place="margin">
            <p>
              <label>a</label> Of these Baines, with what speede and celerity they were finished, Martialis writeth thus: 
              <quote xml:lang="lat">Hic ubi miramur velocia munera, Thermas.</quote> 
            </p>
          </note>
        </div>

        <div n="8" type="chapter">
          <note place="margin">
            <p>
              <label>a</label> Dooing them thus much credit in the eyes of the world, as to give the allowance and approbation, or otherwise, of the weapons wherewith they should fight. 
              For, in this sense may Ornaments be taken: the rather, because some copies have <term xml:lang="lat">Ferramenta</term>. 
              Or this place may be understood of other furniture, as well as armes, wherwith they should come appointed into the listes. 
            </p>
          </note>
        </div>

        <div n="9" type="chapter">
          <note place="margin">
            <p>
              <label>a</label> This hath beene observed in all ages, to fore-runne the death of some Prince. 
              Thus, before the end of Julius Cæsar, as Virgil writeth, 
              <quote xml:lang="lat">Non alias lato occiderunt plura sereno Fulgura, etc.</quote> 
              Horace likewise, 
              <quote xml:lang="lat">Per purum sonantes Egit equos volucremque currum.</quote> 
              Our owne Chronicles<ptr target="#f1"/> also exemplifie no lesse.  
              To say nothing of the fresh resemblance of that, which happened with us three yeares since, in July. 
            </p>
          </note>
        </div>

        <div n="10" type="chapter">
          <p>Some write, and Tzetzes by name, that hee was poysoned with eating of Sea-hares. </p>
        </div>

        <note xml:id="f1" type="footnote">
          <p>1 A little before the death of king Henry the second. </p>
        </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>