<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
          <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>The Agamemnon</title>
      <title>The Dramas of Aeschylus</title>
      <title type="sub">Digitized and encoded by the University of Leipzig (2014)</title>
      <author>Aeschylus</author>
      <editor role="translator">Anna Swanwick</editor>
      <sponsor>University of Leipzig</sponsor>
      <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>OCR, correction, and encoding</resp>
        <name>Jouve</name>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Project management</resp>
        <name>Greta Franzini</name>
      </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
        <resp>Technical advising</resp>
        <name>Bruce Robertson</name>
      </respStmt>
      <funder n="org:ESF-Saxony">European Social Fund Saxony</funder>
    </titleStmt>

    <extent>n/a</extent>

    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>University of Leipzig</publisher>
      <pubPlace>Germany</pubPlace>
      <authority>University of Leipzig</authority>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
          Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License
        </licence>
      </availability>
      <idno type="filename">aeschylus_1886.xml</idno>
      <date when="2014">2014</date>
    </publicationStmt>

    <sourceDesc>
      <biblStruct>
        <monogr>
          <author>Aeschylus</author>
          <title>Aeschylus</title>
          <title type="sub">Dramas</title>
          <editor role="translator">Anna Swanwick</editor>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            <publisher>George Bell and Sons</publisher>
            <date when="1886">1886</date>
          </imprint>
        </monogr>
        <ref target="http://www.archive.org/details/dramasswa00aescuoft">Internet Archive</ref>
      </biblStruct>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>

  <encodingDesc>
    <editorialDecl>
      <quotation marks="none"/>
    </editorialDecl>
    <refsDecl n="CTS">
      <cRefPattern n="l"
        matchPattern="(\w+)"
        replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div//tei:l[@n='$1'])">
        <p>This pointer pattern extracts lines</p>
      </cRefPattern>
    </refsDecl>
    <p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture.</p>
  </encodingDesc>

  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="eng">English</language>
    </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>

  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-10-21" who="gcrane">Restructured teiHeader to Perseus-style format. normalized roles and source bibliography.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">

      <body>
        <div type="preface">
        <pb n="vii" xml:id="p15"/>
        <head>PREFACE TO THE TRILOGY.</head>
        <p>Ir has been truly remarked by Shelley, <q>that the jury
        which sits in judgment upon a poet must be composed
        of his peers; it must be empanelled by time from the
        selectest of the wise of many generations.</q> By the
        verdict of this august tribunal, Aeschylus takes rank
        with Homer, Dante, and Shakespeare, and may justly
        be regarded as one of <q>the unacknowledged legislators
        of the world.</q></p>
        <p>As it may appear presumptuous to offer to the public
        a new translation of the Aeschylean trilogy, the
        grandest dramatic work of classical antiquity, I may
        perhaps be allowed to state that I have not entered
        upon the task altogether uninvited. On the publication
of my translation of <title>Faust</title>, and the other masterworks
of Goethe, in Bohn's Standard Library, I was
        strongly urged by the late Baron Bunsen to undertake
        the translation of the Greek dramas. I felt honoured
        by the proposal; and though I was not immediately
        impelled to act upon the suggestion, his words have
        dwelt in my memory, and have encouraged me to complete
an arduous and very difficult undertaking.</p>
        <p>Considerable diversity of opinion prevails respecting
        the propriety of employing rhymed metres as substitutes for the complex forms of classical poetry;
        
        <pb n="viii" xml:id="p16"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">viii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">Preface.</fw>
        hence it may not be inexpedient briefly to state my
        reasons for adopting them, as affording in my judgment
        the only adequate vehicle for reproducing the choral
        odes of the Greek dramas.</p>
        <p>With regard to the principles which should guide
        the translator in the execution of his task, it is, I
        believe, universally recognized that a translation ought,
        as faithfully as possible, to reflect the original, both in
        spirit and in form, and that any wilful or unacknowledged
deviation from it is tantamount to a breach of
        trust. The difficulty of rigidly applying these principles
to the translation of the choral odes will be
        apparent when we remember that the medium through
        which the thought of the ancient poet has to be re-
        <lb/>embodied differs so essentially from that of the original
        as to render the principle of imitation, with reference
        to their musical intonations, inapplicable. The futility
        of attempting to imitate the forms of classical poetry
        in a language the metres of which are governed not by
        Time, but by Accent, has been pointed out by
        Professor Newman, in the preface to his admirable
        translation of the <title>Iliad</title>, the excellence of which can
        only be fully appreciated by a careful comparison with
        the original.</p>
        <p><q>An accented metre,</q> he says, <q>in a language
        loaded with consonants cannot have the same sort of
        sounding beauty as a quantitative metre in a highly
        vocalized language. It is not audible sameness of
        metre, but a likeness of moral genius which is to be
        
        <pb n="ix" xml:id="p17"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">Preface.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">ix</fw>
        aimed at.</q> The translator, having thus no authoritative
models to necessitate the adoption of particular
        forms, is at liberty, without incurring the charge of
        unfaithfulness, to adopt those metres, rhymed or
        unrhymed, which approve themselves to his judgment
        as most in harmony with the spirit of the original.
        In order to fulfil this condition, however, he must take
        into consideration the highly lyrical character of the
        choral odes, which associated themselves not only with
        music, but also with the choral dance.</p>
        <p>Now, this lyrical element of ancient poetry, not
        admitting of translation, requires to be born anew, and
        for this purpose we have a most felicitous adjunct in
        rhyme, which, when judiciously employed, may be
        regarded as a musical accompaniment, pervading the
        choral harmonies, enhancing their beauty, and at the
        same time serving to mark the time.</p>
        <p>The only possible objection to the use of an ornament
        so attractive and significant, and at the same time so
        conformable to the English language, is the notion,
        very generally entertained, that <q>the exigencies of
        rhyme forbid faithfulness.</q> Holding fidelity to the
        spirit of the original to be the cardinal virtue of a
        translator, I should, if this opinion were well founded,
        abandon rhyme without hesitation. It appears to me,
        however, that the objection is overstated, and that it is
        better to aim at the true lyrical ideal, however difficult
        of realization. The solution of the problem can only
        be worked out by experience. How far I have
        succeeded in combining scrupulous fidelity to the</p>
        <fw type="signature" place="bottom-center">KK</fw>
        
        <pb n="x" xml:id="p18"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">x</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">Preface.</fw>
        <p>original with the employment of rhyme, it is not for
        me to judge; metrical translation must always be a
        matter of compromise, and no one can be so sensitively
        aware of the shortcomings of a translation as the
        translator.</p>
        <p>My desire to bespeak for the dramas of Aeschylus
        that intelligent study which is essential for their true
        appreciation has induced me to attempt in my introduction
a very slight sketch of the progress of religious
        thought, as manifested through a few of the great
        master-works of literature and art. Poets are representative
men; and poetry, under its higher aspects,
        may justly be regarded as the fairest flower of the age
        and country which gave it birth, drawing its nourishment
from the deepest roots of national life, and concealing
beneath its delicate petals the germs of the
        future. Hence every great poem requires for its
        elucidation, not only to be studied in connection with
        contemporaneous history, but also to be brought into
        comparison with the kindred productions of other
        ages and nations. New insight is thus gained into
        the developments of history, and the tendencies of
        modern thought are more clearly interpreted when
        brought face to face with the conceptions and aspirations
of the old pagan world. If a complete history
        of religious development were to be given, it would of
        course be necessary to go back to the prior Monotheism
        which probably preceded the earliest Pantheistic natureworship
of which we have any record, and also to
        investigate the links of transition from the Vedic
        
        <pb n="xi" xml:id="p19"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">Preface.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xi</fw>
        Divinities to the ideal Personalities of Olympus. Such
        an inquiry would, however, exceed the scope of an
        introduction.</p>
        <p>In considering the Zeus of Aschylus I have confined
myself almost entirely to the conception of the
        Olympian king embodied in the <title>Oresteia</title>, leaving
        untouched the apparent discrepancy between the
        character there portrayed and that depicted in the
        <title>Prometheus Bound</title>. I agree with those critics who
        believe that the discrepancy is only apparent, and
        would vanish had we the opportunity of studying the
        other members of the Promethean trilogy. Critics
        are agreed that the <title>Suppliants</title> ought also to be
        regarded as a member of a trilogy, in association with
        the lost dramas of the <title>Aegyptii</title> and the <title>Danaïdes</title>.
        These fragmentary works can, I believe, be only
        satisfactorily interpreted when studied in connection
        with the <title>Oresteia</title>. The investigation would, however,
        necessitate a reference to the remaining dramas of
        Aeschylus, and must therefore be postponed to a future
        opportunity.</p>
        <p>All true lovers of Art, who recognize her legitimate
        function as a revealer of truth, a mediator between the
        Finite and the Infinite, cannot fail to regret the subordinate
position to which she is condemned in the present
day, when she is too often regarded in the light of
        a mere elegant superfluity, as one of the costly adjuncts
        of our modern civilization. The true dignity of art
        has been nobly vindicated by Hegel in his celebrated
        work, entitled <title>Vorlesungen über die Aesthetik</title>. As
        
        <pb n="xii" xml:id="p20"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">Preface.</fw>
        this work is, I believe, comparatively little known in
        England, I have ventured to recast, with some modifications,
a few of his leading ideas, and to embody
        them in my introduction. I refer more especially to
        his analysis of the Greek dramas, and to his exposition
        of the fundamental ideas which characterize the three
        great eras-the symbolical, classical, and romanticwhich
mark alike the history of religion and of art. I
        have also availed myself of C. O. Müller's admirable
        dissertations on <q>the <title>Eumenides</title>,</q> together with Professor
Max Müller's lectures on language, second
        series, and his history of ancient Sanscrit literature.</p>
        <p>With regard to mythological lore, I am chiefly indebted
to Welcker's <title>Griechische Götterlehre</title>, Kuhn's
        <title>Herabkunft des Feuers</title>, and also to Guigniant's
        <title>Religions de l'Antiquité</title>, translated from the German
        of Creuzer.</p>
        
        <signed>
          <dateline><name type="place">REGENT'S PARK</name>, <date when="1865-06">June 1865</date>.</dateline>
        </signed>
      </div>
<div type="preface">
        <pb n="xiii" xml:id="p21"/>
        <head>PREFACE TO THE FOUR PLAYS.</head>
        <p>THE kind reception accorded to my version of the
        Oresteian trilogy has encouraged me to complete my
        task by translating the remaining dramas of the great
        Athenian bard.</p>
        <p>It is impossible to determine with accuracy the
        original number of the Aeschylean dramas; the lowest
        estimate is seventy-five, the highest one hundred. Of
        this treasure of poetry seven dramas only, together
        with a few isolated fragments, have escaped the wreck
        of time. Aeschylus has been compared, not inaptly, to
        the Sphinx of the Egyptian desert, buried up to its
        shoulders beneath the accumulated sands of ages.
        <q xml:lang="fr">Enseveli et éternel, le front sortant du sépulcre,
        Aeschyle regarde les générations.</q></p>
        <p>The influence of his genius has been far-reaching in
        space, as well as enduring in time:-it is interesting
        to consider the vast area over which the spirit and
        language of Hellas were diffused by means of her
        colonies, which were found scattered and isolated in
        every region of the known world; from Spain in the
        west to the countries bordering upon the Euxine in
        the east; from Pannonia in the north to Libya in the
        south.</p>
        
        <pb n="xiv" xml:id="p22"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xiv</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">Preface.</fw>
        <p>The importance of poetry as one of the great civiliz-
        ing forces of humanity was not overlooked by these
        Hellenic communities. They recognized the prime
        truth that <q>the mind of a nation constitutes its firmest
        bulwark.</q> Theatres accordingly were erected beside
        their citadels. These edifices, it must be remembered,
        were not, as with us, mere places of amusement.
        Owing to the religious element, which from its cradle
        pervaded the Athenian drama, the Hellenic theatres
        were invested with somewhat of a sacred character, and
        their dramatic performances constituted a characteristic
        feature of the national life. Aeschylus, we are told,
        was the favourite poet of the Hellenic colonists.
        <q>Aeschylus present, Hellas was not altogether absent.
        His colossal genius thus protected these infant com-
        munities from the inroads of surrounding barbarism,
        and maintained them in the circle of Hellenic
        civilization.</q></p>
        <p>It would be well if the civilizing agency of poetry
        were more universally recognized. The human mind
        requires to be lifted occasionally above the level of
        ordinary life, where it is exposed to the perpetual
        harass of material cares. Poetry, the highest embodi-
        ment of idealized passion and imaginative thought,
        must ever be regarded as a mighty agent for the
        accomplishment of this object. Poets of the highest
        order belong, however, not to one age or country, but
        to humanity. It is therefore important that the
        productions of these master-spirits should be adequately
        translated and thus rendered generally accessible.</p>
        
        <pb n="xv" xml:id="p23"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">Preface.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xv</fw>
        <p>This is more especially true at the present time, when,
        with the spread of education, the multitude of readers
        will be indefinitely increased.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare has been not inappropriately styled <q>the
        modern Aeschylus;</q> an association which, to the
        English reader at least, invests with peculiar interest
        the prophetic poet of the ancient world. The perusal
        of his master-works, like those of his great compeer,
        illustrates the truth proclaimed by the Apostle from
        the Athenian Areopagus, <q>that God has made of one
        blood all nations of men;</q> notwithstanding the diver-
        sity of external surrounding, we discern, in the per-
        sonages of the Aeschylean dramas, whether human or
        superhuman, beings of like passions with ourselves,
        endowed with the same mental constitution, and subject
        to the moral laws impressed by the Creator upon our
        common humanity. In his sublimer passages we soar
        with the poet as on eagle's wings, and anon we come
        upon pregnant utterances which</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l>fix themselves</l>
          <l>Deep in the heart as meteor stones in earth</l>
          <l>Dropped from some higher sphere.</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <quote><lg>
          <l>Who can mistake great thoughts?</l>
          <l>They seize upon the mind,-arrest and search</l>
          <l>And shake it; bow the tall soul as by wind,—</l>
          <l>Rush over it like rivers over reeds,</l>
          <l>Which quaver in the current.</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>Such are the thoughts of Aeschylus !</p>
        <p>From all this wealth of poetry many readers are,
        however, practically excluded, not only by the foreign
        <lb/>language in which it is embodied, but also by their
        unfamiliarity with the mythological lore of Hellas.
        Like travellers in a foreign country, they shrink from
        the exertion of exploring an unknown region without
        the assistance of a guide. In order in some measure
        to supply this want, I have prefixed to each drama a
        brief introduction, setting forth the main incidents of
        the situation, together with other explanatory details.
        In these introductions I make no claim to originality;
        I have consulted the various works, bearing upon the
        subject, to which I had access, and from them I have
        endeavorued to bring together, as concisely as possible,
        such materials as seemed subservient to the object
        which I had in view.</p>
        
        <pb n="xvi" xml:id="p24"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xvi</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">Preface.</fw>
        <p>With regard to Prometheus, I have felt the im-
        possibility of treating adequately, within the narrow
        limits of an introduction, a subject so vast, and with
        reference to which such diverse opinions are enter-
        tained. The theory propounded by Schoemann appears
        to me to be one of the most successful attempts to
        reconcile the apparent discrepancy between the cha-
        racter of Zeus as portrayed in the <title>Prometheus Bound</title>,
        and that depicted in the remaining dramas of Æschylus,
        more especially in the <title>Suppliants</title> and the <title>Oresteian
        trilogy</title>. I have accordingly given, in my introduction,
        a brief epitome of some leading ideas embodied in
        Schoemann's essay, and to that I must refer the reader
        for a more complete exposition of his views.</p>
        <p>In the introduction to my translation of the Ores-
        teian trilogy, I have alluded at some length to the
        
        <pb n="xvii" xml:id="p25"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">Preface</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xvii</fw>
        theory which refers the origin of the Hellenic mytho-
        logy to the phenomena of the natural world; and which,
        through the researches of Prof. Max Müller and other
        mythologists, is shown to rest upon a basis of fact.
        The application of the theory to the legendary lore of
        Hellas has given rise to so much controversy, and has
        opened so wide a field of speculation, that I have
        abstained from entering upon the subject, and must
        refer the reader to the Rev. G. W. Cox's <title>Mythology
        of the Aryan Nations</title>, where it is fully discussed.</p>
        <p>Having in the choral odes of my second volume
        observed the arrangement of Strophe and Antistrophe,
        which forms a characteristic feature of the original, I
        have thought it advisable to bring my version of the
        Oresteian trilogy, in this respect, into harmony with
        the remaining dramas of Aeschylus, and have moreover
        carefully revised the whole.</p>
        <p>In conclusion, I have great pleasure in expressing
        my grateful acknowledgments to my friend Professor
        Newman, for his most kind and valuable assistance.
        This assistance has reference not merely to the inter-
        pretation of the more obscure passages of the original,
        the difficulty of which is greatly enhanced by the
        corrupt condition of the text, but also to his proposed
        corrections, for which I refer the reader to the notes
        printed, as in the Trilogy, at the end of each drama.</p>
        <p>I have in addition to thank him for important aid
        in rendering the original into English. The whole
        of my translation has been submitted to his revision,
        and, with his permission, I have freely availed myself
        <fw type="signature" place="bottom-center">b</fw>
        
        <pb n="xviii" xml:id="p26"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xviii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">Preface.</fw>
        of the numerous proposed emendations with which he
        has from time to time most kindly favoured me.</p>
        <p>I am also indebted to my friend Mr. W. W. Lloyd
        for several valuable suggestions, for which I beg to
        express my cordial thanks. I moreover gladly
        acknowledge my obligation to previous commentators
        and translators.</p>
        <p>In the preparation of my introductions I have
        consulted the following works, from which, for the
        most part, I have borrowed my materials. Grote's
        <title>History of Greece</title>; Bunsen's <title>Gott in der Geschichte</title>;
        <title>Ariadne</title>, von O. F. Gruppe; <title>Die Aeschylische
        Trilogie Prometheus</title>, etc., von F. G. Welcker; <title>Des
        Aeschylos gefesselter Prometheus</title>, von G. F. Schoemann;
        <title>Des Aeschylos Werke</title>, übersetzt von J. G. Droysen ;
        Hegel's <title>Vorlesungen über die Aesthetik</title>. I am also
        indebted to an interesting essay on the religion of
        Aeschylus, by Brook F. Westcott, which appeared in the
        <title>Contemporary Review</title>. In the preface to my second
        volume I have borrowed some thoughts from Victor
        Hugo's <title>Shakespeare</title>.</p>
        <p>I am happy to state that in a separate volume my
        translation of the Aeschylean dramas is asssociated
        with Flaxman's illustrations.</p>
        
        <signed>
          <dateline><name type="place">REGENT'S PARK</name>, <date when="1872">1872</date>.</dateline>
        </signed>
      </div>

      <div type="introduction">
        <pb n="xix" xml:id="p27"/>
        <head>INTRODUCTION TO THE TRILOGY,</head>
        <p>In order to appreciate the poetry of antiquity, it is
        necessary to take into consideration the religious
        ideas which lie at its root, which also in the course
        of their development have determined the character
        alike of ancient literature and art; when we consider,
        moreover, the immense influence which the stream of
        Aryan thought, by its interfusion with Christianity,
        has exerted over the culture of the Western world, a
        new and twofold interest attaches to each of the great
        master-works of classical antiquity, as exhibiting not
        only the level which the religious thought of the age
        had already reached, but also as indicating the direc-
        tion of its future development.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, in offering to the public a new version
        of the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title>, the only complete trilogy which has
        escaped the wreck of time, it may not be altogether
        irrelevant if I endeavour to determine the position of
        Aeshylus among those kindlers of the beacon-fire,
        through whose agency the light of ancient wisdom
        was transmitted from age to age before the advent of
        Christianity.</p>
        <p>With this view it will be necessary to give a sketch
        
        <pb n="xx" xml:id="p28"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xx</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        (necessarily very meagre and imperfect) of the progress
        of religious thought, both before and after his appear-
        ance on the stage of history, and as art has its root in
        the religious nature of man, we shall thus obtain a key
        to the three great epochs which mark the artistic
        development of humanity, which have been charac-
        terized as the Symbolical, the Classical, and the
        Romantic eras.</p>
        <p>When the rays of tradition first dawn upon our
        planet, we discover the primeval ancestors of the
        Aryan race, before their dispersion from their common
        home, still gazing with awe and wonder upon the
        working of the vast nature-powers by which they were
        environed. While led through the religious instincts
        implanted in human nature to recognize the existence
        of a Being or Beings who hear and answer prayer,
        they were unable to separate the idea of mind, as a
        causal power, from the aspects of external nature.
        Accordingly, the shadowy divinities of the Vedic
        Pantheon, Indra, Agni, Varuna, can hardly be regarded
        as distinct personalities, holding definite relations to
        each other, or to their worshippers. As in the fluctu-
        ating scenery of the diurnal drama the sun is obscured
        by clouds, which in their turn are scattered and anon
        collected again, so these deified impersonations of
        physical phenomena loom dimly before our mental
        vision, each supreme and absolute in turn; nor is it
        easy to determine whether behind these innumerable
        divinities, the conception of One infinite Spirit had yet
        dawned upon the Aryan mind.</p>
        
        <pb n="xxi" xml:id="p29"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxi</fw>
        <p>The deities of the Vedas vanish from our gaze, lost
        <q>In the deep backward and abysm of time.</q>
        After the lapse of ages they reappear upon the stage,
        so modified, however, that it is difficult to recognize
        their identity: on the southern side of the Himalayahs
        they assume the form of the great Brahminical trinity,
        Vishnu, Brahma, and Siva, emerging from a back-
        ground of Pantheism; while in Greece we behold
        them metamorphosed into the hierarchy of the
        Olympian gods. So striking is the contrast between
        the deities apostrophized by the Vedic bards, and the
        grand impersonations of Grecian poetry and art, that
        without conclusive evidence the connection between
        them could hardly be recognized. This evidence is
        twofold;-in the first place, comparative philology
        reveals the fact that the sacred names of the Greek
        Pantheon are in the Vedas intelligible words, expres-
        sive of natural phenomena; while in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> we are
        introduced to the Olympian deities during the process
        of transformation; we detect their forms gradually dis-
        engaging themselves from the physical phenomena with
        which they were associated, of which also they may be
        regarded as the spiritual but almost impalpable essence.</p>
        <p>This transformation of physical into humanized
        deities has been compared by Welcker to the myste-
        rious process by which the chrysalis passes into its
        more perfect form. <q>The Nature-god,</q> he says,
        <q>became enveloped in a web of mythical fable, and
        emerged as a divine, humanized personality.</q> For
        
        <pb n="xxii" xml:id="p30"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        the principle which lies at the root of this meta-
        morphosis, he points to the gradual development of
        human nature, to the growing consciousness of free-
        will, accompanied by the recognition of mind as a
        higher manifestation of deity than any material pheno-
        mena, and consequently of man as the true Shekinah.</p>
        <p>As, however, in the earlier Vedic worship men were
        unable to separate the idea of mind, as a causal
        power, from the varied aspects of external nature, so,
        when they began to direct their thoughts within, they
        were equally embarrassed to distinguish between the
        divine and human elements in the soul of man. Every
        inward movement which appeared at all exceptional was
        ascribed to the prompting of a deity; not only were
        the nobler emotions of courage and self-restraint
        referred to divine inspiration (of which in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> we
        find innumerable examples), but the gods are also
        represented as the authors of delusion (ii. 8, xxii. 24)
        and treachery (iv. 93), as when Zeus sends the
        deceitful dream to Agamemnon, and Athena prompts
        Pandarus to violate the treaty. One of the most
        noteworthy instances to this perplexity is found in
        Agamemnon's exculpation of himself touching the
        outrage upon Achilles (xix. 85):</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>I am not guilty, Jove and Fate and the dusk-roaming
        Fury-</q></l>
          <l><q>'Tis these who in assembly fir'd | my breast with savage
        frenzy.</q><ref n="xxii.1"/>*</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <note n="xxii.1">* I have availed myself here and in subsequent quotations
        of Professor Newman's translation.</note>
        
        <pb n="xxiii" xml:id="p31"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxiii</fw>
        <p>A plea, the justice of which is admitted by Achilles,
        who echoes the sentiment of Agamemnon:</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>O Father Jove, great frenesies | to men thou truly sendest.</q></l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>Moreover, on the first transference of human passion
        and emotion, together with the conditions of human
        existence, to the super-mundane sphere, the very con-
        ception of divine existence, as absolved from restraint,
        would lead to the deification of human infirmity to-
        gether with the higher attributes of humanity: of this
        we have a memorable example in the character of the
        Homeric Zeus. This tendency would doubtless be
        accelerated by the phenomena expounded by Prof. Max
        Müller, in his <title>Lectures on Language</title>. As the several
        branches of the Aryan stock dispersed, migrating from
        their common home in Central Asia, the original
        signification of words was forgotten or obscured; and
        thus, language originally descriptive of natural pheno-
        mena became transferred to the conditions of human
        life-a translation which totally metamorphosed the
        character of the occurrence.</p>
        <p>The transference of human faith and worship from
        the vague nature-powers of the Vedas to the humanized
        deities of Olympus, together with the association of
        the latter into a celestial hierarchy, under the supre-
        macy of Zeus, assumed in Grecian mythology the form
        of a revolution, and was symbolized under the grand
        old allegory of the battle between the Titans and the
        Olympian gods. This revolution, involving a variety
        of complex phenomena, especially the fusion of the
        
        <pb n="xxiv" xml:id="p32"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxiv</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        mythology of different tribes or nations into one, was
        doubtless accomplished in its main features in the ages
        anterior to Homer.</p>
        <p>However, as we have no Grecian literature to illus-
        trate this period, we are unable to trace the history of the
        transition, nor can we determine how far the current
        mythology of his age was modified by the individual
        genius of the great epic bard, whose immortal work,
        while inaugurating a new epoch in the history of
        civilization, at the same time exhibits, as has been
        truly said, the last lingering traces of the primeval
        age. A superficial acquaintance with the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> suffices
        to reveal the original elemental character of the
        Homeric divinities, a fact which would be more
        generally recognized, were we not accustomed to carry
        to the perusal of the earlier poet the conceptions
        derived from the artistic impersonations of a later age.
        This transitional character of the Homeric mythology
        will be more apparent if we carry back to their original
        root in natural phenomena a few of the Olympian
        divinities, and then follow the process of their develop-
        ment, as they appear successively in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and in
        the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title>. The connection between Jupiter and the
        sky, familiar to Greek and Latin scholars, may be
        traced down to the latest period of classical poetry;
        so Horace—<q>Manet sub Jove frigido venator.</q> It
        was reserved, however, for the science of comparative
        philology to point out the origin of this connection.
        Thus we learn that <q>Zeus, the most sacred name in
        Greek mythology, is the same word as Dyaus in
        
        <pb n="xxv" xml:id="p33"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxv</fw>
        Sanscrit, which means the sky; and that originally
        Dyu was the bright heavenly deity in India, as well as
        in Greece.</q></p>
        <p>It is remarked by Welcker, that <q>the greatest fact,
        when we go back to the highest Grecian antiquity, is the
        idea of God, as the Supreme Being, associated with a
        nature-worship, never entirely suppressed, together with
        the conception of a divine family derived from Zeus.</q>
        Accordingly, we recognize in the Homeric Zeus
        three distinct elements, the divine, the physical, and
        the human, welded together into an artificial unity, and
        exhibiting a character of marvellous incongruity, en-
        dowed with attributes the most inconsistent and con-
        tradictory. Thus, in not a few passages, he is re-
        presented as the supreme deity—</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>Who reigneth mighty over all, both mortals and
        immortals.</q> (Il. xii. 242.)</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p><q>Whose decree, once
        sanctioned by the nod, is neither deceptive, nor re-
        vokable.</q> (Il. i. 527.) <q>The Counsellor, greatest and
        best; Father of gods and men; the Guardian of the
        oath.</q> (iv. 235.) <q>The Vindicator of righteous law.</q>
        (xxi. 387.) <q>The High Arbiter of war.</q> (xix. 224.) His
        superiority over the other gods is forcibly brought
        out in the beginning of the 8th book (18-27,) where the
        other dwellers in Olympus are invited to grasp the
        golden chain dropped from Heaven's heights, and held
        immovably in the hand of Zeus:</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>Lay hold, and throw your force on it, all gods both male
        and female,</q></l>
          
          <pb n="xxvi" xml:id="p34"/>
          <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxvi</fw>
          <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
          <l><q>Yet never shall ye down to earth, drag from the lofty
        heaven</q></l>
          <l><q>Zeus the supreme deviser.</q></l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>It is as the god of compassion that the diviner
        aspect of his character is the most conspicuous
        (ix. 502): when we consider the savagery of an age in
        which human victims were sacrificed to appease the
        Manes of the dead, and where tendencies to cannibalism
        may perhaps be detected (iv. 35), (xxii. 345), (xxiv.
        212), the prominence given to compassion as an attri-
        bute of the supreme Deity is very remarkable.</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding these high attributes, no exercise of
        providential power is ever assigned to the Homeric
        Zeus; he is beguiled by Hera, yet swayed by her
        counsel (xvi. 460), and though desirous to save Ilium,
        yet, at her entreaty, he surrenders it to destruction
        (iv. 43). Like the heavens, now bright with sunshine,
        and anon dark with storm, he exhibits all the capricious
        fluctuations of an elemental power, being alternately
        malignant and benign, without any apparent motive
        beyond his own caprice, uninfluenced by moral con-
        siderations. Then, again, with regard to his supre-
        macy, not only is it questioned by Poseidon (xv. 185),
        it is actually imperilled by that deity, in conjunction
        with Hera and Athena (i. 396-406), and is only
        rescued from their machinations by the intervention of
        Briareus.<ref n="xxvi.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="xxvi.1">* Creuzer has pointed out the same image in a passage
        of the <title rend="italic">Bhagavat-gîta</title>.</note>

        <pb n="xxvii" xml:id="p35"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxvii</fw>
        <p>These legends probably symbolize convulsions of the
        elements, which threaten to blot out the sky, of which
        Zeus is the impersonation. In this character, as
        an elemental god, he is not only the father of
        rivers, he also presides over all meteorological pheno-
        mena.</p>
        <p>Thus with his Ægis, the dark storm-cloud, he veils
        the summit of Mount Ida (xvii. 593), and even ocean
        shudders at his dreadful bolt. He rains (xii. 5). He
        snows (xii. 280). He deviseth hail and piercing sleet,
        and rainy flood (x. 5). He uproots the sturdy oak
        (xiv. 415), and he snaps the bow-string of Teucer (xv.
        469). Occasionally the moral and physical elements
        are most curiously blended, as in the elaborate descrip-
        tion of the rain deluge with which he punishes the
        crooked verdict of the unjust judge (xvi. 385). Many
        other passages of a similar character might be cited.</p>
        <p>But it is in his relation with Hera, and the various
        heroines who are represented as the objects of his love,
        that the human element in the conception of the
        Homeric Zeus appears under its most revolting aspect.
        His character has accordingly been described as the
        most repulsive in the whole circle of Olympian life,
        exhibiting the very temper of the most advanced
        depravity.<ref n="xxvii.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="xxvii.1">*<title rend="italic">Gladstone's Homer</title>.</note>
        <p><q>It is the Jupiter of Homer in whom
        we see first the most complete surrender of personal
        morality and self-government to mere appetite, and the
        most thoroughly selfish groundwork of character.</q>
        
        <pb n="xxviii" xml:id="p36"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxviii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        Abandonment to gross passion, ungovernable self-
        indulgence rises to its climax in him.</p>
        <p>We seem to inhale a purer atmosphere when, by the
        aid of comparative philology, we are enabled to trans-
        late back into natural phenomena occurrences which,
        when transferred to the sphere of human life, are
        repulsive and revolting. Thus it is not difficult to
        recognize the physical idea which underlies the con-
        ception of Hera, whose name, derived from <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">epa</foreign>, the
        earth (which has been traced back to the Sanscrit),
        sufficiently indicates the original conception sym-
        bolized by her marriage with Zeus, the sky. Ge, the
        earth, is invoked in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, with Zeus and other
        divinities (ii. 277; xix. 258). Of the three goddesses,
        Hera, Dione, and Demeter, in whom the primeval
        goddess reappears mythically metamorphosed (who also
        originally held the same relation to Zeus as seen on
        ancient coins), Hera is alone distinguished in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>
        as the Queen of Heaven, while Demeter, without Divine
        significance, is alluded to in connection with agri-
        cultural pursuits (xiii. 322; v. 500), and Dione appears
        as the mother of Aphrodite (v. 370).</p>
        <p>It was through the Achæan race that Hera acquired
        her high position in the Olympian theogony: among a
        warlike people, who abandoned agriculture to their
        dependants, the physical attributes of the goddess were
        gradually obscured, and accordingly we find her in the
        <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> as the peculiar patroness of Achilles, chief of the
        battle-loving myrmidons (i. 208; ix. 254). Though
        the physical attributes of Hera are almost entirely
        
        <pb n="xxix" xml:id="p37"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxix</fw>
        suppressed in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, we trace a curious lingering of
        the nature element in the Theogamia, described with
        such luxuriance of imagery in the 14th book (345—
        351). <q>As the story of the Olympian Father descend-
        ing as golden rain into the prison of Danaï was meant
        for the bright sky, delivering earth from the bonds of
        winter;</q> so the union of Zeus and Hera, shrouded in
        golden mist, doubtless typified the same natural pheno-
        menon, followed as it was by a new outgrowth of
        tender herbage, <q>the lotus, the crocus, and the hya-
        cinth.</q> A similar remnant of natural symbolism
        might probably be detected in other Homeric legends,
        which in their human aspect are puerile and revolting;
        as when the refractory spouse of Zeus hangs suspended
        by a golden chain, a pair of anvils attached to
        her ankles (xv. 19). How far Homer recognized
        the original significance of these legends is an inter-
        esting but still unsettled question.-Müller (Prolog.
        279).</p>
        <p>If from the thundering, cloud-compelling Zeus of
        the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, we turn to the Zeus of the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title>, the
        contrast is so remarkable, that it would almost appear
        as if the great dramatist, by the very emphasis with
        which he brings out the providential character of the
        Supreme Ruler, desired, like his contemporary, Pindar,
        to enter his protest against the unworthy conception
        of the Epic bard. This hypothesis seems the more
        plausible when we consider that the age of Æschylus
        immediately succeeded that of Pisistratus, who had
        given his sanction to the enactments of Solon, <q>by
        
        <pb n="xxx" xml:id="p38"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxx</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        which the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> was raised into a liturgy, periodically
        rehearsed by law at the greatest of the Athenian
        festivals;</q> <q>exhibiting for the first and last time in
        the history of the world the preservation of a poet's
        compositions made an object of permanent public
        policy.</q></p>
        <p>Accordingly, in the opening chorus of the <title rend="italic">Agamem-
        non</title>, Zeus is represented as conducting in person the
        grand judicial retribution which, in consequence of the
        crime of Paris, involves Ilium in ruin. In the second
        chorus this providential action of Zeus is brought out
        with even stronger emphasis; he is there represented
        as having with prescient might foreordained the blow
        which fell at length in accomplishment of his decree.
        The mighty net of Divine retribution is cast over
        the devoted city, and the character of Zeus is vindi-
        cated as the righteous governor of men. So again in
        the third chorus, it is Zeus, protector of the guest, who
        sends Helen, a fury fraught with destruction, to avenge
        on the sons of Priam the violated rights of hospitality ;
        and whereas, in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, there is division in heaven,
        the deities, swayed by motives purely personal, and
        often of the lowest character (xxiv. 30; iv. 48), take
        part in the quarrel, and appear arrayed against one
        another in the hostile ranks ;-in the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title>, on the
        contrary, they are represented as leagued with Zeus in
        carrying out the great ends of justice. Thus, when
        the cause is brought before the celestial tribunal,
        <q>without dissentient voice they cast their votes into
        the bloody urn, sealing the doom of Troy.</q> (Ag. 789.)
        
        <pb n="xxxi" xml:id="p39"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxxi</fw>
        Zeus is not only represented as exercising supreme
        authority in the moral government of mankind—</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l>“In will, in deed,</l>
          <l>Sole cause, sole fashioner” (Ag. 1462);</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>he also acts inwardly on the souls of men: it is Zeus
        whose highest gift is an untainted mind (Ag. 900);
        who leads men to wisdom through suffering (Ag. 169);
        a function in which he is aided by the subordinate
        deities (Ag. 175), who are represented as the exponents
        of his will. (Eum. 588.)</p>
        <p>In the <title rend="italic">Suppliants</title>, together with a curious lingering
        of the mythological element, we find the grandest
        ascriptions of omnipotence to the Olympian king.
        Thus, he is invoked as <q>King of kings, most blessed
        of the blest, among the Perfect, Power most perfect,
        Zeus, supreme in bliss!</q> (Sup. 518.) He is charac-
        terized as <q>Mighty Zeus, Protector of the guest, the
        Highest, who directs Destiny by hoary law.</q> (Sup.
        655.) <q>Zeus, Lord of ceaseless time</q> (Sup. 567),
        <q>almighty Ruler of the earth.</q> (Sup. 795.) He is
        likewise apostrophized as the great Artificer, supreme
        Ruler, who knows no superior, whose deed is prompt
        as his word to execute the designs of his deep-counsel-
        ling mind. (Sup. 587.) Thus the mythological vesture,
        woven of Nature and Humanity, which had well-nigh
        shrouded the grander features of the Homeric Zeus, is
        partially withdrawn in Aeshylus, and we behold a
        Being whom men could worship without degradation,
        till in the fullness of time the light of celestial
        
        <pb n="xxxii" xml:id="p40"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxxii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        Truth burst with clear effulgence on the heathen
        world.</p>
        <p>We can hardly imagine that the capricious elemental
        deity of the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> should have been metamorphosed
        into the venerable deity of the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title> by the slow
        process of spiritual development alone, without the
        action of external agency: if we consider the affinity
        between the Hellenic and the Persian races, and the
        close contact into which they were brought in Asia
        Minor, the modification of Grecian thought by the
        interfusion of Persian elements will not appear re-
        markable. In support of this hypothesis, I might
        appeal not only to the high spiritual character attri-
        buted to Ahura-Mazda, the Zeus of <title rend="italic">Zend-Avesta</title>, but
        also to the sharp contrast there exhibited between the
        principles of Good and Evil, a feature which strikingly
        distinguishes the theogony of Aeshylus from that of
        Homer.</p>
        <p>The relics of ancient sun-worship which are dis-
        covered in various localities of Greece bear witness to
        the vast influence exerted by the celestial luminary
        over the imaginations and the religious emotions of the
        primeval world, an influence which is also attested by
        the numerous divinities in whom the Sun-god reappears,
        mythically metamorphosed. Helios, in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, is
        characterized as <q>the Unweariable;</q> <q>the Bringer of
        light;</q> like Mithra, who has a thousand ears and ten
        thousand eyes, <q>He overseeth all, and hearkeneth to
        all things</q> (iii. 277). On the reconciliation of Aga-
        memnon and Achilles, a boar is sacrificed to Helios
        
        <pb n="xxxiii" xml:id="p41"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxxiii</fw>
        and to Zeus (xix. 197). The Trojans sacrifice to the
        Earth and to Helios, the Achæans to Zeus (iii. 104).</p>
        <p>In the opening chorus of the <title rend="italic">Agamemnon</title>, the ancient
        Arcadian Sun-god, Pan, whose name is not mentioned
        in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, is associated with Zeus and Apollo, as
        sending the Fury to punish crime. The original charac-
        ter of this divinity, who with Zeus and Apollo shares
        the epithet Lykeios, is betrayed by many significant
        symbols, associated with his effigies and his worship.</p>
        <p>Among the various impersonations of the Sun, how-
        ever, there is none which can compare in interest and
        significance with Dionysos and Apollo, both solar
        divinities, whose worship, nevertheless, offers many
        remarkable points of opposition and contact.</p>
        <p>The celestial luminary was imagined to sleep during
        the winter and to awake to consciousness in spring;
        accordingly Dionysos, rising from the sea at the vernal
        equinox to inaugurate the new solar year, was hailed
        with transports of joy by his enthusiastic votaries.</p>
        <p>The fluctuating character of Dionysos reminds us of
        the nature deities of the Vedas; Proteus-like, he
        assumes every variety of form and age; he is the god
        of summer and of winter, of darkness and of light; he
        holds in his hand the inebriating chalice, together with
        the cosmical mirror, exhibiting the images of all things.</p>
        <p>His worship is of peculiar interest, from its association
        with the Greek drama. Grecian tragedy, as is well
        known, was an expansion of the choruses chanted at
        the Dionysic festivals, which rehearsed the vicissitudes
        of the solar god, in his progress through the heavenly

        

        <pb n="xxxiv" xml:id="p42"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxxiv</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
       signs.
        This circumstance exerted <q>an overruling
        effect upon the quality of the Athenian drama;</q> <q>from
        this early cradle of tragedy arose a sanctity which
        compelled all things to modulate into the same religious
        key.</q><ref n="xxxiv.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="xxxiv.1">* <title rend="italic">Theory of Greek Tragedy</title>. De Quincey.</note>
        <p>Peculiar interest moreover attaches to Dionysos,
        from his association with the mysteries which exerted
        so powerful an influence over the Grecian mind.
        The story of Dionysos, embodying some of the main
        features of his worship, appears in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> (vi. 132),
        invested, however, with ethical, not religious signifi-
        cance. <q>It is a remarkable circumstance that pre-
        cisely those divinities, Demeter and Dionysos, whose
        truly religious influence was most profound and
        pervading in Greece, are all but unmentioned in
        Homer, and may be said, in fact, to be excluded from
        his scheme of the divine community.</q><ref n="xxxiv.2"/>†</p>
        <note n="xxxiv.2">† <title rend="italic">Homer, his Art and his Age</title>. W. Watkiss Lloyd,
        <title rend="italic">Classical Museum</title>, XXII.</note>
        <p>An interesting
        question arises as to the cause of this omission on the
        part of the great epic bard. Are we to imagine that
        the peculiar sanctity which attached to these divinities
        induced him deliberately to avoid the subject; or must
        we conclude that in the Homeric age their worship
        had not yet assumed that mysterious and impressive
        character which subsequently distinguished it? I
        confess I am unable to decide the question, but incline
        to the latter hypothesis.</p>
        
        <pb n="xxxv" xml:id="p43"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxxv</fw>
        <p>The original solar signification of Apollo is main-
        tained among other eminent scholars by Creuzer,
        Welcker, and Gerhard, who appeal alike to ancient
        monuments and coins, and to vestiges of ancient Sun-
        worship found in various localities in Greece.</p>
        <p><q>If we
        desire,</q> says Creuzer, <q>in studying Greek mythology,
        to reach its ultimate roots, we must explore the ancient
        literatures of Persia and India. If from this point of
        view we investigate the original identity of the Sun-
        god and Apollo, we shall find in the figurative language
        of the Vedas the primitive occasion of the transition
        from the former to the latter.</q></p>
        <p>One of the most striking features of the ancient Sun-
        worship was its dualistic character, founded upon the
        twofold aspect of the solar luminary, as at the same
        time a beneficent and a destroying power, as conquer-
        ing and conquered, as dying, yet endowed with ever-
        renovated life; a conception which explains the enigma
        said to be uttered by the oracle of Apollo at Claros, in
        Ionia, <q>I am Jupiter Ammon in Spring, and black
        Pluto in Winter.</q> In order to understand the more
        terrible aspects of the ancient Sun-god, we have only
        to remember the annual fevers occasioned by his
        scorching rays, and the danger of famine from failure
        of the crops: after the lightning of Zeus, there was no
        natural agent so destructive as the arrow of Helios; as
        calamity, moreover, was regarded in ancient times as
        the expression of Divine anger, expiatory and peniten-
        tial rites formed an essential element of the ancient
        Sun-worship. This twofold aspect of Helios finds
        
        <pb n="xxxvi" xml:id="p44"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxxvi</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        expression also in the name of the latter Sun-god,
        Apollo, which, in the ancient Doric Æolian form, was
        not <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">'Aróλλv</foreign>, the Destroyer, but <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">'Améλλw</foreign>, the Averter.</p>
        <p>It is under his darker aspect as <q>the Minister of
        Vengeance, and the Chastiser of Arrogance,</q> that he
        appears for the most part in the poetry of Homer.
        <q>His punishments are pestilence and death ;</q> <q>Achilles,
        to whom he is particularly hostile, calls him the most
        pernicious of all the gods.</q><ref n="xxxvi.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="xxxvi.1">* C. O. Müller's <title rend="italic">History of the Dorians</title>.</note>
        <p>While the Homeric Apollo, in his relation with
        mortals, appears thus in the light of a malevolent
        and destroying power, among the Olympians he
        is introduced in association with the Muses, as
        the god of Music, charming the assembled deities
        with his harp (i. 603). The notion that the stars
        and the other heavenly bodies accomplished their
        revolutions to the sound of music is expressed in the
        ancient poetry of India, and also in that of the Persians.
        As the rhythm of the cosmical movements depended
        upon the solar luminary, the great orderer of times and
        seasons, it is not surprising that from the most remote
        antiquity the Sun-god was represented as playing on
        the cithara; in this character he is portrayed on the
        oldest Archaic vases, encircled by the dancing hours.</p>
        <p>Although in the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title> Apollo is introduced inci-
        dentally as a destroying and avenging deity, as in the
        passage already quoted in the 1st Chorus of the
        <title rend="italic">Agamemnon</title>, and also where he is invoked by Cassandra
        
        <pb n="xxxvii" xml:id="p45"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxxvii</fw>
        as her destroyer (1047), he nevertheless wears, for
        the most part, a more benignant aspect. He is
        emphatically the Healer, the Prophet-leech, who
        purifies from all defilement (<title rend="italic">Eum.</title> 62); the god of joy,
        whom it befits not to invoke with words of sorrow
        (<title rend="italic">Ag.</title> 1056): the most striking point of divergence
        from the Homeric conception of Apollo is to be found
        in his relation to Zeus, with whom he appears in the
        most intimate association. As the god of prophecy,
        the guardian of the sacred oracles, he declares most
        emphatically that he is simply the expounder of his
        father's will, and consequently that he cannot lie.
        (<title rend="italic">Eum.</title> 585, 588.) It is under this aspect, as the god
        of Truth, that a deep significance attaches to the func-
        tion which he assumes in the court of Areopagus as
        Exegetes, or expounder of the unwritten law. <q>At
        Athens, the Exegetæ, who presided over the purification
        of blood-guilty persons, were elected, or at least their
        election was ratified, by the Delphic Oracle.</q><ref n="xxxvii.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="xxxvii.1">* <title rend="italic">Dissertations on the Eumenides</title>. C. O. Müller.</note>
        <p>In this
        character, Apollo appears before the Areopagites, to
        expound the law in relation to homicide, and thus the
        deep-thoughted poet enforces the important principle
        that the judicial proceedings of human tribunals must
        be under the presidency of Truth.</p>
        <p>According to Welcker, however, the Moon appears
        of all natural objects to have been the most universally
        adored. Several tribes in Africa and America are said
        at the present day to worship the moon without the
        
        <pb n="xxxviii" xml:id="p46"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xxxviii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        sun, while no nation has been known to whom the sun
        is sacred without the moon. In primeval ages the
        computations of time were based upon the changes of
        the moon, which accordingly in the Indo-Germanic
        languages is known as <q>The Measurer;</q> and so deeply
        did the lunar phenomena appeal to the religious
        emotions of humanity, that among all early nations, as
        well as among the Jews, the new-moon festivals were
        celebrated with peculiar solemnity. In warm climates,
        moreover, vegetation is nourished almost entirely by
        the dew, which falls most copiously when the moon is
        full; hence Selene was early characterized as the
        mother of Herse, the Bringer of the Dew. It would
        be very interesting to trace the various media of tran-
        sition by which the bright nocturnal luminary was
        gradually metamorphosed into the Huntress Diana—</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>Fair silver-shafted queen for ever chaste,</q></l>
          <l><q>Who set at nought the frivolous bolts of Cupid.</q></l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>So great, however, is the diversity of form under which
        the Moon-goddess has been conceived, exhibiting a
        different physiognomy in every different locality, ac-
        cording to the varied aspect under which she has been
        regarded, that I must content myself with a brief notice
        of her characteristics, as she appears in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> and
        the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title>.</p>
        <p>To the goddess of the green-wood and the glade
        belonged of right all animals both tame and wild;
        accordingly she is characterized in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> as
        (<foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">Tóτnia Onpâν</foreign>), <q>Queen of all Venison</q> (xxi. 470),
        
        <pb n="xxxix" xml:id="p47"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xxxix</fw>
        and in the <title rend="italic">Agamemnon</title> she is represented as taking
        under her especial care—</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>The tiny brood</q></l>
          <l><q>Of all wild things that love the teat,</q></l>
          <l><q>Whether of gentle or of savage mood.</q> (Ag. 138.)</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>While thus gracious to the lower animals, towards
        humanity, on the contrary, she, like the Homeric
        Apollo, wears the aspect of a destroying rather than of
        a benignant power. Thus she is represented as made
        by Zeus (<foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">éovra yúnaixi</foreign>), <q>a lion unto women, to
        whom he hath granted might to slay whomso she
        willeth</q> (xxi. 484). Accordingly, in her anger she
        slew Laodamia, daughter of Bellerophontes (vi. 205),
        and wrathful, on account of her neglected rites, she
        sends the savage, white-tusked boar—</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>Who visited with dire annoy | the orchard-grounds of
        Eneus.</q> (ix. 540.)</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>Andromache, too, in her address to Hector, alludes
        to her mother slain by <q>arrow-pouring Artemis.</q>
        (vi. 428.)</p>
        <p>In the <title rend="italic">Agamemnon</title> she appears under the same
        dark aspect, as the goddess for whose propitiation
        the sacrifice of Iphigenia was consummated, a tragedy
        which, by calling down upon her husband the ven-
        geance of Clytemnestra, forms the groundwork of the
        drama.</p>
        <p>Far more prominent, however, is the position as-
        signed to the Maiden Goddess, Pallas Athena, who
        may be justly regarded as the bright, consummate flower
        
        <pb n="xl" xml:id="p48"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xl</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        of Grecian mythology; and most interesting it is to
        trace the history of her growth from her rise in the
        land of the Aryans to her culmination in the majestic
        goddess of the <title rend="italic">Eumenides</title>.</p>
        <p>The elemental character of the Homeric Zeus sug-
        gests the idea of some natural phenomenon underlying
        the extraordinary birth of his brilliant offspring, <q>from
        no mother born.</q> Accordingly her name has been
        regarded as corresponding to the Sanscrit Aháná, a
        recognised appellation of the dawn in the Veda; and
        thus her miraculous birth from the head of Zeus, trans-
        lated back into Sanscrit, implies that Ushas, the Dawn,
        sprang from the East, the forehead of the sky.<ref n="xl.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="xl.1">* Max Müller. <title rend="italic">Lectures on Language</title>. 2nd Series.</note>
        <p>Welcker gives a different interpretation of her name.
        <q>The Grecians,</q> he says, <q>brought with them from
        their distant home the conception of an element of
        light and warmth above the atmosphere, independent of
        the sun.</q> He derives her name from <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">ae</foreign>, to burn,
        with the ancient suffix <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">ήνη</foreign>, and regards her as the
        impersonation of the pure Ether, the abode of Zeus.</p>
        <p>The peculiar rites with which her worship was
        celebrated in different localities, together with the
        symbolism associated with her effigy on ancient vases
        and coins, attest, according to Welcker, the original
        elemental character of the goddess. This deified im-
        personation of a nature-power, whether identified with
        the Ether or the Dawn, became gradually invested with
        a variety of attributes, human and superhuman; accord-
        
        <pb n="xli" xml:id="p49"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xli</fw>
        ingly, the Athena of the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, though more sharply
        defined than the Olympian Zeus, nevertheless exhibits
        the same transitional character which marks the other
        deities of the Homeric theogony. In her divine capacity
        she is the goddess of war and of industrial art, the re-
        presentative of practical sagacity as opposed to poetic
        inspiration, which was assigned to Apollo. She hears
        and answers prayer; she acts inwardly on the minds
        of the Hellenic heroes; she restrains the wrath of
        Achilles (i. 198); she imparts aid to Tydeus (iv. 390).
        Many similar examples might be adduced. Neverthe-
        less she is not above the practice of deceit, as when she
        persuades Pandarus to violate the treaty (iv. 94), and
        also where she lures Hector with guile. Moreover, the
        intimate connection between the bright, heaven-sprung
        goddess and her father, which in the later mythology
        forms one of her most striking characteristics, is only
        slightly indicated in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> (viii. 38, 373). In
        general, her relation to the Thunderer is one of hostility;
        she is represented as leagued with Hera and Poseidon
        in their attempt to shackle Zeus, for whom she ex-
        presses her contempt in no measured terms, while with
        Hera she appears most intimately associated:</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>Close sat they, side by side, and woes against the Trojans
        plotted,</q></l>
          <l><q>Truly Athena dumb abode before her proper Father,</q></l>
          <l><q>Though wounded by his argument, and seized with fierce
        displeasure.</q> (viii. 458; iv. 21.)</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>Traces of meteoric symbolism in connection with
        the virgin goddess may, I think, be traced in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>.
        
        <pb n="xlii" xml:id="p50"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xlii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        Thus, in girding herself for battle, she lets fall upon
        the starry pavement of her father the brilliant robe—</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>Whose tissue she herself had wrought, and with her hand
        embroidered;</q></l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>her Ægis is the terrible storm-cloud; her casque, all
        golden, measured to contain a hundred cities' footmen,
        recalls the vaulted sky. She descends from heaven
        like a meteor (iv. 70), or like a rainbow wrapped in
        purple cloud (xvii. 551). Thus, too, she is described
        as blowing with gentle breath the spear of Hector (xx.
        440), and as becoming invisible by assuming the casque
        of Aïdes (v. 845).</p>
        <p>The flaming chariot, with its golden-trapped steeds,
        in which she descends with Hera to the assistance of
        the Greeks (v. 720, 748), while suggesting to the
        imagination the bright rays of light, which spring with
        the speed of lightning through the portals of the east,
        recalls also the Vedic invocation to Ushas (the dawn)
        to come in her ample and beautiful chariot, dispersing
        the darkness; or we think of the Golden chariot of
        Savitri, or of Indra, decorated with golden ornaments,
        his white-footed coursers harnessed to his car with a
        golden yoke.</p>
        <p>The function assigned to birds in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> seems
        also like an echo of the Vedas. Thus, when Athena is
        despatched by Zeus to distil nectar and ambrosia
        into Achilles—</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>She plunged in semblance of a bird, the lengthy-feather'd
        osprey,</q></l>
          <l><q>Shrill screaming down from upper sky.</q> (xix. 349.)</l>
        </lg></quote>
        
        <pb n="xliii" xml:id="p51"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xliii</fw>
        <p>It is interesting to remember in this connection the
        Aryan myth according to which the gods allowed the
        heavenly soma drink, the Vedic prototype of the
        Grecian nectar, to be brought down to earth by a falcon.
        In illustration of this subject Kuhn quotes two Vedic
        hymns (R. iv. 26), (R. iv. 27), in the first of which
        occurs the following passage:— <q>The speeding falcon,
        the strong bird, allied to the gods, brought the quicken-
        ing, invigorating soma from afar, stealing it from
        highest heaven.</q></p>
        <p>When Athena and Apollo</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>Over the armies take their seats, in guise of plumèd
        vultures,</q></l>
          <l><q>Upon the lofty beech of Zeus, the Ægis-holding Father,</q>
        (vii. 59.)</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>they remind us of the two birds who sit in friendly
        fashion upon the summit of the soma-bearing tree of
        the Vedas. Thus, too, she sends a heron to greet
        Ulysses and Diomede; they recognized the cry, and
        rejoiced in the divine message (x. 275). Welcker
        detects a figurative allusion to meteoric fact in the
        epithets <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">γλαυκώπις</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">τριτογένεια</foreign>, by which the Homeric
        Athena is distinguished.</p>
        <p>If we turn now to the Athena of Aeshylus, the
        grand impersonation of the wisdom, benignity, and
        might of her father, we recognise, as before, the
        emergence of the classic ideal from the symbolizing
        tendencies of the earlier nature-worship. Seldom has
        the imagination of poet been haunted by a more
        majestic image than the Athena of the <title rend="italic">Eumenides</title>; and
        
        <pb n="xliv" xml:id="p52"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xliv</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        as we picture her <q>like an orator on the <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latn">Bμa</foreign>,</q>
        organizing the court of the Areopagus, she recalls the
        grand vision of Divine Wisdom recorded in the book of
        <title rend="italic">Proverbs</title> (viii.). She, too, standeth in the top of high
        places, and her voice is heard, unfolding the great
        truth that human laws and institutions are entitled to
        reverence only in so far as they are based upon the
        strong foundations of eternal justice and morality.</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>By me kings reign and princes decree justice;</q></l>
          <l><q>By me princes rule, and nobles, even all the judges of the
        earth.</q> Prov. viii. 15, 16; compare Eum. (461, 535).</l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>Most emphatically does the Grecian poet proclaim
        through the lips of Athena, that righteousness must be
        based upon reverence and holy fear, thus coinciding
        with the highest utterance of Hebrew wisdom; <q>The
        fear of the Lord is to hate evil</q> (Prov. viii. 13), (Eum.
        661, 669). Thus, too, wisdom is represented by the
        Grecian as by the Hebrew bard, as presiding over the
        phenomena of external nature (Prov. viii. 27), (Eum.
        792). Yet while Athena alone unlocks the sealed
        thunder-halls of Zeus, she, like her Hebrew prototype,
        <q>rejoiceth in the habitable parts of the earth,</q> and as a
        gardener cherishes his saplings, so <q>she loves the race
        of righteous men, exempt from suffering</q> (Eum. 872).</p>
        <p>This recognition of moral distinctions as the ground
        of divine favour forms, perhaps, the most striking
        point of divergence between Homer and Aeshylus, and
        forcibly recalls the high moral tone of the religion of
        Ahura-Mazda.
        
        <pb n="xlv" xml:id="p53"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xlv</fw>
        Truly it may be said of the Virgin Goddess that,
        like the golden dawn, which she is thought to imper-
        sonate, she brightens more and more, still heralding by
        her effulgent but imperfect light the advent of the
        perfect day. In following the history of the Virgin
        Goddess, it is interesting to remember that the dis-
        appearance of her colossal statue from the Parthenon
        in the fifth century was coincident with the hymn
        addressed to her by her passionate worshipper, the neo-
        Platonist, Proclus; thus at the last <q>she makes a
        swan-like end, fading in music,</q> and vanishes from
        history, after commanding, for upwards of a thousand
        years, the love and veneration of her votaries.</p>
        <p>In connection with the study of ancient poetry, as
        recording the religious life of humanity, it is interesting
        to consider the history of plastic art, which may be
        regarded as its sensible expression, and as manifesting,
        through the medium of ideal forms, the successive
        stages of its development. Thus if we revert to that
        phase of the religious life which is embodied in the
        earliest literary relics of the Aryan race, we shall re-
        cognize the impossibility of embodying in harmonious
        forms beings so impalpable as the deities apostrophized
        by the Vedic bards. In the poetry of those early
        times we discern the working of the untutored mind
        struggling to body forth, through the imagery of
        external nature, its religious yearnings and aspirations;
        embarrassed by the complexity of unintelligible pheno-
        mena, and destitute of any principle of selection, the
        imagination runs riot, blends together images the most
        
        <pb n="xlvi" xml:id="p54"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xlvi</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        incongruous, and exhibits that tendency to symbolism
        which subsequently blossomed out into the colossal
        systems of India and Eleusis.</p>
        <p>The transference of human faith and worship from
        vague nature-powers, dimly recognized as personal
        agencies, to veritable personalities, endowed with con-
        sciousness and will, and distinguished by diversity of
        attribute, moral and intellectual, constitutes, as we have
        seen, the second great stage in the history of human
        progress. This emancipation of the divine idea from
        its association with natural phenomena would lead to
        the recognition of the human form as affording the sole
        adequate medium for the manifestation of spiritual
        existence, a discovery which lies at the root of classic
        art, and inaugurates the second epoch in the artistic
        development of humanity. We have only to pass from
        the Hall of Egyptian Antiquities, in the British
        Museum, to the gallery of the Elgin Marbles, in order
        to appreciate the importance of the transition.</p>
        <p>The Greeks thus realizing the idea that their divini-
        ties manifested themselves through the human form, and
        striving to glorify the temple hallowed by the presence
        of Deity, were led to discover the essential charac-
        teristics of the human organism as a vehicle of superior
        intelligence. In reproducing their impressions through
        the medium of art, they have given birth to models of
        ideal beauty, which show us how fair is the tabernacle
        of the immortal soul, when the lower propensities are
        subjected to higher needs. They detected the Divine
        idea with reference to the human form, and accordingly,
        
        <pb n="xlvii" xml:id="p55"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">xlvii</fw>
        in contemplating these glorious creations we experience
        that indescribable content which invariably comes over
        the soul, when, by any agency, we are lifted above the
        limitations of the finite and phenomenal into the region
        of eternal truth.</p>
        <p>Grand and beautiful as are the classic gods, they
        nevertheless fail to touch the deepest springs of human
        feeling. Though invested with the attributes of
        humanity, we feel that in their emancipation from the
        sorrows and sufferings incident to our mortal life they
        are not true exponents of human nature, while as
        symbols of Deity they are inadequate to shadow forth
        the one infinite and eternal mind. From their cold
        though perfect beauty, the heart of suffering humanity
        turns to the thorn-crowned figure of the Son of Man,
        and recognizes in the man of sorrows its true type and
        representative.</p>
        <p>By revealing God as a spirit immanent in the human
        soul, imparting authority to the oracles of conscience,
        and sanctity to the inner life, Christianity has dispersed
        the crowd of heathen divinities, and exalted to the
        throne of the universe a Heavenly Father whose glory
        is reflected in the Son of Man. Christ's realization of
        conscious union between the divine and human spirit,
        wrought out through the discipline of sorrow, and
        issuing in perfect love, has revealed a depth of spiritual
        life of which in the profoundest myths of classical
        antiquity we see only a dim but most wonderful fore-
        shadowing.</p>
        <p>The transition from the classical to the romantic era
        
        <pb n="xlviii" xml:id="p56"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">xlviii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        finds its explanation in these grand central truths of
        Christianity, which have left their impress alike on art
        and on literature. Thus, in the head of our Saviour in
        the <title rend="italic">Cena</title> of Leonardo da Vinci, we see that marvellous
        union of sublimity and pathos, which, while lifting the
        soul into a higher atmosphere, at the same time appeals
        to the deepest sympathies of the human heart. Thus,
        too, the grand figures of the <title rend="italic">Sistine Chapel</title>, the pro-
        phets and sibyls of Michael Angelo, while exhibiting
        the human form cast in the majestic mould of the
        Olympian gods, bear traces, at the same time, of those
        inner life-struggles which impart to every noteworthy
        countenance so deep and often so tragic an interest.</p>
        <p>The literary productions of the romantic era also bear
        witness to the deeper significance which attaches to
        human nature since the advent of Christianity-a phe-
        nomenon the recognition of which is essential to the
        true appreciation of classical literature.</p>
        <p>The fundamental distinction between the ancient and
        modern drama will be more fully recognized if we
        bring into closer comparison the two great fathers of
        dramatic art, Aeshylus and Shakespeare, who, though
        separated from one another by an interval of nearly
        twenty centuries, yet offer some remarkable points
        both of analogy and contrast.</p>
        <p>In studying the dramas of Aeshylus, when we
        penetrate below the surface, we find that the solution
        of problems, ethical and religious, bearing upon man's
        nature and destiny, constitutes their essence, an object
        to which the delineation of character is made 
        
        <pb n="xlix" xml:id="p57"/>
subser-vient; whereas in the dramas of Shakespeare the de-
        velopment of character constitutes the primary aim,
        to which he subordinates the underlying idea of the
        whole; accordingly we should vainly seek in the im-
        personations of the ancient bard that marvellous
        insight into the more subtle phenomena of human
        nature which imparts so intense an interest to the
        productions of Shakespeare. In Aeshylus the collision
        between moral principles, whose harmonious action is
        essential to the moral order of the world, is set forth
        by personages, human and superhuman, whose charac-
        ters are drawn in bold relief, without exhibiting that
        delicate shading which charms us in the delineation
        of the modern bard. These personages are led in
        obedience to one moral principle to violate another,
        which in its turn finds advocates and champions. The
        collision between these opposing interests and the
        various passions evoked in the struggle sustain the
        interest of the drama, while the <hi rend="italic">dénouement</hi> exhibits the
        vindication of eternal order by the triumph of that
        principle which is of primary obligation. If we apply
        these principles to the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title>, we find that while the
        several members of the trilogy are linked together by
        a chain of ethical sequence, which resolves itself into
        the great doctrine of retribution, each drama is at the
        same time devoted to the solution of a particular
        problem, and constitutes accordingly a complete and
        independent whole.</p>
        <p>The collision of duties set forth in the <title rend="italic">Agamemnon</title>
        is of peculiar interest, as illustrating a struggle which
        <fw type="signature" place="bottom-center">d</fw>
        
        <pb n="l" xml:id="p58"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">l</fw> <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        has its counterpart in the most touching narrative of
        Jewish history. Agamemnon, as king and army chief,
        receives what he believes to be a divine command to
        propitiate Artemis by the sacrifice of his daughter; an
        ordeal, the terrible reality of which can only be ap-
        preciated when we consider the proneness to human
        sacrifice which characterized the early ages of society.
        Abraham, when subjected to a like trial or temptation,
        after manifesting his perfect submission to what
        appeared to him to be a divine monition, was led to
        recognize the true voice of God as harmonizing with
        the most sacred intuitions of the human heart, and
        accordingly forbore to slay his child.<ref n="l.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="l.1">*I have followed Dean Stanley's interpretation of this
        narrative.</note>
        <p>Agamemnon,
        on the contrary, yields to the suggestion of Calchas,
        and by the sacrifice of Iphigenia violates his obli-
        gations to his daughter and his wife. Clytemnestra
        appears as the avenger of her child, and in vindication
        of nature's violated rights, prepares for her husband
        an ignominious death. The stern reprobation of Aga-
        memnon expressed by the Chorus may be compared to
        the sublime protest of Micah, and other Hebrew
        prophets, against such deeds of blood. Thus the
        cruel perversion of religion which found expression
        in human sacrifice was condemned by the Grecian poet
        no less than by the Hebrew sage, a consideration which
        invests the Aeshylean drama with profound signifi-
        cance.</p>
        
        <pb n="li" xml:id="p59"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">li</fw>
        <p>In order to appreciate the fundamental idea which
        underlies the drama of the <title rend="italic">Choephori</title> we must take
        into consideration the sacred duty of avenging blood,
        <q>recognized by the earliest customs and national laws
        of the East as well as of the West.</q><ref n="li.1">*</ref> On the murder
        of Agamemnon by Clytemnestra, it was the bounden
        duty of his son Orestes to avenge his death; the ghost
        of his murdered father and the Delphic god demand it
        of him. The collision, therefore, which forms the
        groundwork of the drama is between the duty of
        Orestes as the avenger of his father, and his instinctive
        recognition of the reverence due to his mother, which
        tends to withhold him from the commission of the
        deed. With admirable skill the poet makes us feel
        the terrible nature of the struggle, and the religious
        motives which decide the issue. When Orestes, almost
        overcome by his mother's agonizing entreaties, hesitates
        to commit the bloody act, Pylades, who has accom-
        panied him as a representative of the god, admonishes
        him of his duty, exclaiming—</p>
        <quote><lg>
          <l><q>Choose all for foemen rather than the Gods.</q></l>
        </lg></quote>
        <p>A profound thought underlies the greater heinousness
        attached to the murder of Agamemnon by Clytem-
        nestra, than to the murder of Clytemnestra by Orestes.
        The bond which unites the mother and the son, which
        Orestes is required to violate, is instinctive, resting
        upon a law of nature; the tie which unites the
        <note n="li.1">*<title rend="italic">Dissertations on the Eumenides</title>. C. O. Müller.</note>
        
        <pb n="lii" xml:id="p60"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">lii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        husband and the wife is of a different order, involving
        intelligent volition and reciprocal engagement. The
        institution of marriage, morever, lies at the root of all
        law and order, and with the consequent permanence and
        sanctity of the domestic relations is the sole guarantee
        for the healthy development of society; hence the
        conjugal tie requires to be placed under the special
        guardianship of the gods and of eternal justice.
        Hera, who in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> plays so prominent and often
        so undignified a part, is introduced in the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title> in
        her grand matronly character, her union with Zeus
        being alluded to as imparting sanctity to the marriage
        tie. A comparison between the <title rend="italic">Choephori</title> of Aeshylus
        and the <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> of Shakespeare may serve to exhibit
        more strikingly the fundamental difference between
        the ancient and modern drama. In both tragedies the
        father of the hero has been murdered, and the mother
        has married the murderer; in both, the son is urged
        by supernatural visitations to avenge the crime, and
        both are prompted by the same motives of disappointed
        ambition. In the ancient drama, however, the death
        of Agamemnon is represented as the vindication of a
        moral principle, violated in the person of Clytemnestra.
        Accordingly, when pleading for her life, she not only
        appeals to the filial reverence of her son, but also
        represents herself as having, by the death of her
        husband, accomplished the ends of divine justice. In
        the modern drama the murder of the king is repre-
        sented as an act of pure wickedness; hence when
        Hamlet is summoned to avenge his father's death, no
        
        <pb n="liii" xml:id="p61"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">liii</fw>
        external object which claims his reverence intervenes
        to check his purpose. The hesitancy must therefore
        come from within; accordingly the collision is found
        not in opposing moral principles, but in the personal
        character of Hamlet. His soul is not organized to
        perpetrate this deed of horror; consequently, wavering
        in his resolution, and overwhelmed with disgust at the
        world and at life, he perishes in the consummation of
        his revenge. So marvellous is the skill with which the
        character of Hamlet is drawn, so absorbing the in-
        terest which it awakens, that in studying it we are apt
        to forget the fundamental idea which underlies the
        drama, the <hi rend="italic">dénouement</hi> of which, like that of the
        several members of the <title rend="italic">Oresteia</title>, sets forth the great
        law of retribution, and vindicates the moral order of
        the Divine government.</p>
        <p>In the third member of the trilogy, the poet, while
        making his drama subservient to objects connected
        with the political state of Athens, nevertheless subor-
        dinates these local interests to the exposition of higher
        truth. Among these political objects the most impor-
        tant was the defence of the Areopagus, the existence of
        which was threatened by the growing ascendency of the
        democracy. It would be difficult to 'imagine a more
        impressive means of recommending this tribunal to
        the reverence of the Athenians than thus to introduce
        the celestial powers as assisting at its inauguration.
        Of far higher significance, however, is the ethical
        conception which underlies the drama. The word
        Erinys in Greek has been defined to mean <q>the feeling
        
        <pb n="liv" xml:id="p62"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">liv</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        of deep offence, of bitter displeasure, when sacred rights
        belonging to us are impiously violated by persons who
        ought most to have respected them.</q> These vengeance-
        prompting feelings, personified as active, ever-wakeful
        spirits, became associated with the great nature-power,
        Demeter, under her more malignant aspect, and hence
        arose the worship of the dread goddess, Demeter
        Erinys. Both these names have been traced back to
        the Sanscrit; the Greek Demeter being identified with
        Dyâvâ Mâtar, the Mother, corresponding to Dyaus
        Pitar, the Father, and the Erinyes being identified
        with the Sanscrit Saranyû. Thus it appears that the
        venerable goddesses, like Zeus and Athena, have their
        root in the Vedas. <q>In early Greek mythology they
        were attributed more especially to the Father, the
        Mother, and the Elder Brother, whenever their sacred
        rights had been impiously violated.</q> They are thus
        introduced in the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> (ix. 449; ix. 572; xv. 204),
        where they are represented as avenging any violation
        of the natural order.</p>
        
        <p>In this character they also appear at the conclusion
        of the <title rend="italic">Choephori</title>, and in the opening scenes of the
        <title rend="italic">Eumenides</title>, where, like blood-thirsty hounds, they
        pursue Orestes for the murder of his mother: they
        take cognizance only of the outward act, and exercise
        their functions with the inflexibility of natural law.
        They would not the less have claimed him as their
        prey had he left unavenged the murder of his father
        (<title rend="italic">Choeph.</title> 283, 911). In this fatal collision Athena
        appears as umpire: by establishing the court of
        
        <pb n="lv" xml:id="p63"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">lv</fw>
        Areopagus she proclaims the great principle, <q>that the
        highest tribunal upon earth is the collective conscience
        of humanity.</q><ref n="lv.1">*</ref> The cause is tried before this august
        assembly; righteous regard is had for the special
        circumstances of the deed; Orestes is acquitted, the
        sanctity of the primeval goddesses is recognized ;
        their wrath is appeased, and thus the intuitive thirst
        for revenge is transmuted into the principle of eternal
        justice. Thus the drama of the <title rend="italic">Eumenides</title> exhibits,
        under one of its grandest phases, the contest between
        the Titans and the Olympian gods, issuing in the
        triumph of free will and moral power over blind
        instinct and necessity, while the transmutation of the
        Erinyes into the Eumenides symbolizes the profound
        thought that even the instinctive tendencies in human
        nature are implanted there by its Divine Author, and
        consequently that man's highest well-being demands,
        not their suppression or annihilation, but their harmo-
        nious subordination to the higher faculties of the soul.</p>
        <p>Classical poetry affords the true key to classic art;
        it is, therefore, interesting to turn from the study of
        Aeshylus to the contemplation of the Parthenon,
        where the Athenians beheld translated into marble the
        same profound ideas which the great dramatist has
        embodied in his immortal works. Thus the sculptures
        of the eastern pediment, having reference to the birth
        of Athena, indicate, by the presence of the Fates and
        other divine personages, the deep significance attached
        <note n="lv.1">*<title rend="italic">'Gott in der Geschichte.'</title> Bunsen.</note>
        
        <pb n="lvi" xml:id="p64"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">lvi</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        by the sculptor to the manifestation of Divine Wisdom
        in the person of the Virgin Goddess; while in the
        grand composition of the western pediment, which set
        forth the contention of Poseidon and Athena for
        supremacy over the country of Attica, we trace, as in
        the <title rend="italic">Eumenides</title>, the association of interests purely local
        and national with truths of higher significance. Thus
        the contending divinities have been regarded as
        typifying the antagonism between agricultural and
        maritime pursuits, which formed one main feature of
        Athenian life; and also as reflecting the conflicting
        powers of land and sea, as exhibited in the topography
        of the interior and the coast.<ref n="lvi.1">*</ref> I doubt not, however,
        that there rose also before the mental vision of Phidias
        the grand old allegory of the battle between the Titans
        and the Gods, which may be regarded as the mythical
        expression of that eternal struggle between the lower
        and higher elements of being, of which the drama of
        the <title rend="italic">Eumenides</title> affords so impressive and magnificent a
        symbol: this hypothesis appears the more plausible
        when we consider the intimate mythological connection
        which obtained between Poseidon and Demeter-
        Erinys.</p>
        <p>Another most interesting illustration of the intimate
        association which, in classical times, existed between
        Poetry and her sister arts is to be found in the paint-
        ings of Polygnotus in the Lesche at Delphi, of which
        <note n="lvi.1">*<title rend="italic">Explanation of the Groups in the Western Pediment
        of the Parthenon</title>. <title rend="italic">'Classical Museum.'</title> W. Watkiss Lloyd.</note>

<pb n="lvii" xml:id="p65"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">lvii</fw>
       a minute description is given by Pausanias, and which
        have been admirably restored by Fr. and Joh. Riepen-
        hausen.<ref n="lvii.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="lvii.1">* On the paintings of Polygnotus in the Lesche at Delphi.
        <title rend="italic">'Classical Museum,'</title> vol. i. W. Watkiss Lloyd.</note>
        <p>The first picture exhibits the capture of
        Ilion, the desecration of her sanctuaries, and brings
        before the mental eye the outrage committed against
        Athena in the person of Cassandra, thus setting forth
        the origin of the disasters which befell the returning
        armament of the Greeks: it would be impossible for
        the beholders of this picture not to recall the speech of
        Clytemnestra in the <title rend="italic">Agamemnon</title> (320), in which she
        forcibly describes the contrast between the state of
        victors and vanquished in the captured city, the
        desolation of which is touchingly symbolized in the
        painting by the empty cuirass that lies on the altar to
        which a child is clinging. The exhibition of the very
        crimes so earnestly deprecated by the poet (330),
        prepares the mind for the second picture, exhibiting
        the descent of Ulysses to Hades, to learn from the
        prophet the means by which a safe return might be
        secured. The punishment of the sacrilegious Tityus,
        and the retaliation on the undutiful son, could not fail
        to suggest to the mind of the spectator those passages
        of the <title rend="italic">Eumenides</title> in which the poet, with terrible
        earnestness, describes the direful fate which in the
        lower regions is the sure award of filial impiety and
        sacrilege (260).</p>
        <p>The schools of design which are springing up
        
        <pb n="lviii" xml:id="p66"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">lviii</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        throughout the length and breadth of the land bear
        witness to the importance which is now attached to
        artistic culture in England.</p>
        <p>It must not be forgotten, however, that imagination
        constitutes the vital principle of art; that the practised
        eye and well-trained hand are powerless except as
        instruments to embody the conceptions of the creative
        mind. Hence the study of poetry acquires new
        significance, not only as throwing light upon the
        master-works of classical antiquity, the recognized
        models of ideal form, but also as enriching the imagi-
        nation, while at the same time it opens both eye and
        soul to discern the familiar beauty of common life.
        What Joubert has said of Plato may be applied with
        equal truth to poetry:-<q xml:lang="fr">Platon ne fait rien voir, mais
        il éclaire, il met de la lumière dans nos yeux, et place
        en nous une clarté, dont tous les objets deviennent
        ensuite illuminés. Comme l'air des montagnes sa
        lecture aiguise les organes, et donne le goût des bons
        aliments.</q></p>
        <p><q>Of imagination, fancy, taste, of the highest cul-
        tivation in all its forms, this great nation has abun-
        dance; of industry, skill, perseverance, mechanical
        contrivance, it has a yet larger stock, which overflows
        our narrow bounds and floods the world.
        The one
        great want is to bring these two groups of qualities
        harmoniously together.</q><ref n="lviii.1"/>*</p>
        <note n="lviii.1">*Wedgewood, an address by the Rt. Hon. W. E.
        Gladstone, M.P.</note>
        <p>I believe that in poetry will
        
        <pb n="lix" xml:id="p67"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">The Trilogy.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">lix</fw>
        be found one of the missing links through whose agency
        this alliance between the spheres of beauty and utility
        is to be consummated. Milton speaks of <q>the glorious,
        the magnificent, uses which may be made of poetry
        both in divine and human things;</q> while Shelley
        characterized it as <q>a fountain for ever flowing with
        the waters of wisdom and delight.</q> It becomes,
        therefore, a question of deep national interest to con-
        sider by what agencies these renovating and purifying
        influences may be diffused, and brought home to the
        heart of this great nation. <q>From Greece, the fountain
        of all instruction in matters of art,</q> we may perhaps
        take a hint as to one large and important department
        of national education.</p>
        <p>In this connection I am tempted to quote a passage
        from Grote's <title rend="italic">History of Greece</title>, where, after alluding
        to the abundance in the productions of the tragic
        muse, at Athens, he proceeds :-<q>All this abundance
        founds its way to the minds of the great body of the
        citizens, not excepting even the poorest. So powerful
        a body of poetic influence has probably never been
        brought to act upon the emotions of any other popula-
        tion; and when we consider the extraordinary beauty
        of these immortal compositions, which first stamped
        tragedy as a separate department of poetry, and gavo
        to it a dignity never since reached, we shall be
        satisfied that the tastes, the sentiments, and the intel
        lectual standard of the Athenian multitude must have
        been sensibly improved and exalted by such lessons.
        The reception of such pleasures through the eye and
        
        <pb n="lx" xml:id="p68"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top-left">lx</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top-right">The Trilogy.</fw>
        ear, as well as amidst a sympathizing crowd, was a
        fact of no small importance in the mental history of
        Athens. It contributed to exalt their imagination,
        like the grand edifices and ornaments added during the
        same period to the Acropolis.</q></p>
        <p>The designs of Flaxman from Homer and Aeshylus
        are wrought into our damask and engraved upon our
        glass; it is time that the thoughts of the great poets,
        from whom he drew his inspiration, should be brought
        home, with all their rich treasure of imagery to the
        hearts and minds of our people. What noble enter-
        tainment might not be drawn from <q>Heroic poems and
        Attic tragedies of stateliest and most regal ornament,</q>
        if, appealing as they do to the feelings of our common
        humanity, they were made appreciable to the popular
M        understanding by illustrations drawn from history and
        art!</p>
        <p>With reference to the moral influence of poetry,
        Joubert says, <q xml:lang="fr">Voulez-vous connaître la morale?
        Lisez les poëtes; ce qui vous plaît chez eux, appro-
        fondissez-le; c'est le vrai; ils doivent être la grande
        étude du philosophe qui veut connaître l'homme.</q></p>
        <p>Believing that Aeshylus strikingly corroborates this
        utterance, in all humility I offer to the public this
        version of his greatest work.</p>

      </div>
         <div type="translation"
              xml:lang="eng"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0085.tlg005.perseus-eng2">
  
        
<ab>
            <title type="sub">AGAMEMNON.</title>
          </ab>
          <stage>The WATCHMAN is discovered reclining on the flat roof of <lb/>
            the palace.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>WATCHMAN</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I PRAY the gods deliverance from these toils,</l>
              <l>Release from year-long watch, which, couch'd aloft</l>
              <l>On these Atreidan roofs, dog-like, I keep,</l>
              <l>Marking the stars which nightly congregate;</l>
              <l>And those bright potentates who bring to mortals</l>
              <l>Winter and summer, signal in the sky,</l>
              <l><ref n="3.2">2</ref>What time they wane I note, their risings too.</l>
              <l>And for the beacon's token now I watch,</l>
              <l>The blaze of fire, bearing from Troy a tale,</l>
              <l><ref n="3.2">2</ref>Tidings of capture; for so proudly hopes<ref n="3.1">1</ref></l>
              <l>A woman's heart, with manly counsel fraught.</l>
              <l>Dew-drenched and restless is my nightly couch,</l>
              <l>By dreams unvisited, for at my side,</l>
              <l>Fear stands, in place of sleep, nor suffers me</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="4"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>WATCHMAN</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Soundly, in slumberous rest, my lids to close.</l>
              <l>Then when I think to chant a strain, or hum,</l>
              <l>(Such against sleep my tuneful counter-charm,)</l>
              <l>Moaning, I wail the sorrows of this house,</l>
              <l>Not wisely governed as in days of old.</l>
              <l>But may glad respite from these toils be mine,</l>
              <l>When fire, joy's herald, through the darkness gleams.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>He suddenly beholds the beacon-light and starts to his feet.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>WATCHMAN</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hail lamp of night, forth shining like the day,</l>
              <l>Of many a festive dance in Argos' land,</l>
              <l>Through joy at this event, the harbinger.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Hurrah! Hurrah! To Agamemnon's queen,</l>
              <l>Thus with shrill cry I give th' appointed sign.</l>
              <l>That from her couch up-rising with all speed,</l>
              <l>She in the palace jubilant may lift</l>
              <l>The joyous shout, to gratulate this torch,</l>
              <l>If Ilion's citadel in truth is ta'en,</l>
              <l>As, shining forth, this beacon-fire proclaims.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The joyous prelude I myself will dance,</l>
              <l>For to my lords good fortune I shall score,</l>
              <l>Now that this torch hath cast me triple six.</l>
              <l>Well! be it mine, when comes this mansion's lord,</l>
              <l>In this my hand his much-loved hand to hold !</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>The rest I speak not; o'er my tongue hath passed</l>
              <l>An ox with heavy tread: the house itself,</l>
              <l>Had it a voice, would tell the tale full clear ;</l>
              <l>And I, with those who know, am fain to speak,</l>
              <l>With others, who know nothing, I forget.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Exit.</stage>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="footnotes">
            <note n="1">* The figures correspond to the number of lines in the <lb/>original. </note>
            <note n="2">† The obelisks refer to the conjectural emendations of <lb/>the text at the end of each drama.</note>
          </div>
          <pb n="5"/>
          <stage>Enter in rank and file the Chorus of ARGIVE ELDERS, each leaning on his staff; during their slow and measured advance they sing the following Ode, the conclusion of which brings them in front of the stage.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Lo the tenth year rolls apace</l>
              <l>Since Priam's mighty challenger,</l>
              <l>Lord Menelas and Atreus' heir,</l>
              <l>Stalwart Atridæ,--by heaven's grace</l>
              <l>Twin-throned, twin-sceptered,-from this land</l>
              <l>A thousand sail, with Argives manned,</l>
              <l>Unmoor'd,-a martial armament,</l>
              <l>Warriors on just reprisal bent,</l>
              <l>Fierce battle clanging from their breast,</l>
              <l>Like vultures of their young bereaved,</l>
              <l>Who, for their nestlings sorely grieved,</l>
              <l>Wheel, eddying high above their nest,</l>
              <l>By oarage of strong pennons driven,</l>
              <l>Missing the eyrie-watching care</l>
              <l>Of callow fledglings ; but from heaven,</l>
              <l>Some guilt-avenging deity,</l>
              <l>Or all-retrieving Zeus, doth lend</l>
              <l>An ear attentive to the cry</l>
              <l>Of birds, shrill-wailing, sore-distrest,</l>
              <l>And doth upon the guilty send</l>
              <l>Erinys, late-avenging pest.</l>
              <l>So for the dame, by many wooed.</l>
              <l>Doth mighty Zeus, who shields the guest,</l>
              <l>'Gainst Paris send th' Atridan brood;</l>
              <l>Struggles limb-wearing, knees earth-pressed</l>
              <pb n="6"/>
              <l>The spear-shaft, rudely snapt in twain</l>
              <l>In war's initial battle,—these</l>
              <l>For Danaoi as for Trojans he decrees.</l>
              <l>As matters stand, they stand ; the yet to be</l>
              <l>Must issue as ordained by destiny.</l>
              <l>Nor altar fires, nor lustral rain</l>
              <l>Poured forth, nor tear-drops shed in vain,</l>
              <l>The wrath relentless can appease</l>
              <l>Of violated sanctities.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But we, unhonoured, weak of frame,</l>
              <l>Excluded from that proud array,</l>
              <l>Tarry at home, and, age-oppressed,</l>
              <l>On staves our child-like strength we lean;</l>
              <l>In tender years and age, the same,</l>
              <l>Life's current feebly sways the breast;</l>
              <l>His station Ares holds no more;</l>
              <l>Decrepid Eld, with leafage hoar,</l>
              <l>No stronger than a child for war,</l>
              <l>Treadeth his triple-footed way,</l>
              <l>Like dream in daylight seen.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Enter CLYTEMNESTRA, followed by a female train. The Chorus sings the following Ode as it advances to take up its usual position round the altar of ZEUS, adorned with a statue of the god.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But Clytemnestra, thou,</l>
              <l>Tyndareus' daughter, Argos queen,</l>
              <l>What hath befallen ? What hast heard ?</l>
              <l>Confiding in what tidings now</l>
              <l>Sendest thou round the altar-kindling word ?</l>
              <l>Of all the gods who guard the state,</l>
              <l>Supernal, or of realms below,</l>
              <pb n="7"/>
              <l>In heaven, or in the mart who wait,</l>
              <l>With gifts the altars glow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Now here, now yonder, doth a torch arise,</l>
              <l>Streaming aloft to reach the skies,</l>
              <l>Charmed with pure unguent's soothing spell,</l>
              <l>Guileless and suasive, from the royal cell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>What here 'tis lawful to declare,</l>
              <l>What may be told proclaim;</l>
              <l>Be healer of this care</l>
              <l>Which now a lowering form doth wear,</l>
              <l>Till fawning Hope, from out the flame</l>
              <l>Of sacrifice, with gentle smile</l>
              <l>Doth sateless grief's soul-gnawing pang beguile.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>While CLYTEMNESTRA offers sacrifice, the following Ode is sung by the Chorus from the altar of ZEUS.</stage>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The way-side omen mine it is to sing,<ref n="7.1">1</ref></l>
              <l>The leaders' prosperous might foreshadowing,</l>
              <l>For still my age, unquenched its natal power,</l>
              <l>Doth suasive song inspire, a heaven-sent dower,</l>
              <l>How the rapacious bird, the feathered king,</l>
              <l>Sends forth against the Teucrid land,</l>
              <l>With spear and with avenging hand,</l>
              <l>Achaia's double-thronèd Might,</l>
              <l>Accordant chiefs of Hellas' martial flower.</l>
              <pb n="8"/>
              <l>Toward spear-poising hand, the palace near,</l>
              <l>On lofty station, manifest to sight,</l>
              <l>The bird-kings to the navy-kings appear,</l>
              <l>One black, and one with hinder plumage white ;</l>
              <l>A hare with embryo young, in evil hour,</l>
              <l>Amerced of future courses, they devour.</l>
              <l>Chant the dirge, uplift the wail!</l>
              <l>But may the right prevail!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then the sagacious army-seer, aware</l>
              <l>How diverse-minded the Atridan kings,</l>
              <l>In the hare-renders sees the martial pair,</l>
              <l>And thus, the augury expounding, sings;—</l>
              <l>“Priam's stronghold in time this martial raid</l>
              <l>Captures, but first the city's store,</l>
              <l>Tho people's wealth, shall fate destroy :</l>
              <l>Now from no god may jealous ire</l>
              <l>O'ercloud the mighty curb forged against Troy,<ref n="8.1">1</ref></l>
              <l>Marshalled for battle; for the holy Maid</l>
              <l>Is angered at the house, since of her sire</l>
              <l>The winged hounds the wretched trembler tare,</l>
              <l>Mother and young unborn, her special care;</l>
              <l>Therefore doth she the eagles' meal abhor.</l>
              <l>Chant tho dirge, uplift tho wail!</l>
              <l>But may the right prevail!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">EPODE.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>†For she, the beauteous goddess, loves</l>
              <pb n="9"/>
              <l>The tender whelps, new-dropped, of creatures rude,</l>
              <l>Sparing the udder-loving brood</l>
              <l>Of every beast through field or wood that roves,--</l>
              <l>Hence with Apollo pleads the seer that he</l>
              <l>From these events fair omens will fulfil,</l>
              <l>Judging the way-side augury,</l>
              <l>Partly auspicious, partly fraught with ill.</l>
              <l>Oh ! God of healing! thee I supplicate,</l>
              <l>Let not the Huntress on the Danaï bring</l>
              <l>Dire ship-detaining blasts and adverse skies,</l>
              <l>Preluding other sacrifice,</l>
              <l>Lawless, unfestive, natal spring</l>
              <l>Of feudful jar and mortal hate,</l>
              <l>By husband-fear unawed;</l>
              <l>For child-avenging wrath, with fear and fraud,</l>
              <l>Dread palace-warden, doth untiring wait."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Such woes, with high successes blent,</l>
              <l>By Fate on the twain royal houses sent,</l>
              <l>Did Calchas from the way-side auguries</l>
              <l>Bodeful proclaim :-Then consonant with these,</l>
              <l>Chant the dirge, uplift the wail!</l>
              <l>But may the right prevail!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Zeus, whoe'er he be, this name</l>
              <l>If it pleaseth him to claim,</l>
              <l>This to him will I address;</l>
              <l>Weighing all, no power I know</l>
              <l>Save only Zeus, if I aside would throw</l>
              <l>In sooth as vain this burthen of distress.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="footnotes">
            <note n="7.1">* The original being here in oracular style is purposely <lb/>obscure, and cannot be fitly rendered otherwise in the trans­ <lb/>lation. </note>
            <note n="8.1">* By a harsh metaphor the Greek army is called a curb <lb/>forged against Troy. </note>
          </div>
          <pb n="10"/>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Nor doth he so great of yore,<ref n="10.1">1</ref></l>
              <l>With all-defying boldness rife,</l>
              <l>†Longer avail; his reign is o'er.</l>
              <l>The next, thrice vanquished in the strife,</l>
              <l>Hath also passed ; but who the victor-strain</l>
              <l>To Zeus uplifts, true wisdom shall obtain.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To sober thought Zeus paves the way,</l>
              <l>And wisdom links with pain.</l>
              <l>In sleep the anguish of remembered ill</l>
              <l>Drops on the troubled heart; against their will</l>
              <l>Rebellious men are tutored to be wise;</l>
              <l>† A grace I ween of the divinities,</l>
              <l>Who mortals from their holy seats arraign.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>E'en so the elder of the twain,</l>
              <l>Achaia's fleet who swayed,</l>
              <l>No seer upbraiding, bowed, with grief suppressed,</l>
              <l>His soul to fortune's stroke ; what time the host,</l>
              <l>In front of Chalcis, tossing off the coast</l>
              <l>Of wave-vexed Aulis, lingered, sore-distressed,</l>
              <l>While store-exhausting gales their progress stayed.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Blasts, dire delay and famine in their train,</l>
              <l>And evil-anchorage, from Strymon sweep,-</l>
              <l>Ruin to mortals; with malignant power,</l>
              <l>Ruthless to ships and cordage, they</l>
              <pb n="11"/>
              <l>Doubling the sojourn on the deep</l>
              <l>Wither the Argive flower.</l>
              <l>But to the chiefs of that array,</l>
              <l>When, than the bitter storm, the seer</l>
              <l>A cure shrieked forth, weighted with deadlier banc,-</l>
              <l>In name of Artemis,-the Atridan twain,</l>
              <l>Smiting on earth their sceptres, strove in vain</l>
              <l>To quell the rising tear.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then thus aloud the elder chieftain cried :—</l>
              <l>" Grievous, in sooth, the doom to disobey,</l>
              <l>But grievous too if I my child must slay,</l>
              <l>My home's fair ornament, my pride,</l>
              <l>Defiling these paternal hands,</l>
              <l>E'en at the altar's side,</l>
              <l>With virgin-slaughter's gory tide.</l>
              <l>What course exempt from evil? Say,</l>
              <l>The fleet can I desert, the leaguèd bands</l>
              <l>Failing? With hot desire to crave the spell</l>
              <l>Of virgin blood, the storm that shall allay,</l>
              <l>Is just. May all be well!"</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE IV.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then harnessed in Necessity's stern yoke</l>
              <l>An impious change-wind in his bosom woke,</l>
              <l>Profane, unhallowed, with dire evil fraught,</l>
              <l>His soul perverting to all daring thought.</l>
              <l>For frenzy, that from primal guilt doth spring,</l>
              <l>Emboldens mortals, prompting deeds of ill;</l>
              <l>Thus, armed a woman to avenge, the king</l>
              <l>In sacrifice his daughter dared to kill;</l>
              <l>The fleet's initial rite accomplishing.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="footnotes">
            <note n="10.1">* The combatants probably are Uranos, father of Kronos ; <lb/>and Kronos, father of Zeus. </note>
          </div>
          <pb n="12"/>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE IV.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Her prayers, her cries of " Father," her young life</l>
              <l>Were nought to those stern umpires, breathing strife:</l>
              <l>So, after prayer, her sire the servants bade,</l>
              <l>†Stooping, with steelèd hearts, to lift the maid</l>
              <l>Robe-tangled, kid-like, as for sacrifice,</l>
              <l>High o'er the altar; them he also bade,</l>
              <l>Guarding her lovely mouth, her bodeful cries,</l>
              <l>Stern curse entailing on their houses twain,</l>
              <l>With voiceless muzzles forceful to restrain.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE V.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then letting fall her veil of saffron dye,</l>
              <l>She smote, with piteous arrow from her eye,</l>
              <l>Each murderer; while, passing fair,</l>
              <l>†Like to a pictured image, voiceless there,</l>
              <l>Strove she to speak; for oft in other days,</l>
              <l>She in her father's hospitable halls,</l>
              <l>With her chaste voice had carolled forth his praise,</l>
              <l>What time the walls</l>
              <l>Rang to the Pæan's sound,</l>
              <l>Gracing her sire, with third libation crowned.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE V.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What next befel I know not, nor relate;</l>
              <l>Not unfulfill'd were Calchas' words of fate.</l>
              <l>For justice doth for sufferers ordain</l>
              <l>To purchase wisdom at the cost of pain.</l>
              <l>Why seek to read the future? Let it go !</l>
              <l>Since dawns the issue clear with dawning day,</l>
              <pb n="13"/>
              <l>What boots it to forestal our date of woe ?</l>
              <l>Come weal at last!</l>
              <l>So prays, these mischiefs past,</l>
              <l>Of Apia's land this one sole guard and stay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>Hail Clytemnestra! Hither am I come</l>
              <l>Thy majesty revering. For 'tis meet</l>
              <l>When the male throne is empty, that we pay</l>
              <l>To our high captain's consort honour due.</l>
              <l>If thou hast heard auspicious news, or not,</l>
              <l>That with joy-vouching hope thou lightest up</l>
              <l>The altar fires, I, as a friend, would know,-</l>
              <l>Yet shall thy silence nought unkind be deemed.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Joy's harbinger, be radiant Morning born</l>
              <l>From kindly, mother Night! So runs the saw.</l>
              <l>But thou of joy beyond all hope shalt hear,</l>
              <l>For Priam's city have the Argives won.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>How queen! through unbelief I miss thy word.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Troy is in Argive hands; now speak I plain?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Joy, stealing o'er my heart, calls forth the tear.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>'Tis true, thine eye thy loyalty bewrays.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="14"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Of these great tidings what the certain proof?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Warrant I have; -how not? or Heaven deceives me.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Trusting the suasive augury of dreams?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The fancies of the sleep-bound soul I heed not.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But hath some wingless rumour buoy'd thee up?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou chidest me as were I a young girl.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But since what time was Priam's city spoiled?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>This very night now bringing forth the day.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What messenger could travel with such speed?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hephaestos, a bright flash from Ida sending.</l>
              <l>Hither through swift relays of courier-flame,</l>
              <l>Beacon transmitted beacon. Ida first</l>
              <l>To the Hermæan rock on Lemnos' Isle;</l>
              <l>Thence Athos' summit, dedicate to Zeus,</l>
              <pb n="15"/>
              <l>The third in order, caught the mighty glow.</l>
              <l>Upsoaring, bridging in its might the sea,</l>
              <l>With gathered strength, the onward speeding torch,</l>
              <l>In golden splendour, like another sun,</l>
              <l>Its message to Makistos' watch-tower sends,</l>
              <l>Who, nor delaying, nor by Sleep o'erpowered,</l>
              <l>The courier's duty faithfully discharged.</l>
              <l>The torch, far-gleaming to Euripos' stream,</l>
              <l>Gives signal to Messapios' sentinels.</l>
              <l>Firing of withered heath a giant pile,</l>
              <l>With answering blaze, they pass the message on.</l>
              <l>The stalwart flame, unwearied and undimm'd,</l>
              <l>Like a bright moon, o'erleaps Asopos' plain,</l>
              <l>And wakens, on Cithaeron's lofty crag,</l>
              <l>Another speeder of the fiery post.</l>
              <l>The warder hailing the far-journeying fire,</l>
              <l>Kindles a beacon of surpassing glow;</l>
              <l>Bounded the radiance o'er Gorgopis' lake,</l>
              <l>And reaching Aegiplanctos' mountain peak</l>
              <l>Urged on without delay the fiery chain.</l>
              <l>With vigour unimpaired they onward send,</l>
              <l>Kindled anew, a mighty beard of flame,</l>
              <l>That, flaring from afar, the headland crossed</l>
              <l>†O'erlooking Saron's gulf. Down shooting then,</l>
              <l>The blaze, alighting on Arachnæ's height,</l>
              <l>The city's nearest watch-tower, reached its goal;</l>
              <l>Thence to the roof of Atreus' son this light</l>
              <l>Darted, true scion of Idaian fire.</l>
              <l>Thus in succession, flame awakening flame</l>
              <l>Fulfilled the order of the fiery course:</l>
              <pb n="16"/>
              <l>The first and last are victors in the race.</l>
              <l>Such is the proof, the warrant that I give</l>
              <l>Of tidings sent me by my Lord from Troy.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The gods, O queen, will I invoke hereafter.</l>
              <l>But now I fain would marvel at thy words,</l>
              <l>Heard more at large so thou wouldst speak again.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Troy on this very day th' Achaians hold.</l>
              <l>I ween ill-blending clamour fills the town:</l>
              <l>Pour in one vessel vinegar and oil,</l>
              <l>They will not lovingly consort, I trow;</l>
              <l>So now from captives and from captors rise</l>
              <l>Two voices, telling of their twofold fate.</l>
              <l>For those, flung prostrate on the lifeless forms</l>
              <l>Of husbands and of brothers, children too,</l>
              <l>Prone on their aged sires, lamenting wail;</l>
              <l>While these, night-stragglers after toilsome fight,</l>
              <l>Keen for all viands that the city yields,</l>
              <l>Upon no order standing, but as each</l>
              <l>Hath snatched the lot of fortune, take their fill.</l>
              <l>At length from frost and skiey dews set free,</l>
              <l>They dwell in Ilion's spear-won halls, and sleep</l>
              <l>†The live-long night, unsentinelled like gods.</l>
              <l>If now the tutelary powers they fear,</l>
              <l>Who hold the conquered land, and spare their</l>
              <l>shrines,</l>
              <l>Captors, they shall not captured be in turn.</l>
              <l>But may no greedy passion seize the host</l>
              <pb n="17"/>
              <l>To plunder things unlawful, smit with gain.</l>
              <l>A safe return has yet to be secured,</l>
              <l>And half the double course is yet to run.</l>
              <l>But guilty to the gods if come the host,</l>
              <l>Wakeful may rise the sorrows of the slain</l>
              <l>For vengeance, though no sudden ill befal.</l>
              <l>These words from me, a woman thou hast heard;</l>
              <l>But may the good in overpoise prevail !</l>
              <l>For I of many blessings choose this joy.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Like prudent man well hast thou spoken, lady.</l>
              <l>But I, on hearing of thy certain proofs,</l>
              <l>Forthwith prepare me to salute the gods,</l>
              <l>For no unworthy meed requites our toil.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
          <stage>Exit CLYTEMNESTRA.</stage>
          
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hail, sovereign Zeus, and friendly Night,</l>
              <l>Mistress of mighty glories, hail!</l>
              <l>Thou who o'er Troia's tower-crowned height,</l>
              <l>A snare so closely meshed hast flung,</l>
              <l>That none, or fully grown or young,</l>
              <l>Thraldom's huge drag-net may avail</l>
              <l>To overleap. Vast ruin captures all.</l>
              <l>Great guardian of the guest,</l>
              <l>Thee I adore ;-</l>
              <l>Wrought were those deeds at thy behest:</l>
              <l>The bow thou didst of yore</l>
              <l>'Gainst Alexander strain,</l>
              <l>That nor the destined hour before,</l>
              <l>Nor shooting o'er the stars, in vain</l>
              <l>The shaft might fall.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="18"/>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>"Tis Zeus who smote them, this we may aver,</l>
              <l>For easy 'tis to trace;</l>
              <l>The end he shaped as he decreed.</l>
              <l>Yet gods supernal, some declare,</l>
              <l>To sinful mortals give no heed</l>
              <l>Who trample under foot the grace</l>
              <l>Of sacred things. But such are reprobate ;-</l>
              <l>Kindred they claim with those, in heaven's despite,</l>
              <l>†Who rebel war breathe forth, transgressing right.</l>
              <l>Wealth in excess breeds mischief, and o'erturns</l>
              <l>The balance of the constant mind;</l>
              <l>No bulwark 'gainst destructive fate</l>
              <l>In riches shall that mortal find</l>
              <l>Who Justice' mighty altar rudely spurns.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Frenzy's unhappy suasion, fraught with bane</l>
              <l>To hapless children, sways the will;</l>
              <l>Against the mischief cure is vain;</l>
              <l>Not hidden is the flagrant ill ;-</l>
              <l>Baleful it bursts upon the sight;</l>
              <l>Like spurious coin, his metal base</l>
              <l>Use and the touchstone bring to light,</l>
              <l>Who, boy-like, to a winged bird gives chase,</l>
              <l>And whelms his native soil in hopeless night.</l>
              <l>His orisons tho heavenly powers disclaim,</l>
              <l>But sweep to doom the sinful wight</l>
              <l>Practised in guile;-thus Paris came</l>
              <l>To Atreus' halls;-the friendly board</l>
              <l>He shamed, the consort luring from her lord.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="19"/>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Bequeathing to her people deadly stour</l>
              <l>Of shielded hosts, of spears, and ships' array,</l>
              <l>And Ilion's ruin bearing as her dower,</l>
              <l>She through the portal swiftly took her way,</l>
              <l>Daring what none may dare;-with many a wail,</l>
              <l>The palace seers peal'd forth the tale.</l>
              <l>"Woe for the house, the house and chieftains, woe!</l>
              <l>Woe for the couch, the trace of her once true!"</l>
              <l>Wronged, yet without reproach, in speechless woe</l>
              <l>There stands he, yearning still her form to view</l>
              <l>Lost o'er the far sea-wave: his dreamy pain</l>
              <l>Conjures her phantom in his home to reign.</l>
              <l>He loathes the sculptor's plastic skill</l>
              <l>Which living grace belies;</l>
              <l>Not Aphrodite's self can still</l>
              <l>The hunger of his eyes.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>And dreamy fancies, coinage of the brain,</l>
              <l>Come o'er the troubled heart with vain delight;</l>
              <l>For vain the rapture, the illusion vain,</l>
              <l>When forms beloved in visions of the night,</l>
              <l>With changeful aspect, mock our grasp, and sweep</l>
              <l>On noiseless wing adown the paths of sleep.</l>
              <l>Such sorrows o'er the hearth brood evermore,</l>
              <l>And woes o'ertowering these. The warrior train</l>
              <l>Comrades in danger, steered from Hellas' shore,</l>
              <l>Leaving in Hellas' homes heart-withering pain;</l>
              <pb n="20"/>
              <l>Full many sorrows rankle at the core.</l>
              <l>Those whom he sent each holds in ken,</l>
              <l>But to their homes return</l>
              <l>Armour and in the funeral urn,</l>
              <l>Ashes instead of men.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>For Ares, bartering for gold</l>
              <l>The flesh of men, the scales doth hold</l>
              <l>In battle of the spear.</l>
              <l>From Ilion, back to sorrowing friends,</l>
              <l>Rich dust, fire-purified, he sends,</l>
              <l>Wash'd with full many a tear.</l>
              <l>No living warriors greet them, but instead</l>
              <l>Urns filled with ashes smoothly spread.</l>
              <l>Groaning, each hero's praise they tell;</l>
              <l>How this excelled in martial strife;</l>
              <l>And that in fields of carnage fell,</l>
              <l>Right nobly for another's wife.</l>
              <l>Breathing such murmurs, jealous hate</l>
              <l>Doth on the Atridan champions wait.</l>
              <l>Achaians, cast in fairest mould,</l>
              <l>Ensépulchred 'neath Ilion's wall,</l>
              <l>The foughten shore now firmly hold,</l>
              <l>The hostile sod their pall.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Direful the people's voice, to hate</l>
              <l>Attuned, which worketh soon or late</l>
              <l>As ban of public doom.</l>
              <pb n="21"/>
              <l>Now o'er my spirit anxious fear</l>
              <l>Broodeth, lest tidings I should hear</l>
              <l>That night still shrouds in gloom;</l>
              <l>For blind to deeds of blood the gods are not.</l>
              <l>In Time the swarthy brood of Night</l>
              <l>With slow eclipse reverse his lot,</l>
              <l>Who Fortune reareth in despite</l>
              <l>Of Justice. Reft of succour lies</l>
              <l>The wretch once prone. Excessive praise</l>
              <l>Is bodeful ever; 'gainst men's eyes</l>
              <l>Zeus hurls his blinding rays.</l>
              <l>But may ungrudged success be mine!</l>
              <l>No city-spoiler let me be!</l>
              <l>Nor, subject to another, pine</l>
              <l>Myself in slavery.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">EPODE.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Borne by the joy-announcing flame</l>
              <l>Swift through the town the tidings fly;</l>
              <l>But whether true who may proclaim,</l>
              <l>Or not a heavenly lie?</l>
              <l>For who so childish, so distraught,</l>
              <l>To warm his spirit at the beacon's glow,</l>
              <l>When other news, with evil fraught,</l>
              <l>His joy may change to woe?</l>
              <l>'Tis woman's way the boon, ere seen, to prize;</l>
              <l>Too credulous, her fancy open lies</l>
              <l>To rumour's rapid inroad, but the fame</l>
              <l>Published by women quickly dies.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="22"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Soon shall we know whether the signal fires,</l>
              <l>The swift relays of courier-light be true,</l>
              <l>Or whether, dreamlike, they beguiled our minds</l>
              <l>With grateful splendour; -Yonder, from the coast,</l>
              <l>A herald comes, shaded with laurel boughs;</l>
              <l>While Clay's twin-brother, thirsty Dust, attests</l>
              <l>That neither voiceless, nor of mountain wood</l>
              <l>Kindling the blaze, will he report in smoke;</l>
              <l>No, either will his voice announce more joy,</l>
              <l>Or, but ill-omened words I deprecate.</l>
              <l>Be omens fair with fair assurance crown'd!</l>
              <l>May he who 'gainst the state breathes other prayer,</l>
              <l>First reap the fruit of his malignant thought.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Enter Herald.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh soil of Argos, oh my native land,</l>
              <l>In light of this tenth year to thee I come;</l>
              <l>While many a hope hath snapt, this one still holds,</l>
              <l>For ne'er I counted, dying here, to share</l>
              <l>Beloved sepulture in Argive soil.</l>
              <l>Now hail, O earth, bright sunlight hail, and Zeus,</l>
              <l>Supreme o'er Argos.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Here the Herald salutes the statues of the gods in the <lb/>
            orchestra.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou too, Pythian king,</l>
              <l>With thy fell darts assailing us no more;</l>
              <l>Let it suffice that on Scamander's banks</l>
              <l>Thy mien was hostile; now, Apollo, lord,</l>
              <pb n="23"/>
              <l>Be thou the Saviour,-be the Healer thou!</l>
              <l>Ye Gods of Council, all I now invoke,</l>
              <l>Thee, my protector Hermes, Herald dear,</l>
              <l>Whom Heralds venerate, and Heroes, ye</l>
              <l>Who sent us forth, now kindly welcome back</l>
              <l>The Argive host, poor remnant of the spear.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>He turns to the stage.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hail royal palace! roofs beloved, hail!</l>
              <l>Ye seats august, ye powers that front the sun,</l>
              <l>If e'er of yore, now, with those cheerful eyes</l>
              <l>Receive in state the monarch absent long,</l>
              <l>For he returns bringing in darkness light</l>
              <l>Common to you and all assembled here,</l>
              <l>King Agamemnon. Welcome, as beseems,</l>
              <l>Him who with mattock of avenging Zeus</l>
              <l>Hath Ilion razed, her under-soil uptorn.</l>
              <l>Quenched are the fanes, the altars of the gods,</l>
              <l>And of the land entire the seed is crushed.</l>
              <l>Such yoke round Troy hath Atreus' elder son</l>
              <l>Fastened: and lo! blest by the gods, he comes</l>
              <l>Of living men most worthy of renown.</l>
              <l>Nor Paris now nor his associate town</l>
              <l>Their deed may vaunt as greater than their woe</l>
              <l>Cast in a suit for rapine and for theft,</l>
              <l>His surety forfeit, he to utter doom</l>
              <l>Hath mowed his natal home. Thus Priam's sons</l>
              <l>With twofold forfeit have atoned their crime.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hail, herald of Achaia's host!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>

          
        <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>All hail!</l>
              <l>So please the gods, I grudge not now to die.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Love for thy father-land thy heart hath wrung!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>So wrung that from mine eyes fall tears of joy.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Sweet the heart-sickness that o'ercame you thus.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The key I lack which may thy words unlock.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Smit with desire for those who longed for you.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hath Argos yearned then for the yearning host ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ay, so that oft from darken'd soul I groaned.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Whence this sad gloom, abhorrent to the host?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Silence I long have held bale's safest cure.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>How! Aught didst fear in absence of thy lords?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To die was oft my wish as whilom thine.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="25"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Well ended, all is well. But, in long years,</l>
              <l>Some chances, one might say, fell happily,</l>
              <l>While others adverse were. For who, save gods,</l>
              <l>Lives through the whole of life by grief unscathed ?</l>
              <l>For should I tell of toils, of lodgment rude,</l>
              <l>Infrequent landings, vexed by dangerous surf,</l>
              <l>†What portion of the day exempt from groans?</l>
              <l>Still more abhorrent was our life ashore ;-</l>
              <l>For close to hostile walls our beds were strewn ;</l>
              <l>Dank vapours fell from heaven, while from the earth</l>
              <l>Drizzled the meadow dews,—our raiment's canker,</l>
              <l>Matting, like savage beast's, our shaggy hair.</l>
              <l>Or spake I of bird-killing winter's cold,</l>
              <l>Unbearable, from snows of Ida born ;</l>
              <l>Or summer's heat, when, stretched on noonday couch,</l>
              <l>By breeze unruffled, slept the waveless sea ?</l>
              <l>But why lament these hardships ? Past the toil!</l>
              <l>Past now and gone,-past also for the dead,</l>
              <l>Who ne'er will trouble them again to rise.</l>
              <l>Why call the spectral army-roll? and why,</l>
              <l>Living, bemoan reverses ? Nay, I claim</l>
              <l>With many a farewell to salute mischance.</l>
              <l>For us, the remnant of the Argive host,</l>
              <l>Joy triumphs, nor can Sorrow tilt the scale.</l>
              <l>Winging o'er land and sea our homeward flight.</l>
              <l>We to the sun-light well may make this boast,</l>
              <l>" The Argive host, captors at length of Troy,</l>
              <l>These spoils, an off'ring to Achaia's gods,</l>
              <l>Hang up, bright glory of their ancient shrines."</l>
              <l>Whoso these tidings hears must needs extol</l>
              <pb n="26"/>
              <l>The city and the leaders of the host;</l>
              <l>Also the consummating grace of Zeus</l>
              <l>Due honour shall attain. My tale is told.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ungrudged surrender yield I to thy words.</l>
              <l>Age still is young enough for grateful lore.</l>
              <l>But Atreus' halls and Clytemnestra most</l>
              <l>These news concern ; me also they enrich.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Enter CLYTEMNESTRA.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The shout of jubilee erewhile I raised,</l>
              <l>When first by night the fiery herald came,</l>
              <l>Telling of Ilion captured and o'erthrown.</l>
              <l>Then some one spake and taunting asked," Dost think</l>
              <l>Trusting the beacon-light, that Troy is sacked ?</l>
              <l>'Tis woman's way to be elate of heart."</l>
              <l>By such bold utt'rance was my wit misprised:</l>
              <l>Yet still I sacrificed : and through the town</l>
              <l>With woman's note they tuned the joyous trill,</l>
              <l>Pæans uplifting in the gods' abodes,</l>
              <l>The while they lulled the fragrant incense-flames.</l>
              <l>And now, what need that thou shouldst tell me more ?</l>
              <l>I from the king himself the tale shall hear.</l>
              <l>With honour due, my venerated lord</l>
              <l>To welcome home, myself will hasten : for-</l>
              <l>What sight for woman sweeter than the day</l>
              <l>Which to her spouse, Heaven-shielded from the fight,</l>
              <l>Throws wide the gates? Then hither bid my lord,</l>
              <l>Beloved of Argos, to return with speed.</l>
              <pb n="27"/>
              <l>Arriving, may he find a faithful wife,</l>
              <l>Such as he left her, watch-dog of his house,</l>
              <l>To him devoted, hostile to his foes,</l>
              <l>In all points like herself, no single seal</l>
              <l>Through these long years invaded by her hand.</l>
              <l>Pleasure, or blameful word from other man,</l>
              <l>Foreign to me as dyer's hue to brass.</l>
              <l>A boast like this, fraught as it is with truth,</l>
              <l>The lip misseems not of a high-born dame.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Exit CLYTEMNESTRA.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Behold! The queen herself hath tutored thee;</l>
              <l>Decorous words her clear interpreters.</l>
              <l>But tell me, Herald, touching Menelas,</l>
              <l>Doth he in safety homeward with the host</l>
              <l>Hither return, prince to his country dear ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>False news were I to tell, in flatt'ring terms,</l>
              <l>Not long would friends enjoy the fair deceit.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh, could'st thou speak auspicious words yet true!</l>
              <l>That here they sundered are is all too plain.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The man is vanished from th' Achaian host;</l>
              <l>Himself and galley. No untruth I tell.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Steering ahead from Troy ? or hath a storm,</l>
              <l>A common terror, snatched him from the host?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="28"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Like skilful archer thou hast hit the mark;</l>
              <l>And hast in brief a mighty woe declared.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Say, doth the voice of other mariners</l>
              <l>Report of him as living, or as dead ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Not one so knoweth as to speak his doom,</l>
              <l>Save the bright Sun, feeder of teeming earth.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>How ! Burst the tempest on the naval host</l>
              <l>Through anger of the gods ? say, what the end ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>HERALD</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Auspicious day with ill-announcing tongue</l>
              <l>Beseems not to defile. In weal and woe</l>
              <l>Diverse the honour due unto the gods.</l>
              <l>When messenger, sad-visaged, tidings dire</l>
              <l>Of routed armies to the city bears,</l>
              <l>A common wound inflicting on the state,</l>
              <l>While many men from many homes are banned,</l>
              <l>Smit by the twofold scourge which Ares loves,</l>
              <l>Twin-speared Calamity, a gory pair :—</l>
              <l>Whoso is laden with such woes as these</l>
              <l>The pæan of the Furies well may raise.</l>
              <l>But coming to a town in jubilee,</l>
              <l>Glad messenger of safety and success,</l>
              <l>How shall I tidings mingle fair and foul,</l>
              <pb n="29"/>
              <l>The tale unfolding of the storm that smote</l>
              <l>The Achaian host, not without wrath of Heaven ?</l>
              <l>For fire and ocean, bitter foes of yore,</l>
              <l>Sware true alliance and redeemed their pledge,</l>
              <l>Whelming Achaia's luckless armament.</l>
              <l>Then in the night foul-surging mischiefs rose :</l>
              <l>Beneath the Thracian blasts ship against ship</l>
              <l>Dashed wildly; they, sore-butted by the storm,</l>
              <l>With furious wind and stress of pelting rain,</l>
              <l>Vanished from sight, 'neath whirl of shepherd dire.</l>
              <l>And when uprose the sun's fair light, behold,</l>
              <l>The Ægean sea with flowerage overstrewn,—</l>
              <l>Corpses of Grecian men and wrecks of ships.</l>
              <l>Us, and our vessel with undamaged hull,</l>
              <l>Some god, I ween, (not mortal was the power,)</l>
              <l>Ruling the helm, hath saved, by stealth or prayer.</l>
              <l>But Saviour Fortune lighting on our ship,</l>
              <l>At moorage she nor felt the billows' strain,</l>
              <l>Nor drave against the iron-girded coast.</l>
              <l>Then safe at last, from watery Hades snatch'd,</l>
              <l>In genial daylight, still mistrusting chance,</l>
              <l>With anxious thought o'er this new grief we brooded,—</l>
              <l>Our host sore wearied, and in evil plight.</l>
              <l>And doubtless now, if any still survive,</l>
              <l>They speak of us as dead. Why should they not ?</l>
              <l>As we imagine a like fate for them.</l>
              <l>But may the best befal! For Menelas,</l>
              <l>Foremost and chief, expect him to arrive;</l>
              <l>If any sunbeam knows of him as safe,</l>
              <l>Rejoicing in the light, (through the device</l>
              <pb n="30"/>
              <l>Of Zeus, not willing yet the race to whelm,)</l>
              <l>Good hope there is that he may yet return.</l>
              <l>Hearing this tale, know, thou the truth hast heard.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Who, oh who, with truest aim,</l>
              <l>Did the battle-wedded dame,</l>
              <l>Prize of conflict, Helen name ?</l>
              <l>Was it not one, unseen, in happy hour,</l>
              <l>Guiding his tongue with Fate-presaging power?</l>
              <l>Helen, the captor;-titled fittingly,—</l>
              <l>Captor of ships, of men, of cities, she</l>
              <l>From dainty curtained bower hath fled,</l>
              <l>By Titan zephyr borne along ;</l>
              <l>Straight in her quarrel mustered strong</l>
              <l>The shielded hunters' mighty throng,</l>
              <l>Marshalled for battle;-forth they sped,</l>
              <l>Swift on their track whose viewless oar</l>
              <l>Harbour had found on Simois' leafy shore.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Wrath, with direful issue fraught,</l>
              <l>Thus to hapless Ilion brought</l>
              <l>Dear alliance, dearly bought:</l>
              <l>Requiter of the outraged festal board,</l>
              <l>And of high Zeus, tho hearth's presiding Lord ;</l>
              <l>Late vengeance wreaking on the guilty throng,</l>
              <l>Who carol jubilant tho bridal song,</l>
              <l>Which, fate-impelled, tho bridegroom's kin prolong.</l>
              <l>But aged Priam's city hoar</l>
              <l>A novel hymn doth now intone,</l>
              <l>From many a voice; with mighty groan,</l>
              <pb n="31"/>
              <l>Woe upon Paris' bridal bed</l>
              <l>She utters ;—she who long before</l>
              <l>A dirgeful life, alas ! had led,</l>
              <l>Weeping her sons in wretched slaughter sped.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>So once did wight incautious rear</l>
              <l>A suckling lion, for the breast</l>
              <l>Still yearning, to the house a pest.</l>
              <l>Tame in life's early morning, dear</l>
              <l>To childhood, and by Eld caressed.</l>
              <l>Carried full oft in fondling play,</l>
              <l>Like to a babe in arms he lay;</l>
              <l>The hand with winning glances wooed,</l>
              <l>And, smit with pangs of hunger, fawned for food.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But time the temper doth bewray</l>
              <l>Inherent in his race. Due meed</l>
              <l>Of gentle nurture to repay,</l>
              <l>Rending the flocks with cruel greed,</l>
              <l>Unbidden he prepares the feast,</l>
              <l>And mars with gory stain the halls.</l>
              <l>Resistless, dire, athirst for prey,</l>
              <l>The pest the menial train appals,</l>
              <l>Reared for the house by Heaven, fell Atè's priest.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>So came to Troia's walls, in evil hour,</l>
              <l>Spirit of breathless calm, fair pride</l>
              <l>Of riches, love's soul-piercing flower,</l>
              <l>The eyes' soft dart; but from her course aside</l>
              <pb n="32"/>
              <l>Swerving, to wedlock bitter end she wrought.</l>
              <l>To Priam's offspring came she, mischief fraught,</l>
              <l>Evil companion, bringing evil dower.</l>
              <l>By Zeus escorted, guardian of the guest,</l>
              <l>She sped, dire Fury, bridal pest.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Lives among men this saw, voiced long ago;</l>
              <l>" Success consummate breeds apace,</l>
              <l>Nor childless dies, but to the race</l>
              <l>From prosperous Fortune springeth cureless Woe."</l>
              <l>Apart I hold my solitary creed.</l>
              <l>Prolific truly is the impious deed;</l>
              <l>Like to the evil stock, the evil seed;</l>
              <l>But fate ordains that righteous homes shall aye</l>
              <l>Rejoice in goodly progeny.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE IV.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>†But ancient Arrogance, or soon or late,</l>
              <l>When strikes the hour ordained by Fate,</l>
              <l>Breedeth new Arrogance, which still</l>
              <l>Revels, wild wantoner in human ill;</l>
              <l>And the new birth another brood</l>
              <l>Unhallowed, in the house doth bear ;—</l>
              <l>Gorged Insolence, and, not to be withstood,</l>
              <l>Defiant Boldness, demon unsubdued ;—</l>
              <l>Swart curses twain, their parents' mien that wear.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE IV.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But Justice doth the smoke-begrimèd cell</l>
              <l>Illumine with celestial sheen,</l>
              <pb n="33"/>
              <l>And loves with honest worth to dwell.</l>
              <l>Gold-spangled palaces with hands unclean,</l>
              <l>Forsaking with averted eyes,</l>
              <l>To holy Innocence she flies.</l>
              <l>The power of wealth, if falsely stamped with praise,</l>
              <l>With homage she disdains to recognize,</l>
              <l>And to their fated issue all things sways.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <p>[Enter warriors and captives; at last AGAMEMNON appears, <lb/>
            seated on a chariot, with CASSANDRA at his side; soon after <lb/>
            CLYTEMNESTRA, accompanied by female attendants, issues <lb/>
            from the palace.]</p>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hail, royal lord! Stormer of Ilion, hail!</l>
              <l>Scion of Atreus! How compose my speech,</l>
              <l>How due obeisance render thee,</l>
              <l>Yet neither overshoot the mark, nor fail</l>
              <l>The goal of fitting compliment to reach ?</l>
              <l>For many men, transgressing right, there be</l>
              <l>Semblance who place above reality.</l>
              <l>To him who groans beneath affliction's smart,</l>
              <l>All men have prompt condolence; but the sting</l>
              <l>Of feignèd sorrow reaches not the heart.</l>
              <l>So men with others' joy rejoicing, bring</l>
              <l>Over their visage an enforced smile :</l>
              <l>But the discerning shepherd knows his fleck,</l>
              <l>And his unerring glance detects their guile,</l>
              <l>Who simulating love, with glozing art</l>
              <l>And watery kindness fawn, but inly mock.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>But thou, 0 King, (I speak without disguise,)<note n="33.1">1</note></l>
              <pb n="34"/>
              <l>In Helen's quarrel asking war's array,</l>
              <l>A mien didst wear unseemly in mine eyes,</l>
              <l>Guiding not well the rudder of thy mind,</l>
              <l>Who didst, on death-devoted men, essay</l>
              <l>Courage to urge, by sacrifice.</l>
              <l>But those who have achieved the great emprize,</l>
              <l>Not from the surface of my mind alone,</l>
              <l>I welcome now, with feelings not unkind ;</l>
              <l>And inquest made, in time shall it be known,</l>
              <l>Who of thy citizens at home the while</l>
              <l>Guarded thy state with truth, and who with guile.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <p>speaking from the chariot.</p>
            <lg>
              <l>First Argos and her tutelary gods,</l>
              <l>Who with me wrought to compass my return,</l>
              <l>And visit Priam's town with vengeance due,</l>
              <l>Justly I hail. For in this cause the gods,</l>
              <l>Swayed by no hearsay, in the bloody urn</l>
              <l>Without dissentient voice the pebbles cast,</l>
              <l>Sealing the doom of Ilion and her sons.</l>
              <l>But to the rival urn, by no hand filled,</l>
              <l>Hope only came. Smoke still uprising marks</l>
              <l>The captured city ; Atè's incense-fires</l>
              <l>Are living still, but, dying as they die,</l>
              <l>The ash sends upward costly fumes of wealth.</l>
              <l>Wherefore 'tis meet to render to the gods</l>
              <l>Memorial thanks; since round them we have east</l>
              <l>Our vengeful toils, and in a woman's cause</l>
              <l>The Argive monster, offspring of the horse,</l>
              <l>Host shield-accoutred, made its deadly leap,</l>
              <l>And Priam's city levelled to the dust,</l>
              <pb n="35"/>
              <l>What time the Pleiades in ocean waned;</l>
              <l>So, bounding o'er the towers, of princely blood</l>
              <l>The raw-devouring lion lapped his fill.</l>
              <l>This lengthened prelude to the gods! and now</l>
              <l>Weighing the judgment ye erewhile expressed,</l>
              <l>I say the same, and am with you agreed.</l>
              <l>To few is it congenial, envy-free,</l>
              <l>To venerate the friend whom Fortune crowns.</l>
              <l>The jealous poison, lodged within the heart,</l>
              <l>Tortures with twofold pang whom it infects ;</l>
              <l>By his own griefs oppressed, the envious man</l>
              <l>Groans also to behold another's joy.</l>
              <l>Out of my proof I speak, for, well I wot,</l>
              <l>Who friendship most pretended, only were</l>
              <l>Its mirrored image, shadow of a shade.</l>
              <l>None but Odysseus, who unwilling sailed,</l>
              <l>Once harnessed, was my trusty yoke-fellow;</l>
              <l>This I affirm, be he alive or dead.</l>
              <l>But for the rest, what to the state pertains,</l>
              <l>And to the gods, a full assembly called,</l>
              <l>We'll weigh in free debate. Counsel we need.</l>
              <l>That where the state is sound, we keep it so;</l>
              <l>But where disease the healer's art requires,</l>
              <l>By kind excision, or by cautery,</l>
              <l>We shall attempt to remedy the harm.</l>
              <l>Now to my palace and my household hearth</l>
              <l>Returning, first will I the gods salute,</l>
              <l>Who forward sped me, and who lead me home;</l>
              <l>Since victory so far hath followed me,</l>
              <l>Here may she henceforth stedfastly abide!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
     
          <pb n="36"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Men of our city, Argive elders here,</l>
              <l>I shame not in your presence to avow</l>
              <l>My wifely temper ; bashful Fear in time</l>
              <l>From mortals dieth : not by others taught,</l>
              <l>But from myself, the wretched life I'll tell</l>
              <l>'Twas mine to lead while this man was at Troy.</l>
              <l>First, for a woman severed from her mate,</l>
              <l>To sit forlorn at home is grievous woe,</l>
              <l>Hearing malignant murmurs manifold.</l>
              <l>One courier comes, another in his train</l>
              <l>Worse tidings brings to echo through the house ;</l>
              <l>And as for wounds, had my dear lord received</l>
              <l>As many as report kept pouring in,</l>
              <l>A net methinks had not been more transpierced.</l>
              <l>Or had he died oft as reported then,</l>
              <l>A second triple-bodied Geryon,<ref n="36.1">1</ref></l>
              <l>†A threefold cloak of earth he must have donned,<ref n="36.2">2</ref></l>
              <l>Enduring death in every form he wore.</l>
              <l>Thus harassed by these ever-rife reports,</l>
              <l>Full often from my neck have forceful hands</l>
              <l>Seized and untied the beam-suspended noose.</l>
              <l>And for this cause our son, pledge of our troth,</l>
              <l>Of mine and thine, stands not beside me now,</l>
              <l>As stand he should, Orestes. Marvel not,</l>
              <pb n="37"/>
              <l>For him thy trusty spear-guest nourisheth ; <ref n="37.1">1</ref></l>
              <l>Strophius, the Phocian, who hath me forewarned</l>
              <l>Of twofold peril, thine 'neath Ilion's wall,</l>
              <l>And next lest clamour-fostered Anarchy</l>
              <l>Hazard the plot, for 'tis with men inborn</l>
              <l>To trample further him already down.</l>
              <l>This pretext, trust me, carries no deceit.</l>
              <l>But for myself the gushing founts of grief</l>
              <l>Are all dried up, no single tear is left;</l>
              <l>Sore with late watching are my weary eyes,</l>
              <l>Weeping the fiery beacons set for thee</l>
              <l>Neglected ever. Often from my dreams</l>
              <l>Was I awakened by the tiny hum</l>
              <l>Of buzzing gnat, seeing, endured by thee,</l>
              <l>More woes than could have filled mine hour of sleep.</l>
              <l>These sorrows past, now with a heart unwrung</l>
              <l>I hail my husband, watchdog of the fold,</l>
              <l>Sure forestay of the ship; of lofty roof</l>
              <l>Pillar firm based ; Sire's sole-begotten child ;</l>
              <l>Land beyond hope looming to mariners;</l>
              <l>Day after storm most brilliant to behold;</l>
              <l>To thirsty wayfarer clear gushing spring.</l>
              <l>Sooth, sweet it is to 'scape from harsh constraint;</l>
              <l>With such addresses do I honour him.</l>
              <l>Let Envy stand aloof! for we have borne</l>
              <l>Ere this full many a woe. Now dear my lord</l>
              <l>Come from thy car; but on the ground, 0 King,</l>
              <pb n="38"/>
              <l>Plant not the foot that trampled Ilion.</l>
              <l>Maidens, why tarry ye, whose duty 'tis</l>
              <l>With carpets to bespread his stepping-floor ?</l>
              <l>Swift, purple-strew his passage to a home</l>
              <l>Unlooked for, e'en as Justice may conduct;</l>
              <l>What further she decreeth with the gods,</l>
              <l>Thought, not by sleep o'ermastered, shall dispose.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="footnotes">
            <note n="36.1">* Geryon, a monster represented by the poets as having <lb/>three bodies and three heads, and located by them in the <lb/>fabulous island of Erytheia. The capture of the oxen of <lb/>Geryon was one of the twelve labours of Heracles.</note>
            <note n="36.2">‡ [<quote xml:lang="grc">Πολλὴν ἄνωθεν, τὴν κάτω γὰρ οὐ λέγω</quote>.]</note>
            <note n="36.3">I agree with those critics who reject this line as spurious.</note>
            <note n="37.1">* Spear-guest. The Greek word <quote xml:lang="grc">δορύξενος</quote> is explained <lb/>by Plutarch, whom Bishop Thirlwall follows, as expressing <lb/>the relation established when a prisoner of war dismissed on <lb/>parole has honourably paid his ransom.</note>
          </div>
<sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Daughter of Leda! Guardian of my home!</l>
              <l>Such as my absence was, is now thy speech,</l>
              <l>Drawn out to ample length. With better grace</l>
              <l>My praise had come from others than from thee.</l>
              <l>And for the rest, seek not in woman's guise</l>
              <l>To pamper me, nor, gaping forth loud cries,</l>
              <l>Bow down to me, as to barbaric wight.</l>
              <l>Make not my path with tapestries bestrewn</l>
              <l>A mark for envy. To the gods belong</l>
              <l>Such signal honours ; but for mortal man,</l>
              <l>On bright-hued broidery to plant his foot,</l>
              <l>I own it, is to me not free from dread ;</l>
              <l>As mortal honour me, but not as god;</l>
              <l>Without foot-carpeting or gorgeous web,</l>
              <l>Glory resounds ; a constant mind to keep</l>
              <l>Is Heaven's best gift; him only call we blest</l>
              <l>Who ends in fair prosperity his days.</l>
              <l>If thus I bear myself I need not fear.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Against my settled purpose speak not thus.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="39"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Deem not my sober purpose I will mar.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Haply thou thus to act hast vowed in fear.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Final and sure my word as man e'er spake.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What, thinkest thou, had Priam done if victor ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Purples, I ween, he verily had trod.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then stand not thou in fear of human blame.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet hath the people's rumour mighty power.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Life envy-free is life unenviable.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>'Tis not for woman to be fond of strife.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But it becomes the fortunate to yield.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Does conquest in this struggle rate so high ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="40"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yield thee; thy will bend willingly to mine.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>If thou wilt have it so, let one with speed</l>
              <l>These buskins loosen, vassals of the foot;</l>
              <l>Lest, if with them sea-tinctured robes I tread,</l>
              <l>Some jealous eye of gods smite me from far.</l>
              <l>For much it shameth me, with wanton feet</l>
              <l>To mar this wealth of silver-purchased web.</l>
              <l>Of this enough. This stranger damsel now</l>
              <l>Kindly receive. Zeus, with propitious eye,</l>
              <l>Beholds the victor's sway with mercy crowned.</l>
              <l>For willingly none bears the captive yoke;</l>
              <l>But she, the chosen flower of many a spoil,</l>
              <l>Fair present from the host, hath followed me.</l>
              <l>But since herein I yield me to thy will,</l>
              <l>Treading on purple to my halls I go.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>A sea there is (which who may drain ?) that breeds</l>
              <l>Abundant purple, fresh from many a shell,</l>
              <l>Precious as silver, brilliant dye of robes,</l>
              <l>Whereof, through favour of the gods, these halls</l>
              <l>May boast, O King, a store right plentiful;</l>
              <l>And poverty is stranger to our house</l>
              <l>Trampling of many garments had I vowed,</l>
              <l>Had thus the oracles our house enjoined,</l>
              <l>Ransom devising for this precious life.</l>
              <l>For while the root lives on, the leafage spreads,</l>
              <pb n="41"/>
              <l>Screening the mansion from the dog-star's ray.</l>
              <l>So now, returning to thy household hearth,</l>
              <l>As warmth in winter doth thy presence show.</l>
              <l>And when Zeus breweth from the acrid grape</l>
              <l>Rich wine, then coolness thro' the halls is shed,</l>
              <l>Where, crowner of the home, the husband dwells.</l>
              <l>Zeus, Zeus, all-crowner, my petitions crown :</l>
              <l>Thine be the care of that which crown thou wilt.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Exeunt CLYTEMNESTRA and AGAMEMNON into the palace.</stage>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Whence this dread portent, that untired</l>
              <l>Before my bodeful spirit floats ?</l>
              <l>Wherefore, unbidden and unhired,</l>
              <l>Waken these dark prophetic notes?</l>
              <l>Why sits not on my bosom's throne</l>
              <l>The direful presage to disown</l>
              <l>As riddling dream, assurance strong?</l>
              <l>Time's youth hath flown</l>
              <l>Since the stern-cables from the boats</l>
              <l>Were flung, what time the ship-borne host</l>
              <l>Marched on to Ilion from the sandy coast.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>After long absence their return</l>
              <l>With self-informing eyes I learn ;</l>
              <l>Yet in its depths my soul, self-taught,</l>
              <l>Chanteth Erinys' lyreless strains ;</l>
              <l>My hopes, of courage reft, depart;</l>
              <l>Not vainly throb my inmost reins ;</l>
              <pb n="42"/>
              <l>Whirleth on eddies of dark thought</l>
              <l>My bodeful heart;</l>
              <l>Yet, against hope, the gods I pray,</l>
              <l>That, false to augury, my lay</l>
              <l>Futile may fall, with vain foreboding fraught.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Never will perfect health confess</l>
              <l>Her limit sated ; though disease,</l>
              <l>Neighbour, with party-wall, against her press.</l>
              <l>Sailing with prosperous course elate,</l>
              <l>Strikes on the hidden reef man's proud estate.</l>
              <l>Then if reluctant Fear, with well-poised sling,</l>
              <l>His bales doth into ocean fling,</l>
              <l>Riseth once more the bark ; and though</l>
              <l>With evil freighted to the full,</l>
              <l>Floateth secure the lightened hull.</l>
              <l>So likewise, gift of ample worth</l>
              <l>From Zeus, the year's increase,</l>
              <l>Whose teeming harvests in the furrows grow,</l>
              <l>Quells the disease of dearth.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But when on earth the crimson gore</l>
              <l>Of man hath fallen, never more</l>
              <l>May charm or spell the vanished life evoke;</l>
              <l>Hence he of old, whose mystic lore</l>
              <l>Was skilled the dead from Hades to restore,</l>
              <l>Fell, blasted by the Thunderer's warning stroke.</l>
              <l>†Now did not Fate—a heaven-sent Fate—</l>
              <l>Baffle my impulse, ere too late,</l>
              <pb n="43"/>
              <l>Leaving behind the lagging tongue,</l>
              <l>My heart its bodeful strain had sung.</l>
              <l>But now it raves; no cheering rays</l>
              <l>My anguished spirit knows,</l>
              <l>And hopeless to unravel Fate's dark maze</l>
              <l>With fiery ardour glows.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Enter CLYTEMNESTRA, stepping hastily out of the palace.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Come thou too in, Cassandra, thee I mean;</l>
              <l>For not in wrath Zeus placed thee in our house</l>
              <l>A sharer in our lustral rites to stand,</l>
              <l>With many slaves beside his household altar.</l>
              <l>Now from this car descend; be not too proud,</l>
              <l>For e'en Alcmena's son,—so runs the tale,—</l>
              <l>Sold as a slave, endured the forceful yoke ;</l>
              <l>But if such fate befal thee, great the boon</l>
              <l>Heirs of ancestral wealth to own as lords ;</l>
              <l>For upstarts, beyond hope who fortune reap,—</l>
              <l>These reckless are and cruel to their slaves.</l>
              <l>From us thou hast what usuage warranteth.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thee in clear words she hath addressed, and thou,</l>
              <l>Meshed as thou art within the toils of Fate,</l>
              <l>Yield if thou canst; mayhap thou wilt not yield.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Nay, an she be not, swallow-like, possessed</l>
              <l>Of an unknown, barbaric tongue, my words,</l>
              <l>Reaching her mind, must move her to comply.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="44"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Follow! She counsels for thy need the best:</l>
              <l>Be thou persuaded;—leave thy chariot-seat.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>No leisure have I here before the gates</l>
              <l>To linger; for, beside the central hearth,</l>
              <l>The victims wait the sacrificial fire ;</l>
              <l>A favour that our fondest hope transcends.</l>
              <l>But thou, if aught wilt do of what I say,</l>
              <l>Make no delay; but if, of sense bereft,</l>
              <l>Thou canst not catch the meaning of my words,</l>
              <l>In lieu of voice, speak with barbarian hand.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>A clear interpreter the stranger needs :</l>
              <l>Distraught she seems, like creature newly caught.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Nay, she is mad ; to her distempered thoughts</l>
              <l>She listens ; from a newly-captured town</l>
              <l>She cometh here, nor knows the yoke to bear,</l>
              <l>Till quelled in foam the passion of her blood.</l>
              <l>But words I'll waste no more, thus to be scorned.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But I, by pity moved, will not be wroth ;</l>
              <l>Come, wretched sufferer, this car forsake ;</l>
              <l>To Fortune yielding, hansel this new yoke.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah mo ! alas ! Gods, Earth!</l>
              <l>Apollo, O Apollo!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="45"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Why raise for Loxias these cries of bale ?</l>
              <l>Not he the god to need the mourner's wail.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah me ! alas ! Gods, Earth!</l>
              <l>Apollo, O Apollo!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Once more she calleth with ill-omened cry,</l>
              <l>The god who hath no part in misery.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Apollo, O Apollo!</l>
              <l>Thou way-god! my destroyer!</l>
              <l>Once more thou hast destroyed me utterly.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>She seems about to augur her own ills ;</l>
              <l>Heaven's breathing e'en in bonds her spirit fills.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Apollo, O Apollo!</l>
              <l>Thou way-god! my destroyer !</l>
              <l>Ah, whither hast thou led me ? to what roof?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To the Atreidan; an thou dost not know</l>
              <l>I tell thee; thou'lt not say it is not so.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="46"/>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah! Ah!</l>
              <l>A heaven-detested house, whose walls of yore</l>
              <l>Halters have seen, and streams of kindred gore;</l>
              <l>A human shambles with blood-reeking floor.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Keen scented seems the stranger, like a hound ;</l>
              <l>Ay, and the blood she's tracking will be found.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah! Ah!</l>
              <l>Lo ! witnesses trust-worthy ! Vouchers dire!</l>
              <l>These babes, who weep their death-wound, faith inspire,</l>
              <l>Their roasted members eaten by their sire!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy fame oracular hath reached our ear;</l>
              <l>But certes seek we now no prophet here.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE IV.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Alas! ye gods!</l>
              <l>What is she plotting? what new blow ?</l>
              <l>A mighty mischief plots she 'neath this roof;</l>
              <l>An unimaginable cureless woe,</l>
              <l>Unbearable to friends. Help stands aloof.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Dark are these oracles ; the first I know ;</l>
              <l>For, them the city voucheth wholly true.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE IV.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah wretched one!</l>
              <l>The deed wilt consummate? With guile</l>
              <pb n="47"/>
              <l>Wilt in the bath thy wedded consort cheer?</l>
              <l>How speak the issue ? Soon it will be here ;—</l>
              <l>Hand after hand is lifted. Woe the while !</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I comprehend her not; this mystic lore,</l>
              <l>These blear-eyed oracles perplex me sore.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE V.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe! woe! Look! look! What see I there?</l>
              <l>Is it, ye gods, a net of hell ?</l>
              <l>The wife herself, joint-slayer, is the snare.</l>
              <l>Now o'er the accursèd rite</l>
              <l>Let the dread brood of Night,</l>
              <l>Unglutted with the race, their chorus swell!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE VI.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What Fury 'gainst this house doth summon ? What,</l>
              <l>The shriek to raise ? Such utt’rance cheers me not.</l>
              <l>Pallid through every vein</l>
              <l>Blood to my heart doth run,</l>
              <l>Which to the battle-slain</l>
              <l>Quencheth life's sun ;</l>
              <l>But Atè comes amain.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE V.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hold! hold ! Woe! woe! The heifer there</l>
              <l>Keep from the bull. In meshes fell</l>
              <l>†Of black-woofed garb entangled,-guileful snare,-</l>
              <l>Catching,—she smites him dead;-</l>
              <l>Prone in his watery bed</l>
              <l>He falls. The laver’s guileful doom I tell.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="48"/>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. ANTISTROPHE VI.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I boast not to be skilled in auguries,</l>
              <l>Yet mischief here I cannot but surmise.</l>
              <l>Through spells, say, if ye know,</l>
              <l>To mortals here below,</l>
              <l>What grateful cheer is sent ?</l>
              <l>Their wordy arts from human woe</l>
              <l>Breed dark presentiment.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE VII.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe! woe! my wretched ill-starred lot!</l>
              <l>Wailing another's fate mine own I mourn ;</l>
              <l>Why hast thou led me hither, all forlorn,</l>
              <l>Unless with thee to perish ? Wherefore not ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE VIII.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou'rt frenzied, by some god possest,</l>
              <l>And tuneless quirest forth thy doom,</l>
              <l>Like nightingale, with dusky plume</l>
              <l>Sateless of song. From heart opprest,</l>
              <l>Ceaseless her Itys, Itys, flows,<ref n="48.1">1</ref></l>
              <l>Her life bewailing, rich alone in woes.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE VII.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe ! woe ! Clear-voicèd bird, arrayed</l>
              <l>In plumed shape, by powers divine ;</l>
              <pb n="49"/>
              <l>Sweet life, unmarred by tears, is thine :</l>
              <l>But me awaits the double-edged blade.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. ANTISTROPHE VIII.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Whence hast thou these prophetic throes,</l>
              <l>Rushing athwart thy soul, in vain ?</l>
              <l>Why body forth in dismal strain,</l>
              <l>Blent with shrill cries, these direful woes ?</l>
              <l>Whence cometh thus to vex thy soul</l>
              <l>Of prophecy the dark, ill-omened goal ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="footnotes">
            <note n="48.1">* In the Odyssey (xix. 518) Penelope compares herself to <lb/>Pandareos’ child, the sylvan nightingale which, in the open­<lb/>ing spring, perched amid the dense foliage of the trees, <lb/>warbles beautifully, with frequent change of key, lamenting <lb/>her boy, her beloved Itylos, son of King Zethus, whom, <lb/>through insensate folly, she had slain. This is the oldest <lb/>form of the legend.</note>
          </div>
<sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Daughter of Leda! Guardian of my home!</l>
              <l>Such as my absence was, is now thy speech,</l>
              <l>Drawn out to ample length. With better grace</l>
              <l>My praise had come from others than from thee.</l>
              <l>And for the rest, seek not in woman's guise</l>
              <l>To pamper me, nor, gaping forth loud cries,</l>
              <l>Bow down to me, as to barbaric wight.</l>
              <l>Make not my path with tapestries bestrewn</l>
              <l>A mark for envy. To the gods belong</l>
              <l>Such signal honours ; but for mortal man,</l>
              <l>On bright-hued broidery to plant his foot,</l>
              <l>I own it, is to me not free from dread ;</l>
              <l>As mortal honour me, but not as god;</l>
              <l>Without foot-carpeting or gorgeous web,</l>
              <l>Glory resounds ; a constant mind to keep</l>
              <l>Is Heaven's best gift; him only call we blest</l>
              <l>Who ends in fair prosperity his days.</l>
              <l>If thus I bear myself I need not fear.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Against my settled purpose speak not thus.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="39"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Deem not my sober purpose I will mar.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Haply thou thus to act hast vowed in fear.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Final and sure my word as man e'er spake.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What, thinkest thou, had Priam done if victor ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Purples, I ween, he verily had trod.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Then stand not thou in fear of human blame.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet hath the people's rumour mighty power.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Life envy-free is life unenviable.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>'Tis not for woman to be fond of strife.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But it becomes the fortunate to yield.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Does conquest in this struggle rate so high ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="40"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yield thee; thy will bend willingly to mine.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>If thou wilt have it so, let one with speed</l>
              <l>These buskins loosen, vassals of the foot;</l>
              <l>Lest, if with them sea-tinctured robes I tread,</l>
              <l>Some jealous eye of gods smite me from far.</l>
              <l>For much it shameth me, with wanton feet</l>
              <l>To mar this wealth of silver-purchased web.</l>
              <l>Of this enough. This stranger damsel now</l>
              <l>Kindly receive. Zeus, with propitious eye,</l>
              <l>Beholds the victor's sway with mercy crowned.</l>
              <l>For willingly none bears the captive yoke;</l>
              <l>But she, the chosen flower of many a spoil,</l>
              <l>Fair present from the host, hath followed me.</l>
              <l>But since herein I yield me to thy will,</l>
              <l>Treading on purple to my halls I go.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>A sea there is (which who may drain ?) that breeds</l>
              <l>Abundant purple, fresh from many a shell,</l>
              <l>Precious as silver, brilliant dye of robes,</l>
              <l>Whereof, through favour of the gods, these halls</l>
              <l>May boast, O King, a store right plentiful;</l>
              <l>And poverty is stranger to our house</l>
              <l>Trampling of many garments had I vowed,</l>
              <l>Had thus the oracles our house enjoined,</l>
              <l>Ransom devising for this precious life.</l>
              <l>For while the root lives on, the leafage spreads,</l>
              <pb n="41"/>
              <l>Screening the mansion from the dog-star's ray.</l>
              <l>So now, returning to thy household hearth,</l>
              <l>As warmth in winter doth thy presence show.</l>
              <l>And when Zeus breweth from the acrid grape</l>
              <l>Rich wine, then coolness thro' the halls is shed,</l>
              <l>Where, crowner of the home, the husband dwells.</l>
              <l>Zeus, Zeus, all-crowner, my petitions crown :</l>
              <l>Thine be the care of that which crown thou wilt.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Exeunt CLYTEMNESTRA and AGAMEMNON into the palace.</stage>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Whence this dread portent, that untired</l>
              <l>Before my bodeful spirit floats ?</l>
              <l>Wherefore, unbidden and unhired,</l>
              <l>Waken these dark prophetic notes?</l>
              <l>Why sits not on my bosom's throne</l>
              <l>The direful presage to disown</l>
              <l>As riddling dream, assurance strong?</l>
              <l>Time's youth hath flown</l>
              <l>Since the stern-cables from the boats</l>
              <l>Were flung, what time the ship-borne host</l>
              <l>Marched on to Ilion from the sandy coast.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>After long absence their return</l>
              <l>With self-informing eyes I learn ;</l>
              <l>Yet in its depths my soul, self-taught,</l>
              <l>Chanteth Erinys' lyreless strains ;</l>
              <l>My hopes, of courage reft, depart;</l>
              <l>Not vainly throb my inmost reins ;</l>
              <pb n="42"/>
              <l>Whirleth on eddies of dark thought</l>
              <l>My bodeful heart;</l>
              <l>Yet, against hope, the gods I pray,</l>
              <l>That, false to augury, my lay</l>
              <l>Futile may fall, with vain foreboding fraught.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Never will perfect health confess</l>
              <l>Her limit sated ; though disease,</l>
              <l>Neighbour, with party-wall, against her press.</l>
              <l>Sailing with prosperous course elate,</l>
              <l>Strikes on the hidden reef man's proud estate.</l>
              <l>Then if reluctant Fear, with well-poised sling,</l>
              <l>His bales doth into ocean fling,</l>
              <l>Riseth once more the bark ; and though</l>
              <l>With evil freighted to the full,</l>
              <l>Floateth secure the lightened hull.</l>
              <l>So likewise, gift of ample worth</l>
              <l>From Zeus, the year's increase,</l>
              <l>Whose teeming harvests in the furrows grow,</l>
              <l>Quells the disease of dearth.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But when on earth the crimson gore</l>
              <l>Of man hath fallen, never more</l>
              <l>May charm or spell the vanished life evoke;</l>
              <l>Hence he of old, whose mystic lore</l>
              <l>Was skilled the dead from Hades to restore,</l>
              <l>Fell, blasted by the Thunderer's warning stroke.</l>
              <l>†Now did not Fate—a heaven-sent Fate—</l>
              <l>Baffle my impulse, ere too late,</l>
              <pb n="43"/>
              <l>Leaving behind the lagging tongue,</l>
              <l>My heart its bodeful strain had sung.</l>
              <l>But now it raves; no cheering rays</l>
              <l>My anguished spirit knows,</l>
              <l>And hopeless to unravel Fate's dark maze</l>
              <l>With fiery ardour glows.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Enter CLYTEMNESTRA, stepping hastily out of the palace.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Come thou too in, Cassandra, thee I mean;</l>
              <l>For not in wrath Zeus placed thee in our house</l>
              <l>A sharer in our lustral rites to stand,</l>
              <l>With many slaves beside his household altar.</l>
              <l>Now from this car descend; be not too proud,</l>
              <l>For e'en Alcmena's son,—so runs the tale,—</l>
              <l>Sold as a slave, endured the forceful yoke ;</l>
              <l>But if such fate befal thee, great the boon</l>
              <l>Heirs of ancestral wealth to own as lords ;</l>
              <l>For upstarts, beyond hope who fortune reap,—</l>
              <l>These reckless are and cruel to their slaves.</l>
              <l>From us thou hast what usuage warranteth.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thee in clear words she hath addressed, and thou,</l>
              <l>Meshed as thou art within the toils of Fate,</l>
              <l>Yield if thou canst; mayhap thou wilt not yield.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Nay, an she be not, swallow-like, possessed</l>
              <l>Of an unknown, barbaric tongue, my words,</l>
              <l>Reaching her mind, must move her to comply.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="44"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Follow! She counsels for thy need the best:</l>
              <l>Be thou persuaded;—leave thy chariot-seat.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>No leisure have I here before the gates</l>
              <l>To linger; for, beside the central hearth,</l>
              <l>The victims wait the sacrificial fire ;</l>
              <l>A favour that our fondest hope transcends.</l>
              <l>But thou, if aught wilt do of what I say,</l>
              <l>Make no delay; but if, of sense bereft,</l>
              <l>Thou canst not catch the meaning of my words,</l>
              <l>In lieu of voice, speak with barbarian hand.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>A clear interpreter the stranger needs :</l>
              <l>Distraught she seems, like creature newly caught.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Nay, she is mad ; to her distempered thoughts</l>
              <l>She listens ; from a newly-captured town</l>
              <l>She cometh here, nor knows the yoke to bear,</l>
              <l>Till quelled in foam the passion of her blood.</l>
              <l>But words I'll waste no more, thus to be scorned.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But I, by pity moved, will not be wroth ;</l>
              <l>Come, wretched sufferer, this car forsake ;</l>
              <l>To Fortune yielding, hansel this new yoke.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah mo ! alas ! Gods, Earth!</l>
              <l>Apollo, O Apollo!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="45"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Why raise for Loxias these cries of bale ?</l>
              <l>Not he the god to need the mourner's wail.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah me ! alas ! Gods, Earth!</l>
              <l>Apollo, O Apollo!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Once more she calleth with ill-omened cry,</l>
              <l>The god who hath no part in misery.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Apollo, O Apollo!</l>
              <l>Thou way-god! my destroyer!</l>
              <l>Once more thou hast destroyed me utterly.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>She seems about to augur her own ills ;</l>
              <l>Heaven's breathing e'en in bonds her spirit fills.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Apollo, O Apollo!</l>
              <l>Thou way-god! my destroyer !</l>
              <l>Ah, whither hast thou led me ? to what roof?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To the Atreidan; an thou dost not know</l>
              <l>I tell thee; thou'lt not say it is not so.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="46"/>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah! Ah!</l>
              <l>A heaven-detested house, whose walls of yore</l>
              <l>Halters have seen, and streams of kindred gore;</l>
              <l>A human shambles with blood-reeking floor.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Keen scented seems the stranger, like a hound ;</l>
              <l>Ay, and the blood she's tracking will be found.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah! Ah!</l>
              <l>Lo ! witnesses trust-worthy ! Vouchers dire!</l>
              <l>These babes, who weep their death-wound, faith inspire,</l>
              <l>Their roasted members eaten by their sire!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thy fame oracular hath reached our ear;</l>
              <l>But certes seek we now no prophet here.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE IV.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Alas! ye gods!</l>
              <l>What is she plotting? what new blow ?</l>
              <l>A mighty mischief plots she 'neath this roof;</l>
              <l>An unimaginable cureless woe,</l>
              <l>Unbearable to friends. Help stands aloof.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Dark are these oracles ; the first I know ;</l>
              <l>For, them the city voucheth wholly true.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE IV.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah wretched one!</l>
              <l>The deed wilt consummate? With guile</l>
              <pb n="47"/>
              <l>Wilt in the bath thy wedded consort cheer?</l>
              <l>How speak the issue ? Soon it will be here ;—</l>
              <l>Hand after hand is lifted. Woe the while !</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I comprehend her not; this mystic lore,</l>
              <l>These blear-eyed oracles perplex me sore.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE V.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe! woe! Look! look! What see I there?</l>
              <l>Is it, ye gods, a net of hell ?</l>
              <l>The wife herself, joint-slayer, is the snare.</l>
              <l>Now o'er the accursèd rite</l>
              <l>Let the dread brood of Night,</l>
              <l>Unglutted with the race, their chorus swell!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE VI.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What Fury 'gainst this house doth summon ? What,</l>
              <l>The shriek to raise ? Such utt’rance cheers me not.</l>
              <l>Pallid through every vein</l>
              <l>Blood to my heart doth run,</l>
              <l>Which to the battle-slain</l>
              <l>Quencheth life's sun ;</l>
              <l>But Atè comes amain.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE V.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hold! hold ! Woe! woe! The heifer there</l>
              <l>Keep from the bull. In meshes fell</l>
              <l>†Of black-woofed garb entangled,-guileful snare,-</l>
              <l>Catching,—she smites him dead;-</l>
              <l>Prone in his watery bed</l>
              <l>He falls. The laver’s guileful doom I tell.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="48"/>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. ANTISTROPHE VI.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I boast not to be skilled in auguries,</l>
              <l>Yet mischief here I cannot but surmise.</l>
              <l>Through spells, say, if ye know,</l>
              <l>To mortals here below,</l>
              <l>What grateful cheer is sent ?</l>
              <l>Their wordy arts from human woe</l>
              <l>Breed dark presentiment.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE VII.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe! woe! my wretched ill-starred lot!</l>
              <l>Wailing another's fate mine own I mourn ;</l>
              <l>Why hast thou led me hither, all forlorn,</l>
              <l>Unless with thee to perish ? Wherefore not ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE VIII.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thou'rt frenzied, by some god possest,</l>
              <l>And tuneless quirest forth thy doom,</l>
              <l>Like nightingale, with dusky plume</l>
              <l>Sateless of song. From heart opprest,</l>
              <l>Ceaseless her Itys, Itys, flows,<ref n="48.1">1</ref></l>
              <l>Her life bewailing, rich alone in woes.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE VII.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe ! woe ! Clear-voicèd bird, arrayed</l>
              <l>In plumed shape, by powers divine ;</l>
              <pb n="49"/>
              <l>Sweet life, unmarred by tears, is thine :</l>
              <l>But me awaits the double-edged blade.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. ANTISTROPHE VIII.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Whence hast thou these prophetic throes,</l>
              <l>Rushing athwart thy soul, in vain ?</l>
              <l>Why body forth in dismal strain,</l>
              <l>Blent with shrill cries, these direful woes ?</l>
              <l>Whence cometh thus to vex thy soul</l>
              <l>Of prophecy the dark, ill-omened goal ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="footnotes">
            <note n="48.1">* In the Odyssey (xix. 518) Penelope compares herself to <lb/>Pandareos’ child, the sylvan nightingale which, in the open­<lb/>ing spring, perched amid the dense foliage of the trees, <lb/>warbles beautifully, with frequent change of key, lamenting <lb/>her boy, her beloved Itylos, son of King Zethus, whom, <lb/>through insensate folly, she had slain. This is the oldest <lb/>form of the legend.</note>
          </div>
 <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. STROPHE IX.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh, nuptial rite, oh, nuptial rite,</l>
              <l>Of Paris, fraught with doom !</l>
              <l>Scamander ! whence my fathers drank,</l>
              <l>Nourished of yore upon thy bank,</l>
              <l>I throve in youthful bloom.</l>
              <l>Me now Cocytos and the streams of night</l>
              <l>To augur on their dismal shores invite.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE X.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What thought hast uttered all too clear?</l>
              <l>An infant might interpret here.</l>
              <l>Smitten within am I with gory sting,</l>
              <l>The while thy bird-like cry to hear</l>
              <l>My heart doth wring.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">CASSANDRA. ANTISTROPHE IX.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh deadly coil, oh, deadly coil</l>
              <l>Of Ilion, doomed to fall !</l>
              <l>Alas, the flower-cropping kine</l>
              <l>Slain by my father at the shrine</l>
              <pb n="50"/>
              <l>To save her sacred wall!</l>
              <l>But cure was none : she perished ; vain the toil!</l>
              <l>I too, soul-kindled, soon shall press the soil.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. ANTISTROPHE X.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>This tallies with thy former strain ;</l>
              <l>Sure some ill demon smites thy brain,</l>
              <l>And falling on thee moves thee thus to tell</l>
              <l>In piteous chant thy doleful pain.</l>
              <l>The end I cannot spell.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>In sooth the oracle no more shall peer</l>
              <l>Forth from a veil, like newly wedded bride ;</l>
              <l>But flashing on the soul, like wind that blows</l>
              <l>Sunward, it dasheth 'gainst the orient beams</l>
              <l>A mighty surge that doth this grief o'ertop.</l>
              <l>No more through dark enigmas will I teach!</l>
              <l>And bear me witness, how in eager chase</l>
              <l>The track I scent of crimes wrought long ago.</l>
              <l>For from this roof departeth never more</l>
              <l>A choir, concordant but unmusical,</l>
              <l>To evil tuned. Ay, drunk with human blood,</l>
              <l>And by the draught made bold, within these halls</l>
              <l>Abides a rout, not easy to eject,</l>
              <l>Of sister Furies ; lodged within these walls</l>
              <l>They chant in chorus the primeval curse.</l>
              <l>Hostile to him his brother's couch who trod,</l>
              <l>In turn they tell their loathing. Have I missed,</l>
              <l>Or, like true archer, have I hit the mark?</l>
              <l>Or strolling cheat, or lying prophet am I ?</l>
              <pb n="51"/>
              <l>Before I die, attest ye now on oath</l>
              <l>That of these halls the hoary crimes I know.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>And how can oath be healer of a woe</l>
              <l>Inherent in the race? Yet marvel I</l>
              <l>That, nurtured o'er the sea, thou know'st to speak</l>
              <l>Of foreign city as though native there.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Loxias, the seer, me with this grace endowed.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>How! passion-smitten was he, though a god?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Till now it shamed me to speak of this.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>True ; for who fareth well grows over-nice.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Love-wrestler was he, warm his favour breathed.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Came ye in course to rite conjugial ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Consent I gave, but cheated Loxias.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Mistress already of presaging art?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="52"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ay, to the townsmen all their woes I spelled.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>How then by wrath of Loxias unharmed ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>No credence won I after this offence.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To us thy oracles seem all too true.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe! woe! alas! alas! ye miseries !</l>
              <l>Of faithful augury the direful toil</l>
              <l>Racks me once more, with bodeful preludings</l>
              <l>Vexing my soul.-Seated within these halls,</l>
              <l>See, tender boys, like dreamy phantoms; children,</l>
              <l>As by their dear ones done to death, their hands</l>
              <l>Filled with their proper flesh, for nutriment;</l>
              <l>Their heart and vitals,—loathsome, piteous, meal,—</l>
              <l>Look, how they hold,-their sire has tasted, look!</l>
              <l>For these, I say, vengeance devising, waits</l>
              <l>A dastard lion, wallowing in bed;</l>
              <l>House-warden, sooth, to him that's come, my master.</l>
              <l>For the slave’s yoke, alas ! I needs must bear.</l>
              <l>The naval leader, leveller of Troy,</l>
              <l>He knows not that the fell she-dog, whose tongue</l>
              <l>Spoke words of guileful welcome, long drawn out,</l>
              <l>Like lurking Atè, will achieve his doom.</l>
              <l>Such things she dares ; the female slays the male!</l>
              <pb n="53"/>
              <l>Her,—what detested monster may I name</l>
              <l>Aud hit the mark ?-Some basilisk, or Scylla</l>
              <l>Housing in rocks, deadly to mariners,</l>
              <l>Infuriate dam of Hades, breathing forth,</l>
              <l>Against her dearest, curse implacable ?</l>
              <l>What triumph-notes exultantly she raised,</l>
              <l>All daring one, as in the turn of fight,</l>
              <l>Feigning to gratulate his safe return !</l>
              <l>What boots it whether I persuade or no ?</l>
              <l>The doomed must come ; ere long to pity moved,</l>
              <l>Me thou wilt own a prophet all too true.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Thyestes' banquet of his children's flesh</l>
              <l>I knew and shudder at; fear takes my soul,</l>
              <l>Hearing the truth, no imaged counterfeit.</l>
              <l>The rest I heard, but follow not the track.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>On Agamemnon dead, I say, thou'lt look.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Lull, poor forlorn one, thy ill-omened tongue.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet o'er this speech no healing god presides.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>If be it must; but may it never be;</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The while thou prayest, theirs it is to slay.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="54"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What man deviseth this accursèd deed ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Widely thy glance hath missed mine oracles.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ay, for the plotter's scheme to me is dark.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet in Hellenic speech my words are couched.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>So too are Pythian chants, yet hard to spell.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Alas ! what fire is this! It seizes me.</l>
              <l>Woe! woe! Lykeian god! Apollo! Woe!</l>
              <l>The biped lioness, that with the wolf</l>
              <l>In absence of the noble lion couched,</l>
              <l>Will me, her victim, slaughter, and as one</l>
              <l>Poison who mixeth, she my doom will add</l>
              <l>To crown her vengeance ; whetting 'gainst her lord</l>
              <l>The murderous knife, sho boasteth to exact</l>
              <l>His death, as payment for escorting me.</l>
              <l>Why longer wear this scorn-provoking gear,</l>
              <l>This wand, these wreaths prophetic round my neck ?</l>
              <l>Thee I will shatter ere myself am doomed.</l>
              <l>Hence to destruction : I will follow soon;</l>
              <l>Another, in my place, enrich with woes.</l>
              <l>Behold, Apollo’s self doth strip me bare</l>
              <l>Of the prophetic robe ; coldly he gazed,</l>
              <pb n="55"/>
              <l>What time, in these adornments vainly tricked,</l>
              <l>To friends and enemies, with one consent,</l>
              <l>All undeserved, a laughter I became :</l>
              <l>Vagrant yclept, poor hunger-stricken wretch,</l>
              <l>A strolling mountebank, I bare it all;</l>
              <l>And now the seer (his vengeance wreaked on me</l>
              <l>The seeress) calls me to this deadly fate.</l>
              <l>My father at the altar fell, but me</l>
              <l>The slaughter-block awaiteth, smitten down</l>
              <l>By stroke relentless, reeking with hot gore.</l>
              <l>Yet not unhonoured of the gods we fall;</l>
              <l>For other champion of our cause shall come,</l>
              <l>Seed matricidal, venger of his sire.</l>
              <l>An exiled wanderer, from this land estranged,</l>
              <l>Returns, this vengeance for his friends to crown.</l>
              <l>For, lo, the gods a mighty oath have sworn,</l>
              <l>His father's prostrate form shall lead him home.</l>
              <l>But why, an alien here, pour I my wail ?</l>
              <l>When that I first have seen my Ilion fare</l>
              <l>As fared it hath, and they who won the town</l>
              <l>In sorry plight, through judgment of the gods.</l>
              <l>I'll do! I'll suffer ! I will dare to die.</l>
              <l>These gates, as gates of Hades, I adjure,</l>
              <l>One prayer I offer, " mortal be the stroke</l>
              <l>Free from convulsive throes, in easy death,</l>
              <l>While ebbs my life-blood, may I close mine eyes.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh woman, thou most wretched and most wise;</l>
              <l>Lengthy thy speech hath been ; but if thou knowest</l>
              <l>Truly thine own sad doom, how walkest thou</l>
              <l>Like heaven-led victim, boldly to the altar ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="56"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>There’s no escape; brief respite, nothing more.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet to be last is gain at least of time.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>The day is come, small were my gain by flight.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Enduring art thou, and of dauntless mind.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Yet dear to mortals is a glorious death.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Such words none heareth from the fortunate.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Alas, my sire, for thee and thy brave sons!</l>
            </lg>
            <stage>She suddenly starts back.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What may this mean ? What terror drives thee back ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Alas! alas!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Why this alas, unless some horror scare thee?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Blood-reeking murder breatheth from these halls.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="57"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>'Tis but the scent of victims at the hearth.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Nay, but such breath as issues from a tomb.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>No Syrian odour tell'st thou for the house.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Well! I will go, within these palace halls</l>
              <l>To wail mine own and Agamemnon's doom.</l>
              <l>Enough of life ! Strangers! Alas! Alas!</l>
              <l>Yet quail I not, as bird at the brake,</l>
              <l>Idly ; in death my vouchers be in this,</l>
              <l>When, in my place, woman for woman dies,</l>
              <l>And when for man ill-wedded, man shall fall.</l>
              <l>Dying, this hospitable grace I crave.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Poor wretch ; Thy fateful doom my pity moves.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CASSANDRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Once more I fain would speak, but not to pour</l>
              <l>Mine own funereal wail; but to the Sun,</l>
              <l>Looking my last upon his beams, I pray</l>
              <l>That my avengers pay my murderers back,</l>
              <l>Requiting me, poor slave, their easy prey.</l>
              <l>Alas, for man's estate! If Fortune smile,</l>
              <l>A shadow may o'erturn it; should she frown,</l>
              <pb n="58"/>
              <l>A moistened sponge the picture doth destroy.</l>
              <l>More than the first this doom my pity moves.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Exit into the palace.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>All are of boundless weal insatiate ;—</l>
              <l>None warneth from his halls</l>
              <l>Him at whom Envy points, as rich or great,</l>
              <l>Saying, " Come here no more."—</l>
              <l>So to this man the Blessed Ones have given</l>
              <l>To capture Priam's walls ;—</l>
              <l>Home he returns, beloved of Heaven;—</l>
              <l>But must he now the blood repay</l>
              <l>Of ancient murder ; must he die,</l>
              <l>And dying expiate,</l>
              <l>With his own death, their deaths who died of yore ;</l>
              <l>Who, being mortal, this can hear, nor pray,</l>
              <l>That he were born to scathless destiny ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <stage>In the palace.</stage>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe's me ! I'm smitten with a deadly blow !</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hush! Wounded unto death who lifts this cry.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe’s me ! Again ! a second time I'm struck.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Choraphæus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>By the groaning of the monarch, wrought methinks is now the deed ;</l>
              <l>But together taking counsel, weave we now some prudent scheme.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="59"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>I. To you my counsel is to raise the cry,</l>
              <l>And to the palace call the citizens.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>II. To me seems best, at quickest, breaking in,</l>
              <l>To prove the deed by newly-dripping blade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>III. I, this opinion sharing, give my vote</l>
              <l>For action ;-not to dally is the point.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>IV. 'Tis manifest; for they, thus preluding,</l>
              <l>Give to the city signs of tyranny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>V. Ay, we delay ;-they, treading under foot</l>
              <l>All thoughts of dalliance, sleep not with the hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VI. No plan I know to fashion or propose ;</l>
              <l>Against the guilty doer we must plot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VII. That view I share, for no device I know,</l>
              <l>By words, the dead man to restore to life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>VIII. What! dragging on our lives, shall we obey</l>
              <l>These home-polluters? Them our leaders make?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>IX. That were past hearing, better far to die;</l>
              <l>For milder doom were death than tyranny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>X. How ! may we not on evidence of groans</l>
              <l>Augur full surely that the man is dead ?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>XI. Ere we can argue, we must know the facts;</l>
              <l>Assurance differs widely from surmise.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
              <l>XII. This I commend, taking the general vote,</l>
              <l>Plainly to know how fareth Atreus' son.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="60"/>
          <p>[The doors of the royal palace are thrown open ; CLYTEMNESTRA <lb/>
            is discovered standing with the axe over her shoulder. Be­ <lb/>
            hind her, under a cover, are the bodies of AGAMEMNON and <lb/>
            CASSANDRA.]</p>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Though much to suit the times before was said,</l>
              <l>It shames me not the opposite to speak :</l>
              <l>For, plotting against foes,—our seeming friends,-</l>
              <l>How else contrive with Ruin's wily snare.</l>
              <l>Too high to overleap, to fence them round?</l>
              <l>To me, not mindless of an ancient feud,</l>
              <l>Hath come at last this contest ;-late indeed.</l>
              <l>The deed achieved, here stand I, where I slew.</l>
              <l>So was it wrought (and this I'll not deny),</l>
              <l>That he could neither 'scape, nor ward his doom;</l>
              <l>Around him, like a fish-encircling net,</l>
              <l>This garment’s deadly splendour did I cast ;—</l>
              <l>Him twice I smote, and he, with twofold groan,</l>
              <l>His limbs relaxed ;—then, prostrate where he lay,</l>
              <l>Him with third blow I dowered, votive gift</l>
              <l>To nether Hades, saviour of the dead.</l>
              <l>Thus as he fell he chafed his soul away;</l>
              <l>And gurgling forth the swift death-tide of blood,</l>
              <l>He smites me with black drops of gory dew,</l>
              <l>Not less exultant than, with heaven-sent joy</l>
              <l>The corn-sown land, in birth-hour of the ear.</l>
              <l>For this great issue, Argive Senators,</l>
              <l>Joy ye, if joy ye can, but I exult.</l>
              <l>Nay, o'er the slain were off'rings meet, with right</l>
              <l>Here were they poured,—with emphasis of right.</l>
              <pb n="61"/>
              <l>Such goblet having filled with cursèd ills</l>
              <l>At home,-himself on his return drains off.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
    
  <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>We marvel at thy tongue, how bold thy speech,</l>
              <l>Who o'er thy husband makest so thy vaunt.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>As witless woman are ye proving me ;</l>
              <l>But I with steadfast heart, to you who know,</l>
              <l>Proclaim,—and whether ye will praise or blame,</l>
              <l>It recks me not,-this man is Agamemnon,-</l>
              <l>My husband, dead, the work of this right hand,</l>
              <l>Doer of righteous deed ;-so stands the case.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>O woman, what earth-nurtured bane,</l>
              <l>What potion, upsent from the wind-ruffled sea,</l>
              <l>Hast tasted, that on thine own head dost heap</l>
              <l>Curses, for incense, folk-mutter'd and deep !</l>
              <l>Hast cast off, hast slain ;—</l>
              <l>Out-cast, uncitied, thyself shalt be,</l>
              <l>Huge hate of the townsmen blasting thee.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Me thou dost doom to exile,-to endure</l>
              <l>The people's hate, their curse deep-muttered,-thou,</l>
              <l>Who 'gainst this man of yore hadst naught to urge.</l>
              <l>He, all unmoved, as though brute life he quenched,</l>
              <l>The while his fleecy pastures teem'd with flocks,</l>
              <pb n="62"/>
              <l>His own child slaughtered,-of my travail throes</l>
              <l>To me the dearest, ---charm for Thracian blasts.</l>
              <l>Him shouldst thou not have chased from land and home</l>
              <l>Just guerdon for foul deed ? Stern judge thou art</l>
              <l>When me thou dost arraign ;- but, mark my words,</l>
              <l>(Nerved as I am to threat on equal terms,)</l>
              <l>If with strong hand ye conquer me, then rule;-</l>
              <l>But should the god decree the opposite,</l>
              <l>Though late, to sober sense shalt thou be schooled.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. ANTISTROPHE.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>O haughty of council art thou ; —</l>
              <l>And haughtily-minded thou vauntest amain,</l>
              <l>As raveth thy mind 'neath blood-reeking fate.</l>
              <l>Calling for vengeance, glares forth on thy brow</l>
              <l>Of blood the foul stain ;—</l>
              <l>Forsaken of friends, the common hate,</l>
              <l>Death-blow with death-blow shalt expiate.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>This solemn sanction of mine oaths thou hearest ;—</l>
              <l>By the accomplished vengeance of my child,</l>
              <l>By Atè, by Erinyes, unto whom</l>
              <l>I slew this man,—Expectancy for me</l>
              <l>Treads not the halls of Fear, while on my hearth,</l>
              <l>Ægisthos, kind as heretofore, burns fire ;—</l>
              <l>For he of boldness is no puny shield.</l>
              <l>There prostrate lies this woman's outrager,</l>
              <l>Minion to each Chryseis under Troy.</l>
              <pb n="63"/>
              <l>There too, this captive slave, this auguress,</l>
              <l>And this man's concubine,-this prophetess,</l>
              <l>His faithful bedfellow, who shared with him</l>
              <l>The sailor's bench. Not unrequited wrought they ;</l>
              <l>For he lies-thus. While she, in swan-like fashion,</l>
              <l>Having breathed forth her last, her dying wail,</l>
              <l>Lies here, to him a paramour, and so</l>
              <l>Adds keener relish to my sweet revenge.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">Chorus. STROPHE I.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Oh might some sudden Fate</l>
              <l>Not tethered to a weight</l>
              <l>Of couch-enchaining anguish, hither waft</l>
              <l>The boon of endless sleep!</l>
              <l>For our most gracious guardian slain we weep,</l>
              <l>In woman's cause of yore</l>
              <l>Full many a pang who bore,</l>
              <l>And now lies smitten by a woman's craft.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE II.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe! frenzied Helen, woe !</l>
              <l>Through thee alone, through one,</l>
              <l>How many souls, how many, were undone ;</l>
              <l>What havoc dire 'neath Troia thou hast wrought.</l>
              <l>* * * * *</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <ab>
            <title type="sub">STROPHE III.</title>
          </ab>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>And now the cureless woe,</l>
              <l>Heirloom of blood, shed long ago,</l>
              <l>Through thee hath blossomed, causing strife</l>
              <l>Unquenchable, with husband-murder rife.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="64"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">STROPHE IV.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Bowed beneath sorrow's weight,</l>
              <l>Invoke not deadly Fate,</l>
              <l>Nor in thine anger Helen thus arraign,</l>
              <l>As though through her, through one,</l>
              <l>Fell many a Danaan son ;—</l>
              <l>She-man-destroyer, working cureless bane!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE I.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Demon, who now dost fall</l>
              <l>Ruthless on Atreus' hall</l>
              <l>Making the twin Tantalidæ thy prey,</l>
              <l>†Through women's haughty reign,</l>
              <l>Gnawing my heart, thou dost confirm thy sway.</l>
              <l>Like bodeful raven hoarse,</l>
              <l>She standeth o'er the corse,</l>
              <l>And chants exulting her discordant strain.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE IV.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Ay now thy speech in sooth</l>
              <l>Runs even with the truth,</l>
              <l>Calling the thrice-dread demon of this race ;</l>
              <l>For in their veins is nursed,</l>
              <l>By him, the quenchless thirst</l>
              <l>For blood ; ere pales the trace</l>
              <l>Of ancient pang, now ichor flows apace.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">STROPHE V.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Mighty the demon, dire his hate,</l>
              <l>Whom here thou boastest to preside ;</l>
              <pb n="65"/>
              <l>Woe ! woe ! ill-omened praise of Fate,</l>
              <l>Baneful and still unsatisfied !</l>
              <l>Alas! 'Tis Zeus, in will, in deed,</l>
              <l>Sole cause, sole fashioner; for say</l>
              <l>What comes to mortals undecreed</l>
              <l>By Zeus, what here, that owneth not his sway ?</l>
            </lg>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">STROPHE VI.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe ! woe!</l>
              <l>King ! King! how thee shall I bewail ?</l>
              <l>How voice my heartfelt grief? Thou liest there</l>
              <l>Entangled in the spider's guileful snare;</l>
              <l>In impious death thy life thou dost exhale.</l>
            </lg>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">STROPHE VII.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah me! ah me! to death betrayed,</l>
              <l>Sped by the two-edged blade,</l>
              <l>On servile couch now ignominious laid.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">STROPHE VIII.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Dost boast as mine this deed ?</l>
              <l>Then wrongly thou dost read,</l>
              <l>†To count me Agamemnon's wife ;-not so;</l>
              <l>Appearing in the mien</l>
              <l>Of this dead monarch's queen,</l>
              <l>The ancient fiend of Atreus dealt the blow ;—</l>
              <l>Requiting his grim feast,</l>
              <l>For the slain babes, as priest,</l>
              <l>The full-grown victim now he layeth low.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
       
          <pb n="66"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE V.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>That thou art guiltless of this blood</l>
              <l>Who will attest? Yet by thy side,</l>
              <l>Haply, as thy accomplice, stood</l>
              <l>The Fury who doth here preside.</l>
              <l>Through streams of kindred gore</l>
              <l>Presseth grim Ares on to claim</l>
              <l>Requital for the deed of shame</l>
              <l>The clotted blood of babes devoured of yore.</l>
            </lg>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE VI.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Woe ! woe!</l>
              <l>King ! King ! thee how shall I bewail ?</l>
              <l>How voice my heartfelt grief ? Thou liest there</l>
              <l>Entangled in the spider's guileful snare,</l>
              <l>In impious death thy life thou dost exhale.</l>
            </lg>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE VII.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah me ! ah me! to death betrayed,</l>
              <l>Sped by the two-edged blade,</l>
              <l>On servile couch now ignominious laid.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE VIII.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>By no unjust decree</l>
              <l>Perished this man, for he</l>
              <l>Through guile hath household death enacted here :—</l>
              <l>His proper child he slew,</l>
              <l>Sweet bud from me that grew,</l>
              <l>Iphigenia, wept with many a tear.</l>
              <l>Foul quittance for foul deed ;—</l>
              <pb n="67"/>
              <l>He reaped the sword's due meed,</l>
              <l>Hence no proud boast from him let Hades hear!</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">STROPHE IX.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Perplexed I am, bewildered sore</l>
              <l>Which way to turn; escape is vain ;</l>
              <l>Totters the house; I dread the crimson rain</l>
              <l>That with loud plashing shakes these walls; no more</l>
              <l>Falleth in niggard droppings now the gore.</l>
              <l>And bent on deed of mischief, Fate anew</l>
              <l>On other whetstones, whetteth vengeance due.</l>
            </lg>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE II.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Earth! Earth! oh hadst thou been</l>
              <l>My shroud ere I my king</l>
              <l>Prone in the silver-sided bath had seen !</l>
              <l>Who will inter him? Who his dirge shall sing?</l>
              <l>So hardy thou? Wilt thou who didst assail</l>
              <l>Thy husband's life, thyself uplift the wail ?</l>
              <l>Wilt to his shade, for the great deeds he wrought,</l>
              <l>Render a graceless grace, with malice fraught ?</l>
            </lg>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE III.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>With tears of honest grief</l>
              <l>Weeping the godlike chief,</l>
              <l>Above the tomb who now shall raise</l>
              <l>The funeral hymn ? Who speak the hero's praise ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">STROPHE X.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Not thine the task to counsel here.</l>
              <l>By us he fell: this man we slew;</l>
              <l>Ours be it to inurn him too;</l>
              <l>Borne from the palace, o'er the bier</l>
              <pb n="68"/>
              <l>Shall sound no notes of wailing ;-no,</l>
              <l>But him, with blandishments, shall meet</l>
              <l>Iphigenia ; by the rapid streams</l>
              <l>Of Acheron, his daughter, as beseems,</l>
              <l>Facing her father, shall around him throw</l>
              <l>Her loving arms, and him with kisses greet.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE IX.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>That taunt still answers taunt we see.</l>
              <l>Here to adjudge is hard indeed.</l>
              <l>Spoiled be the spoiler ; who sheds blood must bleed.</l>
              <l>While Zeus surviveth shall this law survive.</l>
              <l>Doer must suffer; 'tis the Fates' decree;</l>
              <l>Who from the house the fated curse may drive ?</l>
              <l>The race is welded to calamity.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <ab>
              <title type="sub">ANTISTROPHE X.</title>
            </ab>
            <lg>
              <l>Ay! now on Truth thou dost alight!</l>
              <l>I with the demon of this race-</l>
              <l>The Pleisthenid—an oath will plight.</l>
              <l>My doom, though grievous, I embrace.</l>
              <l>But for the rest, hence let him haste!</l>
              <l>Leaving this house, let him another race</l>
              <l>Harass with kindred murders. For myself,</l>
              <l>When from these halls blood-frenzy I have chased,</l>
              <l>Small pittance shall I crave of worldly pelf.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Enter ÆGISTHOS, arrayed in royal robes, and with armed attendants.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hail, joyous light of justice-bearing day!</l>
              <l>At length I can aver that Gods supernal,</l>
              <pb n="69"/>
              <l>Judges of men, look down on earthly woes,</l>
              <l>Beholding, in the Erinyes' woven robes,</l>
              <l>This man, thus prostrate, welcome sight to me,</l>
              <l>The wiles atoning compassed by his sire.</l>
              <l>For Atreus, Argos' ruler, this man's father,</l>
              <l>Did from the city and his home expel</l>
              <l>Thyestes, rival in the sovereignty,-</l>
              <l>My father, to be plain, and his own brother.</l>
              <l>But coming back, a suppliant of the hearth,</l>
              <l>Wretched Thyestes found a lot secure,</l>
              <l>Not doomed his natal soil with blood to stain,</l>
              <l>Here in his home: but this man's godless sire,</l>
              <l>Atreus, with zeal officious more than kind,</l>
              <l>Feigning a joyous banquet-day to hold,</l>
              <l>Served to my sire, for food, his children's flesh.</l>
              <l>Their feet indeed, the members of their hands,—</l>
              <l>Seated aloof, in higher place, he hides.</l>
              <l>Partaking of the undistinguished parts,</l>
              <l>In ignorance, Thyestes eats the food,</l>
              <l>Curse-laden, as thou seest, to the race.</l>
              <l>Discerning then the impious deed, he shrieked,</l>
              <l>And back recoiling the foul slaughter spewed.</l>
              <l>Spurning, with righteous curse, th' insulted board</l>
              <l>Dread doom he vows to the Pelopidæ ;—</l>
              <l>" So perish the whole race of Pleisthenes."</l>
              <l>Hence is it that ye see this man laid low;</l>
              <l>The righteous planner of his death am I.</l>
              <l>For me, the thirteenth child, in swathing clothes,</l>
              <l>He with my wretched sire, to exile drove.</l>
              <l>But, grown to manhood, Justice led me back,</l>
              <l>And I, although aloof, have reached this man,</l>
              <pb n="70"/>
              <l>The threads combining of the fatal plot.</l>
              <l>Now for myself 'twere glorious to die,</l>
              <l>Seeing this man entrapped in Justice' toils.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To honour insolence in guilt, Ægisthos,</l>
              <l>I know not ;—that with purpose thou didst kill</l>
              <l>This man, thou boastest; of his piteous doom</l>
              <l>Sole author thou :—I tell thee thine own head</l>
              <l>To Justice brought, be sure shall not escape</l>
              <l>The curse of stoning by the people's hand.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Plying the lowest oar, dost menace us</l>
              <l>Who from the upper benches sway the helm ?</l>
              <l>Being old thou know’st how bitter at thy years</l>
              <l>Wisdom by stern necessity to learn.</l>
              <l>But bonds and hunger-pangs, to cure the mind</l>
              <l>Of stubborn old, are skilful leeches found.</l>
              <l>Hast eyes, yet seest not this? Against the pricks</l>
              <l>Kick not, lest stumbling, thou shouldst come to grief.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Woman, house-mate to him from recent war</l>
              <l>Return’d,— defiler of thy husband's bed,</l>
              <l>Death thou didst plot against this warrior chief.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>These words will fountains be of bitter tears.</l>
              <l>Thy tongue the opposite to Orpheus is;</l>
              <l>For he drew all by rapture of his voice,</l>
              <pb n="71"/>
              <l>While thou, by idle bark, dost all things stir</l>
              <l>†To hate ; — when conquered, thou wilt tamer</l>
              <l>show.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Shalt thou be ruler of the Argives, thou,</l>
              <l>Who, when that thou hadst plotted this man's death,</l>
              <l>Didst courage lack to strike the blow thyself?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To spread the snare was plainly woman's part,</l>
              <l>For I, his ancient foeman, was suspect;</l>
              <l>But armed with this man's treasure, be it mine</l>
              <l>To rule the citizens. Th' unruly colt</l>
              <l>That, barley-fed, turns restive, I will bind</l>
              <l>†With heavier thong than yokes the trace-horse;</l>
              <l>—him,</l>
              <l>Darkness' grim comrade, Famine, shall see tamed.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>This man why didst thou not, O base of soul,</l>
              <l>Slaughter thyself? But him his wife, with thee,</l>
              <l>The land polluting, and her country's gods,</l>
              <l>Hath slain. Orestes, sees he still the light,</l>
              <l>That, home-returning with auspicious Fate,</l>
              <l>He may, with mighty stroke, deal death to both ?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Since thou art minded thus to act, not talk alone,</l>
              <l>know quickly.</l>
              <l>* * * * *</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="72"/>
          <stage>To his attendants.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Come on, my faithful body-guard, the fray is not far distant.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Come on then, and with hand on hilt, his sword let each make ready.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Be well assured, with hand on hilt, to die I too refuse not.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To die,—thine utterance we accept, and take as thy death-omen.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Dearest of husbands let us not, I pray, work further mischief.</l>
              <l>Already in our many woes reaped have we wretched harvests.</l>
              <l>Of sorrow there hath been enough ; let us forbear more bloodshed.</l>
              <l>Go thou, and ye too aged men, seek your appointed mansions,</l>
              <l>Ere aught ye do to work mischance. As fate enjoined we’ve acted.</l>
              <l>If trouble is the lot of man, enough have we encountered ;</l>
              <l>Sore smitten by the heavy hoof of some avenging demon.</l>
              <l>Thus ye a woman's counsel have, if any deign to hearken.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="73"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>To think that their vain tongue 'gainst me into such speech should blossom;-</l>
              <l>That they should hurl forth words like these, their proper doom, thus tempting :</l>
              <l>They against sober reason err, thus to insult their ruler.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Upon the evil man to fawn is not the wont of Argives.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>But, be assured, some future day, I yet shall overtake you.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Not so if hither to return some god should guide Orestes.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Full well I know that exiles still on hopes are wont to batten.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Work as thou listest. Gorge thy fill. Stain justice. Thou canst do it.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>ÆGISTHOS</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Be sure that thou to me shalt pay the forfeit of thy folly.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Be boastful and be bold, like cock beside his partner strutting.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="74"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>CLYTEMNESTRA</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>These senseless barkings heed not thou ; thyself and I together,</l>
              <l>Ruling within these royal halls, will all things wisely order.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage>Exeunt.</stage>

          <div type="notes">
          <pb n="75"/>
          <head>NOTES TO THE AGAMEMNON.</head>
          <stage>My friend the translator wishing to obviate the charge of arbitrarily departing from Æschylus, requests me to draw up a list of the conjectural emendations of the text which I have suggested. Space forbids my here justifying them. I will state them as briefly as I can. F. W. N.</stage>
          <head>AGAMEMNON.</head>
          <p><label>VERSE 7.</label> Omit <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀστέρας</quote> as an interpretation of <quote xml:lang="grc">δυνάστας</quote>, and read <quote xml:lang="grc">ὅταν φθίνωσιν, ἀντολάς τε τῶνδ᾽, ὁρῶ</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>10, 11.</label> Read <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐλπίζει</quote> for <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐλπίζω</quote>, and retain the infinitive <quote xml:lang="grc">κρατεῖν</quote>. Then <quote xml:lang="grc">κέαρ</quote> is nominative, and <quote xml:lang="grc">ὧδε κρατεῖν</quote> refers to the capture of Troy, “get such mastery.”</p>
          <p><label>138.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">τόσσον περ εὔφρων καλὰ</quote> . . . read—<lb/>
            <quote xml:lang="grc">† πᾶσιν † γὰρ εὔφρων [Αρτεμίς ἐστι] καλὰ<lb/>
            δρόσοισι λεπτοῖσιν † μαλακῶν τε * λαγῶν . . .</quote></p>
          <p><label>142.</label> <quote xml:lang="grc">
<l>τερπνὰ [δὲ δαίμονα θέσπιν ὁ μάντις]</l>
<l>τούτων αἰτεῖ σύμβολα κρᾶναι,</l>
<l>δεξιὰ μὲν κατάμομφα δὲ φάσματα † κρίνων.</l>
<l>Ιήϊον † αὖ καλέω</l>
<l>“Παιᾶνα [θεῖον], μήτινας ἀντιπνόους</l>
<l>Δαναοῖς χρονίας ἐχενῇδας</l>
<l>-Ἄγρεια τεύξη, σπευδομένα θυσίαν</l>
<l>ἑτέραν .</l>
          </quote></p>
          <p>In 142, 146, such words as I insert seem to be deficient.</p>
          <p>In 144 I have written <quote xml:lang="grc">κρίνων</quote> for the absurd <quote xml:lang="grc">στρούθων</quote>.</p>
          <p>In 148 a nominative, expressive of Artemis, is deficient. I have changed <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀπλοίας</quote>, which can hardly bear the epithet <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀντιπνόους</quote>, into <quote xml:lang="grc">Ἄγρεια</quote> (huntress).</p>
          <pb n="76"/>
          <p><label>164.</label> Read <quote xml:lang="grc">εὔξεται</quote> for the old <quote xml:lang="grc">λέξει</quote>. <quote xml:lang="grc">οὐδεν εὔξεται πρὶν ὤν</quote>· “ will not vaunt that he was aught of yore.”</p>
          <p><label>175.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">δέ που</quote> read <quote xml:lang="grc">γέ που</quote>, and remove the stop after <quote xml:lang="grc">σωφρονεῖν</quote>. Join <quote xml:lang="grc">ἄκοντας</quote> with <quote xml:lang="grc">σωφρονεῖν</quote>, <quote xml:lang="grc">ἦλθε</quote> with <quote xml:lang="grc">βιαίως</quote>. “ And to men, loath to learn sobriety, there cometh forcibly a grace (I trow) of deities, who sit on holy bench.” The “ grace” is the painful wisdom learned by suffering.</p>
          <p><label>226.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">προνωπῆ</quote> read <quote xml:lang="grc">προνωπεῖς</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>233.</label> After <quote xml:lang="grc">γραφαῖς</quote> insert [<quote xml:lang="grc">ποικίλαις</quote>]. In the antistrophe do not omit <quote xml:lang="grc">προκλύειν</quote>, but for <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐπεὶ</quote> read <quote xml:lang="grc">πῆ</quote>, and omit <quote xml:lang="grc">ἡ</quote> before <quote xml:lang="grc">λύσις</quote>. <quote xml:lang="grc">Τὸ μέλλον δὲ προκλύειν, πῆ γένοιτ' | ἂν λύσις, προχαιρέτω</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>278.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">ἰσχὺς</quote> read <quote xml:lang="grc">ὄσχας</quote> or <quote xml:lang="grc">ὄσχους</quote>, “ twigs” of flame ; suggested by <quote xml:lang="grc">πεύκη</quote>, the pine. In the corrupt <quote xml:lang="grc">πρὸς ἡδονὴν</quote> a verb is concealed, such as <quote xml:lang="grc">προήχμασεν</quote>, <quote xml:lang="grc">προήκρισεν</quote>, vibrated, perked forward. <quote xml:lang="grc">Προσήλασεν</quote> is possible, but was less likely to be corrupted than some rarer verb.</p>
          <p><label>299.</label> Before <quote xml:lang="grc">φλέγουσαν</quote> a whole line seems to be lost, such as [<quote xml:lang="grc">αὐγὴν κελεύουσ', ἀστραπαῖς εὐαγγέλοις</quote>] <quote xml:lang="grc">φλέγουσαν</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>327.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">ὡς δυσδαίμονες</quote> Blomfield well gave <quote xml:lang="grc">ὡς δ᾽ εὐδαίμονες</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>365.</label> Treading in Blomfield's steps, I attempt the corrupt passage thus—<lb/>
            <quote xml:lang="grc">πέφανται δ' † ἐγγενὴς<lb/>
            ἀτολμήτως "Αρη<lb/>
            πνεόντων, μεῖζον ἢ δικαίως.<lb/>
            φλεόντων δωμάτων ὑπερφεῦ,<lb/>
            † τόδ' οὔτε βέλτιστόν † ἐστ'<lb/>
            οὔτ᾽ ἀπήμαντον . . .</quote><lb/>
            (<quote xml:lang="grc">Τόδε</quote>, the fact of excessive abundance.)</p>
          <p><label>412.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">πάρεστι σιγὰς ἄτιμος ἀλοίδορος<lb/>
            ἅδιστος ἀφεμένων ἰδεῖν</quote>:<lb/>
            read (until we get something better)—<lb/>
            <quote xml:lang="grc">πάρεστι σιγὰ κατ᾽ οἴμους, ἀλοίδορος,<lb/>
            ταϊστ᾽ ἀφωμένων ἰδεῖν</quote>.</p>
          <pb n="77"/>
          <p>Join <quote xml:lang="grc">σιγὰ ἀφωμένων</quote>. “There is silence along (her) paths, while they grope to see things that cannot be seen.” I understand <quote xml:lang="grc">αφωμένων</quote> of Helen's <quote xml:lang="grc">ὁμηλικίη</quote>, her maids of honour. In antistrophe for <quote xml:lang="grc">Ελλάδος</quote> read <quote xml:lang="grc">Ελλᾶνος</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>541.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">οὐ λαχόντες</quote>, which is nonsense, read <quote xml:lang="grc">ὀλολύζοντες</quote>, οι <quote xml:lang="grc">οἰμώζοντες</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>741.</label> This very corrupt passage admits of an approximate sòlution, thus—<lb/>
            <quote xml:lang="grc">ὕβριν, τότ᾽ ἢ τόθ᾽, ὅτε τὸ κύριον μόλῃ,<lb/>
            † νεαροῖς † φανοῦσαν † τόκοισι<lb/>
            δαίμονα - παντομάχαν<lb/>
            ἀνίερον θράσος μελαι<lb/>
            νας μελάθροισιν "Ατας,<lb/>
            εἰδομέναν τοκεῦσιν.</quote><lb/>
            Vulgo, <quote xml:lang="grc">ἢ νὰ † φαόυς κότον | δαίμονά † τε † τὸν ἄμαχον ἀπόλεμον | ἀνίερον Θράσος "Ατης</quote>. <quote xml:lang="grc">θράσος "Ατης</quote> is put for <quote xml:lang="grc">θράσεια "Ατη</quote>, and <quote xml:lang="grc">εἰδομένη</quote>, fem., agrees with it. If <quote xml:lang="grc">μελαίνας</quote> is correct, it seems to mean “gloomy (funereal),” and is joined with the dative <quote xml:lang="grc">μελάθροις</quote>. Then the antistrophe is omitting <quote xml:lang="grc">βίον</quote> in 749, and reading <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔδεθλα</quote> with Dindorf, &amp;c.<lb/>
            <quote xml:lang="grc">τὰ χρυσόπαστα δ᾽ ἔδεθλα σὺν πίνῳ χερῶν<lb/>
            ....<lb/>
            παλιντρόποις ὄμμασιν λιποῦσ᾽, Ὁσίαν προσέβα, . . . .</quote><lb/>
            (for vulg., <quote xml:lang="grc">ὅσια</quote>).</p>
          <p><label>776.</label> Adopting from Franke <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐκ θυσιῶν</quote> for <quote xml:lang="grc">ἑκούσιον</quote>, read also <quote xml:lang="grc">θρήσκοισι</quote> for <quote xml:lang="grc">θνήσκουσι</quote>, which cannot be right. Then, we get<lb/>
            “ <quote xml:lang="grc">θράσος ἐκ θυσιῶν<lb/>
            ἄνδρασι θρήσκοισι κομίζων.</quote> ”<lb/>
            “infusing into religious men confidence from the sacrifices.”</p>
          <p><label>844.</label> <quote xml:lang="grc">Πολλὴν . . . λέγω.</quote> Schutz, if I remember, regards the line as spurious, and with good reason. <quote xml:lang="grc">Πολλὴν ἄνωθεν</quote> has come from <quote xml:lang="grc">πολλὰς ἄνωθεν</quote> just above; and he imagines a commentator to have expounded the second Geryon to be Agamemnon : <quote xml:lang="grc">τὸν κάτω γὰρ οὐ λέγει ;</quote> “ for he does not mean the Geryon below.”</p>
          <pb n="78"/>
          <p><label>994.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">μοῖρα μοῖραν</quote>, which is nonsense, read <quote xml:lang="grc">μοῖρ᾽ ἄμοιρά μ'</quote> ; and compare <quote xml:lang="grc">νâες ἄναες</quote>, <quote xml:lang="grc">γάμος ἄγαμος</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>1095.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">μελαγκέρων</quote>, by all means read <quote xml:lang="grc">μελαγκρόκῳ</quote>, and for <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐν πέπλοισι</quote> perhaps <quote xml:lang="grc">ἐμπλακέντα</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>1443.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">πολύμναστον</quote> read (metri causa) <quote xml:lang="grc">πολυυμνατον</quote>, and after the word mark a hiatus of five lines. The antistrophic to <quote xml:lang="grc">πολυύμνατον</quote> is <quote xml:lang="grc">τίς ὁ θρηνήσων</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>1446.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">κράτος ἰσόψυχον</quote> (which is defective in metre as well as sense) read <quote xml:lang="grc">κράτος σινόψυχον</quote>, “thou establishest a soul-blighting sway by means of women.” Hermann by inserting <quote xml:lang="grc">τ'</quote> after <quote xml:lang="grc">κράτος</quote> did not improve the sense.</p>
          <p><label>1476.</label> Read, for the sense, <quote xml:lang="grc">εἶναί μ᾽ ἄλοχον [τοῦδ᾽ ὀλέτειραν]</quote>, also 1480, . . . <quote xml:lang="grc">τόνδ' ἀπέτισεν [φονίαισι δίκαις]</quote>. In antistrophe omit '<quote xml:lang="grc">Ipɩyévecav</quote> as a gloss, and read<lb/>
            <quote xml:lang="grc">τὴν πολύκλαυτον ἀνάξια δράσας,</quote><lb/>
            then strophe and antistrophe become commensurate. Perhaps in 1497 <quote xml:lang="grc">doλig</quote> should be <quote xml:lang="grc">dovλí</quote>, and in 1501 <quote xml:lang="grc">δολίαν</quote> should be <quote xml:lang="grc">δούλιον</quote>, which the argument from <quote xml:lang="grc">ἀνελεύθερον</quote> seems to demand. (Indeed the metre of <quote xml:lang="grc">doλío</quote> in 1497 is not satisfactory.) Yet the argument of <quote xml:lang="grc">ovde yàp</quote> in 1501 remains obscure or strained.</p>
          <p><label>1610.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">ἄξει</quote> read <quote xml:lang="grc">ἔχθει</quote>, in contrast to <quote xml:lang="grc">χαρᾷ</quote>.</p>
          <p><label>1618.</label> For <quote xml:lang="grc">σειραφόρον</quote> read <quote xml:lang="grc">σειραφόρων</quote>: “ bands heavier than common harness.”</p>
        </div>
      
        </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </TEI>